<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>What to Say? – Marking the 25<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Anniversary of
                    Slovenian Independence</title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename>Jurij</forename>
                        <surname>Perovšek</surname>
                        <roleName>research councellor</roleName>
                        <roleName>PhD</roleName>
                        <affiliation>Institute of Contemporary History</affiliation>
                        <address>
                            <addrLine>Kongresni trg 1</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>SI-1000 Ljubljana</addrLine>
                        </address>
                        <email>jurij.perovsek@inz.si</email>
                    </name>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>2016-10-19</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>
                    <orgName xml:lang="sl">Inštitut za novejšo zgodovino</orgName>
                    <orgName xml:lang="en">Institute of Contemporary History</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Kongresni trg 1</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>SI-1000 Ljubljana</addrLine>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>http://ojs.inz.si/pnz/article/view/187</pubPlace>
                <date>2016</date>
                <availability status="free">
                    <licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title xml:lang="sl">Prispevki za novejšo zgodovino</title>
                <title xml:lang="en">Contributions to Contemporary History</title>
                <biblScope unit="volume">56</biblScope>
                <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
                <idno type="ISSN">2463-7807</idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source, born digital.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc xml:lang="en">
                <p>Contributions to Contemporary History is one of the central Slovenian scientific
                    historiographic journals, dedicated to publishing articles from the field of
                    contemporary history (the 19th and 20th century).</p>
                <p>The journal is published three times per year in Slovenian and in the following
                    foreign languages: English, German, Serbian, Croatian, Bosnian, Italian, Slovak
                    and Czech. The articles are all published with abstracts in English and
                    Slovenian as well as summaries in English.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <projectDesc xml:lang="sl">
                <p>Prispevki za novejšo zgodovino je ena osrednjih slovenskih znanstvenih
                    zgodovinopisnih revij, ki objavlja teme s področja novejše zgodovine (19. in 20.
                    stoletje).</p>
                <p>Revija izide trikrat letno v slovenskem jeziku in v naslednjih tujih jezikih:
                    angleščina, nemščina, srbščina, hrvaščina, bosanščina, italijanščina, slovaščina
                    in češčina. Članki izhajajo z izvlečki v angleščini in slovenščini ter povzetki
                    v angleščini.</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="sl"/>
                <language ident="en"/>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords xml:lang="en">
                    <term>independence</term>
                    <term>politics</term>
                    <term>ideology</term>
                    <term>narcissistic society</term>
                    <term>historiography</term>
                    <term>psychiatry</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords xml:lang="sl">
                    <term>osamosvojitev</term>
                    <term>privatizacija</term>
                    <term>politika</term>
                    <term>ideološkost</term>
                    <term>narcistična družba</term>
                    <term>zgodovinopisje</term>
                    <term>psihiatrija</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change>
                    <date>2016-11-08</date>
                    <name>Neja Blaj Hribar</name>
                    <desc>Pretvorba iz DOCX v TEI, dodatno kodiranje</desc>
                </change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <docAuthor>Jurij Perovšek<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn0" n="*"
                    ><hi rend="bold" xml:space="preserve">research councellor, PhD, Institute of Contemporary History, Kongresni trg 1, 1000 Ljubljana, Slovenia, <ref target="mailito:jurij.perovsek@inz.si">jurij.perovsek@inz.si</ref></hi></note></docAuthor>
            <docImprint>
                <idno type="cobissType">Cobiss type: 1.01</idno>
                <idno type="UDC">UDC: 930:94(497.4)"1991"</idno>
            </docImprint>
            <div type="abstract" xml:lang="sl">
                <head type="main">IZVLEČEK</head>
                <head>KAJ REČI? – OB PETINDVAJSETLETNICI SLOVENSKE OSAMOSVOJITVE</head>
                <p><hi rend="italic">V prispevku avtor opozarja na negativne plati družbenega,
                        političnega in gospodarskega razvoja v Republiki Sloveniji po njeni
                        osamosvojitvi. Izstopa t. i. divja privatizacija nekdanjega družbenega in
                        državnega premoženja, ki so ji bili vodilo nepošteni nameni, okoriščanje in
                        pohlep, pri čemer je manjši del prebivalstva zelo obogatel. Za to nosita
                        velik del odgovornosti pravni sistem in politika, ki nista pripravila
                        ustreznih zakonov. Politika ne uživa zaupanja, ki je temelj demokracije. V
                        družbi se je uveljavil narcistični tip človeka, ki želi čim bolj poskrbeti
                        zase in pri tem odrivati druge, »šefovske etaže« v podjetjih pa neusmiljeno
                        pobijajo socialni čut. Družbo pretresajo hudi ideološki spori in
                        preprečujejo nacionalno soglasje o etičnem temelju slovenske države in
                        smotrom njenega obstoja. Tiste, ki so ob osamosvojitvi s polnimi pljuči
                        zadihali narodno čustvo in pričakovali zgodovinski dvig slovenstva, je tak
                        razvoj razočaral. Zgodovinopisje in psihiatrija sta o omenjeni problematiki
                        v zadnjih letih opravila več kvalitetnih, tudi monografskih,
                    obravnav.</hi></p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Ključne besede: osamosvojitev, privatizacija, politika,
                        ideološkost, narcistična družba, zgodovinopisje, psihiatrija</hi></p>
            </div>
            <div type="abstract">
                <head>ABSTRACT</head>
                <p><hi rend="italic">In his paper, the author points out the negative aspects of the
                        social, political and economic development in the Republic of Slovenia,
                        following its independence. What stands out is the uncontrolled
                        privatisation of former public and state property, which was rooted in
                        dishonest intentions, profiteering and greed, and resulted in a small part
                        of the population becoming very rich. The legal system and the politics are
                        largely to blame for the situation, as they failed to prepare suitable laws
                        that would prevent it from happening. Trust, the very foundation of
                        democracy, is not something that would currently be associated with the
                        politicians. The society has witnessed the rise of narcissistic characters
                        who only care for their own well-being and who trample over others, while
                        the companies' executives are doing their best to eradicate any social
                        concern. Society is being shaken by severe ideological conflicts, which
                        prevent a national consensus on the ethical foundation of the Slovenian
                        state and the purpose of its existence. Those who fully embraced the
                        national sentiment and expected a historic rise of Slovenianism when
                        Slovenia became independent were disappointed by such development of events.
                        In recent years, historiography and psychiatry have been examining the issue
                        in a number of publications, including monographs.</hi></p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Key words: independence, privatisation, politics, ideology,
                        narcissistic society, historiography, psychiatry</hi></p>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <p> It was already evening on 15<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> January 1992, when I was
                walking along Vegova Street, headed for the Institute of Contemporary History in
                Ljubljana, after spending the day reviewing historical materials at the National and
                University Library. I first heard and then saw an exemplar meandering in the middle
                of the street, crying out: “Slovenia, I love you so! I would give half of my life
                for you!” – “As would I, as would I!” it crossed my mind, but I derailed the train
                of thought. My profession as a historian prevented me from giving into the
                intoxicating sensation brought about by the fact that, on that day, Slovenia was
                internationally recognised by the states of the European Community. I subsequently
                recalled this event on several occasions and tried to assess the unfinished thought
                of that day.</p>
            <p> I witnessed the “offering” on Vegova Street after spending time with the Slovenians
                who lived in the first Yugoslav state. Therefore, it makes sense that, while making
                a list of the years of Slovenian independence, which fulfilled the promise of a
                "success story" for a while, I was faced with the question of what Slovenians
                revealed about themselves after leaving multinational states in which they
                ultimately saw their national and democratic demise. Given our historical position
                after 1991, the question is even more engaging, since we are not ruled neither by
                Vienna or Belgrade, nor by any single-party political system. We do, however, feel
                the influence of Brussels and the Euro-Atlantic powers. </p>
            <p> After turning from the Austrian south to the Yugoslav north in 1918, the Slovenians
                expected to find themselves in the "promised land". They had dreamt and written
                about it before the above-mentioned change.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn1" n="1"
                    >Jurij Perovšek,
                    <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Liberalizem in vprašanje slovenstva. Nacionalna politika liberalnega tabora v letih 1918–1929 </hi>[Liberalism
                    and the Question of Slovenianism. National Policy in the Liberal Camp from 1918
                    to 1929] (Ljubljana: Modrijan, 1996), 46–65.</note> But the reality was somewhat
                different. Autonomy was not attained, the nations were constitutionally wiped out
                and merged into a Serbian-Croatian-Slovenian nationality, the same name was given to
                the official language, there were no more Slovenian regiments (a Slovenian military
                force was, however, formed in the State of Slovenes, Croats and Serbs in November
                1918), and Slovenian soldiers were dispersed across the entire Kingdom of Serbs,
                Croats and Slovenes, i.e. Yugoslavia. The belief that the toxic battles fought among
                political parties were at their end, which was expressed by a liberal politician
                Albert Kramer in his address to the leader of the Catholic Vseslovenska ljudska
                stranka (Pan-Slovenian People's Party) Dr Anton Korošec, when he visited Ljubljana
                on 23 and 24 March 1918,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn2" n="2"> “Praznik slovenskega
                    ženstva” [Slovenian Women Day], <hi rend="italic">Slovenski narod</hi>, 26 March
                    1918, 2.</note> did not come true. Almost 20 years later, the Maribor-based
                newspaper <hi rend="italic">Neodvisnost</hi> revealed that </p>
            <quote>"Slovenians no longer consider themselves as a unit but as a mixture of different
                tribes without any sense of community, who are engaged in a fierce, insensitive and
                brutal fight against extermination. These tribes include the clericals, liberals,
                Marxists, and others, whatever they may be called. The fire of passion and hatred is
                stoked by the media which is daily poisoning our society. No supreme and unalterable
                national principles, no clear and firm objectives can therefore be found in it and
                in our public."<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn3" n="3"> “Neodvisnost” [Independence],
                        <hi rend="italic">Neodvisnost</hi>, 1 December 1936, 1.</note></quote>
            <p>There were still Carniolan and Styrian people to be found, even though Ivan Hribar,
                in October 1918, expected that the people of Slovenia would <hi rend="italic">“all
                    (…) simply be Slovenians”</hi>.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn4" n="4"> Ivan
                    Hribar, “Uprava Jugoslavije” [Yugoslavia administration], <hi rend="italic"
                        >Slovenec</hi>, 15 October 1918, 2.</note> There was, however, cultural and
                economical progress but the Sava river flowed “downstream”, which was “patriotic” as
                written by the very young Mitja Ribičič in 1927.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn5"
                    n="5"> Mitja Ribičič, “Patriotizem” [Patriotism], <hi rend="italic">Učiteljski
                        tovariš</hi>, 13 January 1927, 2.</note> Comfort was sought in the notion of
                the Slovenian people being hard-working, honest, reliable, kind-hearted and
                generally non-problematic, i.e. in the attributes which supposedly illustrated the
                truth of their civilisational image. We should not forget to mention the political
                parties, organisations and associations, which multiplied across the Slovenian
                territory. Those with federalist inclinations tended to mention the North American
                countries and Switzerland as national models to be emulated.</p>
            <p> Historiography clarified the above issues rather well, while the contemporaries of
                the first 22-year-Yugoslav period managed to prepare two extensive, comprehensive
                presentations of the then Slovenian development This shows the extent of their
                interest in the subject matter. The collections entitled
                <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Slovenci v desetletju 1918–1928 (Slovenians in the decade 1918–1928) </hi>(1928)
                and <hi rend="italic">Spominski zbornik Slovenije : ob dvajsetletnici Kraljevine
                    Jugoslavije (Memorial booklet of Slovenia : the twentieth anniversary of the
                    Kingdom of Yugoslavia)</hi> (1939) are still considered to be two definitive
                works of academic literature.</p>
            <p> And our twenty-five years? Slovenians have taken up an international legal position
                – the Republic of Slovenia. The Slovenian language retained its official nature from
                the second Yugoslavia; once again, the Slovenians got their own army and witnessed
                several remarkable cultural and sports-related successes at home and abroad; the
                media developed further, and, as for the economy, we will mention that later;
                however, Sava river does not necessarily seem to flow downstream when it leaves the
                Slovenian territory any more. Slovenians were taking leave as the “objects of
                history who caught a cold.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn6" n="6"> Tomaž Šalamun,
                    “Duma 1964,” <hi rend="italic">Naši razgledi</hi>, 9 May 1964, 178.</note> Tomaž
                Šalamun, who coined this description, repeated it in his speech marking the
                Slovenian cultural holiday – the Prešeren Day, in 2000. He described Slovenia as a </p>
            <quote>“beautiful, relatively rich, lively and creative country. The people are
                friendlier, the changes are profound, the language is fresh and stimulating (...).
                The wonder of a civilising momentum is happening here with great force. We are
                actualised to such a degree that we will hopefully no longer yearn for the watchful
                eyes of protective big brothers, and we will maintain our sovereignty and democracy.
                The wisdom of the people can also be seen in them refusing to follow its elites if
                they stray, but simply relieving them of their duty.”<note place="foot"
                    xml:id="ftn7" n="7"> Tomaž Šalamun, “Govor na prireditvi ob slovenskem kulturnem
                    prazniku 2000” [Speech at the event held for the Prešeren Day 2000], in: <hi
                        rend="italic">Prešernov sklad 2000</hi> [Prešerenʼs Fund 2000] (Ljubljana:
                    upravni odbor Prešernovega sklada, 2000), 4, 5.</note></quote>
            <p> What was created was “a flawed paradise”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn8" n="8">
                    Marko Bucik, “Raj z napako. Slovenija leta 2041. V kakšni državi si želim živeti
                    čez 25 let in kako priti do nje?” [A flawed paradise. Slovenia in 2041. In what
                    kind of country do I want to live in 25 years and how to achieve it?], <hi
                        rend="italic">Delo</hi>, 7 June 2016, 5. </note> The ideological “tribes”
                remained, using new tools being, along with the old ones – the experiences of the
                second world conflict and of the attainment of independence as well as of the
                previous society, which was saturated with “organisation, politics, matter,
                ideology, and everything of importance in the world, it was the World.” This is how
                Taras Kermauner perceived the then society.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn9" n="9">
                    Taras Kermauner, “Vladimir Bartol – predhodnik današnje slovenske moderne
                    literature” [Vladimir Bartol – the predecessor of today’s modern Slovenian
                    literature], in: Vladimir Bartol, <hi rend="italic">Demon in
                    Eros</hi>.<hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve"> Al Araf</hi> [Demon and Eros.
                    Al Araf] (Ljubljana: Mladinska knjiga, 1974), 441.</note> While some fully
                embraced the national sentiment and expected the historic rise of Slovenianism and
                its ethical acknowledgement and “everyone was invited to participate” – as Šalamun
                described it,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn10" n="10"> Šalamun, “Govor 2000,”
                    4.</note> the new Slovenian world witnessed <hi rend="italic">the open
                    season</hi> – a hunting season for predators engaging in privatisation,
                accumulation of weapons, ruthless politics and the like. The aptness of circuses
                without bread, i.e. either political or ideological wars, including what was
                practically an online civil war, was never under question. What is more, the lack of
                cognitive powers and a greater focus on money, adrenaline and human indifference, as
                opposed to the spirit, attest to such significant decline in values. Slovenians
                failed to become "moral juggernauts", as the nation's fulfilment was envisaged by
                Edvard Kocbek.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn11" n="11"> Edvard Kocbek, “Slovenski
                    človek” [The Slovenian Man], <hi rend="italic">Dejanje</hi> 1, No. 1 (1938): 2.
                </note> Intolerance and aggression prevailed, Slovenians did not succeed in morally
                withstanding the civilising momentum. These two topics were best dealt with by one
                of the leading Slovenian experts in the field of psychoanalysis, Dr Matjaž Lunaček,
                and an observer of Slovenians, the academic named Niko Grafenauer. When asked about
                which type of personality is the most characteristic for the Slovenian society at
                this moment, Lunaček replied:</p>
            <quote>“Most definitely the narcissistic one since the social environment enables or
                even demands to develop a personality of such type. Everybody endeavours to take
                care of themselves by pushing others away. Due to the increasing workload we can, to
                some extent, talk about obsessiveness.”</quote>
            <p>The generation who grew up in a system that slowly slipped into today's situation
                lacks ethical and moral norms. “Inculpability and impertinence are the biggest
                mischiefs in our society.” Besides that, the politicians are completely ignorant of
                the real situation in the country. Just like the clergy, the politicians should
                visit a psychoanalyst to</p>
            <quote>“develop an awareness of their deeds. Being in touch with reality is, in fact, an
                aspect that is developed only to a limited extent in a narcissistic population.
                Compared to other professions of special significance, politicians mainly possess a
                combination of ambitiousness and a steep career upward trajectory. The situation of
                this kind is anything but stable. However, it is a marvellous opportunity for the
                functioning of narcissists.”</quote>
            <p>However, the employers who encouraged the crisis of values, also took advantage of
                this. If we take history into consideration,</p>
            <quote>"we find that worker's rights increased due to huge efforts and extensive
                sacrifices. But then neoliberalism came and brought with it the possibility to
                exploit the workers to a great extent. Employers do not feel any moral obligation
                towards their employees with there being such vast amounts of unemployed people. It
                is a regressive process and a torpedoing of society and of a state in which
                employers try to establish their own order. Countries with tradition are able to
                fight this, while Slovenia is merely letting it all happen freely. Despite legal
                standards that regulate the attitude of employers towards employees, there have
                always been options to circumvent the law."<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn12" n="12">
                    Matjaž Lunaček, ”Največje zlo v naši družbi sta nekrivdnost in brezsramnost”
                    [The Biggest Evil in Our Society are Blamelessness and Shamelessness], acquired
                    8 June 2016, <ref
                        target="http://siol.net/novice/siol/psihoanalitik-matjaz-lunacek-najvecje-zlo-v-nasi-druzbi-sta-nekrivdnost-in-brezsramnost-242309"
                        >http://siol.net/novice/siol/psihoanalitik-matjaz-lunacek-najvecje-zlo-v-nasi-druzbi-sta-nekrivdnost-in-brezsramnost-242309</ref>.</note></quote>
            <p>This enables “the ruling caste” to ruthlessly suppress social sense and silence the
                employees' voices, while mobbing casts its victims into social isolation; in it,
                they fall into a complex state of anxiety, depression and addiction that prevents
                them from functioning normally, resulting in a substantial diminution of the quality
                of their lives.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn13" n="13"> Matija Grah, Borut Škodlar
                    and Bojana Avguštin Avčin, “Na robu obupa, na robu blaznosti. Mobing, psihično
                    nasilje na delovnem mestu“ [At the edge of despair, at the edge of insanity.
                    Mobbing, psychological harassment at work], <hi rend="italic">Delo: sobotna
                        priloga</hi>, 10 March 2012, 10, 11. </note> Even though there are legal
                instruments which exist to protect employees from mobbing in the EU and
                    Slovenia,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn14" n="14">
                    <hi rend="italic">MOBING</hi>, acquired 29 June 2016, <ref
                        target="http://www.mobing.si/slo/pravna_ureditev.html"
                        >http://www.mobing.si/slo/pravna_ureditev.html</ref>.</note> only a few have
                the courage to resort to these laws. </p>
            <p>Niko Grafenauer shared a similar point of view a while ago, believing that the
                suicide in Slovenia now exists only in one comprehensive form. The reason for this
                situation cannot be attributed to anyone other than us. We are what we are –
                quarrellers, clique members, thieves, cynics, show-offs etc. In short, we are
                provincials without any vision and without any sense of civic self-responsibility.
                “It does not matter what others do to us,” once said Dušan Pirjevec, “but it is
                important what we do to ourselves.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn15" n="15"> Niko
                    Grafenauer, “Smo vaška srenja brez vizije in državljanske odgovornosti” [We are
                    a village community without a vision and civic responsibility], <hi
                        rend="italic">Delo: sobotna priloga</hi>, 29 November 2011, 26.</note>
                Obviously, the consolation from the first (and also the second) Yugoslavia does no
                longer apply. The same goes for comparisons with other nations, as we are only
                responsible for ourselves. We need to take a look in the mirror. And Hribar’s soul,
                intertwined with celestial global dynamics, as he wrote in his farewell letter on 18
                April 1941,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn16" n="16"> Vasilij Melik, “Ivan Hribar in
                    njegovi Spomini” [Ivan Hribar and his Memories], in: Ivan Hribar,
                    <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Moji spomini: II del </hi>[My memories:
                    part II] (Ljubljana: Slovenska matica, 1984), 654. </note> still awaits the
                Slovenians (which is probably why those who hear this national signifier when
                travelling around the world don not seem to want to acknowledge each other). However
                in an interview for <hi rend="italic">Misteriji</hi> magazine, a pamphlet on the
                verge of medicine and other sciences, conducted in May 2014, Slovenian ambassador
                Bojan Grobovšek talks about his book entitle<hi rend="italic">d Zakaj Slovenija ni
                    Švica (Why Slovenia is not Switzerland)</hi>, in which he speaks in favour of
                rendering the Slovenian language as half as important in terms of being the official
                language. According to Grobovšek, "it would probably be extremely good for Slovenia
                to introduce another official language – English, to be exact – next to
                    Slovenian."<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn17" n="17"> Bojan Grobovšek, “Zakaj
                    Slovenija ni Švica” [Why is Slovenia not Switzerland], <hi rend="italic"
                        >Misteriji</hi> 21, No. 250 (2014): 25.</note> Less than three weeks after
                the 25<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> anniversary of independence, on 15 July 2016 –
                after the first reading of the Act amending the Higher Education Act as proposed by
                the Slovenian government, the National Assembly of the Republic of Slovenia adopted
                the amendment of the aforementioned law with 46 votes for and 15 against. The
                adoption of the amendment permits teaching in foreign languages, namely English, at
                Slovenian universities. For now, this amendment serves as a legal basis for
                neglecting Slovenian in tertiary education. This might even result in a paradoxical
                situation in which lectures by Slovenian professors for Slovenian students at
                Slovenian universities would be held in English. The reason for this subservient
                linguistic suicide is not rooted abroad but in those Slovenian university circles
                who consider Slovenian as less appealing in terms of business. “Reading room
                exaltation” cannot be a form of resistance to this phenomenon, according to the
                opinion expressed in a parliamentary discussion on 15 July by Saša Tabaković, a
                member of the Stranka modernega centra political party.<note place="foot"
                    xml:id="ftn18" n="18"> 21<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> regular session of the
                    National Assembly of the Republic of Slovenia, 15 July 2016.</note> If the
                amendments of the proposed bill are adopted in the aforementioned law, we can
                illustrate Dr Boris A. Novak's opinion on the position of the culture expressed
                fifteen years ago by declaring that the Slovenian language is exposed to a threat by
                the state itself.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn19" n="19"> Boris A. Novak, “V
                    slovenskem nacionalnem značaju je premalo mediteranskega duha” [There is too
                    little Mediterranean spirit in the Slovenian national character], <hi
                        rend="italic">Primorski dnevnik</hi>, 7 August 2001, 8.</note> At the round
                table entitled “Zagovor slovenščine (Defending Slovenian language)” held on 13 July
                2016 at Slovenska matica in Ljubljana, Boris A. Novak, a poet, essayist, stage
                director, lecturer at the Department of Comparative Literature and Literary Theory
                at the Faculty of Arts Ljubljana, Slovenian, cosmopolitan, guest lecturer at
                American universities, and translator of more than ten languages, including from
                Slovenian to English and back, expressed his disapproval towards Anglicising changes
                and amendments in the Act Amending the Higher Education Act.<note place="foot"
                    xml:id="ftn20" n="20"> Boris A. Novak, “Zagovor slovenščine” [Defending
                    Slovenian language], <hi rend="italic">Avdio/video ǀ za govor SLOVENŠČINE</hi>,
                    acquired 18 September 2016, <ref
                        target="http://www.zagovor-slovenscine.si/audiovideo/"
                        >http://www.zagovor-slovenscine.si/audiovideo/</ref>, 3<hi rend="superscript">rd</hi> and 4<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>
                    part.</note> Fifteen years ago he said:</p> <quote>“No foreigner and no other culture are
                more harmful to Slovenian culture than Slovenians themselves. If politics becomes
                cynical, only praises consumerism and treats culture (and language – note by J. P.)
                with ignorance, then our future is looking bleak. I believe we are bad at opening up
                to and shutting off from others. Instead of being open to new things when needed,
                our attitude resembles the one of a provincial introvert. And then whenever there is
                an opportunity for us to protect our cultural identity dauntlessly, we are willing
                to trade it in for a small amount of money. This petty tradesman mentality could
                cost us a fortune."<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn21" n="21"> Novak, “V slovenskem
                    nacionalnem značaju je premalo mediteranskega duha,” 8.</note></quote> <p>We must mention
                Anton Korošec's words from 13 March 1923 about Slovenian unwillingness to drown in
                the seas of Serbo-Croatian culture (currently English culture): “Who could blame
                    us?”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn22" n="22"> “Veličasten shod javnih in
                    zasebnih nameščencev” [Impressive rally of the public and private post-holders],
                        <hi rend="italic">Slovenec</hi>, 15 March 1923, 2. </note> – At this point
                we should emphasise that, in reality, Slovenians should protect the Slovenian
                language even more, since less and less people are able to express themselves
                verbally or in written form in proper Slovenian, not to mention the universal
                disrespect of intellectual work.</p>
            <p> A historian and politician, Dr Drago Lončar wrote, in his renowned work <hi
                    rend="italic">Politično življenje Slovencev (The Political Life of
                    Slovenians)</hi> which was published in 1921, about how Slovenians "managed to
                escape the yoke of foreign subordination. Now the history has given the Slovenians a
                mission to prove that they are capable of the greatest human art form: <hi
                    rend="italic">to govern themselves</hi>."<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn23"
                    n="23"> Dragotin Lončar,
                    <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Politično življenje Slovencev: od 4. januarja 1797. do 6. januarja 1919. leta </hi>[The
                    Political Life of Slovenians: from 4 January 1797 to 6 January 1919] (Ljubljana:
                    Slovenska matica, 1921), 129.</note> At that time, the otherwise down-to-earth
                Lončar exaggerated as he wrote down the date of July 1921, the month which followed
                the approval of the centralist and unitarian Vidovdan Constitution, under the
                introduction to his book. Seven decades later, the situation changed. That was the
                actual time of “the greatest human art form”. Some of the art pieces in which it
                manifests itself in Slovenia have already been mentioned here. Nonetheless, the
                systems of the state are in operation and the state is a part of the international
                environment, while we've also witnessed a meteoric rise of some political parties in
                the last couple of years.</p>
            <p>These findings offer a great variety of possibilities for research. The branch of
                science that made the most out of these possibilities is politology. These topics
                were also addressed in the
                <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Pogovori o prihodnosti Slovenije (Talks about the future of Slovenia) </hi>held
                at the cabinet of the President of the Republic of Slovenia, Janez Drnovšek, in
                years 2003–2005 (in years 2009–2011 there were also three talks held by the
                President of the Republic, Dr Danilo Türk)<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn24" n="24"
                    ><hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve"> COBISS / OPAC</hi>, view 18 June 2016,
                        <ref target="http://www.cobiss.si/scripts/cobiss?ukaz=getid&amp;lani=si"
                        >http://www.cobiss.si/scripts/cobiss?ukaz=getid&amp;lani=si</ref><hi
                        rend="Hyperlink">. S</hi>earch parameter Pogovori pri predsedniku republike,
                    1–3.</note> and by the circle of <hi rend="italic">Nova revija</hi> magazine
                    (<hi rend="italic">Kdo smo in zakaj imamo državo (Who we are and why we have a
                    state)</hi> (1996), <hi rend="italic">Ura evropske resnice za Slovenijo (The
                    Time for the European Truth for Slovenia)</hi> (1997), <hi rend="italic">Nekaj
                    je treba storiti (Something has to be done)</hi> (2003)).<note place="foot"
                    xml:id="ftn25" n="25"> France Bučar et al., “Kdo smo in zakaj imamo državo.
                    Pobuda za ponovno presojo slovenskega narodnega položaja” [Who are we and why do
                    we have a country. Initiative for a reassessment of the Slovenian national
                    situation], <hi rend="italic">Nova revija</hi> 15, No. 167 (1996),
                    supplement<hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve"> Ampak</hi>, 2–6. Drago Jančar
                    et al.,
                    <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Ura evropske resnice za Slovenijo </hi>[The
                    Time for the European Truth for Slovenia] (Buenos Aires: Svobodna Slovenija,
                    1997). Barbara Brezigar et al., “Nekaj je treba storiti. Državljanska pobuda”
                    [Something has to be done. The citizens’ initiative], <hi rend="italic"
                        >Dolenjski list</hi>, <ref
                        target="http://cobiss4.izum.si/scripts/cobiss?ukaz=DISP&amp;id=2027528368230080&amp;rec=-16377602&amp;sid=1&amp;fmt=11"
                        >6 March 2003, 20</ref>.</note> The process of democratisation and
                attainment of independence that took place during the 80s and at the beginning of
                the 90s was carefully studied by historiography. For the period that followed,
                historians can not offer much due to the lack of funding for research projects that
                would focus on these times. Nonetheless, we are proud of two exceptional monographs
                on the transition of Slovenian economy from socialism to capitalism in the years
                between 1990 and 2004 or the Slovenian parliamentarism between 1992 and 2012 written
                by two researches from the Institute of Contemporary History, Dr Aleksander
                    Lorenčič<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn26" n="26"> Aleksander Lorenčič,
                    <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Prelom s starim in začetek novega. Tranzicija slovenskega gospodarstva iz socializma v kapitalizem (1990–2004) </hi>[The
                    end of an old regime and the beginning of a new one. Slovenian economy’s
                    transition from socialism to capitalism (1990–2004)] (Ljubljana: Inštitut za
                    novejšo zgodovino, 2012).</note> and Dr Jure Gašparič.<note place="foot"
                    xml:id="ftn27" n="27"> Jure Gašparič,
                    <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Državni zbor 1992–2012. O slovenskem parlamentarizmu </hi>[National
                    Assembly 1992–2012. About the Slovenian parliamentarianism] (Ljubljana: Inštitut
                    za novejšo zgodovino, 2012).</note> Important findings were also made by a
                professor from the Faculty of Arts at the University of Ljubljana, Dr Božo Repe. In
                his book about the first president of the Republic of Slovenia, Milan Kučan, Repe
                illustrated the political development of the Republic of Slovenia until 2002 by
                describing Kučan's activities.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn28" n="28"> Božo Repe,
                    <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Milan Kučan, prvi predsednik </hi>[Milan
                    Kučan, the First President] (Ljubljana: Modrijan, 2015).</note> Even flames
                cannot destroy this writing.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn29" n="29"> This is a
                    reference to the unsuccessful burning of the mentioned book on 19 December 2015
                    in front of Milan Kučan's residence in Ljubljana. The book burning was organised
                    by a small group of citizens of the Republic of Slovenia. </note></p>
            <p>Nevertheless, to summarise the main findings of the monographs which we pointed out,
                it is necessary to emphasize that the transition of the economy and the transition
                to an environment more open in terms of society and trade, deserve to be treated
                positively from the historical stance regardless of the wild privatisation that
                casts a shadow over this process. The main reason for such intense privatisation of
                social and national property was in the lack of legal bases from the very beginning.
                What is more, despite the warnings of competent institutions, the Slovenian
                Parliament (often a political "rooster coop"– note by. J. P.) chose not to react.
                Between the years 1990 and 2004 the social property suffered a loss higher than 104
                billion tolars. A small percentage of the population definitely managed to pile up a
                fortune in that period. The government then was a group of amateurs and neither the
                politics nor the experts could handle this situation (something similar happened in
                other transition countries). It turned out that many Slovenian companies were run by
                dishonest and greedy managers whose main objective was profiteering. Many whom these
                fraudulent deeds are attributed to acquired their fortune by legal means. This can
                mostly be attributed to the legal system and politics as the National Assembly did
                not adopt the much needed laws. Today's situation in society and the economy is not
                a result of yesterday's events or occurrences in the past couple of years. The
                answers to why this has happened should be sought at the beginning of our transition
                period. Slovenia didn't only choose the market economy, but also chose capitalism
                and everything that goes with it. Slovenian capitalism still has social overtones,
                but a capitalism adjusted to human needs, like the one we had imagined, is just an
                    illusion.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn30" n="30"> Lorenčič, <hi rend="italic"
                        >Prelom s starim in začetek novega</hi>, 444–46, 448, 451, 452.</note> We
                believe that the leading Slovenian analyst of social, cultural and political
                phenomena in Slovenia, Dr Janez Markeš, made a good observation by saying that the
                symptom of a “new neoliberal Slovenia” occurred. Gradually and inconspicuously, this
                symptom is ousting the solidarity from a society that, in the end, does not care for
                growing inequalities. With the intention to eliminate the old socialist regime, the
                society does not perceive the solidarity as an essential part of itself.<note
                    place="foot" xml:id="ftn31" n="31"> Janez Markeš, “Let nad nekim gnezdom”
                    (Flying over a nest), <hi rend="italic">Delo: sobotna priloga</hi>, 27 August
                    2016, 7.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Another significant emphasis from Markeš's findings is that it is</p> <quote>“important to
                determine what Slovenia as a state should look like in the future as it is becoming
                more and more obvious that growing inequalities and diminishing solidarity do not
                contribute to anything. However, the everyday speeches by ministers are still
                dominated by economic issues. Besides that, there is a shortage of political debates
                that would revolve around concepts of a socially strong state which would show
                effort to diminish social inequality.”</quote> <p>It seems that after many years of defunding
                social programmes,</p> <quote>"it is time to rethink which type of capitalism is best suitable
                for Slovenia. Two things are clear: the inequality is growing to the extent that it
                is no longer acceptable, even though it is unnoticeable to many, and that to speak
                of neoliberalism as of an immense illusion that does not contribute to the state in
                any way and that may, in the form of extreme social situations, nationalism and
                other phenomena, cause almost irreparable damage, is of public interest. It appears
                that capitalism deserves a second chance to promote innovation and develop business
                flexibility and capabilities. However, in the last two decades, capitalism is being
                substituted with neoliberalism, a self-referencing ideology of elites that Slovenia,
                due to its size, will never be able to have. And it seems right that Slovenia is
                free of elites, as they are a mockery to humanism and to the freethinking view on
                life which is considered as a basic value and protected by the constitution."<note
                    place="foot" xml:id="ftn32" n="32"> Ibid.</note></quote>
            <p>The analysis of the transition in politics is the topic of interest of the second
                monograph that primarily addresses the question of trustworthiness. In the political
                emotional rhetoric of the modern state, trustworthiness has played quite a
                significant role from the 19th century onwards. “Trust is the most essential aspect
                of life. Everything is based on trust, it even became a part of the constitutional
                system.” The opinion polls carried out during the year serve to determine the level
                of trust in political institutions. The results show that the National Assembly is
                considered less trustworthy, as it is always among the least trusted. On the scale
                of trustworthiness, only the political parties are traditionally lower. If we look
                at the prime minister instead of the government as a whole, we can notice that the
                prime minister enjoys a higher degree of trust, while the president of the republic
                is considered as the most trustworthy. This is not surprising, as people are not
                exactly familiar with a single politician's doings. They remember only the
                improprieties, mistakes and scandals that accompany the parliament's actions. In
                addition, politicians are not members of unions or assemblies (they do have their
                own association). They deal with their rivals in an uncensored and unsympathetic
                way, unlike in any other profession. The question remains: how long and to what
                extent can trust be left to wither, if it is supposed to be one of the pillars of
                    democracy.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn33" n="33"> Gašparič, <hi rend="italic"
                        >Državni zbor 1992–2012</hi>, 296, 300, 301.</note> This might be closely
                related to the fact pointed out in the third monograph: that the first president of
                the republic tried to reach the so-called Third National Concensus (after the
                national unification at the plebiscite for Slovenia's independence and the adoption
                of the Constitution of the Republic of Slovenia). This was an agreement with the
                purpose to determine what to do with the people and the state after the independence
                and after joining the Euro-Atlantic Group. The consensus on ethical foundations of
                Slovenia and the sense of its existence were not reached. However, even upon the
                termination of his presidency, Kučan invested a lot of effort into reaching this
                    consensus.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn34" n="34"> Repe, <hi rend="italic"
                        >Milan Kučan, prvi predsednik</hi>, 500, 581.</note></p>
            <p> What is there to say at the end? There is an enormous amount of work to be done and
                the longer Slovenia remains independent, the more work will have to be carried out.
                Hopefully, it will be carried out not only by implementing new approaches based on
                anthropological-interpretative and theoretical bases that avoid historical aspects
                and often remain unfulfilled, but also by considering the public opinion and
                citizens' needs. Here is to hoping that this wish has its consequences. Just like Dr
                Karel Triller, a prominent representative of the Liberal Narodna napredna stranka
                (National Progressive Party) hoped in 1906, when elaborating on the programme of his
                    party.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn35" n="35"> Karel Triller, “Pred shodom
                    narodnonapredne stranke” [Before the Assembly of the National Progressive
                    Party], <hi rend="italic">Slovenski narod</hi>, 23 March 1906, 2.</note> I also
                owe you an explanation about the other half of my life: according to the principle
                of freedom of choice, I have kept it. I do not know what the person from Vegova
                Street did with his half. </p>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="bibliography">
                <head>Sources and Literature</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Electronic sources:</head>
                    <bibl>21<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> regular meeting of the National Assembly
                        of the Republic of Slovenia. <hi rend="italic">TV Slovenija, III
                            programme</hi>, 15 July 2016.</bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">COBISS / OPAC. </hi>View 18 June
                        2016. <ref
                            target="http://www.cobiss.si/scripts/cobiss?ukaz=getid&amp;lani=si"
                            >http://www.cobiss.si/scripts/cobiss?ukaz=getid&amp;lani=si</ref><hi
                            rend="italic">.</hi></bibl>
                    <bibl>Lunaček, Matjaž. ”Največje zlo v naši družbi sta nekrivdnost in
                        brezsramnost” [The Biggest Evil in Our Society are Blamelessness and
                        Shamelessness]. Acquired 8 June 2016. <ref
                            target="http://siol.net/novice/siol/psihoanalitik-matjaz-lunacek-najvecje-zlo-v-nasi-druzbi-sta-nekrivdnost-in-brezsramnost-242309"
                            >http://siol.net/novice/siol/psihoanalitik-matjaz-lunacek-najvecje-zlo-v-nasi-druzbi-sta-nekrivdnost-in-brezsramnost-242309</ref>.</bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="italic">MOBBING</hi>. Acquired 29 June 2016. <ref
                            target="http://www.mobing.si/slo/pravna_ureditev.html"
                            >http://www.mobing.si/slo/pravna_ureditev.html</ref>.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Literature:</head>
                    <bibl>Bučar, France. “Kdo smo in zakaj imamo državo. Pobuda za ponovno presojo
                        slovenskega narodnega položaja” [Who are we and why do we have a country.
                        Initiative for a reassessment of the Slovenian national situation]. <hi
                            rend="italic">Nova revija</hi> 15, No. 167 (1996), supplement <hi
                            rend="italic">Ampak</hi>, 2–6.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Gašparič,
                        Jure.<hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve"> Državni zbor 1992–2012. O slovenskem parlamentarizmu</hi>
                        [National Assembly 1992–2012. About the Slovenian parliamentarianism]<hi
                            rend="italic">.</hi> Ljubljana: Inštitut za novejšo zgodovino,
                        2012.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Grobovšek, Bojan. <hi rend="italic">Zakaj Slovenija ni Švica</hi> [Why is
                        Slovenia not Switzerland]. Tomišelj: Alpemedia, 2014.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Grobovšek, Bojan. “Zakaj Slovenija ni Švica” [Why is Slovenia not
                        Switzerland]. <hi rend="italic">Misteriji</hi> 21, No. 250 (2014): 25,
                        26.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Jančar, Drago et al.
                        <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Ura evropske resnice za Slovenijo </hi>[The
                        Time for the European Truth for Slovenia]. Buenos Aires: Svobodna Slovenija,
                        1997. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Kermauner, Taras. “Vladimir Bartol – predhodnik današnje slovenske moderne
                        literature” [Vladimir Bartol – the predecessor of today’s modern Slovenian
                        literature]. In: Vladimir Bartol, <hi rend="italic">Demon in Eros: Al
                            Araf</hi> [Demon and Eros: Al Araf], 423–45<hi rend="italic">.</hi>
                        Ljubljana: Mladinska knjiga, 1974.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Kocbek, Edvard. “Slovenski človek” [The Slovenian Man]. <hi rend="italic"
                            >Dejanje</hi> 1, No. 1 (1938): 1–3. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Lavrič, Jože, Josip Mal and France Stelè, eds.
                        <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Spominski zbornik Slovenije. Ob dvajsetletnici Kraljevine Jugoslavije </hi>[Memorial
                        booklet of Slovenia. The twentieth anniversary of the Kingdom of
                        Yugoslavia]. Ljubljana: Jubilej, 1939. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Lončar, Dragotin.
                        <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Politično življenje Slovencev: od 4. januarja 1797. do 6. januarja 1919. leta </hi>[The
                        Political Life of Slovenians: from 4 January 1797 to 6 January 1919].
                        Ljubljana: Slovenska matica, 1921.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Mal, Josip, ed.
                        <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Slovenci v desetletju 1918–1928. Zbornik razprav iz kulturne, gospodarske in politične zgodovine </hi>[Slovenians
                        in the decade 1918–1928. A collection of papers on cultural, economical and
                        political history]. Ljubljana: Leonova družba, 1928.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Melik, Vasilij. “Ivan Hribar in njegovi Spomini” [Ivan Hribar and his
                        Memories]. In: Ivan Hribar,
                        <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Moji spomini: II del </hi>[My
                        memories: part II], 619–61. Ljubljana: Slovenska matica, 1984.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Novak, Boris A. “Zagovor slovenščine” [Defending Slovenian language]. <hi
                            rend="italic">Avdio/video ǀ za govor SLOVENŠČINE</hi>. Acquired 18
                        September 2016. <ref target="http://www.zagovor-slovenscine.si/audiovideo/"
                            >http://www.zagovor-slovenscine.si/audiovideo/</ref>, 3<hi rend="superscript">rd</hi> and 4<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>
                        part.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Perovšek, Jurij.
                        <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Liberalizem in vprašanje slovenstva. Nacionalna politika liberalnega tabora v letih 1918–1929 </hi>[Liberalism
                        and the Question of Slovenianism. National Policy in the Liberal Camp from
                        1918 to 1929]. Ljubljana: Modrijan, 1996.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Repe, Božo.
                        <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Milan Kučan, prvi predsednik </hi>[Milan
                        Kučan, the First President]. Ljubljana: Modrijan, 2015.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Šalamun, Tomaž. “Govor na prireditvi ob slovenskem kulturnem prazniku
                        2000” [Speech at the event held for the Prešeren Day 2000]. In:
                        <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Prešernov sklad 2000 </hi>[Prešerenʼs
                        Fund 2000], 3–5. Ljubljana: upravni odbor Prešernovega sklada, 2000).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Newspaper sources:</head>
                    <bibl>Brezigar, Barbara et al. “Nekaj je treba storiti. Državljanska pobuda”
                        [Something has to be done. The citizens’ initiative]. <hi rend="italic"
                            >Dolenjski list</hi>, <ref
                            target="http://cobiss4.izum.si/scripts/cobiss?ukaz=DISP&amp;id=2027528368230080&amp;rec=-16377602&amp;sid=1&amp;fmt=11"
                            >6 March 2003, 20</ref>.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Bucik, Marko. “Raj z napako. Slovenija leta 2041. V kakšni državi si želim
                        živeti čez 25 let in kako priti do nje? ” [A flawed paradise. Slovenia in
                        2041. In what kind of country do I want to live in 25 years and how to
                        achieve it?]. <hi rend="italic">Delo</hi>, 7 June 2016, 5.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Grafenauer, Niko. “Smo vaška srenja brez vizije in državljanske
                        odgovornosti” [We are a village community without a vision and civic
                        responsibility]. <hi rend="italic">Delo: sobotna priloga</hi>, 29 November
                        2011, 24–26.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Grah, Matija, Borut Škodlar and Bojana Avguštin Avčin. “Na robu obupa, na
                        robu blaznosti. Mobing, psihično nasilje na delovnem mestu” (At the edge of
                        despair, at the edge of insanity. Mobbing, psychological harassment at
                        work]. <hi rend="italic">Delo: sobotna priloga</hi>, 10 March 2012, 10,
                        11.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Hribar, Ivan. “Uprava Jugoslavije” [Yugoslavia administration]. <hi
                            rend="italic">Slovenec</hi>, 15 October 1918, 2.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Markeš, Janez. “Let nad nekim gnezdom” [Flying over a nest]. <hi
                            rend="italic">Delo: sobotna priloga</hi>, 27 August 2016, 7.</bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="italic">Neodvisnost</hi>, 1 December 1936, 1. “Neodvisnost”
                        [Independence].</bibl>
                    <bibl>Novak, Boris A. “V slovenskem nacionalnem značaju je premalo
                        mediteranskega duha” [There is too little Mediterranean spirit in the
                        Slovenian national character]. <hi rend="italic">Primorski dnevnik</hi>, 7
                        August 2001, 8.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Ribičič, Mitja. “Patriotizem” [Patriotism]. <hi rend="italic">Učiteljski
                            tovariš</hi>, 13 January 1927, 2.</bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="italic">Slovenec</hi>, 15 March 1923, 2. “Veličasten shod javnih
                        in zasebnih nameščencev” [Impressive rally of the public and private
                        post-holders].</bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="italic">Slovenski narod</hi>, 26 March 1918, 2. “Praznik
                        slovenskega ženstva” [Slovenian Women Day].</bibl>
                    <bibl>Šalamun, Tomaž. “Duma 1964.” <hi rend="italic">Naši razgledi</hi>, 9 May
                        1964, 178.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Triller, Karel. “Pred shodom narodnonapredne stranke” [Before the Assembly
                        of the National Progressive Party]. <hi rend="italic">Slovenski narod</hi>,
                        23 March 1906, 2.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
            <div type="summary" xml:lang="sl">
                <head type="main">KAJ REČI? – OB PETINDVAJSETLETNICI OSAMOSVOJITVE</head>
                <head>POVZETEK</head>
                <docAuthor>Jurij Perovšek</docAuthor>
                <p> V letih slovenske samostojnosti, ki so nekaj časa zdržala pretvorbo v »zgodbo o
                    uspehu«, smo se srečali tudi z vprašanjem, kaj so o sebi razkrili Slovenci po
                    odhodu iz večnacionalnih držav, v katerih so po svojem končnem spoznanju videli
                    nacionalni in demokratični potop. To vprašanje je v zgodovinskem položaju po
                    letu 1991 še toliko bolj pritegujoče, ker nad nami ni ne dunajskega, ne
                    beograjskega pokrova in ne pokrova prejšnje monistične politične oblasti. </p>
                <p> Po odhodu iz Avstro-Ogrske monarhije v Kraljevino Srbov, Hrvatov in
                    Slovencev/Jugoslavijo leta 1918 so Slovenci pričakovali, da bodo prišli v
                    »zaželeno deželo«. A ni bilo tako. Z avtonomijo ni bilo nič, narode so ustavno
                    izbrisali in prelili v srbsko-hrvaško-slovensko narodnost, uradni jezik je nosil
                    prav tako ime, t. i. slovenskih polkov iz avstrijske dobe ni bilo več, slabih
                    dvajset let kasneje, na tedanji državni praznik 1. decembra 1936, pa je
                    mariborska <hi rend="italic">Neodvisnost</hi> k temu še zapisala, da se Slovenci
                    »ne čutimo skoraj več kot enota, ampak kot mešanica različnih plemen, med
                    katerimi ni nobene skupnosti, ampak je samo neizprosen, brezobziren in brutalen
                    boj do iztrebljenja. Ta plemena so ,klerikalci’, ,liberalci’, ,marksisti’ in
                    drugi, kakor se že vsi imenujejo. Vlogo podpihovanja strasti in sovraštva pa
                    vrši naš od teh strank odvisni tisk, ki dan za dnem zastruplja naše ozračje.
                    Zato ni v njem, in po njem tudi v naši javnosti, nikjer nobenih vrhovnih in
                    nespremenljivih narodnih načel, nikjer nobenih jasnih in trdnih ciljev.« </p>
                <p> In naših petindvajset let? Slovenci so dosegli meddržavnopravni položaj –
                    Republiko Slovenijo, njihov jezik je iz druge Jugoslavije prenesel svoj uradni
                    značaj, dobili smo svojo vojsko, kultura in šport sta požela več izjemnih
                    uspehov v tujini, mediji so se še bolj razvili. Slovenci so se poslavljali kot
                    »prehlajeni predmet zgodovine«. Avtor omenjene oznake Tomaž Šalamun je to
                    izrekel v slavnostni besedi ob slovenskem kulturnem prazniku leta 2000.
                    Slovenijo je videl kot lepo, relativno bogato, živo in ustvarjalno deželo. Čudež
                    civilizacijskega pospeška se je dogajal z veliko silo. </p>
                <p> Vendar je nastal »raj z napako«. Ideološka »plemena« so ostala in poleg starih
                    uporabljajo še nova orodja boja – izkušnjo drugega svetovnega spopada, prejšnje
                    družbe in zdaj še slovenske osamosvojitve. V novem slovenskem svetu je, medtem
                    ko so tisti, ki so s polnimi pljuči zadihali narodno čustvo in pričakovali
                    zgodovinski dvig slovenstva, nastopila »the open season«: lovska sezona
                    olastninjevalnih in drugih predatorjov. Prikladnost iger brez kruha – ideoloških
                    in političnih vojn, vključno s tisto, skorajda državljansko, na spletu, za tako
                    početje ni (bila) vprašljiva. Ob tem pomanjkanje spoznavnih moči, potovanja v
                    denar, adrenalin, človeško brezbrižnost in čimmanj v duhá, govorijo o veliki
                    vrednostni oseki. O tem sta najbolje spregovorila eden vodilnih slovenskih
                    psihoanalitikov dr. Matjaž Lunaček in premišljevalec slovenstva akademik Niko
                    Grafenauer. Prvi je na vprašanje, kateremu tipu pacienta ta trenutek ustreza
                    slovenska družba, predlani odgovoril: »Zagotovo narcističnemu, saj družbeno
                    okolje to omogoča, celo zahteva. (…) Generacija, že odrasla v sistemu, ki je
                    drsel v današnjo situacijo, nima razvitih etičnih in moralnih norm. »Največje
                    zlo v naši družbi sta nekrivdnost in brezsramnost.« Podobno je leta 2011
                    ugotovil Niko Grafenauer, ki se mu glede na položaj, ki ga zaznava, »slovenski
                    samomor prikazuje le še v eni sami celostni obliki. Za to stanje pa ni več kriv
                    nihče drug od nas, saj smo, kakršni smo – prepirljivci, klikaši, tatovi, ciniki,
                    nastopači itd. – skratka srenja brez vizije in državljanske samoodgovornosti.«
                    Ob tem je leta 2014 veleposlanik Bojan Grobovšek zagovarjal še razpolovitev
                    veljave slovenskega uradnega jezika. Po njegovem »bi bilo za Slovenijo morda
                    zelo dobro, če bi se poleg nacionalnega uradnega jezika slovenščine uvedlo še en
                    uradni jezik, konkretno angleščina«. V resnici pa bi bilo dobro, če bi pazili na
                    slovenščino, saj njeno znanje v govoru in pisavi postaja vedno bolj oddaljena
                    dobrina. </p>
                <p> O povedanem je mnogo raziskovalnih izzivov. Najbolj jim je nasproti stopila
                    politologija, zgodili pa so se tudi <hi rend="italic">Pogovori o prihodnosti
                        Slovenije</hi> pri predsedniku republike dr. Janezu Drnovšku v letih
                    2003–2005 in predsedniku dr. Danilu Türku v letih 2009–2011, ter dejanja kroga
                        <hi rend="italic">Nove revije</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Kdo smo in zakaj imamo
                        državo</hi> (1996), <hi rend="italic">Ura evropske resnice za Slovenijo</hi>
                    (1997), <hi rend="italic">Nekaj je treba storiti</hi> (2003)). V proces
                    demokratizacije in osamosvojitve konec osemdesetih in v začetku devetdesetih let
                    prejšnjega stoletja se je kvalitetno poglobilo zgodovinopisje. Za kasnejši čas
                    zgodovinarji še ne moremo pokazati veliko, tudi zaradi nedodeljenih gmotnih
                    sredstev za izvedbo nanj osredinjenih raziskovalnih projektov. Vseeno pa se
                    lahko pohvalimo z odličnima monografijama raziskovalcev Inštituta za novejšo
                    zgodovino v Ljubljani – dr. Aleksandra Lorenčiča (<hi rend="italic">Prelom s
                        starim in začetek novega: tranzicija slovenskega gospodarstva iz socializma
                        v kapitalizem (1990–2004)</hi>, 2012) in dr. Jureta Gašpariča (<hi
                        rend="italic">Državni zbor 1992–2012: o slovenskem parlamentarizmu</hi>,
                    2012). Zunaj inštituta je slovenski politični razvoj po letu 1992 v svojo knjigo
                        <hi rend="italic">Milan Kučan, prvi predsednik</hi> (2015) vključil profesor
                    Filozofske fakultete Univerze v Ljubljani dr. Božo Repe. </p>
                <p>Dela je pred nami veliko in čim dlje bo živela Slovenija, tem več ga bo. Upajmo,
                    da kljub »antropološko-interpretativnim«, raznovrstnim resničnemu zgodovinskemu
                    tkivu ogibajočim se teoretskim in dostikrat le v literaturi slonečim novim
                    pristopom, tudi s posluhom za narod in njegove probleme. </p>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
