<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Project Outline: “Constitution and Development of Political Parties in
                    Germany from 1989/90 to the Present”</title>
                <author>
                    <forename>Sven</forename>
                    <surname>Jüngerkes</surname>
                    <roleName>PhD</roleName>
                    <affiliation>Kommission für Geschichte des Parlamentarismus und der politischen
                        Parteien</affiliation>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Schiffbauerdamm 40</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>D-10117 Berlin</addrLine>
                    </address>
                    <email>juengerkes@kgparl.de</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <forename>Tobias</forename>
                    <surname>Kaiser</surname>
                    <roleName>PhD</roleName>
                    <affiliation>Kommission für Geschichte des Parlamentarismus und der politischen
                        Parteien</affiliation>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Schiffbauerdamm 40</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>D-10117 Berlin</addrLine>
                    </address>
                    <email>kaiser@kgparl.de</email>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>2023-04-25</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>
                    <orgName xml:lang="sl">Inštitut za novejšo zgodovino</orgName>
                    <orgName xml:lang="en">Institute of Contemporary History</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Privoz 11</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>SI-1000 Ljubljana</addrLine>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>http://ojs.inz.si/pnz/article/view/4156</pubPlace>
                <date>2023</date>
                <availability status="free">
                    <licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title xml:lang="sl">Prispevki za novejšo zgodovino</title>
                <title xml:lang="en">Contributions to Contemporary History</title>
                <biblScope unit="volume">63</biblScope>
                <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
                <idno type="ISSN">2463-7807</idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source, born digital.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc xml:lang="en">
                <p>Contributions to Contemporary History is one of the central Slovenian scientific
                    historiographic journals, dedicated to publishing articles from the field of
                    contemporary history (the 19th and 20th century).</p>
                <p>The journal is published three times per year in Slovenian and in the following
                    foreign languages: English, German, Serbian, Croatian, Bosnian, Italian, Slovak
                    and Czech. The articles are all published with abstracts in English and
                    Slovenian as well as summaries in English.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <projectDesc xml:lang="sl">
                <p>Prispevki za novejšo zgodovino je ena osrednjih slovenskih znanstvenih
                    zgodovinopisnih revij, ki objavlja teme s področja novejše zgodovine (19. in 20.
                    stoletje).</p>
                <p>Revija izide trikrat letno v slovenskem jeziku in v naslednjih tujih jezikih:
                    angleščina, nemščina, srbščina, hrvaščina, bosanščina, italijanščina, slovaščina
                    in češčina. Članki izhajajo z izvlečki v angleščini in slovenščini ter povzetki
                    v angleščini.</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="sl"/>
                <language ident="en"/>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords xml:lang="en">
                    <term/>
                </keywords>
                <keywords xml:lang="sl">
                    <term>Rusija</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change><date>2023-09-26T10:40:46Z</date>
                    <name>Mihael Ojsteršek</name>
                    <desc>Pretvorba iz DOCX v TEI, dodatno kodiranje</desc>
                </change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <docAuthor>Sven Jüngerkes,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn1" n="*"><hi rend="bold">PhD,
                        Kommission für Geschichte des Parlamentarismus und der politischen Parteien,
                        Schiffbauerdamm 40, D-10117 Berlin; </hi><ref
                        target="mailto:juengerkes@kgparl.de"
                >juengerkes@kgparl.de</ref></note></docAuthor>
            <docAuthor>Tobias Kaiser<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn2" n="**"><hi rend="bold">PhD,
                        Kommission für Geschichte des Parlamentarismus und der politischen Parteien,
                        Schiffbauerdamm 40, D-10117 Berlin; </hi><ref
                        target="mailto:kaiser@kgparl.de">kaiser@kgparl.de</ref></note></docAuthor>
            <docImprint>
                <idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.51663/pnz.63.2.06</idno>
                <idno type="cobissType">Cobiss tip: 1.25</idno>
            </docImprint>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div>
                <head>Overview</head>
                <p>The KGParl lead joint network: “Parties and Party System after 1990”<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn3" n="1">The cooperation partners are the
                        party-affiliated (but formally independant) foundations: the
                        Friedrich-Ebert-Stiftung, the Konrad-Adenauer-Stiftung, the
                        Hanns-Seidel-Stiftung, the Heinrich-Böll-Stiftung, the
                        Friedrich-Naumann-Stiftung für die Freiheit and the Rosa-Luxemburg-Stiftung.
                        There are several PhD-candidates working on the topics mentioned in this
                        paper, see <ref target="https://kgparl.de/forschung/parteien-nach-1990/"
                            >https://kgparl.de/forschung/parteien-nach-1990/</ref>, accessed
                        April, 11, 2023).</note> examines the constitution and the transformation
                    of a new German party landscape after the reunification of 1990. The first focus
                    is on the establishment of party-political structures in the five new German
                    states after system transformation in 1989 and unification in October 1990.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn4" n="2">At the time of reunification, the old
                        Federal German Republic with its 11 federal states (in German: Bundesländer)
                        had a four-party system: Christian Democrats (Christian Democratic Union (
                        Christlich Demokratische Union/CDU), including the Bavarian only Christian
                        Social Union ( Christlich-Soziale Union in Bayern/CSU, the Social democratic
                        Party ( Sozialdemokratische Partei Deutschlands/SPD), the liberal Party (
                        Freie Demokratische Partei/FDP and the Greens ( Die Grünen), which were
                        focused on ecology and pacifism. In October 1990, the GDR joined the
                        territory of the Federal Republic of Germany and the old GDR districts
                        became 5 new federal states. The West German political structure, including
                        the party system, was extended to East Germany. The former GDR state party
                        Socialist Unity Party for Germany ( Sozialistische Einheitspartei
                        Deutschlands/SED, a forced merger of the Social Democrats in the GDR and the
                        communist party) renamed itself Party of the Democratic Socialism ( Partei
                        des demokratischen Sozialismis/PDS)</note> This is to evaluate the different
                    expectations in East and West Germany and the competing influence of the
                    established West German parties, which extended their organizations into the
                    territory of the former German Democratic Republic (GDR), in building what soon
                    was seen as an East German party system. Second, the effects and repercussions
                    of these processes in eastern Germany on the all-German party system should also
                    be examined: Did a co-transformation occur in western Germany? Did the
                    reunification perhaps even accelerate the fragmentation of the traditional
                    federal German party system which has been in place since 1983, when a new,
                    young party, the Greens (Die Grünen), succeeded in entering the German Bundestag
                    for the first time?</p>
                <p>The process of democratization in the GDR, from illegal opposition to the 1990
                    Volkskammer (parliament of the GDR) elections and the election of the all-German
                    Bundestag, is well researched. What remains controversial, however, is the
                    question of what long-term consequences the transfer of West German party
                    structures had for the emergence of a democratic culture in the territory of the
                    former GDR, respectively Germany as a whole. In view of the recruitment of
                    political leadership controlled by the party headquarters of the old Federal
                    German Republic and the appointment of functionaries in the administration and
                    judiciary who had been socialized in the West, was soon followed by discourse
                    and allegations about colonization of the east. <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn5"
                        n="3">See for example Dirk Oschmann, <hi rend="italic">Der Osten: eine
                            westdeutsche Erfindung</hi> (Berlin: Ullstein, 2023). Fritz Micklisch,
                            <hi rend="italic">Die Kolonisierung der DDR: wie die einst „lieben
                            Brüder und Schwestern im Osten“ von den kalten </hi><hi rend="italic"
                            >Kriegern im Westen gehasst, gedemütigt und bestraft werden</hi>. 1.
                        Aufl. (Berlin: Verlag am Park, 2011).</note></p>
                <p>The research project focuses on the period of the 1990s and early 2000s, but also
                    seeks answers to present problems. The 90s and early 2000s was a period in which
                    the internal structures of the nationally established parties reshaped. After
                    the decision to make Berlin the capital of a unified Germany, party headquarters
                    began to move organizations and structures from Bonn to Berlin. Even before the
                    unification they had already begun founding East German state associations or
                    appointing representatives for the east. This period of upheaval during the
                    first years of unification was not easy or free from conflict. A common
                    parliamentary practice between GDR politicians, who often had little experience
                    in politics as a profession, and West German professional politicians had yet to
                    be found. And even today one can still see great differences in mentality
                    between East and West that has led to a different style of politics in the east.
                        <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn6" n="4">See <hi rend="italic">Jahresbericht
                            der Bundesregierung zum Stand der Deutschen Einheit 2021</hi>, ed. German Federal Government (Bundestag Drucksache 19/31840), 14,
                        15.</note></p>
                <p>This new, all-German party system was slightly different from the old Federal
                    German Republic. This became significantly visible during the protests against
                    the so-called Hartz IV reforms, which since 2002 (the second government of
                    Chancellor Gerhard Schröder, a coalition of Social Democrats and the Green
                    Party, 2002–2005) have been restructuring the former West German social welfare
                    system which was extended to East Germany.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn7" n="5"
                        >For the extension see Gerhard Albert Ritter, <hi rend="italic">Der Preis
                            der deutschen Einheit: die Wiedervereinigung und die</hi><hi
                            rend="italic">Krise des Sozialstaats</hi>. 2., Erweiterte Auflage
                        (München: C.H. Beck, 2008). – One of the mostcontroversial main parts of
                        the so called Hartz-IV-reforms (the IV means, that it is part of a bigger
                        reformpackage) merged the former long-term unemployment with welfare
                        benefits, lowering themsignificantly and with strict conditions and
                        monitoring through social security authorities.</note> The five new states
                    became the focal point of vehement citizen protests against the reforms, which
                    severely restricted social benefits. In the West, left-wing groups and trade
                    union representatives split from the ruling Social Democrats and, together with
                    former communist or socialist splinter groups, merged to form a new party, which
                    positioned itself left of the Social Democrats and called itself an electoral
                    alternative for labor and social justice WASG ( Wahlalternative Arbeit und
                    Soziale Gerechtigkeit). Thanks to the protests, the former Socialist Unity Party
                    of the east, now renamed the PDS Party of Democratic Socialism (Partei des
                    Demokratischen Sozialismus), which was mainly confined to eastern Germany and in
                    sharp decline. For example, the PDS fell short of the 5-percent threshold in the
                    2002 elections for the Bundestag and was therefore no longer represented in the
                    new Bundestag. But with growing protest against the labor market reforms the
                    PDS, which rejected the reforms, managed to gain new supporters and establish
                    itself as an all-German new left-wing party that merged with the WASG in 2007.
                    In 2005, the PDS renamed itself The Left ( Die Linke) <hi rend="italic">,
                    </hi>returned to the Bundestag with a gain of almost five percentage points.</p>
                <p>So, in short, the reference framework for the planned studies is, on the one
                    hand, the change in the party landscape after the end of the Cold War in Europe
                    as a whole and on the other hand, the specifically German manifestations of the
                    system transformation.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>The Historical Background </head>
                <p>The understanding of democracy and voter behavior in the new and old federal
                    states differed from the outset, even though the parties represented in the
                    state parliaments since 1990 consistently competed nationwide. Thus, the East
                    German electorate and also the East German local party milieus were primarily
                    shaped by the experience of the political system of the GDR. However, this
                    experience was not universally negative: In surveys conducted as early as 1991,
                    almost two-thirds of respondents thought that GDR socialism was a good idea, but
                    that it had been poorly executed. Especially in view of social upheavals after
                    reunification, deindustrialization and mass unemployment in East Germany, the
                    GDR appeared ambivalent: Lack of freedom on the one hand, steady jobs and a
                    stable social system on the other.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn8" n="6">The
                        historian Ilko-Sascha Kowalczuk pointed out that the GDR-ideology and
                        self-perception, but also its citizens, defined itself in social reality as
                        a state of working people and firmly secured jobs. The loss of this social
                        security, as well as the West's disdain for these GDR biographies, had led
                        to a long-term trauma that has not really been dealt with to this day. See
                        Ilko-Sascha Kowalczuk, <hi rend="italic">Die Übernahme: wie Ostdeutschland
                            Teil der Bundesrepublik </hi><hi rend="italic">wurde</hi>. 2. Aufl. (München: C.H. Beck, 2019).</note></p>
                <p>The lack of pluralism also characterized the GDR's party system. Although
                    different parties existed in the GDR, the voter did not have a real choice.
                    There was only a single list on the ballot: the so called National Front
                    (Nationale Front), in which candidates from all approved eastern German parties
                    and mass organizations like the trade unions were placed. The allocation of
                    mandates was arranged by a fixed distribution key that guaranteed a majority for
                    the SED Socialist Unity Party (Sozialistische Einheitspartei Deutschlands),. So,
                    the self-proclaimed leading role of the GDR's Socialist Unity Party, effectively
                    ruled out any claim to power by the bloc parties, which on paper formally had
                    equal rights. But GDR-parties such as the CDU Christian Democrats (Christlich
                    Demokratische Union), LDPD Liberal Democrats (Liberaldemokratische Partei
                    Deutschlands), the NDPD National Democrats (Nationaldemokratische Partei
                    Deutschlands or the DBD Democratic Farmers’ Party (Demokratische Bauernpartei
                    Deutschlands) had primarily a legitimizing and integrating function <note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn9" n="7">For example, the NDPD integrated former
                        ordinary Members of the banned National Socialist Party.</note>; they
                    allowed the illusion of plurality that did not exist in reality, they were able
                    to render possible protests or dissatisfaction harmless. Critics of the SED's
                    leadership role were able to become involved, without endangering the dominance
                    of the Socialist Unity Party. So, the bloc parties were seen as a
                    system-stabilizing factor.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn10" n="8">Cf. for
                        example Ines Soldwisch, <hi rend="italic">„... etwas für das ganze Volk zu
                            leisten und nicht nur den Zielen einer Partei </hi><hi rend="italic"
                            >dienen ...“: Geschichte der Liberal-Demokratischen Partei (LPD) in
                            Mecklenburg von 1946-1952</hi> (Rostocker Schriften zur
                        Regionalgeschichte, Bd. 1) (Berlin and Münster: Lit., 2007).</note></p>
                <p>In contrast, the Basic Law of the Federal Republic of Germany (Grundgesetz)
                    accorded constitutional status to all political parties that were loyal to the
                    constitution in Article 21, paragraph 1: “The parties shall cooperate in the
                    formation according to the political will of the people.” Political competition
                    between different parties was fundamental to the political system of the Federal
                    Republic and was an elementary factor for the electorate's understanding of
                    democracy. Such party competition did not become established in the GDR until
                    the very last period of the state’s existence: the phase in which the state
                    party, the SED, slowly lost importance against the backdrop of growing protests
                    among the population. Only towards the end of the GDR, did parties represented
                    in the National Front bloc develop into potential power factors, but in the end
                    missed their chance. This development began towards the end of the 9th
                    Volkskammer, which in June 1986 was still elected on the basis of non-free
                    elections with unified lists. The more the power of the SED eroded, the stronger
                    the influence of the old bloc parties on the process of system transformation
                    became at times. This was mainly due to the fact that the GDR's bloc parties
                    were established and had material infrastructure – for example, members, a party
                    organization, municipal officeholders or real estate holdings. Nevertheless,
                    democratic change in the GDR did not come from the bloc parties; they only
                    reacted and at no point did they succeed in gaining an initiative against the
                    SED or in the reform process. Resistance to the system originated from outside
                    the system. It formed itself in the mid-1980s against the SED's monopoly on
                    power and the bloc parties that were integrated into the SED's system of
                    rule.</p>
                <p>However, the heterogeneous opposition, which initially developed primarily in the
                    protective environment of the Protestant Church, for the most part did not see
                    itself in the role of a competing party. It legitimized its existence primarily
                    as a civil citizens' movement separate to political parties. It was not until
                    the founding of the DDR/SDP Social Democratic Party of the GDR (
                    Sozialdemokratische Partei) in a Protestant parsonage in Schwante, a little
                    Brandenburg village north of Berlin, on October 7, 1989, and other newly formed
                    parties such as the DSU German Social Union (Deutsche Soziale Union), which was
                    oriented towards the Bavarian Christian-Social Union, and the DA Democratic
                    Awakening (Demokratischer Aufbruch), which was more or less the east German
                    version of the western Christian Democratic Union, that the existing bloc party
                    system of the National Front was expanded and transformed into a democratic,
                    pluralistic alternative. Thus, the process of disintegration of the
                    power-maintaining system of the bloc parties became apparent. And slowly their
                    western counterparts became involved and took over these organizations.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>State of Research</head>
                <p>The process of the political post-1990 transformation in eastern Germany is well
                    researched. This also applies to the reorganizations or new foundations of
                    individual parties in the territory of the GDR, which led to the integration of
                    the citizens' movements or short-lived "east parties" by the "big sisters" in
                    West Germany. For the unification of the Social Democrats, two well-founded
                    studies by Daniel F. Sturm and Peter Gohle are available.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn11" n="9">For the SPD, the works are Daniel Friedrich Sturm, <hi
                            rend="italic">Uneinig in die Einheit: die Sozialdemokratie und die
                            </hi><hi rend="italic">Vereinigung Deutschlands 1989/90</hi>
                        (Willy-Brandt-Studien) (Bonn: Dietz, 2006). Peter Gohle, <hi rend="italic"
                            >Von der SDP-</hi><hi rend="italic">Gründung zur gesamtdeutschen SPD:
                            die Sozialdemokratie in der DDR und die Deutsche Einheit 1989/90</hi>
                        (Reihe Politik- und Gesellschaftsgeschichte, Bd. 99) (Bonn: Dietz, 2014).
                        Fabian Peterson, <hi rend="italic">Oppositionsstrategie der SPD-</hi><hi
                            rend="italic">Führung im deutschen Einigungsprozeß 1989/1990:
                            Strategische Ohnmacht durch Selbstblockade?</hi> (Politica 35).
                        (Hamburg: Kovač, 1998).</note> The reorganization and transformation of the
                    Socialist Unity Party of Germany into the Party of Democratic Socialism (Partei
                    des demokratischen Sozialismus) and its later reconstitution as the Left Party,
                    which in 2007 merged with the West German left-wing WASG to form a party that
                    became active nationwide and not only in East Germany, has been extensively
                    researched by Thorsten Holzhauser, at least until 2005. <note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn12" n="10">Thorsten Holzhauser, <hi rend="italic">Die
                            "Nachfolgepartei": die Integration der PDS in das politische System der
                            </hi><hi rend="italic">Bundesrepublik Deutschland 1990-2005</hi>
                        (Quellen und Darstellungen zur Zeitgeschichte, Band 122) (Berlin: De Gruyter
                        Oldenbourg, 2019).</note> The merger of the East German civil rights party
                    Alliance for the 90s (Bündnis 90) with the West German Green party is the
                    subject of a current dissertation.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn13" n="11"
                        >Florian Schikowski (Potsdam), among others: Takeover at eye level? The
                        Merger of Bündnis 90 and The Greens. </note> Initial studies are available
                    on the co-operation and later the attempted takeover of the German Social Union,
                    a party founded in 1990, by the Bavarian CSU <hi rend="italic">, </hi>which
                    unsuccessfully attempted to acquire a nationwide party organization beyond its
                    home state of Bavaria.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn14" n="12">Jens
                        Weinhold-Fumoleau, "Der Einheit wegen. Parteienkooperationen am Ende der DDR
                        am Beispiel der CSU-DSU," in <hi rend="italic">Die Mauer ist weg! Mauerfall,
                            Wendejahre und demokratischer Neubeginn</hi>, herausgegeben von Renate
                        Höpfinger (Bayerische Lebensbilder 5. Biographien, Erinnerungen, Zeugnisse)
                        (München: Hanns Seidel Stiftung, 2019).</note> In contrast, a summary study
                    of the integration of the GDR parties, which were part of the national bloc –
                    the eastern Christian Democratic Union, the Democratic Farmers' Party of
                    Germany, the National Democratic Party of Germany, the Liberal Democratic Party
                    of Germany and the German Women's League –, into their Western counterparts CDU
                    and FDP is still pending<hi rend="italic">. </hi>Moreover, the relevant holdings
                    of the “Foundation Archives of Parties and Mass Organizations of the GDR” which
                    are kept in the German Federal Archives, primarily reflect decision-making at
                    the central level. Research dealing with the regional or local decision-making
                    level is still very rare, if only because of the difficulty in sourcing
                    information.</p>
                <p>Thus far, most research work focused on the phase of system transformation.
                    Largely unexplored, on the other hand, is the long-term impact that the transfer
                    of West German party structures had and still has on the emergence of democratic
                    culture in the territory of the former GDR. That this transfer of West German
                    standards and structures was viewed quite controversially is shown, for example,
                    by talk of “colonization” of the lifeworld in the East – in view of the
                    recruitment of political leadership controlled by the party headquarters of the
                    old Federal Republic and the broad appointment of functionaries socialized in
                    the West, to state functions such as administration and the judiciary, such an
                    accusation could not be entirely dismissed.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Project Outline</head>
                <p>The research project carried out by KGParl and the parties' foundations starts
                    with the confrontation of different political experiences and expectations in
                    East and West with regard to the reconstitution of the parties:</p>
                <p>Already in the first German democratic state level (Landtagswahlen), elections in
                    the five new federal states, a significantly different East German variant of
                    the previous West German party system was shaped, in which the Party of
                    Democratic Socialism (PDS) was able to establish itself as a strong regional
                    party., This provided a rallying point for all those who were not satisfied with
                    the course of development in East Germany, while structural dominance of the
                    mainstream parties Christian Democrats and Social Democrats, which still
                    prevailed in the West (although already challenged by the successes of the Green
                    Party), waned. Particular difficulties were experienced by the West German
                    Liberal Party and, to a lesser extent, the Greens who were unable to establish a
                    broad base in eastern parts of Germany up until the present day. Both parties
                    were only able to gain regional political influence on government formation and
                    opposition in the new states as small coalition partners.</p>
                <p>In a second phase - beginning with the brief electoral success of the far-right
                    DVU German People's Union (Deutsche Volksunion) in Saxony-Anhalt in 1998 and
                    somewhat later in Brandenburg - the right-wing extremist protest potential also
                    unfolded more dynamically in the party spectrum than in the West, further
                    intensifying the fragmentation of the all-German party system and the East-West
                    divide. In addition, special regional developments took place that made the East
                    German states appear far from homogeneous in terms of party politics.</p>
                <p>The time frame of the research project covers the phase of the constitution and
                    consolidation of the parties after system transformation up to the reactions to
                    the announcement of comprehensive, partly neoliberal social reforms under Agenda
                        2010<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn15" n="13">See also Footnote 5.</note> by
                    the government of Chancellor Gerhard Schröder. Since 2003 the so-called Hartz-IV
                    shock was felt particularly strongly in the eastern German states, where far
                    larger percentages of the population were dependent on state support payments
                    than in the west. It is therefore not surprising that since the end of 2003
                    opposition to the liberalization of the labor market and the increase in state
                    pressure on social benefit recipients led to mass protests against the federal
                    government, first in the east and later also in the west. After initial
                    hesitation, the West German-dominated trade unions, which were organized under
                    the umbrella organization of the German Trade Union Confederation, also joined
                    the protests. However, protests in West Germany never reached the quality and
                    quantity of East German protests. Here, the labor market reforms became the
                    focal point for long-term alienation of citizens from the party system and, in
                    part, from the welfare state, which for many presented itself primarily as an
                    intrusion into private lives.</p>
                <p>In East Germany, the PDS Socialist Party in particular was able to position
                    itself as an opponent to the Hartz IV reforms and consolidate its position as
                    the East German regional and protest party. For the Social Democrats, the
                    protests also marked a turning point, as the partly neoliberal social policies
                    of the Red-Green federal government led to the reestablishment of the WASG
                    Electoral Alternative Party, which was subsequently able to mobilize parts of
                    the left wing of the Social Democrats around their former party chairman Oskar
                    Lafontaine, who left the Social Democrats in 2005, and left-wing trade unionists
                    who were dissatisfied with the federal government's pro-employer policies. In
                    2006, the WASG merged with the PDS, which one year earlier had renamed itself
                    The Left (Die Linke), and the two together formed a renewed nationwide leftwing
                    party. As a nationwide left-wing party, they regularly succeeded in overcoming
                    the five-percent threshold in state elections in the West as well and after 2005
                    became a left-wing opposition party. <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn16" n="14">A
                        position the Left is losing at the moment as the new populist party
                        Alternative for Germany, a party that was initially founded as an anti-euro
                        movement and now seen as a right-wing populist rallying movement, strongly
                        rooted mostly in the eastern federal states, is taking the role of the aging
                        Left in the eastern German states.</note> Nevertheless, even after
                    unification with the WASG, the strong east-west division remained visible: In
                    the West the party was never able to match the electoral successes it had in
                    eastern parts of Germany, where today The Left holds the position of prime
                    minister in Thuringia. The party's anchoring in society, for example party
                    organization and membership figures, also remained significantly lower in West
                    Germany than in East Germany.</p>
                <p>Perhaps historian Philipp Ther is right when he points out that the importance of
                    the Schröder-Fischer government's social reforms can hardly be underestimated in
                    explaining the current and ongoing differences between East and West.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn17" n="15">For Philipp Ther (Ther 2019), the labor
                        market reforms of the SPD-Green government represent a catch-up
                        co-transformation of the Federal Republic and alignment with the massive
                        social transformation in Eastern Europe. Wages were depressed, incentive
                        systems via pressure and reduction of labor costs for entrepreneurs were
                        recipes of neoliberal reformers in Eastern Europe since 1990 within the
                        framework of the Washington Consensus, competitiveness of the Eastern
                        European economies was initially to be established primarily in the low-wage
                        sector – the Federal Republic caught up with this adjustment from the
                        beginning of the 2000s. Perhaps a thing to come for the western parts of
                        Germany as well.</note> The reactions to the Hartz-IV-reforms show the
                    long-term consequences of massive social insecurity. The changes in the party
                    system are an indication of the political price Germany is still paying for
                    transformation to this day.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn18" n="16">More
                        generally, on the costs of political and social transformation since 1990
                        see Ivan Krastev and Stephen Holmes. <hi rend="italic">The Light that
                            Failed: a Reckoning</hi> (London: Allen Lane, an imprint of Penguin
                        Books, 2019).</note></p>
                <p>The following guiding perspectives, which target both the internal communication
                    of the parties and the political practice in the parliamentary groups, have
                    emerged as an initial focus for study:</p>
                <list type="unordered">
                    <item>What is the relationship between the party headquarters and the East
                        German state associations, how are their concerns represented
                        programmatically and in terms of personnel in the party as a whole, and what
                        conflicts of interest arise between the center and the periphery? What
                        specific difficulties of organization and communication do the local
                        constituencies encounter in recruiting members, in election campaigns, or in
                        public consultations of members of parliament? </item>
                    <item>How are election campaigns (at all levels) organized, how are candidates
                        recruited, and what conclusions do the parties subsequently draw from
                        sometimes surprising election results? What strategies do party headquarters
                        develop with regard to the new, eastern German state associations, what
                        knowledge do they have, how is information obtained and processed, how does
                        this change the relationship with grassroots campaigns? </item>
                    <item>How are local experiences perceived and reflected in party headquarters,
                        and how does internal communication between members, the apparatus and the
                        party leadership function?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn19" n="17">Most of
                            the contemporary research is by political scientists, see for example
                            Manfred Krapf, <hi rend="italic">Die letzten </hi><hi rend="italic"
                                >Bastionen? die deutsche Sozialdemokratie in den Städten und
                                Kreisen</hi> (Baden-Baden: Tectum Verlag, in der
                            NomosVerlagsgesellschaft, 2019).</note> How important is external policy
                        advice, for example, from opinion surveys and political science? </item>
                    <item>Are there differences between West and East German members of the German
                        Bundestag and the state parliaments in appearance and performance (for
                        example, in plenary debates, parliamentary groups and committee meetings)?
                        And if so, how can such performative differences be evaluated, for example,
                        in the media or in sources (meeting minutes, audio or film recordings)?
                        Attention should be paid to the perpetuation of different socialization
                        experiences, insofar as these can be identified verbally and habitually<note
                            place="foot" xml:id="ftn20" n="18">For example the question: Is there a
                            specific eastern identity? Are there different narratives which can be
                            observed in eastern Germany that resulted from its different history?
                            See cf. Thomas Ahbe, <hi rend="italic">Ostdeutschland und </hi><hi
                                rend="italic">die Ostdeutschen als Erzählung: identitätsstiftende
                                Narrative im Widerstreit</hi> (Erfurt: Landeszentrale für politische
                            Bildung Thüringen, 2022). </note> – for example, in language, dialect,
                        dress, presentation, professional understanding of roles, etc.</item>
                    <item>Speech analyses: rhetorical and semantic using audio-visual sources – are
                        there significant differences in interpretation of normative key concepts
                        (the political turnaround 1989, in German often named “Wende”, the social
                        market economy, state and nation, party, etc.) that indicate fundamental
                        differences in the perception and practice of parliamentary democracy? </item>
                    <item>How does the presence of East German elected officials and party
                        politicians change the political culture in the parliament and parties of
                        the united Federal Republic? How does media coverage of party politics
                        develop? What role does the concentration of the press and broadcasting have
                        on local politics and individual lifeworld? </item>
                    <item>Another focus should be on the relationship of party elites and full-time
                        functionaries to the local base and electorate: At least from today's
                        perspective, the social connection and anchoring of party organizations in
                        East German states and municipalities appears to have been far more
                        difficult than in West German state associations and local constituencies.
                        To this day, many parties – with the exception of The Left, which has long
                        been able to draw on a reservoir of members dating back to GDR times – <note
                            place="foot" xml:id="ftn21" n="19">However, by 2006, the Left’s
                            membership had fallen from almost 300,000 in 1990 to just over 60,000 in
                            2006. Following the merger with the Electoral Alternative, WASG,
                            membership rose again and grew slightly over the next few years due to
                            new members, especially in the old, western states. As a result, the
                            party's roots in eastern Germany have declined significantly since 2006,
                            which is also due to the structural aging of its eastern German members,
                            the majority of whom are over 60. According to media reports, The Left
                            now has more members in western Germany than in the east.</note> not
                        only have difficulty recruiting sufficient members, but often fail to
                        establish themselves in the party political arena.<note place="foot"
                            xml:id="ftn22" n="20">Cf. Heiko Tammena, <hi rend="italic">Volkspartei
                                ohne Parteivolk: Organisationsaufbau der SPD in Ostdeutschland 1990
                                –</hi>
                            <hi rend="italic">1994 und organisationspolitische Perspektiven</hi>
                            (Göttingen, 1994).</note> For example, even the Christian Democrats in
                        Saxony, where the party has for many years provided the country’s prime
                        minister and has won absolute majorities in several elections, has
                        difficulty anchoring itself both at local and regional level. Beyond its
                        thin pool of personnel in the municipalities and counties, the Christian
                        Democrats relies mostly on a “phalanx of nonparty elected officials” in
                        district or municipal councils, who frequently evade party discipline when
                        they see fit. <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn23" n="21">"Auf tönernen Füßen."
                                <hi rend="italic">Frankfurter Allgemeine Sonntagszeitung,"</hi>
                            September 2, 2018, 2.</note></item>
                </list>
                <p>The history of the parties after 1990 can therefore no longer be written
                    hermetically from an institutional perspective. The fact that party politics and
                    the political mobilization of social groups proceed asynchronously and
                    increasingly even antagonistically, requires new parameters of analysis. Parties
                    and the media tend to lose their function as agencies of political will
                    formation, the more politics manifests in the self-mobilization of social
                    groups. The private sphere has become political in a new and different way, in
                    that the formation of political will in society is no longer oriented towards
                    programmatic “offers” of parties or social elite discourses, but primarily
                    follows personal experiences or perceptions of reality circulated by social
                    media. In this sense, communication between voters, the local party base and
                    full-time functionaries and elected officials should be the focus of the
                    research project.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="bibliography">
                <head>Sources and Literature</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl>Ahbe, Thomas. <hi rend="italic">Ostdeutschland und die Ostdeutschen als
                            Erzählung: identitätsstiftende Narrative im Widerstreit</hi>. Erfurt:
                        Landeszentrale für politische Bildung Thüringen, 2022.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Gohle, Peter. <hi rend="italic">Von der SDP-Gründung zur gesamtdeutschen
                            SPD: die Sozialdemokratie in der DDR und die Deutsche Einheit
                            1989/90</hi> (Reihe Politik- und Gesellschaftsgeschichte, Bd. 99). Bonn:
                        Dietz, 2014.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Holzhauser, Thorsten. <hi rend="italic">Die „Nachfolgepartei“: die
                            Integration der PDS in das politische System der Bundesrepublik
                            Deutschland 1990-2005</hi> (Quellen und Darstellungen zur
                        Zeitgeschichte, Band 122). Berlin: De Gruyter Oldenbourg, 2019.</bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="italic">Jahresbericht der Bundesregierung zum Stand der
                            Deutschen Einheit 2021</hi>. Edited by the German Federal Government
                        (Bundestag Drucksache 19/31840).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Kowalczuk, Ilko-Sascha. <hi rend="italic">Die Übernahme: wie
                            Ostdeutschland Teil der Bundesrepublik wurde</hi>. 2. Aufl. München:
                        C.H. Beck, 2019.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Krapf, Manfred. <hi rend="italic">Die letzten Bastionen? die deutsche
                            Sozialdemokratie in den Städten und Kreisen</hi>. Baden-Baden: Tectum
                        Verlag, in der NomosVerlagsgesellschaft, 2019.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Krastev, Ivan, and Stephen Holmes. <hi rend="italic">The Light that
                            Failed: a Reckoning</hi>. London: Allen Lane, an imprint of Penguin
                        Books, 2019.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Micklisch, Fritz. <hi rend="italic">Die Kolonisierung der DDR: wie die
                            einst „lieben Brüder und Schwestern im Osten“ von den kalten Kriegern im
                            Westen gehasst, gedemütigt und bestraft werden</hi>. 1. Aufl. Berlin:
                        Verlag am Park, 2011.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Oschmann, Dirk. <hi rend="italic">Der Osten: eine westdeutsche
                            Erfindung</hi>. Berlin: Ullstein, 2023.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Peterson, Fabian. <hi rend="italic">Oppositionsstrategie der SPD-Führung
                            im deutschen Einigungsprozeß 1989/1990: Strategische Ohnmacht durch
                            Selbstblockade?</hi> (Politica 35). Hamburg: Kovač, 1998.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Ritter, Gerhard Albert. <hi rend="italic">Der Preis der deutschen Einheit:
                            die Wiedervereinigung und die Krise des Sozialstaats</hi>. 2.,
                        Erweiterte Auflage. München: C.H. Beck, 2008.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Soldwisch, Ines. <hi rend="italic">„... etwas für das ganze Volk zu
                            leisten und nicht nur den Zielen einer Partei dienen ...“: Geschichte
                            der Liberal-Demokratischen Partei (LPD) in Mecklenburg von
                            1946-1952</hi> (Rostocker Schriften zur Regionalgeschichte, Bd. 1).
                        Berlin and Münster: Lit., 2007.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Sturm, Daniel Friedrich. <hi rend="italic">Uneinig in die Einheit: die
                            Sozialdemokratie und die Vereinigung Deutschlands 1989/90</hi>.
                        Willy-Brandt-Studien. Bonn: Dietz, 2006.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Tammena, Heiko. <hi rend="italic">Volkspartei ohne Parteivolk:
                            Organisationsaufbau der SPD in Ostdeutschland 1990 - 1994 und
                            organisationspolitische Perspektiven</hi>. Göttingen, 1994.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Ther, Philipp. <hi rend="italic">Das andere Ende der Geschichte. Essays
                            zur großen Transformation</hi>. Berlin: Suhrkamp Verlag, 2019.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Weinhold-Fumoleau, Jens. „Der Einheit wegen. Parteienkooperationen am Ende
                        der DDR am Beispiel der CSU-DSU.“ In <hi rend="italic">Die Mauer ist weg!
                            Mauerfall, Wendejahre und demokratischer Neubeginn</hi>, herausgegeben
                        von Renate Höpfinger (Bayerische Lebensbilder 5. Biographien, Erinnerungen,
                        Zeugnisse), 135–64. München: Hanns Seidel Stiftung, 2019.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>

        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
