<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Studying the Economic Transition – Challenges, Problems and
                    Results</title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename>Aleksander</forename>
                            <surname>Lorenčič</surname>
                        <roleName>PhD</roleName>
                        <affiliation>Pokrajinski muzej Ptuj-Ormož</affiliation>
                        <address>
                            <addrLine>Muzejski trg 1</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>SI - 2250 Ptuj</addrLine>
                        </address>
                   </name></author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>2016-10-04</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>
                    <orgName xml:lang="sl">Inštitut za novejšo zgodovino</orgName>
                    <orgName xml:lang="en">Institute of Contemporary History</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Kongresni trg 1</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>SI-1000 Ljubljana</addrLine>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>http://ojs.inz.si/pnz/article/view/178</pubPlace>
                <date>2016</date>
                <availability status="free">
                    <licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title xml:lang="sl">Prispevki za novejšo zgodovino</title>
                <title xml:lang="en">Contributions to Contemporary History</title>
                <biblScope unit="volume">56</biblScope>
                <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
                <idno type="ISSN">2463-7807</idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source, born digital.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc xml:lang="en">
                <p>Contributions to Contemporary History is one of the central Slovenian scientific
                    historiographic journals, dedicated to publishing articles from the field of
                    contemporary history (the 19th and 20th century).</p>
                <p>The journal is published three times per year in Slovenian and in the following
                    foreign languages: English, German, Serbian, Croatian, Bosnian, Italian, Slovak
                    and Czech. The articles are all published with abstracts in English and
                    Slovenian as well as summaries in English.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <projectDesc xml:lang="sl">
                <p>Prispevki za novejšo zgodovino je ena osrednjih slovenskih znanstvenih
                    zgodovinopisnih revij, ki objavlja teme s področja novejše zgodovine (19. in 20.
                    stoletje).</p>
                <p>Revija izide trikrat letno v slovenskem jeziku in v naslednjih tujih jezikih:
                    angleščina, nemščina, srbščina, hrvaščina, bosanščina, italijanščina, slovaščina
                    in češčina. Članki izhajajo z izvlečki v angleščini in slovenščini ter povzetki
                    v angleščini.</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="sl"/>
                <language ident="en"/>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords xml:lang="en">
                    <term>Slovenia</term>
                    <term>independence</term>
                    <term>economy</term>
                    <term>transition</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords xml:lang="sl">
                    <term>Slovenija</term>
                    <term>osamosvojitev</term>
                    <term>gospodarstvo</term>
                    <term>tranzicija</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change>
                    <date>2016-10-06</date>
                    <name>Neja Blaj Hribar</name>
                    <desc>Pretvorba iz DOCX v TEI, dodatno kodiranje</desc>
                </change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <docAuthor>Aleksander Lorenčič<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn1" n="*">
                <hi rend="bold" xml:space="preserve">PhD, Pokrajinski muzej Ptuj-Ormož, Muzejski trg 1, SI – 2250 Ptuj;
                <ref target="mailto:aleksander.lorencic@pmpo.si">aleksander.lorencic@pmpo.si</ref></hi></note></docAuthor>
            <docImprint>
                <idno type="cobissType">Cobiss tip: 1.01</idno>
                <idno type="UDC">UDK: 930:330.342.14/.15(497.4)"1991/2004"</idno>
                <date>Prejeto 04. 10. 2016</date>
            </docImprint>
            <div type="abstract" xml:lang="sl">
                <head type="main">IZVLEČEK</head>
                <head>PROUČEVANJE GOSPODARSKE TRANZICIJE – IZZIVI, ZAGATE IN
                    REZULTATI</head>
                <p><hi rend="italic">V pričujočem prispevku avtor predstavi izzive, zagate in spoznanja, s katerimi se je soočal pri raziskavi in proučevanju slovenske gospodarske tranzicije. Cilj raziskave, ki velja za 'pionirsko' na področju zgodovinopisja, je bil analitično interpretirati proces gospodarske tranzicije in poudariti njene temeljne posebnosti, zakonitosti, nosilce ter rezultate. Rezultat raziskovanja je znanstvena monografija in številni znanstveni ter strokovni članki s področja gospodarske tranzicije. </hi></p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Ključne besede: Slovenija, osamosvojitev, gospodarstvo,
                    tranzicija</hi></p>
            </div>
            <div type="abstract">
                <head>ABSTRACT</head>
                <p><hi rend="italic">In the following article the author presents the challenges,
                    problems and findings that he encountered while researching and studying the
                    Slovene economic transition. The aim of this research, which is considered
                    ‘pioneer’ in the field of historiography, was to analytically interpret the
                    process of economic transition and point out its fundamental characteristics,
                    rules, agents and results. The result of the research is a scientific monograph
                    and a number of scientific and technical articles in the field of economic
                    transition.</hi></p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Key words: Slovenia, independence, economy, transition</hi></p>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <p>In historiography, there are a few so clear and in terms of time so accurately
                delimited milestones as the year 1991 in Slovene history. With the proclamation of
                autonomy and independence, we, the Slovenians, have taken our destiny completely
                into our own hands for the first time, which is why this period, without a doubt,
                deserves special attention in the field of historiographical research. Despite the
                fact that from the viewpoint of historiography it lasts only for a short period of
                two decades and despite the processes many of which have not yet been concluded,
                this period has to be systematically researched by means of the historiographic
                    method.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn2" n="1">
                        Aleksander Lorenčič, "Slovensko gospodarstvo med tranzicijo in globalno
                        krizo (1990–2010)," in: <hi rend="italic">Vizija raziskav slovenske
                            gospodarske in družbene zgodovine</hi>, ed. Darja Mihelič (Ljubljana:
                        Založba ZRC, 2014), 311–12.</note> The study of the period in question,
                which – due to the so-called historical distance – requires taking into account
                several factors that influence the scientific research and the presentation of
                events (from the question of sources, to documentation and the influence of
                politics), is in many countries no longer a novelty. The importance and role of
                economic history as a sub-discipline or a specific genre within the historical
                science is not given much attention. In general, the economic historiography has
                been for decades on the outskirts of interest in the professional circles. In the
                nineties of the 20<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> century, there has been a
                restructuring of the economic historiography, which coincided with the arrival of
                the younger researchers. In fact, only two researchers, Žarko Lazarević and Jože
                Prinčič, both members of the Institute of Contemporary History, have systematically
                and actively dealt solely with the economic history.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn3" n="2"> Žarko Lazarević, "Identitetne zadrege slovenskega
                        ekonomskega zgodovinopisja," in: <hi rend="italic">Podobe modernizacije.
                            Poglavja iz gospodarske in socialne modernizacije Slovenije v 19. in 20.
                            stoletj</hi>u, eds. Žarko Lazarević and Aleksander Lorenčič (Ljubljana:
                        Inštitut za novejšo zgodovino, 2009), 38.</note> Precisely the Institute
                of Contemporary History has decided to systematically focus also on the period after
                1990, and for that purpose employed two young researchers. The result of this
                decision is, among others, a scientific monograph titled
                    <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Prelom s starim in začetek novega: Tranzicija slovenskega gospodarstva iz socializma v kapitalizem (1990–2004) </hi>(<hi rend="italic">A Break With the Old and the Beginning of the New: The Transition
                    of Slovene Economy from Socialism to Capitalism (1990–2004)</hi>), which
                represents a significant contribution to the Slovenian economic historiography.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn4" n="3"> Aleksander Lorenčič, <hi rend="italic">Prelom s starim in začetek novega. Tranzicija slovenskega gospodarstva
                            iz socializma v kapitalizem (1990–2004)</hi> (Ljubljana: Inštitut za
                        novejšo zgodovino, 2012).</note>
            </p>
            <p>Writing about the Slovenian economic transition as a historian has not been an easy
                task, but it has nevertheless represented a great challenge. I agree with Ivan T.
                Berend, who in 2009 in the preface of his book wrote that to write about the present
                or "the unfinished present" is the same as "shooting a moving target".<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn5" n="4"> Ivan T. Berend<index indexName="XE">
                            <term>Berend T. Ivan</term>
                        </index>, <hi rend="italic">From the Soviet Bloc to the European Union. The
                            Economic and Social Transformation of Central and Eastern Europe since
                            1973</hi> (New York: Cambridge University Press, Cambridge, 2009),
                        14.</note> The fact is that anyone who reads the newspapers or watches
                the daily-news programs is aware that in the last few years we have been "bombarded"
                on a daily basis with the information that more or less pertains to the economic
                transition or its consequences. What is more, the market is full of literature and
                articles (non-technical, technical and scientific) which deal with the process of
                economic transition as a whole or focus only on individual problems. I have to admit
                that due to the multitude of often contradictory information (the opinions of the
                economic profession are frequently divided as well), it was rather difficult to
                create a relevant and comprehensive image of such a complex process as the economic
                transition. As far as the methodological approaches are concerned, due to the legal
                restrictions on the access of the archival materials, the research and insights are
                mostly not based on the classic historical (archival) sources. However, judging by
                the previous research experience regarding the period after the Slovenian
                independence, it is clear that the classic method of studying historiography has to
                be upgraded with the new methodological approaches. One of the reasons is also the
                occurrence of informational and communicational revolution after 1990, enabling
                quicker access to various sources (e.g. the digitalization of different documents),
                and at the same time triggering the emergence of new industries. The second reason
                lies in the fact that after 1991, only the state bodies and institutions the
                documentation of which is more or less accessible also today were legally required
                to hand over their material to the archives in a given period of time. Furthermore,
                it is known that a great deal of material was destroyed, be it due to negligence or
                on purpose, for instance the material of various companies. What is interesting as
                well is the information presented by an archivist from the Regional Archives
                Maribor, Gordana Šövegeš, who was wondering about the whereabouts of the documentary
                material of the Prekmurian companies that went bankrupt in the nineties. Inquiring
                with different bankruptcy managers and former company directors yielded no new
                information for the archivist, and the most frequently heard answer was "we do not
                know". The ones responsible also ignored the laws. "Where would we be if we complied
                with all the laws and regulations! " a director replied to the archivist. We have to
                bear in mind that the Prekmurian example is certainly not the only one and, as
                written by the archivist Šövegeš in 2003, it is "generally known that the material
                of the former companies in public ownership is being massively destroyed even
                    today".<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn6" n="5">
                        Gordana Šövegeš Lipovšek<index indexName="XE">
                            <term>Šoevegeš Gordana</term>
                        </index>, "The archival material of the Prekmurian companies," in: <hi rend="italic">Arhivi in arhivsko gradivo v času tranzicijskih
                            sprememb/Infoarh</hi>, eds. Mija Mravlja and Andrej Nared (Ljubljana:
                        Arhivsko društvo Slovenije, 2003), 59–61.</note> Similar things happened
                with the Communist Party material or the CK ZKS (Central Committee of the Slovene
                Communist Party) material. Many municipal committees (18 exactly) did not hand over
                their material. As written by Darinka Drnovšek from the Archives of the Republic of
                Slovenia, some people "destroyed the documentation simply because they feared that
                under the new political circumstances these archives would be taken advantage of",
                others stored the documents somewhere (in the basement or the attic) and "the new
                leaderships did not want to have anything to do with it".<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn7" n="6"> Darinka Drnovšek<index indexName="XE">
                            <term>Drnovšek Darinka</term>
                        </index>, "The material of the Communist Party in the time of transition,"
                        in: <hi rend="italic">Arhivi in arhivsko gradivo v času tranzicijskih
                            sprememb/Infoarh</hi>, eds. Mija Mravlja and Andrej Nared (Ljubljana:
                        Arhivsko društvo Slovenije, 2003), 67–70.</note> Archivists will thus
                have a lot of hard work to make sure that the archival material ends up in the
                archives in the most satisfactory form possible – at least a greater part of what
                has not been destroyed. Since the problem of transition is distinctively
                multidisciplinary, the methodological approach was highly interdisciplinary as well.
                As a historian, I have given priority to the established method of historical
                profession, meaning that on the basis of a detailed study of all the possible and
                available sources and especially the critical analysis of the latter, I have tried
                to determine, confront and confirm as many material facts of the process in question
                as possible. The economic, political, sociological, legal and anthropological
                conceptualizations of the thematic, theoretical and methodological bases for
                studying the transition were all taken into account. The monograph deals with all
                the fundamental processes of the economic transition. Up until now, especially the
                economic profession has dealt with individual problems and processes of this period,
                but not in a manner in which the problem of economic transition is presented in this
                work. As already pointed out, the monograph is written in accordance with the rules
                of historical profession and it represents a comprehensive account of the problem of
                the economic transition. This means the inclusion of all the relevant aspects of the
                problem, since only this way we can expect a comprehensive and authentic
                reconstruction of the complexity of the economic transition. </p>
            <p>The decision to become a sovereign and independent country has made it possible for
                Slovenia to engage in its own economic policy and to take over the responsibility
                for its own economic development. By the end of 1992 Slovenia had already been
                recognized by one hundred countries and become a member of the UN and its
                specialized organizations; by 1996 she had become a member of almost all the
                significant economic associations (European Bank for Reconstruction and Development,
                International Monetary Fund, World Bank and International Finance Corporation, GATT,
                WTO, EFTA and CEFTA). Slovenia was in this way "fastened with a safety belt" to the
                West and thus protected from the war that took place in parts of the former
                Yugoslavia. The biggest strategic objective of the Republic of Slovenia was, due to
                its close political, cultural and economic co-operation with Europe, full membership
                of the EU, which was realized on 1 May 2004. The only organization which Slovenia
                was unable to become a member of quite so rapidly was the OECD which unites the
                economically most developed countries in the world (Slovenia did not become a member
                until 2010).<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn8" n="7">
                        Lorenčič,
                        <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Prelom s starim in začetek novega, </hi>455–56.
                    </note> Slovenia was one of the first to pass over the period of
                transformation depression, which was typical for transition economies in the early
                nineties, as the recovery of economic growth through the revival of domestic demand
                took place in mid–1993. Slovenia relatively quickly exceeded the pretransitional
                level of economic activity – the 1990 level of pretransitional development from in
                1996 and the 1987 level in 1998.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn9" n="8"> Ibid, 456. </note>
            </p>
            <p>Throughout the whole economic transition process, the process of privatization has
                caused by far the most trouble and stress in political and economic circles and to
                the population as a whole. It has certainly proved to be the central and most
                demanding of all the transition processes. Let us say right away that this is not
                just a Slovenian particularity, but similar patterns were also seen in other
                post–communist countries. Privatization of socially-owned property was the process
                that affected the population most deeply. Legally, the process took place in several
                steps. In autumn 1991 two acts relating to the privatization of apartments and
                denationalization were adopted. The Ownership Transformation of Companies Act (OTCA)
                was adopted in November 1992.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn10" n="9"> Ibid, 457–58.</note> The basic principle of the
                privatization of apartments and apartment houses was the equalisation of the right
                to purchase an apartment for all those citizens who held housing rights on the day
                the Housing Act was implemented. An even greater problem was caused by
                denationalization or the implementation of the latter which was often the subject of
                polemics and various accusations, particularly by expropriators who set up the
                Association of Expropriated Property Owners of Slovenia. In their view, the return
                of nationalized property took place too slowly. The property was returned to the
                former owners or their heirs "in kind" and if that was not possible, compensation
                was provided. Return of the property "in kind" provoked most outrage when the Act
                was adopted, which only intensified when the act was put into practice. At the end
                of March 2007, the percentage of settled cases at the national level was 94.9. The
                objective of denationalization and privatization of apartments should be to
                establish ownership and to redress a wrong, but often just the opposite has
                happened. Legislation in the form it was adopted has actually led to a number of new
                injustices. Let us look at, for example, the returning of apartments in kind, even
                when they were occupied by residents with housing rights to them. Slovenia was the
                only one of all the transition countries to implement this. Many people in this
                situation were unjustly treated and indeed exploited by the new owners, but the
                state has done very little to help and has actually continued to write acts that
                have done very little to prevent a number of malversations. The government had by
                far the most problems with the adoption of the privatization of companies act. The
                proposals concerning the method of privatization, put forward by Aleksander Bajt and
                Ivan Ribnikar, were given little serious discussion at government level. However,
                within the coalition there was a conflict between two completely different economic
                and political concepts and in the end, some sort of interim model between
                Mencinger’s and Sachs’s proposal prevailed. During the period from 1990 to the
                adoption of the OTCA at the end of 1992, many companies converted their status,
                increased in capital or reorganized on the basis of the Yugoslav legislation of that
                time. Because at that time the state had not yet fully established the institution
                of control over the status and financial-capital changes of the companies that had
                social capital, there was, of course, wide scope for abuse. During this period,
                so-called "wild privatization" took place. In order to prevent such abuses, in
                December 1990 two state institutions that were supposed to supervise and regulate
                the process of privatization and restructuring were established. The Agency of the
                Republic of Slovenia for Restructuring and Privatization has supervised and followed
                the process, prepared guidelines and verified the privatization programmes, while
                The Fund of the Republic of Slovenia for Development has restructured companies. The
                latter also became the owner of companies and could negotiate and sign sales
                contracts. Today we are often witness to accusations about fearsome social
                stratification, stories about management takeovers and similar. What we have to
                realize is that the situation in society and the economy today is not a result of
                what took place yesterday or in recent years, but that we have to look for answers
                at the beginning of our transition story. The lion's share of controversial
                privatizations can reliably be attributed to delays in the long-term process of the
                adoption of The Ownership Transformation of Companies Act. We cannot affirm that the
                so-called "wild privatization" ran by the so-called Marković acts, because if that
                were the case, it certainly would not be controversial and illegal. In fact, it only
                referred to a legally unresolved Marković conception of privatization. One fact we
                cannot dispute is that while politicians were arguing and discussing possible
                solutions to the problems of ownership transformation, some had already seized a
                considerable section of socially-owned property. Let us recall the two, so-called
                "higher forms" of abusing social property, which some were taking advantage of when
                relevant legislation had not yet been adopted. The first is by-pass companies. This
                was a well-known and widespread phenomenon of establishing a company in private
                ownership, set up by workers employed in a social enterprise with the same or
                similar subject of business for which the social company was registered. The social
                company was then run down, until they entered liquidation and bankruptcy. This
                serves as a clear case of "wild privatization". The other example represents a free
                transfer of social capital, which refers to the second paragraph of article 145 of
                the Law on Enterprises from 1990. The described transfer of the capital, even if
                carried out between companies that were in social ownership, was illegal. In this
                way, mixed companies now became social property owners in social companies and by
                doing so also indirectly privatized social companies without the Privatization Act,
                which was unacceptable and illegal. Of course, there were also other forms of
                abusing social property, such as unfounded abatement of debts, improper
                profit-sharing and unpaid transfer of capital. In any case the fundamental cause of
                "wild privatization" was the fact that the privatization of public property was
                possible from the outset, without adequate rules and regulations. Moreover, despite
                warnings from the relevant institutions, the Slovenian parliament did not react. The
                same was also true in the case of the aforementioned article 145. b of the Law on
                Enterprises, which allowed free transfer of social property under one’s own will and
                which the Slovenian parliament did not withdraw or supplement in time. According to
                data from the Agency for Auditing, during the period from 1 January 1990 to 31
                December 1992 there was a deficit of socially-owned property to the value of 86,174
                million Slovenian Tolars or, if revalorized, the value of 1,238,454,581.87 Euros. In
                total, according to the audit, the deficit of socially-owned property in the period
                from 1 January 1990 to 31 July 2004 was to the value of 104 billion-Slovenian
                    Tolars.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn11" n="10"> Ibid<hi rend="italic">,</hi> 268, 458–60. </note> In any case, a small
                proportion of the population managed to recover significantly during this period.
                The long-term adoption of the appropriate legislation has thus had serious
                consequences. However, it is possible to understand the governing policy of that
                time, at least to a certain extent. According to many, the privatization law which
                was eventually adopted was the best of all those suggested. Certainly, if we accept
                that it is better to pause and reflect rather than make hasty decisions, it was
                certainly preferable to pass an appropriate law later than rush through an
                unsuitable one. It is also true, as Jože Mencinger admits, that the government at
                that time was a group of amateurs and either politicians or the appropriate bodies
                were able to deal with the situation (this was the same in all transition
                countries). In defence of the government at that time, we should also consider that
                processes such as the transition do not happen often and there is no manual for
                producing perfect results. All this can be understood, but what is harder to accept
                is the fact that consequently there were numerous abuses and economic benefits to
                some, which, of course, is the other, darker side of the story. Anyway, the finally
                adopted OTCA provides companies with seven methods of achieving ownership
                transformation and combines the elements of two different approaches, namely the
                decentralized approach, where most of the initiatives and decisions came from
                companies and the mass privatization of part of the shares so that they can be
                divided among citizens in exchange for certificates. Despite the long-term adoption
                of the OTCA, some flaws remained. The legislature had, inter alia, restricted audits
                to a three-year period from 1990 to 1992, assuming that the pre-privatization audit
                procedures would be completed by the end of 1994, which certainly was not the case.
                It turns out that the deadlines set by the legislator were missed completely and
                impossible to execute in practice. Inappropriate rules of law, among other things,
                triggered once again the unnecessary "legalization" of "wild privatization" after 1
                January 1993 and thus the establishment of by-pass companies and similar
                malversations also continued after 31 December 1992.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn12" n="11"> Ibid, 461. </note> Up to the
                beginning of the operation of the Agency of the Republic of Slovenia for the
                Auditing of Ownership Transformation of Companies in August 1996, so after a period
                of almost three years, it was not possible to initiate an appropriate audit of
                previous privatization or to act according to the OTCA. One of the methods of
                becoming rich in Slovenia was provided by certificates. The majority of Slovenian
                citizens sold the certificates quickly, thinking they were nothing more than a
                worthless piece of paper. Since 1993, however, the market in proprietary
                certificates has flourished. Brokerage firms were formed and a handful of
                better-informed citizens purchased the certificates at low value and exchanged them
                later for shares; while the share values increased (mostly), their owners became
                increasingly richer. The processes of ownership and privatization have taken a
                relatively slow course. Up to 7 November 1994, 700 companies submitted their
                programmes for restructuring to The Agency of the Republic of Slovenia for
                Restructuring and Privatization, which was 52 per cent of all those liable for
                transformation by law. In early May 1998 the Act Concluding Ownership Transformation
                and Privatisation of Legal Entities Owned by the Development Corporation of Slovenia
                came into force, which defined the transition from the decentralized to centralized
                form of privatization. In the six years of the process, almost all of the companies
                with social capital carried out ownership transformation, and only a small number of
                companies chose not to privatize, because of their own inactivity, or other
                objective reasons. By completing the process of the ownership transformation of
                companies, the first phase of the transition process was completed, the aim of which
                was to push Slovenia into common global trends and economic flows and also enter
                into the European integration process. With the completion of the process a new
                investment cycle was also initiated, thereby increasing not only the economic growth
                and employment but also the share of foreign investments. After the formal
                completion of the process of ownership transformation of companies, it was necessary
                to complete the second part of the transition process, namely the privatization of
                state property. The sale of state property represents another form of "wild
                privatization". The majority of capital shares in the period 1995–2005 were sold
                without public bids, therefore non-transparently. The privatization method was
                otherwise well-intentioned and allowed a high level of worker and employee
                involvement in ownership changes, but the good intentions came to nothing. During
                the privatization process, the participation of internal owners (non-management
                employees) and state funds declined, but the participation of investment firms and
                managers increased. Slovenia’s entry into the European Union marked the formal end
                of the transition, however the emphasis here is on formal, because only after that
                period did the privatization prey or its results begin to show. We have been witness
                to frequent stories of management takeovers, numerous accusations and polemics.
                These events served the politicians mostly for the purpose of collecting votes; let
                us not forget the story of the sale of Mercator. The management buyouts did not
                start in BTC, Iskra, Merkur or Laško. A unique case of a Slovenian management buyout
                took place in 1995 in the company Agroruše. It is reasonable to add that where
                privatization was carried out fairly and by the will of the people, where there was
                no double crossing and injustice and in particular, where intentions were entirely
                honest, those who undertook the process of ownership transformation were able to
                live with an entirely different spirit and even better. Unfortunately, it transpired
                that in a large number of Slovenian companies the motivating principles of the
                managers were less than fair, accruing benefits and greed. As previously mentioned,
                things were not as closely regulated as they should have been at the very beginning.
                We are thinking in particular here of the legal aspect; little has changed. There
                were many "loopholes" in the acts and many of those who are now accused of all kinds
                of abuses, have acquired their wealth, so to speak, legally. A large share of the
                responsibility lies with the legal system and politicians, because the National
                Assembly is a place where acts are proposed and adopted. As mentioned previously,
                many of the deficits in the first period of transition occurred because legislation
                was inadequate or pending, as well as calls to action being largely ignored. In the
                first phase of transition, politicians behaved – except in the election period,
                obviously – as if wild privatization were only an idea, completely foreign to the
                Slovenian economy. If we mention the later period and the aforementioned notorious
                manager’s takeovers, the fact is that a great deal of them also happened with the
                generous help of the politicians. Whether we like it or not, politics and the
                economy are co-dependent areas, as was illustrated so strikingly during the process
                of privatization, since the latter often served policy as a tool to increase
                influence. Even in stories that were seemingly all about the national interest, it
                transpired that the interests of individuals prevailed. The concept of policy in its
                narrow sense is defined as directing society with the help of the state. And given
                the fact that socially-owned property has mostly landed in the hands of a handful of
                people, that we are witnessing distinctive social stratification, that many do not
                believe in a state governed by the rule of law and the like, it is clear that the
                policy has not entirely successfully directed Slovenian society to the intended
                goal. The restructuring of the Slovenian economy can certainly not be described as
                successful, at least not entirely. If not before, this statement proved to be true
                when after the first quarter of 2009, Slovenia officially lapsed into recession
                brought about by the global financial and economic crisis. The recession occurred
                for the first time since 1993, when our country passed over to the transformation
                recovery and we again witnessed a decline in economic activity, the failure of
                companies and high unemployment. Crises, which are an integral part of economic
                life, highlight accumulated economic imbalances or irregularities, and this is
                exactly what happened in Slovenia. Many of the companies which were not successfully
                and suitably restructured during the transition have collapsed. Many were forced to
                reorganize and restructure.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn13" n="12"> Ibid, 461–64.</note>
            </p>
            <p>With regard to the conclusions and results of the research connected to my study of
                the economic transition, be it individual articles or the monograph <hi rend="italic">Prelom s starim in začetek novega</hi> (<hi rend="italic">A Break
                    With the Old and the Beginning of the New</hi>), the fact is that from today’s
                perspective and with new knowledge I would have written some things differently.
                However, this is precisely the essence of the research and historiography as such:
                it is a vital process that takes the existing knowledge and constantly upgrades it
                in the presence of new knowledge. I believe the crucial thing in understanding the
                economic transition is for the researcher to understand the process and put it in a
                broader context. Taking an example of the grounds or causes for the socio-political
                and economic changes, we must bear in mind that, from a broader perspective, this
                was the time of the collapse of the Soviet Union, the collapse of the bipolar
                division of the world and the time in which socialism became obsolete. In
                Yugoslavia, the political, transnational, cultural and economic disagreements lead
                to the desired goal – the Slovenian independence and the transition to a capitalist
                system. Researching the economic transition as a contemporary researcher, I am aware
                of the fact that capitalism is a causal-consequential process and that Slovenia
                cannot avoid external influences, on which it ultimately depends. Economic crises
                are an integral part of the economy; the two crises Slovenia has faced in the last
                25 years – the transitional and the current one – do not have the same reasons for
                their occurrence, but their consequences for the population are similar: the
                bankruptcies of many companies, unemployment, the problems of the banks, etc. The
                crisis that occurred in 2008 is the third great crisis in the last century and a
                half. Comparing the crisis that hit the countries with the Slovenian population
                after the collapse of the Vienna Stock Exchange in 1873, the crisis that was the
                result of the stock market crash on Wall Street in 1929 and the current crisis, the
                fact is that all three of them have their origin in the financial sector, because
                they are the consequence of the financial, credit and investment speculations, and
                they all occurred after periods of outstandingly positive financial and economic
                trends. The main difference between the transitional crisis on the one hand, and the
                global financial and economic crisis on the other is that the former had regional,
                while the latter had global dimensions. In 1991, Slovenia entered the world of
                capitalism, which was also facing certain changes that ultimately lead to the
                outbreak of the last great crisis. If we consider the events from a broader
                perspective, we discover that in the field of capitalism, especially after the
                outbreak of the oil crisis in 1973, there has been a major shift in mentality,
                leading to the belief that the role of state and interventionism are not essential
                or important for the economy. Neoliberalism occurred: an economic-political paradigm
                which advocates minimizing the role of state in the economy. The economist Davorin
                Kračun believes that neoliberalism received political support with the election of
                President Reagan in the USA and reached its peak at the end of the 1980 with the
                so-called Washington Consensus, which represented a recipe for the countries in
                    transition.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn14" n="13"> Sonja Ploj Ratajc and
                        Vanessa Čokl, "An interview with Davorin Kračun," <hi rend="italic">V
                            soboto/Večer</hi>, 28 July 2012, 3–5.</note> Kračun believes that
                "under these circumstances, the neoliberal economic-political paradigm was fairly
                successful also because it coincided with the collapse of the Eastern Bloc and the
                expansion of the global market to the once impregnable fortresses of Russia and
                China". Moreover, in his opinion, the informational and communicational revolutions
                paved the way for the entirely new industries.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn15" n="14"> Ibid, 3.</note> Ivan T. Berend, a
                comparative historian of the Central and Eastern Europe, is of similar opinion, and
                he believes that capitalism has changed and since the 1970s has definitely not been
                the same. "The developed European countries have been deindustrialized, the industry
                has lost its significance and in the most developed Western countries only 18
                percent of the active population works in the industry. The financial sector,
                including banks, financial institutions, insurance companies and the real estate
                sector, grows six time faster than the real economy and its assets are three or four
                times larger than the entire gross domestic product of the European Union. I am
                talking about the deindustrialized, excessively financially controlled economy,
                which was very fragile and susceptible to the financial panic that occurred. From
                1980 onwards, the entire system has been deregulated: all the regulations
                implemented in the 1930 and after the Second World War with the Bretton Woods
                Agreement, including the lessons learned from the Great Depression, have been
                eliminated. Neoliberalism was convinced that it solved the problems of the crises
                and that they will not occur anymore. The leading economists of the Chicago School
                advised the governments that we no longer need the straightjacket of regulation,"
                believes Berend.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn16" n="15"> Saša Vidmajer, "An
                        interview with Ivan T. Berend," <hi rend="italic">Delo/Sobotna priloga</hi>,
                        accesed 25 March 2012, <ref target="http://www.delo.si/zgodbe/sobotnapriloga/zgodovinar-ivan-t-berend-krizo-je-povzrocila-periferna-mentaliteta.html">http://www.delo.si/zgodbe/sobotnapriloga/zgodovinar-ivan-t-berend-krizo-je-povzrocila-periferna-mentaliteta.html</ref>.</note>
                In Slovenia, we were not fully aware 25 years ago what the transition to capitalism
                will bring. During this period, capitalism has changed in certain aspects as well.
                The financial capitalism prevails, which affects the social differences and rivalry
                even more. 25 years of independence is a relatively short period and it seems that
                after so many years of being an independent country we have only begun to learn
                about the negative aspects of the capitalist system, of which we expected so much
                when we gained independence. Today, this strongly shows in the helplessness and
                despair of people. It is often said that the Slovenian constitution writes about the
                implementation of the market economy, while in reality, we have run into the cruel
                capitalist economy. The romantic ideas make it that much harder to accept the fact
                that in 1991, Slovenia did not only gain independence, but also transited to the
                capitalist system with all of its positive and negative characteristics about which
                we listen on a daily basis.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn17" n="16"> I have summed up my views on the development during
                        the 25 years of independence in an interview for the newspaper <hi rend="italic">Finance</hi> – Aleksander Lorenčič and Lojze Javornik,
                        "Slovenci imamo mitičen odnos do vsake državne tvorbe: Zgodovinar Aleksander
                        Lorenčič o čudnosti čudenja liberalnemu kapitalizmu, slepega prevzemanja
                        ideologije od starejših generacij in o slovenskem zaostajanju zaradi
                        neenotnosti o temeljnih ekonomskih nalogah in odnosu do tujih naložb," <hi rend="italic">Finance</hi>. <hi rend="italic">Priloga Manager: revija za
                            podjetne</hi>, 17 June 2016, 16–19.</note> 1991 marks a significant
                turning point in our history. Attaining independence, gaining international
                recognition and entering into various international bodies, with the pinnacle –
                entrance into the European Union in 2004 – are achievements our ancestors could only
                dream of. If we draw a line, the process of economic transition and the transition
                to an open socio-market economy in Slovenia deserves positive historical appraisal
                with a black dot that, as in other transition countries, points to missed strokes
                and opportunities. This is understandable, because a process as complex as the
                transition cannot be accomplished entirely as planned or intended, since matters in
                practice often do not run as smoothly they are written in textbooks and acts of
                law.</p>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="bibliography">
                <head>Sources and Literature</head>
                <listBibl>
                <head>Literature:</head>
                <bibl>Berend, T. Ivan. <hi rend="italic">From the Soviet Bloc to the European Union.
                    The Economic and Social Transformation of Central and Eastern Europe since
                    1973</hi>. New York: Cambridge University Press, Cambridge, 2009. </bibl>
                <bibl>Drnovšek, Darinka. "The material of the Communist Party in the time of
                    transition." In: <hi rend="italic">Arhivi in arhivsko gradivo v času
                        tranzicijskih sprememb/Infoarh</hi>, eds. Mija Mravlja and Andrej Nared,
                    67–70. Ljubljana: Arhivsko društvo Slovenije, 2003.</bibl>
                <bibl>Lazarević, Žarko. "Identitetne zadrege slovenskega ekonomskega
                    zgodovinopisja." In: <hi rend="italic">Podobe modernizacije. Poglavja iz
                        gospodarske in socialne modernizacije Slovenije v 19. in 20. stoletju</hi>,
                    eds. Žarko Lazarević and Aleksander Lorenčič, 13–57. Ljubljana: Inštitut za
                    novejšo zgodovino, 2009.</bibl>
                <bibl>Lorenčič, Aleksander and Lojze Javornik. "Slovenci imamo mitičen odnos do
                    vsake državne tvorbe: Zgodovinar Aleksander Lorenčič o čudnosti čudenja
                    liberalnemu kapitalizmu, slepega prevzemanja ideologije od starejših generacij
                    in o slovenskem zaostajanju zaradi neenotnosti o temeljnih ekonomskih nalogah in
                    odnosu do tujih naložb." <hi rend="italic">Finance. Priloga Manager: revija za
                        podjetne</hi>, 17 June 2016, 16–19.</bibl>
                <bibl>Lorenčič, Aleksander. <hi rend="italic">Prelom s starim in začetek novega.
                    Tranzicija slovenskega gospodarstva iz socializma v kapitalizem
                    (1990–2004)</hi>. Ljubljana: Inštitut za novejšo zgodovino, 2012.</bibl>
                <bibl>Lorenčič, Aleksander. "Slovensko gospodarstvo med tranzicijo in globalno krizo
                    (1990–2010)." In: <hi rend="italic">Vizija raziskav slovenske gospodarske in
                        družbene zgodovine</hi>, ed. Darja Mihelič, 311–325. Ljubljana: Založba ZRC,
                    2014.</bibl>
                <bibl>Ploj Ratajc, Sonja and Vanessa Čokl. "An interview with Davorin Kračun." <hi rend="italic">V soboto/Večer</hi>, 28 July 2012, 3–5. </bibl>
                <bibl>Šövegeš Lipovšek, Gordana. "The archival
                    material of the Prekmurian companies." In: <hi rend="italic">Arhivi in arhivsko
                        gradivo v času tranzicijskih sprememb/Infoarh</hi>, eds. Mija Mravlja and
                    Andrej Nared, 59–61. Ljubljana: Arhivsko društvo Slovenije, 2003.</bibl>
                <bibl>Vidmajer, Saša. "An interview with Ivan T. Berend." <hi rend="italic">Delo/Sobotna priloga</hi>. Accesed 25. March 2012. <ref target="http://www.delo.si/zgodbe/sobotnapriloga/zgodovinar-ivan-t-berend-krizo-je-povzrocila-periferna-mentaliteta.html">http://www.delo.si/zgodbe/sobotnapriloga/zgodovinar-ivan-t-berend-krizo-je-povzrocila-periferna-mentaliteta.html</ref>.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
            <div type="summary" xml:lang="sl">
            <head type="main">PROUČEVANJE GOSPODARSKE TRANZICIJE – IZZIVI, ZAGATE IN REZULTATI</head>
            <head>POVZETEK</head>
                <docAuthor>Aleksander Lorenčič</docAuthor>
            <p>V pričujočem prispevku avtor predstavi izzive, zagate in spoznanja, s katerimi se je
                soočal pri raziskavi in proučevanju slovenske gospodarske tranzicije. Cilj
                raziskave, katere rezultat je več znanstvenih in strokovnih člankov ter znanstvena
                monografija <hi rend="italic">Prelom s starim in začetek novega</hi>, ki velja za
                'pionirsko' na področju zgodovinopisja, je bil analitično interpretirati proces
                gospodarske tranzicije in poudariti njene temeljne posebnosti, zakonitosti, nosilce
                ter rezultate. Rezultat raziskovanja je znanstvena monografija in številni
                znanstveni ter strokovni članki s področja gospodarske tranzicije. Pisati o
                slovenski gospodarski tranziciji kot zgodovinar je bilo vse prej kot lahko delo, a
                mi je predstavljalo velik izziv. Ivan T. Berend meni, da je o dogodkih iz sedanjosti
                oziroma o "nedokončani sedanjosti" pisati tako, kot da bi "streljal na premikajočo
                se tarčo". Dejstvo je, da vsak, ki prebira časopisje ali gleda dnevno-informativne
                oddaje, ve, da smo bili zadnja leta tako rekoč vsak dan "bombardirani" s številnimi
                informacijami, ki so se tako ali drugače navezovale na gospodarsko tranzicijo
                oziroma njene posledice. Poleg tega je na trgu ogromno literature in člankov,
                poljudnih, strokovnih in znanstvenih, ki celostno ali po posameznih problemih
                obravnavajo proces gospodarske tranzicije. Priznati moram, da si je bilo v tej
                množici podatkov, ki so si pogosto nasprotujoči (tudi ekonomska stroka je v mnenjih
                pogosto deljena), zelo težko ustvariti relevantno, celostno podobo o tako
                kompleksnem procesu, kot je gospodarska tranzicija. Pred 25 leti se v Sloveniji
                nismo zavedali oziroma si je bilo težko predstavljati, kaj bo prehod v kapitalizem v
                celoti prinesel. Tudi kapitalizem se je v tem obdobju v določenih pogledih
                spremenil. Prevladuje finančni kapitalizem, ki še toliko bolj vpliva na socialne
                razlike in tekmovalnost. Četrt stoletja samostojnosti je relativno kratka doba in
                zdi se, da šele po toliko letih samostojne države spoznavamo negativne plati
                kapitalističnega sistema, od katerega smo ob osamosvojitvi toliko pričakovali. To se
                danes izrazito kaže kot nemoč in brezup ljudi. Pogosto je slišati, da smo v
                Sloveniji v ustavo zapisali, da uvajamo tržno gospodarstvo, zašli pa smo v kruto
                kapitalistično gospodarstvo. Zaradi romantičnih predstav je toliko težje sprejeti
                dejstvo, da se Slovenija leta 1991 ni samo osamosvojila, temveč je prešla tudi v
                kapitalistični sistem z vsemi pozitivnimi in tudi negativnimi lastnostmi, o katerih
                danes vsakodnevno poslušamo.</p>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>