<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Većeslav Holjevac - Forgotten Dissident</title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename>Josip</forename>
                        <surname>Mihaljević</surname>
                        <roleName>Research Fellow</roleName>
                        <roleName>PhD</roleName>
                        <affiliation>Croatian Institute of History</affiliation>
                        <address>
                            <addrLine>Opatička 10</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>10000–Zagreb, Croatia</addrLine>
                        </address>
                        <email>josip@isp.hr</email>
                    </name>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>2017-09-03</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>
                    <orgName xml:lang="sl">Inštitut za novejšo zgodovino</orgName>
                    <orgName xml:lang="en">Institute of Contemporary History</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Kongresni trg 1</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>SI-1000 Ljubljana</addrLine>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>http://ojs.inz.si/pnz/article/view/290</pubPlace>
                <date>2018</date>
                <availability status="free">
                    <licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title xml:lang="sl">Prispevki za novejšo zgodovino</title>
                <title xml:lang="en">Contributions to Contemporary History</title>
                <biblScope unit="volume">58</biblScope>
                <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
                <idno type="ISSN">2463-7807</idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source, born digital.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc xml:lang="en">
                <p>Contributions to Contemporary History is one of the central Slovenian scientific
                    historiographic journals, dedicated to publishing articles from the field of
                    contemporary history (the 19th and 20th century).</p>
                <p>The journal is published three times per year in Slovenian and in the following
                    foreign languages: English, German, Serbian, Croatian, Bosnian, Italian, Slovak
                    and Czech. The articles are all published with abstracts in English and
                    Slovenian as well as summaries in English.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <projectDesc xml:lang="sl">
                <p>Prispevki za novejšo zgodovino je ena osrednjih slovenskih znanstvenih
                    zgodovinopisnih revij, ki objavlja teme s področja novejše zgodovine (19. in 20.
                    stoletje).</p>
                <p>Revija izide trikrat letno v slovenskem jeziku in v naslednjih tujih jezikih:
                    angleščina, nemščina, srbščina, hrvaščina, bosanščina, italijanščina, slovaščina
                    in češčina. Članki izhajajo z izvlečki v angleščini in slovenščini ter povzetki
                    v angleščini.</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="sl"/>
                <language ident="en"/>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords xml:lang="en">
                    <term>Većeslav Holjevac</term>
                    <term>dissident</term>
                    <term>League of Communists of Yugoslavia</term>
                    <term>League of Communists of Croatia</term>
                    <term>Croatian Spring</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords xml:lang="sl">
                    <term>Većeslav Holjevac</term>
                    <term>disident</term>
                    <term>Zveza komunistov Jugoslavije</term>
                    <term>Komunistična partija Hrvaške</term>
                    <term>Hrvaška pomlad</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change>
                    <date>2017-12-27</date>
                    <name>Neja Blaj Hribar</name>
                    <desc>Pretvorba iz DOCX v TEI, dodatno kodiranje</desc>
                </change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <docAuthor>Josip Mihaljević<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn1" n="*">
                    <hi rend="bold" style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">Research Fellow, PhD, Croatian Institute of History, Opatička 10, 10000-Zagreb, Croatia, </hi><ref target="mailto:josip@isp.hr"><hi rend="bold" style="font-size:10pt">josip@isp.hr</hi></ref></note></docAuthor>
            <docImprint>
                <idno type="cobissType">Cobiss type: 1.01</idno>
                <idno type="UDC">UDC: 929HOLJEVAC V.:323.281"1918/1945"</idno>
            </docImprint>
            <div type="abstract" xml:lang="sl">
                <head>IZVLEČEK</head>
                <head>VEĆESLAV HOLJEVAC – POZABLJENI DISIDENT</head>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Hrvaški politik Većeslav Holjevac (1917–1970) velja za enega
                    najuspešnejših županov mesta Zagreb. Kljub temu sta njegova osebnost in
                    politično delo javnosti danes malo znana. Njegove zasluge na kulturnem
                    področju so šle večinoma v pozabo, prav tako pa tudi dejstvo, da je bil
                    edenn najpomembnejših hrvaških disidentov. Njegov primer razkriva vprašanje
                    hrvaškega gibanja za nacionalno reformo, znanega pod imenom Hrvaška pomlad.
                    Zaradi močnega značaja ga ni bilo strah braniti lastnih stališč celo v bojih
                    s tovariši komunisti, ki so zasedali pomembnejše funkcije v hierarhiji Zveze
                    komunistov Jugoslavije, kar je povzročilo njegov politični zaton. Članek
                    predstavlja ključne trenutke njegovih disidentskih in političnih nesoglasij
                    s tovariši, zaradi katerih si je v partiji prislužil status odpadnika. Prav
                    tako obravnava trditve, da naj bi Holjevac postal vodja Hrvaške
                    pomladi.</hi></p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Ključne besede: Većeslav Holjevac, disident, Zveza komunistov
                        Jugoslavije, Komunistična partija Hrvaške, Hrvaška pomlad</hi></p></div>
            <div type="abstract" xml:lang="en">
                <head>ABSTRACT</head>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Croatian politician Većeslav Holjevac (1917–1970) has been
                        remembered as one of the most successful mayors of the city of Zagreb.
                        However, his character and political work are scarcely known to the public
                        today. His merits in the cultural sphere are mostly forgotten, as well as
                        the fact that he was one of the most important Croatian dissidents. His case
                        delineates the issue of the Croatian national reform movement known as the
                        Croatian Spring. Due to his solid character he was not afraid to defend his
                        standpoints, even in the fights with communist comrades who were higher in
                        the hierarchy of the League of Communists of Yugoslavia, which caused his
                        political decline. The article presents the critical moments of his dissent
                        and political disagreement with his comrades that led him to the role of the
                        party renegade. The article also discusses the claims that Holjevac was to
                        become the leader of the Croatian Spring.</hi></p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Keywords: Većeslav Holjevac, dissident, League of Communists
                        of Yugoslavia, League of Communists of Croatia, Croatian Spring</hi></p>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div>
                <head>Introduction</head>
                <p> Većeslav Holjevac is partially known in Croatian history, primarily as one of
                    the most beloved mayors of the City of Zagreb. The public image of Holjevac is
                    mostly positive and often reduced to the successful urban development of Zagreb.
                    His political career was promising at one point, but progressively faded and was
                    finally over in 1967 due to his disagreement with some of his communist comrades
                    who were higher in the hierarchy. In this article, I will try to show the key
                    moments in his life that directed him to the path of the Party renegade. I will
                    try to elucidate the reasons for his political decline and to show what kind of
                    dissident he was.</p>
                <p>There is not much written about Većeslav Holjevac as a dissident. Moreover, there
                    are very few scientific papers written about him at all. To date, there is no
                    historiographically relevant biography of his. The only monograph dedicated to
                    him <hi rend="italic">Većeslav Holjevac: builder, visionary, warrior</hi>,
                    edited by Juraj Hrženjak,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn2" n="1">
                            <hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">Juraj Hrženjak, ed., </hi><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Većeslav Holjevac: graditelj,
                                vizionar,
                            ratnik</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve"> (Zagreb: Savez antifašističkih boraca i antifašista Republike Hrvatske; Multigraf Marketing, 2006).</hi>
                        </note> includes some valuable articles and data but it cannot be
                    considered a historiographical biography. The most serious monograph about
                    Holjevac is the MA thesis written by Iva Kraljević, who analysed his presidency
                    of the Emigrant Foundation of Croatia (EFC) in the period 1964-1968.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn3" n="2"><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve"> Iva Kraljević, “Većeslav Holjevac – predsjednik Matice iseljenika Hrvatske 1964. </hi>–
                                <hi style="font-size:10pt">1968” (Magistarski rad, Sveučilište u
                                Zagrebu, 2007).</hi></note> Unfortunately, it has not yet been
                    published as a book, so its availability is quite weak. Holjevac was not much
                    elaborated in the scientific articles as well, except for a few valuable
                    articles by Iva Kraljević<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn4" n="3"><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve"> Iva Kraljević, “Matica iseljenika Hrvatske 1964. – 1968.,” </hi><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Časopis za suvremenu
                                povijest</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve"> 41, No. 1 (2009): 71–92. Iva Kraljević, “Uloga Komande grada Zagreba u životu Grada prvih poslijeratnih mjeseci 1945. godine,” in:</hi>
                            <hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">1945.</hi> – <hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Razdjelnica hrvatske povijesti</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt">, eds. Nada Kisić Kolanović et al. (Zagreb:
                                Hrvatski institut za povijest, 2006), 451</hi>–<hi style="font-size:10pt">61.</hi></note> and the article written
                    by Katarina Spehnjak on Holjevac in 1967.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn5" n="4"><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve"> Katarina Spehnjak, “Većeslav Holjevac u političkim događajima 1967. godine,” </hi><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Časopis za suvremenu
                                povijest</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve"> 32, No. 3 (2000): 567–96.</hi></note>
                    Besides, information about Holjevac can be found in several obituaries and small
                    articles written in his memory,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn6" n="5">
                            <hi style="font-size:10pt">The list of obituaries can be found in</hi>
                            <hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Hrvatski biografski
                                leksikon</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt">, Većeslav Holjevac,
                                accessed July 26, 2017,</hi>
                            <ref target="http://hbl.lzmk.hr/clanak.aspx?id=67"><hi style="font-size:10pt">http://hbl.lzmk.hr/clanak.aspx?id=67</hi></ref><hi style="font-size:10pt">.</hi></note> of which Slavko Goldstein’s
                    was the most informative.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn7" n="6">
                            <hi style="font-size:10pt">Slavko Goldstein, “Nacrt za Vecinu
                                biografiju,”</hi>
                            <hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Kritika</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve"> 3, No. 14 (1970): 618–27; this article was also published in Hrženjak, </hi><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Većeslav
                        Holjevac.</hi></note> Some sporadic information about him can be found
                    in the published diaries and memoirs of his contemporaries.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn8" n="7">
                            <hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">See for example Savka Dabčević Kučar, </hi><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">’71. Hrvatski snovi i
                                stvarnost</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve"> (Zagreb: Interpublic, 1997).</hi></note>
                </p>
                <p>As far as the available resources are concerned, several important archival funds
                    are consulted for writing this paper. I used three archival funds of the
                    Croatian State Archives (HR HDA). The fund of the Central Committee (CC) of the
                    League of Communists of Croatia (LCC) (HR HDA, 1220), the fund of the Parliament
                    of the Socialist Republic of Croatia (SRC) (HR HDA, 1081) and the fund of the
                    Ministry for the newly exempted territories of the Federal People’s Republic of
                    Yugoslavia (FPRY) (HR HDA, 1086). In the State Archives in Zagreb (HR DAZG), I
                    consulted the People's Committee of the City of Zagreb archival fund (HR DAZG,
                    37). As a source for some of the data, I used the interview Tatjana Holjevac
                    (daughter of Većeslav) gave on the radio show Historical Controversies.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn9" n="8">
                            <hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">“Povijesne kontroverze” (radio show), </hi>
                            <hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Third program of Croatian
                                Radio</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt">, November 17,
                        2017.</hi></note> I also used Većeslav Holjevac’s interviews he gave to
                    the press in the 1960s, as well as some books and articles that directly or
                    indirectly referred to Holjevac.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head> Military and Political Career</head>
                <p> Većeslav Holjevac was born in Karlovac on August 22, 1917, in a family of
                    workers. He attended high school in his native city, but due to the difficult
                    financial situation, he had to quit school and become a commercial assistant.
                    The then difficult situation of the entire working class led him to engage in
                    the struggle for workers’ rights, so he soon joined and became an active member
                    of several trade unions. In the summer of 1939 he became a member of the
                    Communist Party of Croatia (CPC),<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn10" n="9"><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve"> Većeslav Holjevac, </hi><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">Zapisi iz rodnog grada </hi><hi style="font-size:10pt">(Zagreb: Nakladni zavod Matice hrvatske,
                                1972), 48.</hi></note> and in early 1941 he was a member of the
                    CPC’s District Committee for Karlovac.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn11" n="10">
                            <hi style="font-size:10pt">Milan Bekić, Ivo Butković and Slavko
                                Goldstein,</hi>
                            <hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Okrug Karlovac
                            1941.</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve"> (Zagreb: Institut za historiju radničkog pokreta, 1965), 21. </hi></note></p>
                <p>At the beginning of the Second World War in Yugoslavia in 1941 he was a soldier
                    of the regular army of the Kingdom of Yugoslavia stationed in Zagreb area, near
                    Samobor. After the proclamation of the Independent State of Croatia on April 10,
                    1941, Holjevac organized the escape of a group of prisoners from Samobor and
                    walked more than 50 km to Karlovac.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn12" n="11"><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve"> Holjevac, </hi><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Zapisi iz rodnog grada</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt">, 71</hi>–<hi style="font-size:10pt">84.</hi>
                        </note> As a member of the Military Committee of the CPC’s District
                    Committee for Karlovac, Kordun and Banija, he was one of the organizers of the
                    Partisan uprising in Kordun.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn13" n="12">
                            <hi style="font-size:10pt">Bekić, Butković and Goldstein,</hi>
                            <hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Okrug Karlovac 1941.</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt">, 238</hi>–<hi style="font-size:10pt">42.</hi></note> In the fall of 1942, Holjevac became Commissar
                    of the Second Operation Zone and from the end of 1942 to 1945, the Commissar of
                    the First Corps of the People’s Liberation Army of Croatia, which, at the same
                    time, was the Fourth Shock Corps of the People’s Liberation Army of
                        Yugoslavia.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn14" n="13"><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve"> Hrženjak,</hi>
                            <hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Većeslav Holjevac</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt">, 154</hi>–<hi style="font-size:10pt">57.</hi></note></p>
                <p>When the Partisan units entered Zagreb in May 1945, Holjevac participated in the
                    final battles for the liberation of Trieste and Istria as Commissar of the
                    Fourth Corps of the Yugoslav Army. However, the Command of the City of Zagreb
                    was formed in Topusko during the war operations, and Holjevac was, as a
                    lieutenant general, scheduled to become its commander.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn15" n="14"><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve"> F. Kiseljak, “Zapisi i intervjui Većeslava Holjevca: Tri puta u Zagrebu,”</hi>
                            <hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">Večernji list </hi><hi style="font-size:10pt">(Zagrebačko izdanje), July 13, 1970, 4.</hi>
                        </note> He took the command of the City of Zagreb on May 9, 1945.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn16" n="15"><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve"> Kraljević, “Uloga Komande grada Zagreba,” 452.</hi></note>
                    He performed the duty until the end of July 1945 when he was appointed deputy
                    commander (he later became commander) of the Military Administration of the
                    Yugoslav Army for Istria and the Slovene Littoral.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn17" n="16"><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve"> HR HDA, 1220, Dispatch Books of the Central Committee's Organizational Instructional Administration 1943 – 1946, book No. 1, dispatch No. 1037, July 23, 1945. According to Kraljević, “Uloga Komande grada Zagreba,” 460.</hi>
                        </note> From 1947 to 1948 he was the head of the Military Mission of the
                    Federal People's Republic of Yugoslavia (FPRY) in Berlin. </p>
                <p>In 1948 Holjevac completed his military career and started his political carrier
                    on a high level. He was a member of the Central Committee of the CPC,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn18" n="17">
                            <hi style="font-size:10pt">The Communist Party of Croatia (CPC) changed
                                its name to League of Communists of Croatia (LCC) in
                        1952.</hi></note> a member of the Parliament of the People’s Republic of
                    Croatia (PRC) from 1947 until his death, a member of the Federal Assembly (of
                    the FPRY), and served as a minister in the Federal Government in several
                        mandates.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn19" n="18">
                            <hi style="font-size:10pt">See Holjevac files in the files of the PRC's
                                Parliament members in HR HDA, 1081, box. 1768, 1773, 1778, 1790,
                                1793.</hi></note> In 1948, he was appointed Minister of the
                    newly established federal Ministry for the Newly Liberated Territories. His
                    primary task was the organization of state administration and economy in Istria
                    and the Slovene Littoral regions that were annexed to the FPRY based on a peace
                    agreement with Italy.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn20" n="19"><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve"> HR HDA, 1086, box. 1.</hi></note>
                    He was in charge until 1950 when he was appointed Minister of Labor in the
                    Federal Government. In 1951, he was appointed Minister of Transport and Maritime
                    Affairs of the PRC’s Government. In autumn 1952 he became the President of the
                    People's Committee of Zagreb, which was equivalent to today's duty of the mayor
                    of Zagreb.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn21" n="20"><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve"> HR DAZG, 37, Sessions of representative bodies, Minutes of the meetings of the People's Committee of the City of Zagreb, book 15, 1952, Short record of the 23</hi><hi rend="superscript" style="font-size:10pt">rd</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve"> Session held on October 6-7, 1952.</hi></note>
                    Holjevac’s mayoral mandate, which lasted more than a decade, was marked by
                    significant projects that accelerated the development of Zagreb.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn22" n="21">
                            <hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">More about his mayoral mandate and city projects see Josip Mihaljević, “Stota obljetnica rođenja Većeslava Holjevca (1917. </hi>–<hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve"> 1970.),”</hi><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve"> Zagreb moj grad</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve"> (Zagreb) 11, No. 64 (2017): 6</hi> –<hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">11. Ivo Goldstein, “Novo lice grada,” in: Goran Hutinec and Ivo Goldstein, </hi>
                            <hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Povijest grada Zagreba</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt">, vol. 2 (Zagreb: Novi Liber, 2013),
                                174</hi>–<hi style="font-size:10pt">241. Marko Blažević, “Vizionar
                                suvremenog Zagreba,” in:</hi>
                            <hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Holjevac, graditelj, vizionar,
                                ratnik</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt">, 42</hi>–<hi style="font-size:10pt">44.</hi></note> He was in the mayoral
                    position until the abolition of the People’s Committees as
                    administrative-representative bodies in 1963.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn23" n="22">
                            <hi style="font-size:10pt">The function that was previously performed by
                                the People's Committee was taken over by the City Assembly. The
                                president of the City Assembly took over mayoral duties. Holjevac
                                was not even elected to the City Assembly. HR DAZG, 37, Sessions of
                                representative bodies, Joint Sessions of the City Council and the
                                Council of Producers, book 94.</hi></note>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Party Conflicts and Disagreements</head>
                <p> Slavko Goldstein believes that the first signs of Holjevac’s disagreements with
                    his Party comrades emerged in the period of the Second World War. He states
                    that, after Vladimir Bakarić left his position as a political commissar of the
                    Main Headquarters of Croatia in 1944, Holjevac was supposed to fill that
                    position. He was the Commissar of the First Corps (the largest formation of the
                    Croatian Partisan Army) and was then a Party member who had most experience as
                    commissar and the one with the best reputation.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn24" n="23"><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve"> Goldstein, “Nacrt za Vecinu biografiju,” 621.</hi>
                        </note> However, instead of Holjevac, Rade Žigić, former Commissar of
                    the 6<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> (Lika) Division, which was a part of the
                    Corps Holjevac commanded. So, Žigić was a person who was directly subordinate to
                    Holjevac. Goldstein findes this “skipping” of Holjevac problematic: <hi rend="italic">“In the absence of a document that would give a reliable
                        answer, we can only speculate: allegedly Veco</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn25" n="24"><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve"> Veco was the nickname of Većeslav Holjevac.</hi></note><hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve"> was not orthodox enough, he was not sufficiently ‘red’ commissar, in the Soviet sense of the word. Alternatively, perhaps he was skipped because of the national key. Due to the relatively large number of Serbs in the Partisan Army of Croatia, a Serb should have come to one of the most important positions? Or Veco was simply considered to be too young for such a duty.”</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn26" n="25">
                            <hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">Goldstein, “Nacrt za Vecinu biografiju,” 621. </hi></note></p>
                <p>According to Slavko Goldstein, first Holjevac’s significant disagreement with the
                    party hierarchy after the war occurred at the Third Congress of LCC, which was
                    held in May 1954. At that time Marijan Stilinović, member of the Executive
                    Committee of the Central Committee of LCC, due to his liberal attitudes was
                    removed from the political leadership and political life.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn27" n="26"><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve"> Zdenko Radelić, “Đilasovci u Hrvatskoj i hrvatska historiografija,” in:</hi>
                            <hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Disidentstvo u suvremenoj
                                povijesti</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt">, eds. Nada Kisić Kolanović
                                et al. (Zagreb: Hrvatski institut za povijest, 2010), 63.</hi>
                        </note> Contrary to usual practice, Holjevac continued to maintain close
                    relations with Stilinović, who was his friend and neighbour. According to
                    Goldstein, this was a sufficient reason for the directive which came from the
                    top, not to choose Holjevac for his next mandate in the Central Committee.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn28" n="27">
                            <hi style="font-size:10pt">Goldstein, “Nacrt za Vecinu biografiju,”
                                626.</hi>
                        </note> Although we cannot be sure that this was the reason, the fact is
                    that Holjevac's absence from the next Central Committee was quite surprising
                    given his reputation at that time.</p>
                <p>Holjevac was known as an active person who skillfully avoided bureaucratic and
                    formal obstacles. <hi rend="italic">Nova Hrvatska</hi>, a journal of Croatian
                    emigres in an article about Holjevac’s sudden death in 1970, says: “In
                    organisational works, he had no peers. As very few of them, he had succeeded in
                    avoiding the influence of the communist bureaucracy that kills any
                        initiative.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn29" n="28">
                            <hi style="font-size:10pt">“Iznenadna smrt Većeslava Holjevca,”</hi>
                            <hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Nova Hrvatska</hi>
                            <hi style="font-size:10pt">12, No. 2-3 (August 1970): 5, 6.</hi>
                        </note> In that sense, his conflict with centralist bureaucracy was most
                    important. That bureaucracy was considered an obstacle for Yugoslavia’s
                    progress, especially in Croatia and Slovenia. Many Croatian communists thought
                    Croatia was investing too much in federal funds and the capital of Yugoslavia
                    (Belgrade) while other republic centres were unjustly lagging behind. As a Mayor
                    of Zagreb, Holjevac had shown that it was possible to develop other cities,
                    their industry and infrastructure, despite the opposition of the centralist
                    bureaucracy.</p>
                <p>Moving the Zagreb Fair to a new location was the risky undertaking of Većeslav
                    Holjevac. Namely, in the fall of 1955, Holjevac found out that Belgrade was
                    planning to build a new trade fair that was supposed to have an international
                    character and should become the central fair event for the whole of Yugoslavia.
                    This meant that the Zagreb Fair would have lost its significance and probably
                    had been abolished as redundant, although it had a long tradition.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn30" n="29">
                            <hi style="font-size:10pt">Mihaljević, “Stota obljetnica rođenja,” 8,
                                9.</hi></note> Moreover, Zagreb would face an even higher degree
                    of isolation. The Croatian Communist leadership did not see any problem in this,
                    because they thought it reasonable for Belgrade, as the capital of Yugoslavia,
                    to take precedence. Holjevac recognised the situation as a potential threat to
                    the development and significance of Zagreb and reacted. He knew that the then
                    location of the Zagreb Fair (Savska cesta) in the centre of the city was
                    perspectiveless because the Fair could not spread due to the lack of space. He
                    took full responsibility and decided to build a new fair at another, more
                    favourable location. He neglected the five-year plan and ordered the entire
                    Zagreb’s constructional industry to build the Zagreb Fair on the southern shore
                    of Sava in only one year. Numerous associates told him that this was an
                    impossible mission, especially because the project did not have the financial
                    support of the state.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn31" n="30"><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve"> Ivan Strižić, </hi><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Hrvatski
                                portreti</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">: </hi><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">lice i naličje hrvatskoga bića,
                                2</hi><hi rend="italic superscript" style="font-size:10pt">nd</hi><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve"> ed.</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve"> (Zagreb: DoNeHa, 1996), 282, 283.</hi></note>
                    However, the construction was completed within the deadline due to the maximum
                    engagement, but also the financing model in which the states that were supposed
                    to exhibit in Zagreb Fair build their pavilions themselves.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn32" n="31"><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve"> Rikard Štajner, “Skok preko Save,” in:</hi>
                            <hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Holjevac, graditelj, vizionar,
                                ratnik</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt">, 49.</hi></note></p>
                <p>Moving to a new location allowed the Zagreb Fair to remain the leading trade fair
                    in Yugoslavia, which was not in favour of centralist-oriented politicians who,
                    according to some opinions, have since become extremely dissatisfied with
                    Holjevac. Moreover, Aleksandar Ranković, the most signifficant representative of
                    the centralist circles within the top hierarchy of the Party, a longtime
                    minister of interior, who had the greatest influence on the notorious State
                    Security Administration (<hi rend="italic">Uprava državne bezbednosti</hi> -
                    UDBA), allegedly directly threatened Holjevac. A very well-informed journal of
                    Croatian emigres <hi rend="italic">Nova Hrvatska</hi>, wrote about Holjevac’s
                    conflict with Ranković saying that Holjevac risked his life in the case of
                    Zagreb Fair.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn33" n="32">
                            <hi style="font-size:10pt">“Iznenadna smrt Većeslava Holjevca,” 5,
                                6.</hi></note> In 1972, at the Zagreb District Court on the
                    trial that was conducted against Franjo Tuđman, Tuđman said that Holjevac was
                    threatened with potential persecution “because he was building a new trade fair
                    without permission and because he retained in Zagreb the money that was supposed
                    to go to the federal government.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn34" n="33"><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve"> Franjo Tuđman, </hi><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Usudbene
                            povjestice</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve"> (Zagreb: Hrvatska sveučilišna naklada, 1995), 258.</hi></note></p>
                <p>According to Tatjana Holjevac’s testimony<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn35" n="34"><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve"> “Povijesne kontroverze.”</hi></note>
                    Aleksandar Ranković threatened Holjevac that he would face the consequences if
                    he builds a new trade fair in Zagreb. She said in the interview that the whole
                    Holjevac family was monitored and eavesdropped by UDBA.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn36" n="35">
                            <hi style="font-size:10pt">UDBA’s file on Holjevac could not be found in
                                the Croatian State Archives where that kind of records and other
                                archival material created by UDBA are preserved (Archival fund HR
                                HDA, 1561). It is hard to answer the question of whether the file
                                existed or not, and if it exists why it is not placed in the
                                Croatian State Archives.</hi></note> Furthermore, she said that
                    Ranković threatened Holjevac saying: “The Fair will go to Belgrade or you will
                    go to Goli Otok!”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn37" n="36">
                            <hi style="font-size:10pt">Goli otok is a small island located in the
                                northern Adriatic Sea which the communist authorities transformed
                                into a secret prison, and labour camp used to incarcerate political
                                prisoners.</hi></note> However, military general Ivan Gošnjak,
                    federal secretary of defense, protected Holjevac by managing him a meeting with
                    Yugoslav President Josip Broz Tito. After four-hour talks, Tito gave support for
                    the construction of the new Zagreb Fair.</p>
                <p>There are no documents available which can confirm that Ranković’s threat
                    happened. Holjevac was a relatively high-rank politician and respected person,
                    with a big reputation as people’s hero to be openly threatened. However, if we
                    have in mind Ranković’s way of action, it is not impossible that he threatened
                    Holjevac. As a longtime head of UDBA and internal affairs, Ranković used these
                    institutions not only against the enemies of the state or the enemies of the
                    ruling Communist Party but also as a means of control within the Party. At the
                    time of Ranković’s political peak, there was a belief that he and his service
                    keep the files on his comrades and that, if necessary, something compromising
                    could be found on almost everyone.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn38" n="37">
                            <hi style="font-size:10pt">See for example Josip Mihaljević,
                                “Razilaženja u SKJ - marginalizacija Vicka Krstulovića,“ in:</hi>
                            <hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Disidentstvo u suvremenoj
                                povijesti</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt">, eds. Nada Kisić
                                Kolanović, Zdenko Radelić, Katarina Spehnjak (Zagreb: Hrvatski
                                institut za povijest, 2010), 259.</hi></note> In that sense, he
                    could have some file on Holjevac and some dangerous material against him.
                    Perhaps this might have been the fact that Holjevac’s older brother Leon was a
                    member of the Croatian Home Guard. At the end of the war, he even gained a
                    military rank, although he did not participate in any military action, but
                    earned the rank as a musician playing in the military orchestra.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn39" n="38">
                            <hi style="font-size:10pt">“Povijesne kontroverze”.</hi></note> In
                    his memoirs, Holjevac describes his brother as a man who was interested only in
                    music, not in politics.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn40" n="39"><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve"> His memoirs (</hi><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Zapisi iz rodnog grada</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt">), which he prepared for printing before his
                                death, were published posthumously in 1972.</hi></note> In the
                    last days of the war, the Partisans captured him somewhere near Zagreb and
                    killed him. It was never established where and how he was killed. Većeslav could
                    not find him and save him.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn41" n="40"><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve"> Goldstein, “Nacrt za Vecinu biografiju,” 622.</hi>
                        </note> The death of Leon was a taboo topic in Holjevac’s family.
                    Tatjana Holjevac said that her mother, Nada, did not allow her children to talk
                    about Leon, as well as about Milovan Đilas or Andrija Hebrang until they became
                        grown-ups.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn42" n="41">
                            <hi style="font-size:10pt">“Povijesne kontroverze.”</hi></note> By
                    all accounts, the fact that his brother was a member of Croatian Home Guard and
                    killed by the partisans could have been information which Ranković could use
                    against Holjevac.</p>
                <p>One of the key questions of Holjevac’s biography is why did not he get a new
                    mayoral mandate in Zagreb? His mandate expired in October 1963. According to
                    many of his contemporaries, although his results in Zagreb were remarkable, his
                    political views, Croatian patriotism and enormous popularity in the Croatian
                    capital city were not met with sympathies in the centralist circles in the Party
                        leadership.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn43" n="42">
                            <hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">This is also one of the motifs of the novel by Josip Barković, </hi><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">Rasplet u Rimu: roman o Zagrebačkom velesajmu </hi><hi style="font-size:10pt">[Denouement in Rome: a novel about the Zagreb
                                Fair] (Zagreb: Naklada Pavičić, 2002), in which the author presents
                                the conflict between the advocates of more liberal political and
                                economic ideas, and the orthodox communist bureaucrats, who
                                supported central planning in economy and total control in social
                                life.</hi></note> Holjevac’s emphasis on the need for stronger
                    integration of Croatia was a thorn in centralists’ side. In an interview he gave
                    while he was still the head of Zagreb, he said that Zagreb needs to use its
                    position more actively and to become a connecting point for all parts of Croatia
                    and that it is a “great harm for Zagreb and for the whole community that we do
                    not yet have modern road connections with Dalmatia.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn44" n="43"><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve"> Kiseljak, “Zapisi i intervjui Većeslava Holjevca,” 4.</hi></note>
                    Whether due to disagreement with individuals in the Party or for some other
                    reason, the fact is that the Presidency of the Central Committee of LCC did not
                    propose Holjevac for a new mayoral mandate.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn45" n="44"><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve"> Kraljević, “Većeslav Holjevac – predsjednik Matice iseljenika Hrvatske,” 17, 18. Barković, </hi><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Rasplet u Rimu</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt">, 143, 144.</hi></note></p>
                <p>After his mayoral mandate, Holjevac continued his political career as a member of
                    the SRC’s Parliament, member of the Executive Council of the Parliament, and in
                    1964 was elected as the new president of the Emigrant Foundation of Croatia
                    (EFC). Although Holjevac’s work in the EFC was considered by many as marginal,
                    in the four-year period, he developed a significant activity in connecting the
                    Croatian diaspora with their homeland. He extended the EFC’s scope and
                    activities. By the end of 1967 EFC co-operated with about a hundred emigrant
                    organisations and more than five thousand individuals. At the time, Holjevac
                    published his first book, <hi rend="italic">Croats abroad</hi>.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn46" n="45"><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve"> Većeslav Holjevac, </hi><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Hrvati izvan
                            domovine</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve"> (Zagreb: Matica hrvatska, 1967).</hi></note>
                    It was the first systematically written book on Croatian emigrants, in which he
                    reported that more than 25 % of Croats live outside Yugoslavia.</p>
                <p>Two significant conflicts that caused his final political decline happened during
                    his mandate in EFC. In 1966, as the president of the Božidar Adžija Awards<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn47" n="46"><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve"> It was the highest state award for scientific and cultural achievements.</hi></note>
                    Committee, Holjevac insisted on awarding Gajo Petrović and Milan Kangrga. They
                    were part of the intellectual circle gathered around the critically oriented
                    journal <hi rend="italic">Praxis</hi>,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn48" n="47"><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve"> More on Praxis intellectuals see Albert Bing, “Praxis and Korčula Summer School Collection,”</hi>
                            <hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">COURAGE Registry</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt">, 2018, accessed August 29, 2018,</hi>
                            <ref target="http://cultural-opposition.eu/registry/?uri=http://courage.btk.mta.hu/courage/individual/n31917&amp;type=collections"><hi style="font-size:10pt">http://cultural-opposition.eu/registry/?uri=http://courage.btk.mta.hu/courage/individual/n31917&amp;type=collections</hi></ref><hi rend="Hyperlink"><seg style="font-size:10pt">.</seg></hi></note>
                    and as such, the highest Party officials considered their philosophical books
                    unsuitable for the prize. The Party leaders considered their social criticism
                        destructive.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn49" n="48"><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve"> Dunja Bonacci Skenderović, “Radio Slobodna Europa o sukobima jugoslavenske vlasti i časopisa Praxis (1972. </hi>–<hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve"> 1975.),” in:</hi>
                            <hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Dijalog povjesničara –
                                istoričara 8</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt">, eds. Hans Georg Fleck
                                and Igor Graovac (Zagreb: Friedrich Naumann Stiftung, 2004), 283.
                                Kraljević, “Matica iseljenika Hrvatske 1964.</hi> –<hi style="font-size:10pt">1968.,” 88.</hi></note> In May 1966, the
                    Secretariat of the LCC’s City Committee of Zagreb wrote a complaint with
                    objections regarding the award criteria and the case was discussed at the
                    meeting of the Executive Committee of the CC LCC.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn50" n="49"><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve"> HR HDA, 1220, Executive Council, Commission for the Examination of Nationalist Phenomena in the Emigrant Foundation of Croatia 1964-1967, box. 30, </hi><hi rend="short_text"><seg style="font-size:10pt">Controversy over the
                                    ‘Božidar Adžija’ Awards
                            in</seg></hi><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve"> 1966, Record No. 02-413/1-1966, May 7, 1966.</hi></note>
                    The Executive Committee rated the decision to award the Praxis intellectuals as
                    a “direct attack on CC LCC and the policy of LCC.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn51" n="50">
                            <hi style="font-size:10pt">HR HDA, 1220, Executive Council, Record of
                                the session of the Executive Council of the Central Committee of the
                                League of Communists of Croatia held on May 12, 1966, p. 1:</hi>
                            <hi rend="short_text"><seg style="font-size:10pt">according
                                to</seg></hi><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve"> Iva Kraljević Bašić, “Većeslav Holjevac i Nagrada fonda Božidar Adžija 1966.,” in:</hi>
                            <hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Disidentstvo u suvremenoj
                                povijesti</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt">, eds. Nada Kisić
                                Kolanović, et al. (Zagreb: Hrvatski institut za povijest, 2010),
                                378.</hi></note> The Party critique was also published in the
                    daily press.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn52" n="51">
                            <hi style="font-size:10pt">“Kamuflirana politička akcija,”</hi>
                            <hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Vjesnik</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt">, June 25, 1966, l. Cf. Kraljević Bašić,
                                “Većeslav Holjevac i Nagrada fonda Božidar Adžija,” 382.</hi>
                        </note></p>
                <p>Contrary to the Party’s judgement, as the chairman of the Awarding Committee,
                    Holjevac continued to justify the Awarding Committee’s choice. He defended the
                    decision stating that the Awarding Committee was composed of members who were
                    recognised experts and academics.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn53" n="52"><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve"> Ibid.,” 380.</hi></note>
                    Because of this, the Republican Chamber of the SRC’s Parliament on the proposal
                    of Miloš Žanko, but in fact on the instruction of Executive Committee of the CC
                    LCC, decided to dismiss Većeslav Holjevac from the position of the chairman of
                    the Awarding Committee. He was prepared to bear the consequences of his actions
                    which is evident “from his indifferent and somewhat disinterested behaviour at
                    the discussion of the Republican Chamber of the SRC’s Parliament.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn54" n="53"><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve"> Ibid., 383.</hi></note></p>
                <p> However, this was not the end of Holjevac’s conflicts with higher Party circles.
                    His political downturn was related to Party purges that were conducted in
                    Croatia after the publication of the Declaration on the Name and Status of the
                    Croatian Literary Language in March 1967. The Declaration was a manifesto of
                    Croatian linguists who were dissatisfied with the published dictionaries and
                    language praxis in Croatia in which the language was called Serbo-Croatian.
                    Croat scholars gathered around <hi rend="italic">Matica hrvatska</hi>, the
                    leading cultural institution in Croatia, made the text of the Declaration and it
                    was signed by the Society of Writers of Croatia, and seventeen other Croatian
                    scolar and cultural institutions. <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn55" n="54">
                            <hi style="font-size:10pt">“Deklaracija o nazivu i položaju hrvatskog
                                književnog jezika,”</hi>
                            <hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Matica
                                hrvatska</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">, accessed August 20, 2018, </hi><ref target="http://www.matica.hr/kolo/314/Deklaracija%20o%20nazivu%20i%20polo%C5%BEaju%20hrvatskog%20knji%C5%BEevnog%20jezika/"><hi style="font-size:10pt">http://www.matica.hr/kolo/314/Deklaracija%20o%20nazivu%20i%20polo%C5%BEaju%20hrvatskog%20knji%C5%BEevnog%20jezika/</hi></ref><hi style="font-size:10pt">.</hi></note></p>
                <p>EFC was not a signatory of the Declaration, nor its President Većeslav Holjevac.
                    However, as one of the leading representatives of the national and democratic
                    reform wing of the LCC, Holjevac advocated the defence of Croatian national
                    interests within the Yugoslav federation. For this reason, even though he was
                    not a signatory to the Declaration, he was subjected to a Party investigation as
                    a person whose “behaviour contributed to the appearance of the Declaration.”
                    Paradoxically, the EFC’s Main Committee, led by Holjevac, condemned the adoption
                    and publishing of the Declaration at its regular session on March 30, 1967.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn56" n="55"><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve"> “Književni jezik Hrvata i Srba,”</hi>
                            <hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Matica</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve"> 17, No. 6 (1967): 219. Cf. Marko Samardžija, ed., </hi>
                            <hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">Deklaracija o nazivu i položaju Hrvatskog književnog jezika 1967. – 2017.: vijesti komentari, osude, zaključci </hi><hi style="font-size:10pt">(Zagreb: Matica hrvatska, 2017), 291</hi>–<hi style="font-size:10pt">95.</hi></note> Why did Holjevac found
                    himself in the line of fire? The answer can be found in Vladimir Bakaric’s
                    speech at the meeting of the CC LCC’s Presidency on April 3, 1967. He said: “I
                    was unwilling to involve comrade Holjevac into this thing if he has nothing to
                    do with it, but we need to talk about the focal points of nationalism and to
                    establish his attitude towards them.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn57" n="56"><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve"> Vladimir Bakarić, </hi><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Socijalistički samoupravni
                                sistem i društvena
                                reprodukcija</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">, </hi><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">vol.
                            2</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve"> (Zagreb: Informator; Mladost; Svjetlost, 1983), 367.</hi></note></p>
                <p>Some of Holjevac’s contemporaries, as well as some historians nowadays, believe
                    that Bakarić was the crucial person responsible for Holjevac’s political fall.
                    Josip Boljkovac, Holjavac’s friend and Party comrade, believed that the case of
                    the Božidar Adžija Awards in 1966 was the beginning of the conflict between
                    Holjevac and Bakarić.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn58" n="57"><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve"> Josip Boljkovac, </hi><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Istina mora izaći van: sjećanja
                                i zapisi prvog ministra unutarnjih poslova neovisne
                            Hrvatske</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve"> (Zagreb: Golden marketing - Tehnička knjiga, 2009), 144.</hi></note>
                    Historian Ivo Goldstein claims that Bakarić wanted to eliminate Holjevac because
                    he “bounced out of nomenklatura too much and was too liberal,” but also because
                    Bakarić saw Holjevac as a direct competitor due to his popularity.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn59" n="58"><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve"> Ivo Goldstein, </hi><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Hrvatska 1918–2008</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve"> (Zagreb: EPH; Novi Liber, 2008), 492, 493. Cf. Dino Mujadžević, </hi>
                            <hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Bakarić: politička
                                biografija</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve"> (Zagreb: Plejada; Hrvatski institut za povijest – Podružnica Slavonski Brod, 2011), 268, 269.</hi></note>
                </p>
                <p>The case of Holjevac was also discussed at the Seventh Plenum of the CC LCC held
                    on 19 and 20 April 1967. On that occasion, defending himself from the attack of
                    pro-unitarist politician Miloš Žanko, Holjevac stated that he always sensed his
                    national identity but that at the same time he always condemned chauvinism and
                        nationalism.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn60" n="59">
                            <hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Sedmi plenum CK SK
                                Hrvatske</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">: </hi><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">O međunacionalnim odnosima </hi><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">(Zagreb: Informativna služba CK SKH, 1967), 70. </hi></note>
                    The Plenum concluded that the CC LCC’s Executive Committee forms a Commission
                    for the Examination of Nationalist Phenomena in the Emigrant Foundation of
                    Croatia, solely to monitor the activities of the EFC’s president, Većeslav
                    Holjevac and some of his associates and to establishing their political
                        responsibility.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn61" n="60"><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve"> HR HDA, 1220, Executive Council, Commission for the Examination of Nationalist Phenomena in the Emigrant Foundation of Croatia 1964-1967, box. 30, A conclusion on the basis of a report submitted by the Commission for the Examination of Nationalist Phenomena in the Emigrant Foundation of Croatia, 1967, p. 1.</hi></note></p>
                <p>At the end of May 1967, the Commission held talks with Većeslav Holjevac and his
                        associates.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn62" n="61"><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve"> HR HDA, 1220, Executive Council, Commission for the Examination of Nationalist Phenomena in the Emigrant Foundation of Croatia 1964-1967, box. 30, Stenographic log of the conversations conducted by the Commission.</hi></note>
                    On June 22, 1967, the Commission wrote the report, in which it stated that the
                    EFC was “one of the focal points of nationalism”, and accused Holjevac of being
                    responsible for a “nationalist turn,” “an unhealthy climate suitable for further
                    deformation in the EFC,” as well as for attempting to “formalistically justify
                    criticized phenomena and actions.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn63" n="62"><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve"> HR HDA, 1220, Executive Council, Commission for the Examination of Nationalist Phenomena in the Emigrant Foundation of Croatia 1964-1967, box. 30, Report submitted by the Commission for the Examination of Nationalist Phenomena in the Emigrant Foundation of Croatia, 1967. Cf. Tatjana Šarić, “Commission for the Examination of Nationalist Phenomena in the Emigrant Foundation of Croatia (1964-1967),”</hi>
                            <hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">COURAGE Registry</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt">, accessed August 20, 2018,</hi>
                            <ref target="http://cultural-opposition.eu/registry/?uri=http://courage.btk.mta.hu/courage/individual/n23156&amp;type=collections"><hi style="font-size:10pt">http://cultural-opposition.eu/registry/?uri=http://courage.btk.mta.hu/courage/individual/n23156&amp;type=collections</hi></ref><hi rend="Hyperlink"><seg style="font-size:10pt">.</seg></hi></note>
                </p>
                <p>Holjevac was accused of being too openminded towards some Croatian organisations
                    in USA. The authorities considered these organisations extreme and hostile to
                    Yugoslavia. The Commission also held that the appeal for help that EFC sent to
                    emigrants during the flood in Zagreb in 1964 was nationalistic because it was
                    addressed to “Croatian emigrants and other Yugoslav citizens on temporary work
                    abroad.” One of Holjevac’s “crimes” was the non-attendance on Republic Day
                    celebration in 1966.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn64" n="63"><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve"> Ibid., 12.</hi></note>
                    The accusations included the singing of Croatian songs on New Year’s Eve.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn65" n="64"><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve"> Ibid.</hi></note>
                    He was accused of hesitating to condemn the Declaration on the Name and Status
                    of the Croatian Literary Language and its signatories, as well as inviting
                    Franjo Tuđman and some other “Croatian nationalists” into EFC’s Main
                        Committee.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn66" n="65"><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve"> Ibid., 13</hi>–<hi style="font-size:10pt">15. Cf. Tatjana Šarić, “Commission for the
                                Examination of Nationalist Phenomena.”</hi>
                        </note>
                </p>
                <p>Holjevac was found guilty of political “deviation” and was suggested to resign
                    from membership in the Central Committee of the LCC.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn67" n="66">
                            <hi style="font-size:10pt">HR HDA, 1220, Executive Council, Commission
                                for the Examination of Nationalist Phenomena in the Emigrant
                                Foundation of Croatia 1964-1967, box. 30, A conclusion on the basis
                                of a report submitted by the Commission for the Examination of
                                Nationalist Phenomena in the Emigrant Foundation of Croatia,
                                1967.</hi></note> Consequently, he was forced to resign from the
                    position of EFC’s president, but he performed the duty until the election of a
                    new president in 1968.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn68" n="67"><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve"> Kraljević, “Većeslav Holjevac – predsjednik Matice iseljenika Hrvatske.”</hi></note></p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Was Holjevac Supposed to Become the Leader of the Croatian Spring?</head>
                <p> Holjevac’s contemporaries knew very soon that he was unfairly accused of being a
                        nationalist.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn69" n="68"><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve"> Goldstein, “Nacrt za Vecinu biografiju,” 626.</hi>
                        </note> Miko Tripalo, who at the session of the Executive Committee of
                    the Central Committee of LCC on June 27, 1967, discussed the EFC case, said that
                    “Veco is a little bit infected with these nationalistic beliefs” soon changed
                    his views. In the time of the Croatian Spring, at the second session of the
                    LCC’s Conference in July 1970, Tripalo said: “we should reconsider some of our
                    decisions from the past regarding the Party relations towards some comrades.”
                    Slavko Goldstein thought Tripalo was thinking primarily of Holjevac.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn70" n="69">
                            <hi style="font-size:10pt">Ironically, Tripalo was one of the Party
                                leaders who in 1967 attacked the adoption of the Declaration and its
                                signatories, and after only a few years, as one of the leaders of
                                the Croatian Spring, he experienced a political fall under the
                                accusations of being a nationalist.</hi></note> Furthermore,
                    Holjevac enjoyed great reputation and respect among the Serbs in Croatia not
                    only because he was one of the leaders of the anti-fascist uprising in the
                    Kordun area but also after the war because he was a man who understood the
                    essence of the Serbs-Croats relations in Croatia and acted in order to improve
                    relations between them. The case of his insistence on the awards to Gajo
                    Petrović and Milan Kangrga in 1966, confirms, in a way, that the accusation for
                    nationalism was meaningless. Namely, besides the fact that he did not share
                    their viewpoints (Praxis philosophy was opposed to the Croatian national
                    movement), both of them were Serbs.</p>
                <p>Holjevac’s resignation from membership in the Central Committee of the LCC was
                    the end of his political career. He did not participate in the Croatian Spring
                    in 1971, in which he would probably be one of the most important actors. One can
                    assume this, given his past work, but also because of his attempt to return to
                    the scene in 1969/1970. Namely, in the last year of his life, together with some
                    Croatian intellectuals and economists,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn71" n="70"><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve"> Josip Boljkovac, Šime Đodan, Danijel Ivin, Božo Singer, Ante Todorić, Marko Veselica, and Vladimir Veselica.</hi></note>
                    Holjevac participated in the attempt to establish a Croatian Economic Bank that
                    supposed to be independent of Belgrade. They aimed to break the economic and
                    financial inferiority of Croatia within Yugoslavia by financing large
                    infrastructure projects and by encouraging entrepreneurship in Croatia.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn72" n="71"><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve"> Josip Boljkovac, </hi><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Istina mora izaći van: sjećanja
                                i zapisi prvog ministra unutarnjih poslova neovisne
                                Hrvatske</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve"> (Zagreb: Golden marketing - Tehnička knjiga, 2009), 139</hi>–<hi style="font-size:10pt">41. Tihomir Ponoš, “Zašto 1970. nije osnovana
                                Hrvatska gospodarska banka,” in:</hi>
                            <hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Holjevac, graditelj, vizionar,
                                ratnik</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt">, 76</hi>–<hi style="font-size:10pt">78.</hi>
                        </note> As the leader of that group, Holjevac had the idea of engaging
                    the Croatian diaspora as a vital financing source for the future bank. He
                    considered that the Croatians who worked abroad would gladly invest their
                    savings in such a bank. The attempt to establish a bank, however, has
                    failed.</p>
                <p>Many Croatian emigrants have seen Holjevac as a potential leader of a future
                    Croatian opposition. For example, Ivo Rojnica, wrote in his memoirs that it is
                    “no exaggeration to say that Holjevac, giving his human, intellectual,
                    organisational and political virtues, was potentially the most important man in
                    Croatia.” He saw Holjevac as an ideal person, “not just as the leader of the
                    unofficial opposition, but was also most suitable to take active leadership in
                    Croatia at any time.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn73" n="72"><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve"> Ivo Rojnica, </hi><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Susreti i doživljaji: razdoblje
                                od 1938. do 1975. u mojim
                                sjećanjima</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">, </hi><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">vol.
                                2</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">: </hi><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">1945</hi><hi rend="italic">–</hi><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">1975</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve"> (Zagreb: DoNeHa, 1994), 296. </hi></note>
                </p>
                <p>However, after a shorter illness, Većeslav Holjevac died in Zagreb on July 11,
                    1970, before his 53<hi rend="superscript">rd</hi> birthday. He died of cancer
                    after a few weeks of sickness. The mentioned Rojnica wrote in his memoirs in the
                    1970s that he arranged a meeting with him in July 1970 in a Western European
                    country: <hi rend="italic">“On the very day when he was supposed to travel, on
                        July 9, he suddenly felt sick and was urgently taken to a hospital, where he
                        died on July 11. It was a public secret that Holjevac was poisoned, and I am
                        giving this historical truth that he died in suspicious
                        circumstances.”</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn74" n="73">
                            <hi style="font-size:10pt">Ibid., 299. Cf. Marijan Grakalić, “Je li
                                Holjevac ubijen?”</hi>
                            <hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Globus</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt">, February 28, 1991, 12.</hi></note></p>
                <p>This was not just a rumour from emigration, but these scary rumours spread out in
                    Croatia as well, and it can be heard even nowadays. In an interview he gave for
                    the daily newspaper in 2012, Holjevac’s son Veco also expressed the suspicion
                    that his father was poisoned. <hi rend="italic">“Our family doubt, which was
                        backed up by various evidences we encountered later, is that our father is
                        actually poisoned. When Boljkovac became the first Croatian Minister of
                        Interior, he came to us with the question of whether we want to
                        re-investigate our father’s death. He came of his own initiative, obviously
                        with some solid clues. My sisters and I did not want to start the
                        investigation, because we were aware of the fact that someone will only
                        collect political points in that way, and that our father will never
                        return.”</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn75" n="74">
                            <hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">In his memoirs published in 2009, Boljkovac mentions nothing on Holjevac being murdered or poisoned. Cf. Boljkovac, </hi><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Istina mora izaći van</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt">, 145.</hi></note>
                </p>
                <p>According to his son’s suspicions, Većeslav Holjevac was assassinated because he
                    was the most prominent leader of the Croatian reform movement which later
                    flourished in the Croatian Spring. Moreover, he said that in 1967, in Plješivica
                    the forerunner of the HDZ<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn76" n="75">
                            <hi style="font-size:10pt">HDZ is an acronym of the Croatian Democratic
                                Union (Croatian: Hrvatska demokratska zajednica - HDZ), a political
                                party founded in 1989 that won the first multi-party elections in
                                Croatia in 1990.</hi></note> was established, which chose his
                    father as its leader, and the whole group later ended up with Franjo
                        Tuđman.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn77" n="76"><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve"> Bojana Mrvoš Pavić, “Veco Holjevac: Sumnjam da je moj otac Većeslav otrovan,”</hi>
                            <hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Novi list</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve"> (on-line), May 13, 2012, accessed May 27, 2018,</hi>
                            <ref target="http://novilist.hr/Vijesti/Hrvatska/Veco-Holjevac-Sumnjam-da-je-moj-otac-Veceslav-otrovan"><hi style="font-size:10pt">http://novilist.hr/Vijesti/Hrvatska/Veco-Holjevac-Sumnjam-da-je-moj-otac-Veceslav-otrovan</hi></ref><hi rend="Hyperlink"><seg style="font-size:10pt">.</seg></hi></note>
                </p>
                <p>Some authors believe that Holjevac was a potential leader of the Croatian
                    opposition. Ivan Strižić believes that in Belgrade Holjevac was considered “the
                    Croat who would be most likely to become a person who will take over the
                    Croatian helm and therefore he had to be eliminated at any cost.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn78" n="77"><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve"> Strižić, </hi><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Hrvatski portreti</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt">, 288.</hi></note> He even claims that
                    the motive for the alleged murder was his reputation among Croatian Serbs and
                    his good relations with them. Strižić believes that the supporters of the idea
                    of Greater Serbia wanted to use the Serbs in Croatia for Greater Serbia goals,
                    for which the good cooperation between Croats and Serbs in Croatia was
                    considered an obstacle.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn79" n="78"><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve"> Ibid., 290.</hi></note></p>
                <p>Holjevac belonged to the pro-Croatian circle of Croatian Communists, which,
                    besides politicians and military officers like Ivan Šibl, Ivan Rukavina, Nikola
                    Kajić, and Srećko Manola, included some important intellectuals such as writers
                    Miroslav Krleža and Petar Šegednin, historians Vaso Bogdanov and Franjo Tuđman,
                    artists Vanja Radauš and Krsto Hegedušić. Ivan Šibl mentioned in his memoirs
                    that they were “some silent, sometimes even loud, constructive opposition in the
                    Party,” and that they had, in some issues, views different from the Party line,
                    and that they advocated democratisation and the improvement of the national
                    relations in Yugoslavia.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn80" n="79"><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve"> Ivan Šibl, </hi><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Sjećanja III: Poslijeratni
                                dnevnik</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve"> (Zagreb: Globus; Naprijed, 1986), 148.</hi></note>
                    Some called this group “Krleža’s intellectual circle” or even “Croatian shadow
                    government,” describing it as a “semi-opposition” to Vladimir Bakarić and LCC’s
                    Central Committee.” They were not satisfied with Bakarić’s leadership of the
                    Croatian communists because they considered that “he does not protect Croatian
                    interests sufficiently from the pressures and manipulations from Belgrade.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn81" n="80"><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve"> Darko Hudelist, </hi><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Tuđman:
                            biografija</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve"> (Zagreb: Profil, 2004), 306, 307.</hi></note></p>
                <p>Of all the above-mentioned, Holjevac was politically the most popular among
                    Croatian people.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn82" n="81">
                            <hi style="font-size:10pt">Around 30,000 citizens attended his funeral,
                                which was by far the largest funeral in Zagreb after the funeral of
                                Stjepan Radić in 1928. See N. Fiegenwald, “Slava drugu Veci!”</hi>
                            <hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Večernji
                            list</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve"> (zagrebačko izdanje), July 14, 1970, 3.</hi></note>
                    Furthermore, he has already made an important step towards connecting the
                    Croatian emigration with the homeland.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn83" n="82">
                            <hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">It should be mentioned that Franjo Tuđman had his first contacts with Croatian emigrants through Holjevac. See Mate Meštrović, </hi><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">U vrtlogu hrvatske politike:
                                kazivanje Peri
                            Zlataru</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve"> (Zagreb: Golden marketing, 2003), 287. Tudjman's link with Croatian emigrants may well be a crucial factor for his victory in the first multi-party elections in Croatia in 1990.</hi></note>
                    Nevertheless, Savka Dapčević Kučar and Miko Tripalo, who couple of years earlier
                    criticised Holjevac of “being infected with nationalist views,” became leaders
                    of the Croatian national movement. It would be interesting to see what role
                    Holjevac would play during the Croatian Spring if he was still alive at the time
                    because he was still quite young but experienced enough. Strižić points out that
                    Holjevac was “the source for the generations of young intellectuals and students
                    who were carriers of the Croatian Spring.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn84" n="83"><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve"> Strižić, </hi><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Hrvatski portreti</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt">, 289.</hi></note></p></div>
               <div>
                   <head>Conclusion</head>
                <p> The analysis of Holjevac’s political carrier confirms the claims that he was a
                    “self-confident person who did not give up his political views.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn85" n="84"><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve"> Spehnjak, “Većeslav Holjevac u političkim događajima 1967. godine,” 593.</hi></note>
                    Due to these characteristics, he occasionally came into conflicts with some of
                    the leading figures of the then ruling League of Communists of Yugoslavia.
                    Already in 1954, he attracted attention as a person who did not blindly follow
                    the usual party praxis because he did not distance himself from some comrades
                    that were thrown off in Party purges. As a member of the pro-reform and
                    anti-dogmatic wing within the Party, he advocated Yugoslavia’s decentralisation
                    and the equitable development of all its republics and regions. These endeavours
                    of his were in contravention to the aspirations of the intercessors of
                    centralism, primarily in Belgrade. With his actions at the local level, Holjevac
                    irritated centralist circles, even their most important representative -
                    Aleksandar Ranković. Regardless of whether Ranković’s threats were real or not,
                    Holjevac’s insistence on creating the new Zagreb Fair was a move against the
                    will of a party official who was above him in the Party hierarchy. Similar to
                    this was the case of awarding Praxis intellectuals in 1966, in which he ignored
                    the instruction that came from Vladimir Bakarić that they should not be
                    rewarded.</p>
                <p>The adoption of the Declaration on the Name and Status of the Croatian Literary
                    Language in 1967 was an ideal moment for Bakarić to politically eliminate the
                    disobedient and (perhaps) too popular Holjevac. Although he was not a signatory
                    to the Declaration, the Executive Committee of the Central Committee of the
                    League of Communists of Croatia, proclaimed Holjevac as a nationalist.
                    Holjevac’s insistence in Croatian patriotism was induced by the feeling that
                    Croatia was withheld in Yugoslavia. That is why his political orientation was a
                    struggle for “fair play politics” (<hi rend="italic">politika čistih
                    računa</hi>), which was the fundamental orientation of the Croatian Spring
                    movement, which would flare up only a few years later. However, while Savka
                    Dabčević Kučar and Miko Tripalo built up their popularity on that policy,
                    Holjevac suffered a political fall. The difference was that Holjevac, as well as
                    some others of his contemporaries, insisted on it too early, before the time in
                    which it was possible to advocate such agenda publicly. Although he was one of
                    the most popular Croatian politicians among the people, many years of isolation
                    and early death prevented him to participate in the Croatian Spring.</p>
                <p>Perhaps this fact holds the answer to the question why Croatian historiography
                    has not published too much on Holjevac. While he was in high politics, he was
                    still relatively young man, and was still relatively young when he experienced
                    his political downturn. So, he did not get the satisfaction, which many of his
                    even less deserving party comrades experienced, to see some historians writing
                    about his life. On the other hand, after the collapse of communism and the
                    creation of the Republic of Croatia, Većeslav Holjevac was not perceived as a
                    man meritorious for Croatia’s national independence, because he did not
                    participate in the Croatian Spring in 1971. So nowadays, Holjevac is one of the
                    most cherished mayors in Zagreb’s history, but he is still forgotten as a
                    dissident.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="bibliography">
                <head>Sources and
                    Literature</head>
                    <list type="unordered">
                        <head>Archival
                            Sources:</head>
                        <item><hi style="font-size:10pt">HR HDA, Hrvatski državni arhiv:</hi>
                            <list type="unordered">
                                <item><hi style="font-size:10pt">HR HDA, 1220, Centralni komitet
                                        Saveza komunista Hrvatske.</hi></item>
                                <item><hi style="font-size:10pt">HR HDA, 1086, Ministarstvo za
                                        novooslobođene krajeve Federativne Narodne Republike
                                        Jugoslavije.</hi></item>
                                <item><hi style="font-size:10pt">HR HDA, 1081, Sabor Socijalističke
                                        Republike Hrvatske.</hi></item>
                            </list></item>
                        <item><hi style="font-size:10pt">HR DAZG, Državni arhiv u Zagrebu:</hi>
                            <list type="unordered">
                                <item><hi style="font-size:10pt">HR DAZG, 37, Narodni odbor grada
                                        Zagreba.</hi></item>
                            </list></item>
                    </list>
                    <listBibl>
                        <head><hi rend="normalweight" style="font-size:10pt">Literature:</hi></head>
                        <bibl><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">Bakarić, Vladimir. </hi><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Socijalistički samoupravni
                                sistem i društvena
                                reprodukcija</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">, </hi><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">vol. 2</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt">. Zagreb: Informator; Mladost; Svjetlost,
                                1983.</hi></bibl>
                        <bibl><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">Barković, Josip. </hi><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Rasplet u Rimu: roman o
                                Zagrebačkom velesajmu</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt">. Zagreb:
                                Naklada Pavičić, 2002.</hi></bibl>
                        <bibl><hi style="font-size:10pt">Bekić, Milan, Ivo Butković, and Slavko
                                Goldstein.</hi>
                            <hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Okrug Karlovac
                            1941.</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve"> Zagreb: Institut za historiju radničkog pokreta, 1965. </hi></bibl>
                        <bibl><hi style="font-size:10pt">Blažević, Marko. “Vizionar suvremenog
                                Zagreba.” In:</hi>
                            <hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Većeslav Holjevac: graditelj,
                                vizionar,
                            ratnik</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">, edited by Juraj Hrženjak, 42–44. Zagreb: Savez antifašističkih boraca i antifašista Republike Hrvatske; Multigraf Marketing, 2006. </hi></bibl>
                        <bibl><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">Boljkovac, Josip. </hi><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Istina mora izaći van: sjećanja
                                i zapisi prvog ministra unutarnjih poslova neovisne Hrvatske</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt">. Zagreb: Golden marketing - Tehnička knjiga,
                                2009.</hi></bibl>
                        <bibl><hi style="font-size:10pt">Bonacci Skenderović, Dunja. “Radio Slobodna
                                Europa o sukobima jugoslavenske vlasti i časopisa Praxis (1972.
                                –1975.).” In:</hi>
                            <hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">Dijalog povjesničara – istoričara </hi><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">8, edited by Hans Georg Fleck and Igor Graovac, 279–97. Zagreb: Friedrich Naumann Stiftung, 2004. </hi><seg xml:space="preserve">  </seg></bibl>
                        <bibl><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">Dabčević Kučar, Savka. </hi><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">’71. Hrvatski snovi i
                                stvarnost</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt">. Zagreb: Interpublic,
                                1997.</hi></bibl>
                        <bibl><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">Goldstein, Ivo. </hi><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Hrvatska
                            1918–2008.</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve"> Zagreb: EPH; Novi Liber, 2008. </hi></bibl>
                        <bibl><hi style="font-size:10pt">Goldstein, Ivo. “Novo lice grada.” In:</hi>
                            <hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Povijest grada
                                Zagreba</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">, </hi><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">vol. 2</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt">, edited by Goran Hutinec and Ivo Goldstein.
                                Zagreb: Novi Liber, 2013.</hi></bibl>
                        <bibl><hi style="font-size:10pt">Goldstein, Slavko. “Nacrt za Vecinu
                                biografiju.”</hi>
                            <hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Kritika</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve"> 3, No. 14 (1970): 618–27.</hi></bibl>
                        <bibl><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">Holjevac, Većeslav. </hi><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Zapisi iz rodnog grada</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt">. Zagreb: Nakladni zavod Matice hrvatske,
                                1972.</hi></bibl>
                        <bibl><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">Holjevac, Većeslav. </hi><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Hrvati izvan domovine</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt">. Zagreb: Matica hrvatska, 1967.</hi></bibl>
                        <bibl><hi style="font-size:10pt">Hrženjak, Juraj,
                                ed.</hi><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve"> Većeslav Holjevac: graditelj, vizionar, ratnik</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt">. Zagreb: Savez antifašističkih boraca i
                                antifašista Republike Hrvatske; Multigraf Marketing,
                            2006.</hi></bibl>
                        <bibl><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">Hudelist, Darko. </hi><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Tuđman: biografija</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt">. Zagreb: Profil, 2004.</hi></bibl>
                        <bibl><hi style="font-size:10pt">Kraljević Bašić, Iva. “Većeslav Holjevac i
                                Nagrada fonda Božidar Adžija 1966.” In:</hi>
                            <hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Disidentstvo u suvremenoj
                                povijesti</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt">, edited by Nada Kisić
                                Kolanović, Zdenko Radelić, and Katarina Spehnjak, 373–84. Zagreb:
                                Hrvatski institut za povijest, 2010.</hi>
                        </bibl>
                        <bibl><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">Kraljević, Iva. “Matica iseljenika Hrvatske 1964. – 1968.” </hi><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Časopis za suvremenu
                                povijest</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve"> 41, No. 1 (2009): 71–92.</hi></bibl>
                        <bibl><hi style="font-size:10pt">Kraljević, Iva. “Većeslav Holjevac –
                                predsjednik Matice iseljenika Hrvatske 1964. –1968.” Magistarski
                                rad, Sveučilište u Zagrebu, 2007.</hi></bibl>
                        <bibl><hi style="font-size:10pt">Kraljević, Iva. “Uloga Komande grada
                                Zagreba u životu Grada prvih poslijeratnih mjeseci 1945. godine.”
                                In:</hi>
                            <hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">1945.</hi>
                            <hi style="font-size:10pt">–</hi>
                            <hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Razdjelnica hrvatske
                                povijesti</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt">, edited by Nada Kisić
                                Kolanović, Mario Jareb, and Katarina Spehnjak, 451-61. Zagreb:
                                Hrvatski institut za povijest, 2006.</hi></bibl>
                        <bibl><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Matica</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve"> 17, No. 6 (1967): 219. “Književni jezik Hrvata i Srba.”</hi></bibl>
                        <bibl><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">Meštrović, Mate. </hi><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">U vrtlogu hrvatske politike:
                                kazivanje Peri Zlataru</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt">. Zagreb:
                                Golden marketing, 2003.</hi></bibl>
                        <bibl><hi style="font-size:10pt">Mihaljević, Josip. “Stota obljetnica
                                rođenja Većeslava Holjevca (1917. –
                            1970.).”</hi><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve"> Zagreb moj grad</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve"> (Zagreb) 11, No. 64 (2017): 6–11.</hi>
                        </bibl>
                        <bibl><hi style="font-size:10pt">Mihaljević, Josip. “Razilaženja u SKJ -
                                marginalizacija Vicka Krstulovića.” In:</hi>
                            <hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Disidentstvo u suvremenoj
                                povijesti</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt">, edited by Nada Kisić
                                Kolanović, Zdenko Radelić and Katarina Spehnjak, 241–70. Zagreb:
                                Hrvatski institut za povijest, 2010.</hi></bibl>
                        <bibl><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">Mujadžević, Dino. </hi><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Bakarić: politička
                                biografija</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt">. Zagreb: Plejada;
                                Hrvatski institut za povijest – Podružnica Slavonski Brod,
                                2011.</hi></bibl>
                        <bibl><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Nova
                            Hrvatska</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve"> 12, No. 2-3 (1970): 5, 6. “Iznenadna smrt Većeslava Holjevca.”</hi></bibl>
                        <bibl><hi style="font-size:10pt">Ponoš, Tihomir. “Zašto 1970. nije osnovana
                                Hrvatska gospodarska banka.” In:</hi>
                            <hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Većeslav Holjevac: graditelj,
                                vizionar, ratnik</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt">, edited by Juraj
                                Hrženjak, 76–78. Zagreb: Savez antifašističkih boraca i antifašista
                                Republike Hrvatske; Multigraf Marketing, 2006.</hi></bibl>
                        <bibl><hi style="font-size:10pt">Radelić, Zdenko. “Đilasovci u Hrvatskoj i
                                hrvatska historiografija.” In:</hi>
                            <hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Disidentstvo u suvremenoj
                                povijesti</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt">, edited by Nada Kisić
                                Kolanović, Zdenko Radelić, and Katarina Spehnjak, 53–74. Zagreb:
                                Hrvatski institut za povijest, 2010.</hi></bibl>
                        <bibl><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">Rojnica, Ivo. </hi><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Susreti i doživljaji: razdoblje
                                od 1938. do 1975. u mojim
                                sjećanjima</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">, </hi><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">vol. 2:
                            1945-1975</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">. Zagreb: DoNeHa, 1994. </hi></bibl>
                        <bibl><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">Samardžija, Marko, ed. </hi><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Deklaracija o nazivu i položaju
                                Hrvatskog književnog jezika 1967. – 2017.: vijesti komentari, osude,
                                zaključci</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt">. Zagreb: Matica hrvatska,
                                2017.</hi></bibl>
                        <bibl><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Sedmi plenum CK SK
                                Hrvatske</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">: </hi><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">O međunacionalnim
                            odnosima</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">. Zagreb: Informativna služba CK SKH, 1967. </hi></bibl>
                        <bibl><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">Spehnjak, Katarina. “Većeslav Holjevac u političkim događajima 1967. godine.” </hi><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Časopis za suvremenu
                                povijest</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve"> 32, No. 3 (2000): 567–96.</hi></bibl>
                        <bibl><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">Strižić, Ivan. </hi><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Hrvatski
                                portreti</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">: </hi><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">lice i naličje hrvatskoga
                                bića</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt">, 2</hi><hi rend="superscript" style="font-size:10pt">nd</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve"> ed. Zagreb: DoNeHa, 1996.</hi></bibl>
                        <bibl><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">Šibl, Ivan. </hi><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Sjećanja III: Poslijeratni
                                dnevnik</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt">. Zagreb: Globus; Naprijed,
                                1986.</hi></bibl>
                        <bibl><hi style="font-size:10pt">Štajner, Rikard. “Skok preko Save.”
                                In:</hi>
                            <hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Većeslav Holjevac: graditelj,
                                vizionar, ratnik</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt">, edited by Juraj
                                Hrženjak, 49. Zagreb: Savez antifašističkih boraca i antifašista
                                Republike Hrvatske; Multigraf Marketing, 2006.</hi></bibl>
                        <bibl><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">Tuđman, Franjo. </hi><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Usudbene povjestice</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt">. Zagreb: Hrvatska sveučilišna naklada,
                                1995.</hi></bibl>
                    </listBibl>
                    <listBibl>
                        <head>Newspaper
                            Sources:</head>
                        <bibl><hi style="font-size:10pt">Fiegenwald, N. “Slava drugu Veci!.”</hi>
                            <hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Večernji
                            list</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve"> (zagrebačko izdanje), July 14, 1970.</hi></bibl>
                        <bibl><hi style="font-size:10pt">Grakalić, Marijan. “Je li Holjevac
                                ubijen?”</hi>
                            <hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Globus</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve"> (Zagreb), February 28, 1991.</hi></bibl>
                        <bibl><hi style="font-size:10pt">“Kamuflirana politička akcija.”</hi>
                            <hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Vjesnik</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt">, June 25, 1966.</hi></bibl>
                        <bibl><hi style="font-size:10pt">Kiseljak, F. “Zapisi i intervjui Većeslava
                                Holjevca: Tri puta u Zagrebu.”</hi>
                            <hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">Večernji list </hi><hi style="font-size:10pt">(zagrebačko izdanje), July 13,
                            1970.</hi></bibl>
                    </listBibl>
                    <listBibl>
                        <head>Online Sources:</head>
                        <bibl><hi style="font-size:10pt">Bing, Albert. “Praxis and Korčula Summer
                                School Collection.”</hi>
                            <hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">COURAGE
                                Registry</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">, 2018. Accessed: August 29, 2018. </hi><ref target="http://cultural-opposition.eu/registry/?uri=http://courage.btk.mta.hu/courage/individual/n31917&amp;type=collections"><hi style="font-size:10pt">http://cultural-opposition.eu/registry/?uri=http://courage.btk.mta.hu/courage/individual/n31917&amp;type=collections</hi></ref><hi style="font-size:10pt">.</hi></bibl>
                        <bibl><hi style="font-size:10pt">Mrvoš Pavić, Bojana. “Veco Holjevac:
                                Sumnjam da je moj otac Većeslav otrovan.”</hi>
                            <hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Novi list</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve"> (on-line), May 13, 2012. Accessed: May 27, 2018. </hi>
                            <ref target="http://novilist.hr/Vijesti/Hrvatska/Veco-Holjevac-Sumnjam-da-je-moj-otac-Veceslav-otrovan"><hi style="font-size:10pt">http://novilist.hr/Vijesti/Hrvatska/Veco-Holjevac-Sumnjam-da-je-moj-otac-Veceslav-otrovan</hi></ref><hi style="font-size:10pt">.</hi></bibl>
                        <bibl><hi style="font-size:10pt">“Većeslav Holjevac.”</hi>
                            <hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Hrvatski biografski
                                leksikon</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve"> (on-line). Accessed: May 27, 2018. </hi><ref target="http://hbl.lzmk.hr/clanak.aspx?id=67"><hi style="font-size:10pt">http://hbl.lzmk.hr/clanak.aspx?id=67</hi></ref><hi style="font-size:10pt">.</hi></bibl>
                        <bibl>
                            <hi style="font-size:10pt">“Deklaracija o nazivu i položaju hrvatskog
                                književnog jezika.”</hi>
                            <hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Matica hrvatska</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">. Accessed: August 1, 2018. </hi>
                            <ref target="http://www.matica.hr/kolo/314/Deklaracija%20o%20nazivu%20i%20polo%C5%BEaju%20hrvatskog%20knji%C5%BEevnog%20jezika/"><hi style="font-size:10pt">http://www.matica.hr/kolo/314/Deklaracija%20o%20nazivu%20i%20polo%C5%BEaju%20hrvatskog%20knji%C5%BEevnog%20jezika/</hi></ref><hi style="font-size:10pt">.</hi></bibl>
                    </listBibl>
                    <listBibl>
                        <head>Oral Sources:</head>
                        <bibl><hi style="font-size:10pt">“Povijesne kontroverze” (radio show).</hi>
                            <hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Third program of Croatian
                                Radio</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt">. November 16, 2017.</hi>
                            <ref target="http://radio.hrt.hr/treci-program/ep/veceslav-holjevac/229498/"><hi style="font-size:10pt">http://radio.hrt.hr/treci-program/ep/veceslav-holjevac/229498/</hi></ref><hi style="font-size:10pt">.</hi></bibl>
                    </listBibl>
            </div>
                   <div type="summary">
                       <docAuthor>Josip Mihaljević</docAuthor>
                    <head>VEĆESLAV HOLJEVAC - FORGOTTEN DISSIDENT</head>
                    <head>SUMMARY</head>
                    <p> Croatian politician Većeslav Holjevac (1917-1970) has
                        been remembered as one of the most successful mayors of the city of Zagreb.
                        However, his character and political work are scarcely known to the public
                        today. His merits in the cultural sphere are mostly forgotten, as well as
                        the fact that he was one of the most important Croatian dissidents. The
                        article presents the critical moments of his dissent and political
                        disagreement with his comrades that led him to the role of the party
                        renegade. The first dissident moment of his happened in 1954 when he did not
                        distance himself from Marijan Stilinović, a Party comrade that was thrown
                        off in a Party purge. However, maybe the crucial reason for Holjevac’s
                        political decline was his hard advocacy of Yugoslavia's decentralisation and
                        the equitable development of all republics and regions. As a member of the
                        pro-reform and anti-dogmatic wing within the Party, he struggled against the
                        aspirations of the intercessors of centralism. In 1955 Holjevac insisted on
                        creating the new Zagreb Fair, which was a move against the will of
                        Aleksandar Ranković, an influential party official who was above him in the
                        Party hierarchy. Similar to this was the case of awarding Praxis
                        intellectuals with the “Božidar Adžija” Awards in 1966. The highest Party
                        officials considered their philosophical books unsuitable for the highest
                        state prize. Holjevac, who was the president of the “Božidar Adžija” Awards
                        Committee, ignored the instruction that came from Vladimir Bakarić that they
                        should not be rewarded. The adoption of the Declaration on the Name and
                        Status of the Croatian Literary Language in 1967 was an ideal moment for
                        Bakarić to politically eliminate the disobedient and (perhaps) too popular
                        Holjevac. Although he was not a signatory to the Declaration, the Executive
                        Committee of the Central Committee of the League of Communists of Croatia,
                        proclaimed Holjevac as a nationalist. Holjevac’s case delineates the issue
                        of the Croatian national reform movement known as the Croatian Spring. Due
                        to his solid character, he was not afraid to defend his standpoints, even in
                        the fights with communist comrades who were higher in the Party’s hierarchy,
                        which caused his political decline. The article also discusses the claims
                        that Holjevac was to become the leader of the Croatian Spring.</p></div>
                <div type="summary" xml:lang="sl">
                    <docAuthor>Josip Mihaljević</docAuthor>
                    <head>VEĆESLAV  HOLJEVAC – POZABLJENI DISIDENT</head>
                    <head>POVZETEK</head>
                    <p> Hrvaški politik Većeslav Holjevac (1917–1970) velja za enega najuspešnejših
                        županov mesta Zagreb. Kljub temu sta njegova osebnost in politično delo
                        javnosti danes malo znana. Njegove zasluge na kulturnem področju so šle
                        večinoma v pozabo, prav tako pa tudi dejstvo, da je bil eden najpomembnejših
                        hrvaških disidentov. Članek predstavlja ključne trenutke njegovih
                        disidentskih in političnih nesoglasij s tovariši, zaradi katerih si je v
                        partiji prislužil status odpadnika. Do prvega nesoglasja je prišlo leta
                        1954, ko se ni oddaljil od partijskega tovariša Marijana Stilinovića, ki je
                        med čistko v partiji izgubil svoj položaj. Morda se ključni razlog za
                        politični propad Holjevca skriva v njegovem zagretemu zagovarjanju
                        decentralizacije Jugoslavije in pravičnega razvoja vseh republik in regij.
                        Kot član krila znotraj partije, ki se je zavzemalo za reforme in zavračalo
                        dogmatska stališča, se je boril proti težnjam zagovornikov centralizma. Leta
                        1955 se je Holjevac zavzemal za ustanovitev novega zagrebškega sejmišča, kar
                        je bilo v nasprotju z voljo takrat vplivnega partijskega uradnika Aleksandra
                        Rankovića, ki je imel v primerjavi s Holjevcem pomembnejšo funkcijo v
                        partijski hierarhiji. Podobno se je zgodilo leta 1966, ko so intelektualcem
                        iz časnika Praxis podelili nagrado Božidarja Adžije. Najvišji partijski
                        uradniki so namreč menili, da njihove knjige s filozofsko vsebino niso
                        primerne za najvišjo državno nagrado. Holjevac, ki je deloval kot predsednik
                        komiteja za nagrado Božidarja Adžije, ni upošteval navodil Vladimirja
                        Bakarića, naj skupine ne nagradi. Sprejetje deklaracije o imenu in položaju
                        hrvaškega knjižnega jezika iz leta 1967 se je izkazalo kot izvrstna
                        priložnost, s katero je Bakarić neposlušnega in (morda) preveč
                        priljubljenega Holjevca izrinil iz politične sfere. Čeprav Holjevac ni bil
                        med podpisniki deklaracije, ga je Izvršni odbor Centralnega komiteja
                        komunistične partije Hrvaške označil za nacionalista. Njegov primer odstira
                        vprašanje hrvaškega gibanja za nacionalno reformo, imenovano Hrvaška pomlad.
                        Zaradi močnega značaja ga ni bilo strah braniti svojih stališč celo v bojih
                        s komunističnimi tovariši, ki so zasedali pomembnejše funkcije v hierarhiji
                        partije, kar je povzročilo njegov politični zaton. Članek prav tako
                        obravnava trditve, da naj bi Holjevac postal vodja Hrvaške pomladi.</p>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>