<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Jože Pučnik on a
                    Path to Becoming a Dissident</title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename>Aleš</forename>
                        <surname>Gabrič</surname>
                        <roleName>Research Counsellor</roleName>
                        <roleName>PhD</roleName>
                        <affiliation>Institute of Contemporary History</affiliation>
                        <address>
                            <addrLine>Kongresni trg 1</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>SI-1000 Ljubljana</addrLine>
                        </address>
                        <email>ales.gabric@inz.si</email>
                    </name>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>2017-12-23</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>
                    <orgName xml:lang="sl">Inštitut za novejšo zgodovino</orgName>
                    <orgName xml:lang="en">Institute of Contemporary History</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Kongresni trg 1</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>SI-1000 Ljubljana</addrLine>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>http://ojs.inz.si/pnz/article/view/314</pubPlace>
                <date>2018</date>
                <availability status="free">
                    <licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title xml:lang="sl">Prispevki za novejšo zgodovino</title>
                <title xml:lang="en">Contributions to Contemporary History</title>
                <biblScope unit="volume">58</biblScope>
                <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
                <idno type="ISSN">2463-7807</idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source, born digital.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc xml:lang="en">
                <p>Contributions to Contemporary History is one of the central Slovenian scientific
                    historiographic journals, dedicated to publishing articles from the field of
                    contemporary history (the 19th and 20th century).</p>
                <p>The journal is published three times per year in Slovenian and in the following
                    foreign languages: English, German, Serbian, Croatian, Bosnian, Italian, Slovak
                    and Czech. The articles are all published with abstracts in English and
                    Slovenian as well as summaries in English.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <projectDesc xml:lang="sl">
                <p>Prispevki za novejšo zgodovino je ena osrednjih slovenskih znanstvenih
                    zgodovinopisnih revij, ki objavlja teme s področja novejše zgodovine (19. in 20.
                    stoletje).</p>
                <p>Revija izide trikrat letno v slovenskem jeziku in v naslednjih tujih jezikih:
                    angleščina, nemščina, srbščina, hrvaščina, bosanščina, italijanščina, slovaščina
                    in češčina. Članki izhajajo z izvlečki v angleščini in slovenščini ter povzetki
                    v angleščini.</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="sl"/>
                <language ident="en"/>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords xml:lang="en">
                    <term>Jože Pučnik</term>
                    <term>Revija 57</term>
                    <term>intellectuals</term>
                    <term>communist regime</term>
                    <term>Slovenia</term>
                    </keywords>
                <keywords xml:lang="sl">
                    <term>Jože Pučnik</term>
                    <term>Revija 57</term>
                    <term>intellectuals</term>
                    <term>communist regime</term>
                    <term>Slovenija</term>
                    </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change>
                    <date>2017-12-28</date>
                    <name>Neja Blaj Hribar</name>
                    <desc>Pretvorba iz DOCX v TEI, dodatno kodiranje</desc>
                </change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <docAuthor>Aleš Gabrič<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn1" n="1"><hi rend="bold">Research Counsellor, PhD, Institute of Contemporary
                        History, Kongresni trg 1, SI-1000 Ljubljana, Slovenia,
                        ales.gabric@inz.si</hi></note></docAuthor>
            <docImprint>
                <idno type="cobissType">Cobiss type: 1.01</idno>
                <idno type="UDC">UDC: 929Pučnik J.:329.052:323.281(497.4)"1965/1991"</idno>
            </docImprint>
            <div type="abstract" xml:lang="sl">
                <head>IZVLEČEK</head>
                <head>JOŽE PUČNIK NA POTI DO DISIDENTA</head>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Primer obračuna z Revijo 57 konec 50-ih let je bil eden najbolj
                    razvpitih sporov slovenskih komunistov z mlajšo generacijo intelektualcev, ki so
                    po drugi svetovni vojni oblikovali svoj svetovni nazor. Jože Pučnik je med
                    somišljeniki, ki so pozornost pritegnili s svojo ostrino, še posebej izstopal.
                    Že med študijem je v svojih člankih v Reviji 57 kritiziral režim. V najbolj
                    spornem članku je analiziral razhajanja med idejami vladajoče elite in
                    realnostjo ter med miselnostjo in delom komunistov dve desetletji prej, ko so
                    delovali nezakonito, in po vojni, ko so se utrdili na oblasti. Konec leta 1958
                    in v začetku 1959 je bila Revija 57 večkrat tarča kritik vodilnih politikov in
                    tema številnih sej visokih organov. Politiki so neprestano ponavljali, da gre za
                    skupino mlajših intelektualcev, ki da je snovala ilegalno sovražno organizacijo,
                    širila protidržavno propagando in đilasovstvo, pozivala delavce k štrajku itd.
                    Višek obračuna je bilo sojenju Pučniku 30. marca 1959, v katerem je bil obsojen
                    na devet let hude zaporne kazni.</hi>
                </p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Ključne besede: Jože Pučnik, Revija 57, intelektualci, komunistični
                    režim, Slovenija</hi></p>
            </div>
            <div type="abstract" xml:lang="en">
                <head>ABSTRACT</head>
                <p><hi rend="italic">The case of settling scores with Revija 57 at the end of 50’s is
                    one of the most infamous disputes of the Communist government in Slovenia with a
                    younger generation of intellectuals who had shaped their worldview after WWII.
                    Jože Pučnik stood out among its contributors, who attracted attention with the
                    sharpness of mind. The criticism of the regime was during his study reflected in
                    Pučnik’s articles in the Revija 57 magazine. In the most controversial article
                    Pučnik analysed the discrepancies between the ideas of the ruling elite and
                    reality, and between the mentality and the work of the Communists two decades
                    earlier, when they were still operating illegally, and after the war, when they
                    consolidated their official power. At the end of 1958 and in early 1959, the
                    Revija 57 magazine was repeatedly targeted by the leading politicians and became
                    the subject of numerous sessions held by high-level authorities. The politicians
                    reiterated that the magazine were a group of young intellectuals, who formed an
                    illegal hostile organization, spread anti-state propaganda and djilasism, called
                    on workers to go on strikes etc. The encounters and intimidations finally
                    escalated in a trial held on 30 March 1959, in which Jože Pučnik was sentenced
                    to nine years of severe imprisonment.</hi></p>
                <p><hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Key words: Jože Pučnik, Revija 57, intellectuals, communist regime, Slovenia  </hi></p>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div><head>Contributor to the <hi rend="italic">Revija
                57</hi> Magazine with a Police Record</head>
            <p>The case of settling scores with <hi rend="italic">Revija 57</hi> is one of the most
                infamous disputes of the Communist government with a younger generation of
                intellectuals who had shaped their world view after WWII. Jože Pučnik stood out
                among its contributors, who attracted attention with the sharpness of mind. His life
                experience distinguished him from most of the magazine’s associates, as he had
                already experienced close encounters with the Internal Administration. As a grammar
                school student, he demonstrated the political aspect of his work when, due to
                disagreement with actions taken by the youth organization, he left the organisation
                and started publishing the <hi rend="italic">Iskanja</hi> bulletin with a few of his
                friends. <hi rend="italic">Iskanja</hi> was mostly a literary newspaper published by
                students without official permission and with articles written under pseudonyms. The
                unnamed author of the first issue editorial published in January 1951 was Jože
                Pučnik. This was confirmed decades later, when he said: “I’m still proud of being
                the first person to write an introductory article, a sort of a programme that was to
                a certain extent, oppositional and, of course, slightly romantic.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn2" n="1"> Janko Lorenci, <hi rend="italic">Jože Pučnik</hi> (Ljubljana: Emonica, 1990), 24.</note></p>
            <p>In fact, said editorial published in <hi rend="italic">Iskanja</hi> stands out due to
                its sharpness of thought. A few years after the war, it was not normal for someone
                to write about the fact that the psyche of “today’s man is chained in the shackles
                of legitimised violence”. “The autocrat is trying to destroy the close ties among
                people,” wrote the editor, and the reader could only smile at the thought of who
                this autocrat could be. “Plain speech is banned,” was the motto of the editor, which
                was followed by a deliberation on fear and courage in the hearts of the people, all
                this just a year and a half before these exact two words, which appeared in the
                title of Kocbek’s collection of novellas, insulted those in authority. In his
                outline of the situation at the time, Pučnik highlighted the violence of the
                government in the form of icy concrete of solitary confinement units, violent hands,
                “empty words accompanied by a hypocritical smile”, and a “tense barbed wire resting
                on bloody bayonets” encircling it all. In order to overcome all of these issues, the
                editorial called for poetry and openness, so “that we would release from his violent
                numbness the healthy vital force and with it a decisive requirement for a free, open
                and beautiful word”.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn3" n="2">
                        Author’s archives <hi rend="italic">Iskanja</hi>, No. 1, January 1951, 1, 2.
                        A copy of the newspaper was sent to me by the son of Jože Pučnik, Gorazd
                        Pučnik, for which I would herewith like to extend my sincere
                    gratitude.</note></p></div>
            <div><head>A Socially Engaged
                    Student</head>
            <p>Pučnik then had to leave grammar school with several other colleagues and was
                forbidden to attend final exams. However, the punishment was subsequently reduced,
                and after returning from military service and completing secondary education, Pučnik
                enrolled as a student at the Department of Philosophy of the Faculty of Arts in
                    Ljubljana.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn4" n="3"> SI AS
                        1931, t. e. 1146, 217, 218, 1, 2.</note> He was active in the <hi rend="italic">Students' Union</hi> (Zveza študentov) and in debates that brought
                him closer to the circle of the <hi rend="italic">Revija 57</hi> magazine. He wrote
                several articles for a newspaper about the state of affairs in the society in
                Yugoslavia at the time. Although Pučnik was no different than others in voicing
                criticism, his words were usually very direct and easy to understand, while the
                articles of some other writers had to be read between the lines. He also differed
                from the central circle of the <hi rend="italic">Revija 57</hi> magazine due to the
                social class from which he originated. While other rebels mostly originated from the
                bourgeoisie, from financially well-established backgrounds, which was especially the
                case with children of political officials, he came from a farming environment and
                was able to witness the poverty of the farming class from up close. He also differed
                by the fact that he had already faced the work of the police, although the thought
                of having to encounter police was also not foreign to many of his contemporaries.
                Janko Kos, for example, heard after his controversial discussions with Ziherl that
                it was allegedly discussed at party meetings whether or not to imprison him, but he
                was taken under the wing by two intellectuals from the upper political circles,
                Ferdo Kozak and Josip Vidmar.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn5" n="4"> Janko Kos, <hi rend="italic">Umetniki in meščani:
                            spominjanja</hi> (Ljubljana: Beletrina, 2015), 166.</note> In early
                1958, Pučnik’s social engagement also led him to join the League of Communists, a
                move which elicited extremely controversial responses. When he informed his
                colleagues of this decision, he had a sense that “they would beat me up”, while
                Primož Kozak asked him in private whether he was a police agent.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn6" n="5"> Lorenci, <hi rend="italic">Jože
                            Pučnik</hi>, 24.</note></p>
            <p>The decision to join the political party in power provoked such unusual responses
                among his colleagues because it contradicted everything they thought and fought for.
                Their articles and conversations had a political note and criticised the system,
                opposed the values of the government, and, to an extent, also the value system of
                their parents, as children of politicians were also in their ranks. The criticism of
                the regime was also reflected in Pučnik’s articles in the <hi rend="italic">Revija
                    57</hi> magazine. In an article titled <hi rend="italic">The Moral Roots of the
                    Personality Cult</hi> from 1957, he devoted himself to this phenomenon in the
                Soviet Union, but clearly wrote among other things: “The problem of the personality
                cult is a general social problem in socialist systems and is not related only to
                Stalinism or the Eastern bloc.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn7" n="6"> Jože Pučnik, <hi rend="italic">Članki in spomini
                            1957–1985</hi> (Maribor: Obzorja, 1986), 9.</note> In the article
                    <hi rend="italic">The Society and the State</hi> from the same year, he touched
                upon the relationship of the individual with the society at large and advocated the
                rights of the individual because “the liberation of a person is a release from
                everything that is above and beyond them, be it God, a monarch or a state”.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn8" n="7"> Ibid., 21.</note>
                In an article titled <hi rend="italic">Towards Freedom</hi>, Pučnik emphasized the
                European tradition of values, embedded Karl Marx into it, and concluded with a
                reflection on freedom within the specific reality in Yugoslavia. Although he
                emphasized that, after the political revolution, there was a time to consolidate the
                new legal system, he also warned as follows: “The legal and political changes
                brought about by the new system are in themselves insufficient.” The rights were all
                too often left at a formal level and could not be exercised by individuals in their
                actual lives. Values in Yugoslavia, stressed Pučnik, have a long way to go before
                they will be transformed from theory to reality.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn9" n="8"> Ibid., 39, 40.</note></p>
            <p> In several articles, Pučnik argued that the state should be built to suit the people
                and not in a way so as to demand that people to personally submit themselves to the
                will of the state. Although Pučnik made no references to Tito in the outline of the
                personality cult, and although he did not point out that a different principle was
                in place in Yugoslavia when emphasizing the rights of the individual in relation to
                the state, it was clear to readers that his ideas were not only about general
                problems, but about problems that people faced at home at every step. Pučnik’s
                articles reveal a person whose views on social issues were quite different from
                those of the government and who also openly advocated these principles in public. </p>
            <p>The leadership of the League of Communists of Slovenia discussed the issues raised by
                    <hi rend="italic">Revija 57</hi> more seriously for the first time at the
                meeting of the ideological committee on 26 November 1957. The rise of criticism at
                    <hi rend="italic">Revija 57</hi> was evident by the mere fact that, in the case
                of its predecessor, a magazine called <hi rend="italic">Beseda</hi>, communist
                ideologists only attacked its ideological premises, while in the case of <hi rend="italic">Revija 57</hi>, they also talked about the integration of informal
                groups that could, in the future, create a political opposition block. The
                <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Revija 57 </hi>team was accused of being a
                part of the younger generation which had not yet comprehended the great changes
                occurring in the society after 1945 and which lacked criticism when assessing the
                western society. From this point of view, <hi rend="italic">Revija 57,</hi>
                according to the party leaders, had an overly strong influence on the students of
                the Faculty of Arts. Ideologists found the power of the <hi rend="italic">Revija 57</hi> circle at the humanities departments especially dangerous, as it
                hindered the League of Communists of Slovenia in its planned transformation of the
                university according its own taste and its indirect (ideological) influence on the
                future generations of intellectuals.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn10" n="9"> Ibid., 28–31.</note>
                The government was able to exercise more political pressure on <hi rend="italic">Revija 57</hi> than on the <hi rend="italic">Beseda</hi> magazine because the
                former had, in accordance with the provisions of the Act on Publishing, a formal
                publisher. However, the Yugoslavian Federation of Students in Ljubljana did not
                utilise this power, as publisher Janez Vrhunc, according to those in power, did not
                play his role, since he did not prevent the publication of any article that the
                ideologists assessed as controversial or inadequate. The University Committee of the
                League of Communists therefore dismissed Janez Vrhunc and in March 1958 appointed in
                his place Rado Jan, the secretary of the basic organization of the League of
                Communists at the Faculty of Arts.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn11" n="10">
                        Mateja Režek, “Ideološko ozadje ukinitve Revije 57.” 
                        <hi rend="italic">Nova
                        revija</hi> 13, No. 151/152 (1994), 196.</note></p>
            <p>Those working for the <hi rend="italic">Revija 57</hi> magazine were aware of the
                political connotations of their work. Pučnik mentioned that he and the circle of
                colleagues, including Janko Kos, Taras Kermauner, Veljko Rus, Primož Kozak and
                others, held “many political discussions.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn12" n="11"> Lorenci, <hi rend="italic">Jože Pučnik</hi>,
                        26.</note> One such conversation, which carried on long into the night,
                took place in the summer of 1958 at Primož Kozak’s home. There, it was agreed to
                write contributions on the social and political reality of the time. However, one
                should not ignore a fact that those describing Pučnik's work have so far not
                emphasised. The agreement among the young intellectuals came to an end shortly after
                the seventh Congress of the League of Communists of Yugoslavia in Ljubljana in April
                1958. Party ideologists saw the event as a turning point because of the new
                programme of the League of Communists of Yugoslavia that was adopted there. On the
                one hand, the programme offered some novelties introduced into socialism by
                Yugoslavian communists after the dispute between Yugoslavia and the Soviet Union a
                decade earlier, but on the other hand, the ruling party’s announcement was about the
                manner in which the society and the state would be developed in the following
                period. The programme was written at a time of newly aggravated relations with the
                Soviet Union and in light of the discontent shown by other communist countries. The
                Congress was important for the internal political scene because it was the first
                time that the topic of international relations was addressed at such a high-level
                event. They added to the traditional political opponents those who allegedly
                advocated fake liberalism and, by defending the rights of the individual, actually
                spread anarchism. Attempts to leverage the artistic and scientific sphere in the
                name of freedom in order to promote anti-socialist ideas were also met with
                    contempt.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn13" n="12">
                        Mateja Režek, <hi rend="italic">Med resničnostjo in iluzijo: slovenska in
                            jugoslovanska politika v desetletju po sporu z Informbirojem:
                            (1948–1958)</hi> (Ljubljana: Modrijan, 2005), 191–202. </note></p>
            <p>In such circumstances, any criticism directed at the party and the state (and,
                indirectly, at the new programme of the ruling political party) was even less
                welcome than usual. What is more, such criticism fit neither the Yugoslavian
                government, which was afraid that other countries might utilise it as evidence that
                citizens were dissatisfied with the state, nor the Slovenian authorities, which, in
                the period of intensified inter-ethnic relations, wanted to have Slovenian
                intellectuals as allies rather than critics of state policies.</p>
            <p>An agreement by the <hi rend="italic">Revija 57</hi> authors to write and publish
                contributions on the current social situation was therefore made in the wake of
                unfavourable political conditions. Only Jože Pučnik, who was the only one to put his
                views on paper, fulfilled the commitment made to his friends to write articles on
                the social situation at the time. He already had a good draft in his drawer because
                he had written an article about the party for the <hi rend="italic">Naši razgledi</hi> magazine, which he had sent to the members of the editorial
                board to read. Pučnik was received by Vlado Vodopivec, the then Secretary of State
                for Culture and Education, and, according to Pučnik, Vodopivec said something like
                this: “This article is interesting because you are right. But we are approaching a
                new phase of Stalinism. Please remove this article, we cannot publish it. This is
                what I wanted to say to you in a friendly manner.” After speaking to his friends,
                Pučnik rewrote the article and offered it to <hi rend="italic">Revija 57</hi> to be
                published, but even the magazine had reservations about whether to publish such a
                sharp text. Ultimately, the majority decided to publish it, and the representative
                of the magazine’s founder in the editorial board, Rado Jan, assumed a
                behind-the-scenes censorship role and prevented the publication of the article.
                Pučnik initially responded by saying that, in accordance with the old tradition,
                they should publish some empty white pages in order to make it clear to the readers
                that the authorities prevented the publication of some of the material confirmed by
                    editors.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn14" n="13">
                        Lorenci, <hi rend="italic">Jože Pučnik</hi>, 27.</note></p>
            <p>In a controversial article titled <hi rend="italic">Our Social Reality and Our
                    Illusions</hi>,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn15" n="14">
                        SI AS 1931, t. e. 1146, 217, 218, 64–73. Pučnik, <hi rend="italic">Članki in
                            spomini</hi>, 50–70.</note> Pučnik analysed the discrepancies
                between the ideas of the ruling elite and reality, and between the mentality and the
                work of the Communists two decades earlier, when they were still operating
                illegally, and after the war, when they consolidated their official power. According
                to Pučnik, after the Communist Party came to power, it suffered a severe crisis from
                which it could not recover, since on the one hand, it formally wanted to be nothing
                more but society’s ideological leader, but on the other hand, it completely merged
                with the government in real life. Although the government relied on the rule of the
                people, the split between its ideology and the people was growing deeper, wrote
                Pučnik, and asked the question: “It goes without saying that much of the blame for
                such a social atmosphere in Slovenia rests with the Party and autocratic forums and
                their antagonistic understanding of society. Distrust and extreme tension, their
                constant sense of the ‘people’s power’ being in jeopardy, and suspicious
                speculations about the constant presence of 'enemies to our socialist social system'
                have now become chronic. One often asks themselves: Do these people have even the
                slightest sense that they live among their own people and in a state community in
                which they also are the holders of power?”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn16" n="15"> Pučnik, <hi rend="italic">Članki in spomini</hi>,
                        69.</note></p></div>
            <div><head>The Government
                    Exercises Power over Revija 57</head>
            <p>Albeit Pučnik’s article was by no means a real cause for the government's actions,
                the authorities used said article as a reason for exerting pressure on a group of
                young intellectuals. In July 1958, the editorial board of <hi rend="italic">Revija 57</hi> was notified that the <hi rend="italic">Secretariat for Culture
                    and Education of Slovenia</hi> proposed the removal of their subsidy, so in the
                next few months the Board repeatedly appealed to the competent state body, either
                through personal contacts or in writing, to prevent this.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn17" n="16"> Vital Klabus, “Pričevanje o
                        Reviji 57 in Perspektivah.” <hi rend="italic">Borec</hi> 48, No. 551/552
                        (1996), 113, 114. </note> However, it was not successful, since an
                official proposal presented in September 1958 by the <hi rend="italic">Fund for the
                    Promotion of the Publishing Activity</hi> at the <hi rend="italic">Council of
                    Culture and Education of Slovenia</hi>, listed <hi rend="italic">Revija 57</hi>
                among those magazines the subsidies of which were to be withdrawn. The <hi rend="italic">Council of Culture and Education of Slovenia</hi> rejected the
                proposal after a stormy debate. However, the Council supported the proposal of its
                own President, Boris Kocijančič, to keep subsidizing the magazine until the end of
                the year, when “both the magazine and the <hi rend="italic">Students’ Union</hi>
                would have to seriously reconsider the criteria which led the commission to make a
                proposal to withdraw the subsidy”. This was why <hi rend="italic">Revija 57</hi>
                could not “count on a subsidy in the coming year if the ideas discussed in the
                magazine deviated from our cultural policy”.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn18" n="17">
                        Režek, <hi rend="italic">Ideološko ozadje ukinitve Revije
                            57</hi>, 198, 199.</note> The
                editorial board of the <hi rend="italic">Revija 57</hi> magazine was thus threatened
                to no longer publish politically undesired articles, otherwise they would lose the
                subsidy at the end of 1958. In the political reality of the time, this would have
                resulted in a cancellation.</p>
            <p>The debate spread to forums which were supposed to oversee <hi rend="italic">Revija 57</hi>. On 4 October 1958, the <hi rend="italic">Central Committee of
                    the People’s Youth Organisation of Slovenia</hi> and the <hi rend="italic">University Committee of the Students’ Union</hi> met at a joint session. It was
                deemed that <hi rend="italic">Revija 57</hi> did not deal with real problems of the
                present time. When a youth organisation official provided the simple fact “that <hi rend="italic">Revija 57</hi>, which is the bulletin of the <hi rend="italic">Students’ Union</hi>, is reaching beyond the university by addressing current
                    issues”,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn19" n="18"> SI AS 1799, t. e. 83, Zapisnik seje predsedstva CK LMS in uni. odbora ZŠJ, 4 October 1958, 7.
                    </note> he pointed out either intentionally or unintentionally something
                that the government feared the most. </p>
            <p>In October 1958, only a month before the first proposal was made to cancel <hi rend="italic">Revija 57</hi>, the government launched a campaign that led to the
                magazine’s ultimate cancellation. As a formal reason, they cited the sharp criticism
                of society in issues 5–6 of the second year of the magazine, although similar
                criticism could also be found in previous issues of the magazine. In the above
                issue, the first sharp criticism was contained right at the beginning, in the
                editorial. Namely, the editorial touched on the meeting of the
                <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Council for Culture and Education of the Slovenian People’s Republic </hi>and
                the proposal to withdraw its subsidy for <hi rend="italic">Revija</hi> <hi rend="italic">57</hi>. At the end of the magazine, two articles were published
                discussing the anniversary of the closing of the <hi rend="italic">Prešeren
                    Theatre</hi> in Kranj and the resulting negative consequences as well as
                criticism directed at publishers who, due to their beliefs, refused to accepted a
                poetry collection by Dane Zajc into their programme.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn20" n="19"> SI AS 1589, IK, t. e. 12, Revija 57.
                    </note>
            </p>
            <p>Jože Pučnik’s <hi rend="italic">Our Social Reality and our Illusions</hi>, which was
                just one of the many disruptive articles, but also the most controversial, was
                deemed by Boris Ziherl as “djilasovskian”. Before it was even printed, the article
                was given to Ziherl to read by “a representative of
                the<hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve"> Students’ Union</hi> in this editorial
                board”, i.e. Rado Jan, who asked Ziherl “what to do with this article”. Ziherl
                replied: “You are the representative of the <hi rend="italic">Students’ Union</hi>
                in this editorial board and if you have given veto to the board, then you have the
                right to appeal to the person who sent you to this editorial board, that is to the
                    <hi rend="italic">Students’ Union</hi>, to decide in this matter.” Ziherl
                reported to the leading politicians that “this is exactly what happened and the <hi rend="italic">Board of Student’s Union</hi> rejected the publication of this
                article”. However, because the editorial board threatened to publish an empty page
                in place of the censored article, “the representative of the <hi rend="italic">Students’ Union</hi> again came to me for advice on what to do”.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn21" n="20"> SI AS 537, t. e. 27, Seja predsedstva SZDLS, 6 November, 1958, 47, 48.
                    </note></p>
            <p>In October 1958, police investigators launched an investigation against <hi rend="italic">Revija 57</hi>. The confiscation proposal no. 5–6 was just the
                beginning, as it soon became apparent that after the issue that had already been
                prepared for printing was confiscated at the Kočevje printing house on
                31 October 1958, the government authorities would go even further. The publication
                of the controversial contribution was by no means a sufficient reason for a wider
                police campaign, since the publication of the article had already been blocked by
                the representative of the <hi rend="italic">Students’ Union</hi>. Far more had to be
                done for a more extensive campaign; the campaigns undertaken a decade earlier had
                been a sign that it would be best for intimidation purposes and for the judicial
                process as such to focus the investigation on proving the attempts to organize an
                anti-state political organization. The main target of the investigation was Jože
                Pučnik, who was arrested on the same day as the magazine issue was seized. House
                searches were carried out at Pučnik’s home and the homes of some of his colleagues,
                several people from the magazine circles were brought in for questioning, and the
                    <hi rend="italic">Revija 57</hi> archives were seized from the editor Vital
                Klabus. Editors Veno Taufer and Vital Klabus complained to the interior affairs
                bodies and county authorities of the <hi rend="italic">Socialist Alliance of the
                    Working People of Ljubljana</hi>, which, however, did not affect the decisions
                made by the government authorities at the highest level. This marked the beginning
                of long-term interrogations for Pučnik and, at least initially, it was not entirely
                clear to him what the authorities wanted from him. He did not want to discuss the
                views of his friends and, during discussions about his contributions, he disagreed
                with the comments of the investigators who considered these views as calls to
                anti-government actions.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn22" n="21"> SI AS 2027, t. e. 14, Dopis uredništva Revije 57, 2 November, 1958. SI AS 1589, IK, t. e. 12, Revija 57 in Naši nadaljnji ukrepi in rezultati preiskave proti skupini Revija 57. Rosvita Pesek, 
                        <hi rend="italic">Pučnik</hi> (Celovec: Mohorjeva, 2013), 79–89. </note></p>
            <p>Because the editors did not yield to political demands and did not agree to withdraw
                certain articles, on 5 November 1958 the Ljubljana District Court complied with the
                request of the public prosecutor and confiscated the magazine.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn23" n="22"> SI AS 537, t. e. 27, Seja predsedstva SZDLS, 6 November, 1958, 40–42.
                    </note> The political fate of the magazine and its authors was decided on
                the following day, on 6 November 1958, at the session of the <hi rend="italic">Presidency of the Socialist Alliance of Working People of Slovenia</hi>.
                Through the following questions, its members indicated the future confrontation with
                the <hi rend="italic">Revija 57</hi> magazine: How can the writers of such articles
                be working as teaching assistants at the university?; Why is such a magazine
                receiving a subsidy?; Is it an organized campaign to provoke the dissatisfied into a
                revolt?; It is not true that there are too few magazines because don’t young people
                have the <hi rend="italic">Mlada pota</hi> magazine?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn24" n="23"> Ibid., 40–56.
                    </note>
            </p>
            <p>In mid-November 1958, the Internal Administration directed the investigation against
                the (imaginary) illegal organization, which was allegedly founded by Jože Pučnik.
                After interrogating those working for the magazine, it was established that most of
                the editorial board agreed with the publication of contributions deemed by the
                police as “hostile propaganda”, namely they agreed that they were preparing the
                founding of the Založba 1551 publishing house, where they would also publish works
                by such writers as Sartre, and that they planned to expand the editorial board with
                “negative elements”, such as Lojze Kovačič and Janko Kos. According to a report of
                the Internal Administration, young intellectuals felt “that the measures are a
                staged and a non-serious matter which intends to cause anxiety among them, and they
                must not fall for it”. The fact that the magazine was also defended by some
                prominent cultural workers of the older generation was also seen as a problem. Among
                them, the Internal Administration first mentioned Josip Vidmar. Vladimir Kralj
                allegedly said that the affair was triggered by the “anti-cultural people from
                Kranj, who will, however, have to quit at the request of Belgrade”, while praises
                for young people also came from the Catholic intellectual circles, i.e. from Anton
                Vodnik and Edvard Kocbek.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn25" n="24"> SI AS 1589, IK, t. e. 12, Naši nadaljnji ukrepi in rezultati preiskave proti skupini Revije 57.
                    </note></p>
            <p>Jože Pučnik also counted on the possibility that the matter could calm down quite
                quickly, but he did not know what was happening outside the prison walls. It was not
                until mid-November, when he was informed that the investigation had been extended
                pursuant to Article 117 of the Penal Code, which sanctioned illegal association
                against the system of government, that it became clear to him that a nasty
                confrontation was in sight. Pučnik’s activities in the framework of the legally
                functioning <hi rend="italic">Students’ Union</hi> and clubs at the Faculty started
                to be categorised as calls to organise. His involvement was seen only as hiding
                behind an external façade with the interest of spreading his own anti-state ideas.
                They began to take the words which he wrote in his articles or spoke at forums out
                of context, especially those that government officials found the most alarming. The
                word organization invoked fear, because it could imply that anyone else, not just
                the leaders in the ruling political parties, were able to discuss political matters
                in the country. Less than a year after the first major workers’ strike in socialist
                Yugoslavia broke out in Trbovlje, government officials found that a mere reference
                to the word strike was almost equal to a declaration of war. Six months after the
                    <hi rend="italic">League of Communists</hi> adopted the best political
                programme, the leading Communists found any debate on the Constitution or the
                political system utterly outrageous. For Jože Pučnik, it was hard to comprehend what
                was he being accused of: “I do not know, for a long time I did not understand what
                they really wanted. They accused me of setting up an illegal organization, but I
                felt that they were not convinced about it either.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn26" n="25"> Lorenci, <hi rend="italic">Jože Pučnik</hi>,
                        27.</note></p>
            <p>The indications that the police authorities highlighted in their reports for the top
                government circles in November 1958 were presented by the leading Slovenian
                Communists in a redacted form at the plenum of the League of Communists of Slovenia
                on 5 December 1958. They announced a strong response to the activity of those
                intellectuals of the younger generation who allegedly acted contrary to the
                interests of the state. Boris Ziherl spoke about ideological political issues, and
                although he did not name his opponents, he referred a few times to <hi rend="italic">Revija 57,</hi> thereby directing his criticism at those who allegedly had too
                much influence on young people.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn27" n="26"> SI AS 1589, IK, t. e. 7, Stenografski zapisnik IX.
                        plenarne seje CK ZKS, 5 December, 1958, 2–13.</note> An explanation of
                the situation concerning the <hi rend="italic">Revija 57</hi> magazine was given in
                greater detail by Janez Vipotnik. With regard to Jože Pučnik, he found that he was
                accepted into the <hi rend="italic">League of Communists</hi> too quickly and
                without sufficient consideration. The information that, at the time, “Pučnik was
                incarcerated due to his anti-state activities”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn28" n="27"> Ibid., 32. </note> was stated by Ziherl as a
                simple fact which was not to be questioned. With regard to the 40 people who were
                considered to be a part of the magazine’s circle, he found that they wanted to
                “address social problems from the perspective of intellectuals who were oriented
                towards non-class division” and that they were not completely on the same page in
                terms of their convictions. The employees of <hi rend="italic">Revija 57</hi>
                allegedly committed a serious political violation because “the group wanted to have
                a literary evening after the strike in Trbovlje, where they wanted to express
                solidarity with the phenomenon in Trbovlje in a political manner”. Vipotnik
                described the magazine’s circle using a distinctly political vocabulary and a very
                negative connotation. Vipotnik tried to prove that <hi rend="italic">Revija 57</hi>
                did not have a significant impact on the generation of students, which raised doubts
                about why the <hi rend="italic">League of Communists of Slovenia</hi> was so
                involved in and why it took on a phenomenon that was supposed to be so
                    marginal.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn29" n="28">
                        Ibid., 32–36.</note></p>
            <p>In December 1958 and in early 1959, the <hi rend="italic">Revija 57</hi> magazine was
                repeatedly targeted by the leading politicians and became the subject of numerous
                sessions held by high-level authorities. The politicians reiterated that the
                magazine were a group of young intellectuals who formed an illegal hostile
                organization, spread anti-state propaganda and djilasism, called on workers to go on
                strikes etc. The process was accompanied by strong media campaigns, but the opposing
                side did not get a chance to defend itself. The interrogations continued, and the
                two editors, Klabus and Taufer, as well as Taras Kermauner were each sentenced to
                ten days in prison. The encounters and intimidations finally escalated in a trial
                held on 30 March 1959, in which Jože Pučnik was sentenced to nine years of severe
                    imprisonment.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn30" n="29"> SI AS 1589, III, t. e. 68, Informacije, No. 49, 11 March 1959, 6, No. 57, 9 April 1959, 10 and No. 59, 18 April, 1959, 4. Klabus, “Pričevanje o Reviji 57 in Perspektivah,” 116, 117. 
                    </note>
            </p></div>
            <div><head>Finding Causes for a Strict Confrontation with
                    Revija 57 and Pučnik</head>
            <p>In the judgment against Jože Pučnik, the court summarized the positions which had
                been served by the investigators. In a very unconvincing explanation, the court
                confirmed that there had been an attempt to set up an illegal organization, which
                allegedly intended to unconstitutionally overthrow the government. By referring to
                the article <hi rend="italic">Our Social Reality and our Illusions,</hi> they
                attempted to prove the hostile propaganda and the defendant’s negative attitude
                towards the social reality.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn31" n="30"> Lorenci, <hi rend="italic">Jože Pučnik</hi>,
                        68–74.</note> After the trial, Pučnik’s friends congratulated him for
                his strong posture; however, this triggered additional measures inflicted by the
                government authorities. </p>
            <p>Subsequent assessments of the judicial confrontation with Jože Pučnik vary, but there
                is little doubt about some common highlighted points, i.e. that the trial was a
                judicial construct and an attempt to intimidate the young generation of
                intellectuals and that the imposed sentence was disproportionately high even by the
                then case-law criteria. Some also emphasize the fact that Pučnik was the only one
                without a strong bourgeois and political support base, and therefore, in the company
                of friends who had fathers in prominent positions, he served as an example to
                everyone else of what might have happened had they continued along this path.
                However, by overly limiting the issue to the influence exerted by important fathers,
                one can easily miss some important emphases. As has already been pointed out, the
                communist government saw the group related to the <hi rend="italic">Revija 57</hi>
                magazine, contrary to its predecessor, the <hi rend="italic">Beseda</hi> magazine,
                as very political. However, members of the young generation of intellectuals did not
                see themselves in the role of (political) opposition at that time. Especially not
                Jože Pučnik, who had been, after all, a member of the <hi rend="italic">League of
                    Communists of Slovenia</hi> until his arrest and who, through legal forms of
                action, had tried to express what the party should correct if it wanted to act as a
                workers’ avant-garde. Unlike those who are too quick to label themselves using terms
                such as opposition, dissidence, or a dissident in describing their own past, Peter
                Božič’s assessment was based on contemplation and analysis, which attempted to
                logically embed the concept of the term opposition into the context of overall
                events. Božič saw the arrival of Pučnik to <hi rend="italic">Revija 57</hi> as a
                turning point after which the debate spread from only being in the cultural sphere
                to integrating cultural and social notions by placing them “into a realistic social
                space opposite the official one, which was still marked with the ideology of the
                PATRY”. Therefore, according to Božič, Pučnik’s role was marked “with the different
                content framework of <hi rend="italic">Revija 57</hi> alone, and thus the first
                alternative to the party programme as well as the opposition were also de facto
                    created”.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn32" n="31"> Peter
                        Božič, “Moja prva srečanja s Pučnikom,” in: Lorenci, <hi rend="italic">Jože
                            Pučnik,</hi> 89.</note></p>
            <p>However, a participant in numerous discussions of this generation, Janko Kos, pointed
                out that there must be, nevertheless, a longer journey from criticising the
                government and drawing ideas that were in glaring contradiction with the party
                programme to developing a comprehensive alternative programme: “Can I gather some
                kind of a new ideology from all of this – a political, social and cultural ideology
                that could be set against the party doctrine? I doubt it, simply because no one has
                ever formulated it in any obvious way.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn33" n="32"> Janko Kos, <hi rend="italic">Ideologi in oporečniki:
                            spominjanja</hi> (Ljubljana: Znanstvena založba Filozofske fakultete;
                        Beletrina, 2015), 85.</note> In the title of Kos’ book describing the
                events, he used the term disputants for the group to which he belonged. The notion
                of disputing was best used by Jure Ramšak in his doctoral thesis in which he
                analysed social criticism in Slovenia during a somewhat later period, i.e. the
                    1970s.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn34" n="33"> Jure
                        Ramšak, “Oporečništvo v samoupravnem socializmu: vsebina in položaj družbene
                        kritike v Sloveniji, 1972–1980” (doktorska disertacija, Univerza na
                        Primorskem, 2013).</note></p>
            <p>The protagonists from the <hi rend="italic">Revija 57</hi> magazine are unanimous in
                assessing that Jože Pučnik was a step ahead of others, and that he, in addition to
                writing, acting as an organizer of talks, clubs, seminars, and activities in the
                framework of legal forums, the League of Communists, and the <hi rend="italic">Students’ Union</hi>, also performed purely (political) organizational work.
                However, regarding assessments of whether this was politics or, more precisely,
                political opposition, opinions differ, even to the point of arguing that the entry
                into the real political scene can only be placed in the 1980s and the 57<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> issue of the <hi rend="italic">Nova revija</hi>
                magazine, and that before that, there were only conceptual fragments that were not
                yet political enough in the area of activities by magazines that mostly dealt with
                    culture.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn35" n="34"> Cf.
                        Taras Kermauner, “Epilog ali nov začetek?,” <hi rend="italic">Borec</hi> 48,
                        No. 551–552 (1996): 246.</note></p>
            <p>The other side, i.e. the top of the ruling <hi rend="italic">League of Communists of
                    Slovenia</hi>, was much more uniform in its assessments of <hi rend="italic">Revija 57</hi>. The word opposition was expelled from publicly used political
                vocabulary, but it was used several times when the narrow circles of the highest
                political authorities discussed their actual and alleged opponents. In the 1950s,
                high-level political circles were more or less clear that they no longer had to fear
                the pre-war generation of politicians. This applies both to those who, after the
                experience of the early post-war years, became passive, and those who experienced
                communist prison. Although the police monitored potential opponents of the
                government for many years, officers of the State Security Administration (UDBA) kept
                getting an increasing number of reports on how various older-generation politicians
                continued to meet with old political figures, but that these were merely meetings
                with drinking buddies to comment current events. People who faced the repressive
                measures of the post-war government were even worse off, as they had to face
                everyday existential problems after their release from prison. The decreasing need
                for controlling the older generation of regime opponents started to divert the
                attention of the police and politicians to the younger critics of the
                government.</p>
            <p>Among them, those who dealt with political issues came to the forefront. According to
                party ideologists, they were by no means true Marxists. The attention of the leaders
                in the country was increasingly directed to the new generation raised in the new
                Yugoslavia, which was more indifferent to pre-war predicaments and very sensitive to
                deviations in post-war reality. The Slovenian Party leadership started considering
                the possibility that the young generation of intellectuals could be seen as a new
                type of opposition in 1957, one year after the political turmoil in Hungary and
                Poland. The main cultural ideologist of the Communist Party of Slovenia, Boris
                Ziherl, reported to the top leaders of the <hi rend="italic">League of Communists of
                    Slovenia</hi> that the events had also had a great influence on intellectuals in
                Yugoslavia and that the leaders were not particularly enthusiastic about the
                direction of the controversy: “Not only in Slovenia, but also elsewhere, cultural
                workers express the opinion that it would be necessary to revise the points on the
                leading role of the working class in the process of building socialism and in
                today’s social development, as recent events have shown that the leading factor in
                this regard are intellectuals, especially writers. This doubt was also expressed in
                interviews with a delegation of Polish writers whom our writers first asked how they
                were preparing the October events, and further in discussions regarding the new <hi rend="italic">League of Communists of Yugoslavia</hi> programme.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn36" n="35"> SI AS 1589, IK, t.
                        e. 7, Minutes of the Executive Committee CK ZKS, 14 May, 1957, 6,
                    7.</note></p>
            <p>The fear of denying the relevant fundamental principles on which the communist
                authorities were based was more and more present. These words reflected the thought
                that the avant-garde should no longer be based on the working class or the party
                that was supposed to be its personification, but on intellectuals. Such a view of
                the social involvement of the young generation of intellectuals was not limited to
                narrow-minded ideologists, such as Boris Ziherl, but was also adopted by political
                pragmatists, such as Boris Kraigher. In light of the scandal with the
                    <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Revija 57 </hi>magazine<hi rend="italic">,</hi> he did not agree with the assessment that the <hi rend="italic">Revija 57</hi> team did not have a political concept and that the concept was
                not the driving force of their operation. The basis for his opinion was that “these
                people sometimes react inappropriately to certain political measures, which means
                that it is then truly necessary to prevent the tendencies that led the Hungarian
                revolution to become a counter-revolution from becoming a reality in Slovenia as
                well”. Due to a quite strong sense of fear that things might (in the future) go
                beyond that which was allowed, the Prime Minister of the Republic of Slovenia warned
                that even the good thoughts that grow in the wrong garden could trigger unfavourable
                consequences because “the Hungarian anti-Stalinist campaign brought the struggle
                directly into the arms of counter-revolution, although I do not agree with the way
                the Russians responded to this”. In the political glossary of terms used by the
                leading communists, Kraigher said that good ideas and good initiatives could never
                hurt anybody. However, it would have presented a double risk if they had given
                incentive to those inspired by the Western-style multi-party system (in the party
                jargon, this was also considered a counter-revolution). It could pose a risk within
                the internal policy as the political monopoly of the ruling party could crumble, and
                the risk within the foreign policy if the tension with the Soviet Union would
                increase and lead to an unpredictable outcome. The uprisings against the communist
                authorities in Poland and Hungary of 1956 were therefore a warning to the
                highest-ranking political leaders that it was better to react more quickly and
                prevent actions that they considered extremely political. According to Kraigher’s
                estimates, “after the events in those countries, some people in Slovenia found
                courage when they saw that something can indeed be done, and therefore they are
                taking certain steps in this direction”. Kraigher also remarked that it was
                perfectly clear to him that those who would think about such moves are no Edvard
                Kocbek, although Kocbek maintained contacts with people whose names had been
                recorded in police files. When he thought about the people for whom it would be a
                mistake to “give them the freedom to act in the name of the freedom of cultural
                engagement and in the name of democracy”, he said that “this completely applies to
                that guy Pučnik”. His articles and his defence for the right of workers to strike
                were everything that the leading Communists did not want to tolerate in their home
                    yard.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn37" n="36"> SI AS
                        537, t. e. 27, Seja predsedstva SZDLS, 6 November, 1958, 52,
                53.</note></p>
            <p>The Slovenian political leadership thus considered the younger generation of
                intellectuals in a purely political context, analysed its work using political
                vocabulary, and ultimately also began to deem it as a political problem. In the 1958
                Annual Report of the Ministry of the Interior, i.e. at the time of the cancellation
                of <hi rend="italic">Revija 57,</hi> and during preparations for the process against
                Pučnik, it was clearly recorded for the first time that the old pre-war opposition
                was no longer the main threat, but that the threat was now coming from elsewhere:
                “Regarding the hostile propaganda activities of the remnants of bourgeois parties,
                it is important to emphasize that this propaganda was mainly limited to various
                discussions and comments, i.e. that there were no organized forms of hostile
                activity among them, but that the problem is posed by young intellectuals who do not
                agree with the socialist system in our country.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn38" n="37"> SI AS 1931, A-13-O, Letno poročilo za leto 1958,
                        3, 4.</note></p>
            <p>This younger generation quite unanimously defended the view that every individual has
                the right to express their opinion. However, during talks with politicians and in
                interrogations conducted by investigators, they denied the suspicions and
                allegations that this was just a step towards establishing an organization aimed at
                destroying the existing social order. The ruling circles had a completely different
                opinion. In a special report drawn up by the State Security Directorate during the
                affair surrounding <hi rend="italic">Revija 57</hi> for the Slovenian political
                leaders, the young generation of intellectuals was first seen as potential
                opposition: “Together with those who are like-minded, they are trying to create an
                opinion that they are being persecuted as opposition, but constructive and
                progressive opposition, which is persecuted precisely for this reason by the
                government. However, by doing so, the government showed it was no longer
                    progressive.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn39" n="38">
                        SI AS 1589, IK, t. e. 12, Naši nadaljnji ukrepi in rezultati preiskave proti
                        skupini Revije 57, 4.</note></p></div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="bibliography">
                <head>Sources and Literature</head>
            <list type="unordered">
                <head>Archival Sources:</head>
                <item>SI AS, Arhiv Republike Slovenije:<list>
            <item>SI AS 537 – Republiška konferenca Socialistične zveze
                delovnega ljudstva Slovenije.</item>
                    <item>SI AS 1589 – Centralni komite Zveze komunistov Slovenije.</item>
                    <item>SI AS 1799 – Centralni komite Ljudske mladine Slovenije.</item>
                            <item>SI AS 1931 – Republiški sekretariat za notranje zadeve
                                Socialistične republike Slovenije.</item>
                    <item>SI AS 2027 – Društvo slovenskih pisateljev. </item></list></item></list>
            <listBibl>
                <head>Literature:</head>
                <bibl><hi rend="short_text" xml:space="preserve">Božič, Peter. „Moja prva srečanja s Pučnikom“. In: </hi>Lorenci,
                    Janko. <hi rend="italic">Jože Pučnik</hi>. Ljubljana: Emonica, 1990, 88–93. </bibl>
                <bibl><hi style="font-size:10pt">Kermauner, Taras. “Epilog ali nov začetek?.”</hi>
                    <hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Borec</hi>
                    <hi style="font-size:10pt">48, No. 551–552 (1996): 241–52.</hi></bibl>
                <bibl><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">Klabus, Vital. “Pričevanje o Reviji 57 in Perspektivah.” </hi><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Borec</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve"> 48, No. 551–552 (1996): 111–36.</hi></bibl>
                <bibl><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">Kos, Janko. </hi><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Ideologi in oporečniki:
                    spominjanja</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt">. Ljubljana: Znanstvena založba
                        Filozofske fakultete, Beletrina, 2015.</hi>
                </bibl>
                <bibl><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">Kos, Janko. </hi><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Umetniki in meščani:
                    spominjanja</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt">. Ljubljana: Beletrina,
                        2015.</hi></bibl>
                <bibl><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">Lorenci, Janko. </hi><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Jože Pučnik</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt">. Ljubljana: Emonica, 1990.</hi></bibl>
                <bibl><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">Pesek, Rosvita. </hi><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Pučnik</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt">.
                        Celovec: Mohorjeva, 2013.</hi></bibl>
                <bibl><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">Pučnik, Jože. </hi><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Članki in spomini 1957–1985</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt">. Maribor: Obzorja, 1986.</hi></bibl>
                <bibl><hi style="font-size:10pt">Ramšak, Jure. “Oporečništvo v samoupravnem
                    socializmu: vsebina in položaj družbene kritike v Sloveniji, 1972</hi>
                    <hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">–</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">1980.” Doktorska disertacija, Univerza na Primorskem, 2013. </hi>
                </bibl>
                <bibl><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">Režek, Mateja. “Ideološko ozadje ukinitve Revije 57.” </hi>
                    <ref target="https://plus.si.cobiss.net/opac7/bib/COBIB/4435458"><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Nova
                        revija</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve"> 13, No. 151–152 (1994): 194–206</hi></ref><hi style="font-size:10pt">.</hi></bibl>
                <bibl><hi style="font-size:10pt">Režek, Mateja.</hi>
                    <hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Med resničnostjo in iluzijo: slovenska
                        in jugoslovanska politika v desetletju po sporu z Informbirojem:
                        (1948–1958)</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt">. Ljubljana: Modrijan,
                            2005.</hi></bibl>
            </listBibl></div>
           <div type="summary" xml:lang="sl">
            <docAuthor>Aleš Gabrič</docAuthor>
            <head>JOŽE PUČNIK NA POTI
                DO DISIDENTA</head>
            <head>POVZETEK</head>
            <p>Med slovenskimi političnimi zaporniki v času komunističnega režima je Jože Pučnik
                specifičen primer. Čeprav je sodeloval s številnimi drugimi intelektualci pri
                ustvarjanju podobe različnih revij, je s svojo kritično ostjo in nato posledično
                usodo političnega preganjanca predstavljal poseben primer. </p>
            <p>Med sodelavci Revije 57, s katerimi je oblast obračunala ob koncu petdesetih let, je
                izstopal že po tem, da je že imel mesto v policijskem dosjeju. Leta 1951 je namreč
                sodeloval v reviji mariborskih srednješolcev <hi rend="italic">Iskanja</hi>, čemur
                so sledila zaslišanja sodelavcev revije in grožnje z onemogočanjem nadaljnjega
                šolanja. Po vpisu na Filozofsko fakulteto v Ljubljani je bil agilen v Zvezi
                študentov in v javnih razpravah, ki so ga približali krogu <hi rend="italic">Revije
                    57</hi>. Za časopis je napisal več prispevkov o tedanjih domačih družbenih
                razmerah. V kritičnosti Pučnik ni bil izjema, toda njegove besede so bile običajno
                zelo neposredne, lahko razumljive, medtem ko je bilo pri člankih nekaterih drugih
                piscev treba brati tudi med vrsticami. Družbena angažiranost je Pučnika v začetku
                leta 1958 pripeljala tudi do vstopa v Zvezo komunistov, kar je naletelo na burne
                odzive med sodelavci <hi rend="italic">Revije 57</hi>, ki so posumili o vzrokih, ki
                so Pučnika vodili do takšne odločitve.</p>
            <p>V <hi rend="italic">Reviji 57</hi> je v letih 1957 in 1958 Pučnik objavil več
                kritičnih člankov o aktualnih družbenih in političnih razmerah. Najbolj pa je
                razburkal stališča sodelavcev in politikov s člankom, v katerem je analiziral
                razhajanja med idejnimi postavkami vladajoče elite in stvarnostjo ter med
                miselnostjo in delom komunistov pred dvema desetletjema, ko so še bili v ilegali, in
                po vojni, ko so se utrdili na oblasti. Oblast je v sklopu širšega obračuna s
                humanistično inteligenco ob koncu petdesetih let na seznam škodljivih zadev uvrstila
                tudi krog <hi rend="italic">Revije 57</hi>. Ker poskusi mehkega utišanja besed
                mlajše intelektualne generacije niso uspeli, je oblast posegla po ostrejših metodah.
                Ob koncu leta 1958 in v začetku 1959 je bila <hi rend="italic">Revija 57</hi>
                večkrat tarča kritik vodilnih politikov, tema številnih sej visokih organov,
                očitkov, da gre za skupino mlajših intelektualcev, ki je snovala ilegalno sovražno
                organizacijo, širila protidržavno propagando in đilasovstvo, pozivala delavce k
                štrajku, vse skupaj pa je spremljala močna medijska gonja proti reviji. Višek
                obračuna pa je bil marca 1959 sodni proces proti Jožetu Pučniku, na katerem je bil
                ta obsojen na devet let zapora. Ostrina obračuna je bila presenetljiva za tedanje
                slovenske politične razmere. Pogled v zakulisje dogajanj v krogih najpomembnejših
                slovenskih oblastnih krogov pa pokaže, da je bil ta posledica ocen, v katerih je
                Uprava državne varnosti mlajšo intelektualno generacijo prvič ocenila kot možno
                potencialno opozicijo in jo namesto stare garde politikov postavila na prvo mesto
                med tistimi, ki so jih ocenjevali kot potencialne organizatorje opozicije.</p></div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>