<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Sustainability of Digital Editions: Static Websites of the History of
                    Slovenia – SIstory Portal</title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename>Andrej</forename>
                        <surname>Pančur</surname>
                        <affiliation>Institute of Contemporary History</affiliation>
                        <address>
                            <addrLine>Kongresni trg 1</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>SI-1000 Ljubljana</addrLine>
                        </address>
                        <email>andrej.pancur@inz.si</email>
                    </name>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>2019-04-15</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>
                    <orgName xml:lang="sl">Inštitut za novejšo zgodovino</orgName>
                    <orgName xml:lang="en">Institute of Contemporary History</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Kongresni trg 1</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>SI-1000 Ljubljana</addrLine>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>http://ojs.inz.si/pnz/article/view/348</pubPlace>
                <date>2019</date>
                <availability status="free">
                    <licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title xml:lang="sl">Prispevki za novejšo zgodovino</title>
                <title xml:lang="en">Contributions to Contemporary History</title>
                <biblScope unit="volume">59</biblScope>
                <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
                <idno type="ISSN">2463-7807</idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source, born digital.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc xml:lang="en">
                <p>Contributions to Contemporary History is one of the central Slovenian scientific
                    historiographic journals, dedicated to publishing articles from the field of
                    contemporary history (the 19th and 20th century).</p>
                <p>The journal is published three times per year in Slovenian and in the following
                    foreign languages: English, German, Serbian, Croatian, Bosnian, Italian, Slovak
                    and Czech. The articles are all published with abstracts in English and
                    Slovenian as well as summaries in English.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <projectDesc xml:lang="sl">
                <p>Prispevki za novejšo zgodovino je ena osrednjih slovenskih znanstvenih
                    zgodovinopisnih revij, ki objavlja teme s področja novejše zgodovine (19. in 20.
                    stoletje).</p>
                <p>Revija izide trikrat letno v slovenskem jeziku in v naslednjih tujih jezikih:
                    angleščina, nemščina, srbščina, hrvaščina, bosanščina, italijanščina, slovaščina
                    in češčina. Članki izhajajo z izvlečki v angleščini in slovenščini ter povzetki
                    v angleščini.</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="sl"/>
                <language ident="en"/>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords xml:lang="en">
                    <term>digital editions</term>
                    <term>digital curation</term>
                    <term>TEI</term>
                    <term>XSLT</term>
                    <term>static website</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords xml:lang="sl">
                    <term>digitalne izdaje</term>
                    <term>digitalno kuratorstvo</term>
                    <term>TEI</term>
                    <term>XSLT</term>
                    <term>statične spletne strani</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change>
                    <date>2019-06-07</date>
                    <name>Mihael Ojsteršek</name>
                    <desc>Pretvorba iz DOCX v TEI, dodatno kodiranje</desc>
                </change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <docAuthor>Andrej Pančur<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn1" n="*"><hi
                        rend="footnote_reference"/>
                    <hi rend="bold">Institute of Contemporary History, Kongresni trg 1, SI-1000
                        Ljubljana, </hi><ref target="mailto:andrej.pancur@inz.si">
                        <hi rend="bold">andrej.pancur@inz.si</hi></ref></note></docAuthor>
            <docImprint>
                <idno type="cobissType">Cobiss type: 1.01</idno>
                <idno type="UDC">UDC: 004.774-026.11</idno>
            </docImprint>
            <div type="abstract" xml:lang="sl">
                <head>IZVLEČEK</head>
                <head>TRAJNOST DIGITALNH IZDAJ: STATIČNE SPLETNE STRANI PORTALA ZGODOVINA SLOVENIJE
                    – SISTORY</head>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Prispevek izhaja iz stališča, da je pri digitalnih izdajah
                        potrebno poskrbeti za čim bolj celovito digitalno trajnost tako podatkov kot
                        prezentacij, funkcionalnosti in programske kode. To je velik izziv predvsem
                        za manjše digitalno humanistične projekte z omejenim financiranjem, ki ne
                        omogoča dolgoročnega vzdrževanja tehnično zahtevnih digitalnih izdaj. Kot
                        alternativno rešitev so v prispevku predstavljene rešitve, ki jih v zadnjih
                        letih ponuja hiter razvoj statičnih spletnih strani. Digitalne izdaje, ki
                        temeljijo na TEI, so s pomočjo osnovnih XML (XSLT) in spletnih tehnologij
                        (HTML, CSS, JavaScript) kot statične spletne strani uspešno vključene v
                        repozitorij portala SIstory. Vse statične spletne strani imajo tudi možnost
                        dinamičnega prikazovanja vsebine.</hi></p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Ključne besede: digitalne izdaje, digitalno kuratorstvo, TEI,
                        XSLT, statične spletne strani</hi></p>
            </div>
            <div type="abstract">
                <head>ABSTRACT</head>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">The contribution is based on the position that, with regard to
                        digital editions, the highest possible degree of digital sustainability of
                        data, presentations, functionalities, and programme code should be ensured.
                        This represents a significant challenge, especially in case of smaller
                        digital humanities projects with limited financing, which does not allow for
                        the long-term maintenance of technically-demanding digital editions. The
                        alternative solutions facilitated by the swift development of static
                        websites in the recent years are presented in the contribution. Digital
                        editions based on the TEI have been successfully included in the SIstory
                        portal repository as static websites, employing basic XML (XSLT) and web
                        technologies (HTML, CSS, JavaScript). All the static websites also have the
                        possibility of displaying dynamic content.</hi></p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Keywords: digital editions, digital curation, TEI, XSLT, static
                        website</hi></p>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div>
                <head>Introduction</head>
                <p>In digital humanities, the awareness of the importance of digital sustainability
                    and permanent preservation of digital sources has been present for a long time
                        (<ref target="#Schaffner.2014">Schaffner and Erway 2014, 7</ref>). The
                    research data of an individual project usually outlives the project in the
                    context of which it has been collected, organised, and published. Therefore it
                    is very important to ensure a high-quality and sustainable storage of digital
                    data even after the project itself has been concluded.</p>
                <p>In the recent years, the technical aspects of research data management and
                    long-term archiving (metadata, archive formats, preservation media, and
                    documentation) have been the subject of intensive discussions. Only lately,
                    however, have we begun to realise that the preservation of data in accordance
                    with the specific requirements of various scientific disciplines is almost more
                    important for the high-quality management and reuse of this data (<ref
                        target="#Moeller.2018">Moeller et al. 2018</ref>). While in the natural and
                    social sciences the data from measurements and questionnaires is typically used,
                    in the humanities the use of cultural objects like manuscripts, texts, pictures,
                    and recordings is predominant. Moreover, researchers in humanities will usually
                    additionally process, visualise, tag, link, and interpret digital cultural
                    objects (<ref target="#DHd-AG.2017">DHd-AG Datenzentren 2017, 7</ref>).</p>
                <p>Such data processing is particularly important in case of digital editions, which
                    are a crucial part of digital humanities (<ref target="#Andorfer.2016">Andorfer
                        et al. 2016)</ref>. Naturally, digital scholarly editions mostly consist of
                    the research in the context of which different transcriptions, indications,
                    analyses, explanations, etc., are produced. Such research data in particular
                    should therefore be available to the research community in the long term and
                    under open access conditions (<ref target="#Robinson.2016">Robinson 2016</ref>).
                    In the case of digital editions, the encoded text is the most crucial long-term
                    result of the project. The display of information is vital as well, as it
                    represents the outlook of the project group on this information in the context
                    of a certain application. However, it is not that every such outlook is unique
                    in any way or even the only one possible. Instead, this information can be
                    displayed in a variety of ways (<ref target="#Turska.2016">Turska et al.
                        2016</ref>). With each new interpretation, the number of other potential
                    user interfaces even increases. Each such presentation is thus a new research
                    result that deserves long-term storage as well.</p>
                <p>Therefore, research results in humanities consist not only of research data, but
                    also of the presentation environment and the applications that enable data
                    interpretation, searching, filtering, browsing, and linking (<ref
                        target="#DHd-AG.2017">DHd-AG Datenzentren 2017, 7</ref>). If we only stored
                    research data, the initial presentation would be lost forever, even though the
                    presentation represents an integral part of any digital edition (<ref
                        target="#Fechner.2018">Fechner 2018</ref>). At the same time, we should not
                    forget that the programming code used for the creation of digital editions is an
                    integral part of the scientific argumentation as well, just like the digital
                    editions (<ref target="#Andrews.2016">Andrews and Zundert 2016</ref>).</p>
                <p>Sustainable storage of digital editions therefore represents a particularly
                    significant challenge. Moreover, digital editions can be very different from
                    each other in terms of their contents, appearance, and functionality. They
                    mostly result from specific research projects with relatively limited financial
                    and human resources at their disposal. As the project group members come from
                    the field of humanities, they often lack the suitable technical expertise, which
                    is why they mostly need to rely on external contractors when it comes to
                    technical development. Furthermore, digital editions depend on the very swift
                    development of online technologies and standards (<ref target="#Andorfer.2016"
                        >Andorfer et al. 2016</ref>).</p>
                <p>As the number of digital editions increases rapidly, the challenges involved in
                    the sustainable storage of digital editions will only become greater in the
                    future (<ref target="#Fechner.2018">Fechner 2018</ref>). In case of smaller
                    digital humanities projects with limited financing, which does not allow for the
                    long-term maintenance of technically-demanding digital editions, this represents
                    a significant challenge and will continue to do so. In the continuation, I will
                    present alternative solutions offered by the rapid development of static
                    websites. In the recent years, static websites have become one of the main
                    online development trends. It appears that this trend will also persist in the
                    future (<ref target="#Williams.2019">Williams 2019</ref>). In the present
                    contribution, I will present the experience gained by generating static websites
                    for the digital editions in the context of the activities of the Research
                    Infrastructure of Slovenian Historiography, which, among other tasks, also
                    manages the History of Slovenia – SIstory web portal.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn2" n="1">“Research Infrastructure of Slovenian Historiography,”
                            <hi rend="italic">History of Slovenia – SIstory</hi>, accessed April 15,
                        2019, <ref target="http://www.sistory.si/publikacije/?menuBottom=2"
                            >http://www.sistory.si/publikacije/?menuBottom=2</ref>.</note> In this
                    regard I will restrict my article solely to the static websites generated from
                    XML files, encoded in accordance with the Text Encoding Initiative Guidelines
                    (TEI) (<ref target="#TEIConsortium.2019">TEI Consortium 2019</ref>). In digital
                    humanities, the TEI Guidelines are the <foreign>de facto</foreign> standard for
                    text encoding, used by many different humanities projects and studies (<ref
                        target="#Romary.2017">Romary et al. 2017, 5</ref>).</p>
                <p>In the chapter <hi rend="italic">Modern Static Websites</hi>, I will first
                    present the main advantages and disadvantages of this type of websites. In our
                    case, we have decided to upgrade the basic XSLT Stylesheets of the TEI
                    Consortium. In the <hi rend="italic">SIstory TEI Profile</hi> chapter, I will
                    present generic upgrade of the TEI Stylesheets. In the chapter <hi rend="italic"
                        >Configuring and Upgrading the SIstory TEI Profile</hi> I will outline the
                    project-specific options for upgrading this profile. In both these chapters, I
                    will also discuss the various options of adding dynamic contents to static
                    websites. In the chapter <hi rend="italic">Publishing Digital Editions</hi> I
                    will outline how these static websites can be made available to the public, in
                    particular by their inclusion in the SIstory portal's digital repository. In the
                        <hi rend="italic">Conclusion</hi>, I will also mention a few more general
                    findings.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Modern Static Websites</head>
                <p>All websites used to be static at first, which is why all of the digital editions
                    in the field of digital humanities were initially created as static HTML
                    websites. This was also true in case of the Slovenian scholarly digital editions
                        (<ref target="#Ogrin.2009">Ogrin and Erjavec 2009</ref>),<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn3" n="2">
                        <hi rend="italic">Scholarly Digital Editions of Slovenian Literature,
                            eZISS</hi>, accessed April 15, 2019, <ref
                            target="http://nl.ijs.si/e-zrc/index-en.html"
                            >http://nl.ijs.si/e-zrc/index-en.html</ref>.</note> which have
                    introduced the paradigm of digital editions in Slovenia (<ref
                        target="#Ogrin.2005">Ogrin 2005</ref>). The creators of these digital
                    editions soon encountered certain shortcomings of static websites. In
                    particular, they missed the option of carrying out structured text searches,
                    adaptable URL query string parameters, and dynamic web content association. In
                    the case of newer digital editions, they therefore opted for the Fedora Commons
                    platform (<ref target="#Erjavec.2011">Erjavec et al. 2011</ref>).</p>
                <p>By that point, the internet had been, for a long time already, dominated by
                    dynamic websites that had successfully replaced the outdated static websites,
                    where the contents could only be altered by the developers directly editing the
                    HTML code. By means of content management systems (e.g. the very popular
                    WordPress, Drupal, and Joomla), dynamic websites have finally made it possible
                    for technically unskilled users to start publishing on the internet.</p>
                <p>The contents of dynamic websites are stored in databases. The server does not
                    construct the contents until the user demands that a website be displayed,
                    adapted to the demands of the user. A suitable programming language is used to
                    communicate with the server. The biggest problem of such dynamic websites is
                    that its technical solutions are often more complicated than the actual needs of
                    their users.</p>
                <p>Modern static websites, however, have been created as an answer to the problems
                    exhibited by dynamic websites. Unlike the latter, static websites do not employ
                    databases and server-side programming languages, but are simply a collection of
                    HTML, CSS, and JavaScript files. Static websites therefore enjoy numerous
                    advantages in comparison with dynamic websites (<ref target="#Rinaldi.2015"
                        >Rinaldi 2015</ref>):</p>
                <list type="unordered">
                    <item>efficiency: as static websites do not require any databases or server-side
                        processing, they are not in danger of becoming slow;</item>
                    <item>hosting: because static websites do not rely on a server-side programming
                        language, their hosting is simple and cheap. There are even free options,
                        for example the GitHub Pages service;</item>
                    <item>security: static websites do not require any databases or server-side
                        programming languages that hackers could breach. Therefore such sites are
                        safe until the files they consist of are stored securely;</item>
                    <item>maintenance: as static websites do not rely on any databases, server-side
                        programming languages, or content management systems, their maintenance is
                        extremely simple;</item>
                    <item>versioning: since static websites consist exclusively of text files, all
                        of their versions can be quite simply stored in version control systems like
                        Git.</item>
                </list>
                <p>These reasons are particularly important to ensure the sustainability of digital
                    editions. The use of standard formats like TIFF and JPEG for digital
                    photographs, HTML and XML for texts, and so on, ensures that the digital
                    editions created will remain readable and useful for a long time to come (<ref
                        target="#RosselliDelTurco.2016">Rosselli Del Turco 2016</ref>).
                    Consequently, this paradigm started to be emphasised in other similar projects
                    in the field of digital humanities as well (<ref target="#Viglianti.2017"
                        >Viglianti 2017</ref>; <ref target="#Daengeli.2017">Daengeli and Zumsteg
                        2017</ref>; <ref target="#Diaz.2018">Diaz 2018</ref>).</p>
                <p>These reasons, however, are less convincing in case we expect digital editions to
                    contain user-generated contents as well. Therefore, static websites are not
                    appropriate for all digital editions in the field of digital humanities, as such
                    solutions will often fail to satisfy the needs of the creators and users. On the
                    other hand, countless digital projects do not call for very complex content and
                    its display. In such cases the existing solutions provided by static websites
                    can be more than satisfactory, especially because modern static websites do not
                    completely lack the option of adding dynamic contents. In reality, static
                    websites have only experienced their renaissance with the appearance of various
                    services and programming solutions that allowed such websites to include dynamic
                    contents.</p>
                <p>Modern static websites are no longer coded manually, but are instead generated by
                    employing static website generators. Nowadays, the selection of such generators
                    is extremely broad. One of the most popular is Jekyll,<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn4" n="3">
                        <hi rend="italic">Jekyll • Simple, blog-aware, static sites</hi>, accessed
                        April 15, 2019, <ref target="https://jekyllrb.com/"
                            >https://jekyllrb.com/</ref>.</note> which is also used in the creation
                    of GitHub pages. Thus its use has also spread to humanities (<ref
                        target="#Visconti.2016">Visconti 2016</ref>). Static website generators
                    assume that the users will write the contents using text formatting syntax like
                    Markdown markup language, which is very popular among developers.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn5" n="4">
                        <hi rend="italic">Daring Fireball: Markdown</hi>, accessed April 15, 2019,
                            <ref target="https://daringfireball.net/projects/markdown/"
                            >https://daringfireball.net/projects/markdown/</ref>.</note> These
                    formats can then be converted to HTML sites with a website generator and then
                    published online. However, the Markdown syntax is very deficient and only allows
                    for basic content publishing. As such, it is inappropriate for the tagging of
                    complex humanities texts. Consequently, humanities texts are most often encoded
                    with Extensible Markup Language (XML). Furthermore, XSLT (Extensible Stylesheet
                    Language for Transformation) is used as a tool for XML conversion. Together,
                    these are the key technologies employed by digital humanities (<ref
                        target="#Flanders.2016">Flanders et al. 2016</ref>). As the use of XSLT
                    transformations is often very similar to static site generator conversions, we
                    can describe XSLT as a “modern, efficient static site generator” as well (<ref
                        target="#Kraetke.2016">Kraetke and Imsieke 2016</ref>).</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>SIstory TEI Profile</head>
                <p>For many years, the TEI Consortium has been regularly maintaining and updating
                    the XSL Stylesheets, which can be used to generate, on the basis of TEI
                    documents, not only (X)HTML websites, but also many other formats, including
                    LaTeX, XSL-FO, EPUB, DOCX, and ODT. These XSL stylesheets are freely available
                    from the GitHub repository and regularly updated in accordance with the new
                    versions of the TEI Guidelines.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn6" n="5">
                        <hi rend="italic">TEI XSL Stylesheets</hi>, accessed April 15, 2019, <ref
                            target="https://github.com/TEIC/Stylesheets"
                            >https://github.com/TEIC/Stylesheets</ref>.</note> Not only is the
                    relevant written documentation very good, but the programming code comments are
                    exemplary as well. XSLT stylesheets are also used, among other things, to
                    generate the static website for each version of the TEI Guidelines.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn7" n="6">“P5: Guidelines for Electronic Text
                        Encoding and Interchange,” <hi rend="italic">TEI: Text Encoding
                            Initiative</hi>, accessed April 15, 2019, <ref
                            target="https://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/index.html"
                            >https://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/index.html</ref>.</note>
                </p>
                <p>Most importantly, by means of custom profiles, the XSLT stylesheets of the TEI
                    Consortium allow for very flexible adaptations to different project
                    requirements. In fact, the XSL Stylesheets for TEI have been written with the
                    intention of being as adaptable as possible. Numerous parameters exist that can
                    be configured according to preferences. The stylesheets contains many variables
                    and templates, which can be adapted to specific requirements. The authors of the
                    code even thought of empty (hook) templates, to which custom contents and XSLT
                    programming code may be added. I have made use of all these options when writing
                    the SIstory profile for the XSLT stylesheets of the TEI Consortium. (<ref
                        target="#Pančur.2019a">Pančur 2019a</ref>)</p>
                <p>Initially, I based the creation of these profiles on the needs of the Research
                    Infrastructure of Slovenian Historiography for flexible and prompt publication
                    of our technical documentation online. In the context of the Research
                    Infrastructure, my colleagues and I are managing the History of Slovenia –
                    SIstory portal, which also contains a repository and digital library. Therefore
                    we have decided to include these digital editions into the existing
                    infrastructure as intensively as possible. Until 2016, the static websites of
                    these digital editions had been stored on an additional www2 server of the
                    SIstory portal,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn8" n="7">
                        <hi rend="italic">www2.SIstory.si</hi>, accessed April 15, 2019, <ref
                            target="http://www2.sistory.si/">http://www2.sistory.si/</ref>.</note>
                    while the digital library itself had only stored the metadata about the digital
                    editions and links to these static sites. After the upgrade of the SIstory
                    portal in 2016, we could start storing the HTML and all other files related to
                    these digital editions directly in the repository and the digital library.</p>
                <p>Due to the desire to maximize the integration of digital editions into the
                    SIstory portal, I also tried to bring the external appearance of digital
                    editions as close as possible to the user interface of the portal. As an
                    example, <ref target="#figure1">Figure 1</ref> shows a snapshot of the home page
                    of the portal between the years 2012 and 2016, and in <ref target="#figure2"
                        >Figure 2</ref>, the user interface of the digital edition of 2014.</p>
                <figure xml:id="figure1">
                    <head>Figure 1: Home page of the History of Slovenia – SIstory portal of
                        2016</head>
                    <graphic url="figure_1.jpg" height="500px"/>
                    <p>Source: Spletni arhiv Narodne in univerzitetne knjižnice, accessed April 10,
                        2018, <ref
                            target="http://nukrobi2.nuk.uni-lj.si:8080/wayback/20160225143401/http://www.sistory.si/"
                            >http://nukrobi2.nuk.uni-lj.si:8080/wayback/20160225143401/http://www.sistory.si/</ref>.</p>
                </figure>
                <figure xml:id="figure2">
                    <head>Figure 2: The 2014 digital edition user interface</head>
                    <graphic url="figure_2.jpg" height="500px"/>
                    <p>Source: (<ref target="#Gašparič.2014">Gašparič 2014</ref>), accessed April
                        10, 2018, <ref
                            target="http://www2.sistory.si/publikacije/monografije/Gasparic_Parlamentaria1/ch01.html"
                            >http://www2.sistory.si/publikacije/monografije/Gasparic_Parlamentaria1/ch01.html</ref>.</p>
                </figure>
                <p>Even though the colour scheme is identical and the layout of the logo, the search
                    bar, main top navigation menu, and the contents are very closely modelled after
                    the SIstory portal, the user interfaces are nevertheless not the same. At the
                    time, the user interface of the portal was still based on the old HTML 4
                    technology, but I had already started to use responsive website design and HTML
                    5 for the digital editions. In this regard, I decided to use the responsive
                    front-end framework ZURB Foundation.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn9" n="8">
                        <hi rend="italic">Foundation: The most advanced responsive front-end
                            framework in the world</hi>, accessed April 15, 2019, <ref
                            target="https://foundation.zurb.com/"
                        >https://foundation.zurb.com/</ref>.</note> I keep my adaptations as well as
                    CSS and JS additions in the GitHub repository. (<ref target="#Pančur.2019b"
                        >Pančur 2019b</ref>) As the use of this framework turned out to be extremely
                    useful, we also included it in the new SIstory portal in 2016. Subsequently I
                    also adapted the appearance of the digital editions to the new portal design
                    (compare <ref target="#figure3">Figures 3</ref> and <ref target="#figure4"
                        >4</ref>).</p>
                <figure xml:id="figure3">
                    <head>Figure 3: Top navigation menu, search bar, and metadata page of the
                        SIstory portal</head>
                    <graphic url="figure_3.jpg" height="500px"/>
                    <p>Source: (<ref target="#Pančur.2016">Pančur 2016</ref>).</p>
                </figure>
                <figure xml:id="figure4">
                    <head>Figure 4: The 2016 digital edition user interface</head>
                    <graphic url="figure_4.jpg" height="500px"/>
                    <p>Source: (<ref target="#Pančur.2016">Pančur 2016</ref>), accessed April 15,
                        2019, <ref
                            target="http://www.sistory.si/cdn/publikacije/36001-37000/36294/ch10.html"
                            >http://www.sistory.si/cdn/publikacije/36001-37000/36294/ch10.html</ref>.</p>
                </figure>
                <p>Apart from the originally envisioned technical documentation, we soon also
                    started to publish other sorts of publications – in particular monographs,
                    collections of scientific texts, and magazines – online in the HTML format.
                    Therefore I reconfigured the SIstory TEI profile with the aim of facilitating
                    the publication of these sorts of digital editions. The profile allows for the
                    transformations of:</p>
                <list type="unordered">
                    <item>individual TEI documents;</item>
                    <item>several TEI documents from a shared TEI corpus. In this case, each TEI
                        document needs to be converted separately. The TEI corpus itself and its
                            <gi>teiHeader</gi> need to be converted separately, as in this manner a
                        common cover, colophon, and tables of contents are generated.</item>
                </list>
                <p>The digital edition's main navigation menu is located at the very top of the web
                    page, as horizontal navigation with a drop-down menu. The structure of this
                    navigation reflects the structure, sections, and divisions of the individual TEI
                    documents. In the continuation I will briefly outline the possible content
                    sections of the navigation as well as the TEI document. In practice, no TEI
                    document contains every single one of these sections. Instead, the authors of
                    TEI documents can use and arrange them completely in accordance with their
                    needs.</p>
                <p>The central part of the content is always contained within the <gi>body</gi>
                    element. The main content must be contained within a single or several
                        <gi>div</gi> elements with the obligatory attribute <att>xml:id</att>. Each
                        <gi>div</gi> element represents its own division of the content or chapter.
                    Therefore the navigation bar's single drop-down menu displays all of the
                        <gi>div</gi> divisions contained within the <gi>body</gi> element. A variety
                    of contents, encoded in the relevant TEI document within the <gi>front</gi> and
                        <gi>back</gi> elements, may also be accessible before and after this part of
                    the drop-down menu. <ref target="#figure5">Figure 5</ref> thus illustrates all
                    of these main content sections.</p>
                <figure xml:id="figure5">
                    <head>Figure 5: The main content sections of a TEI document</head>
                    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                        <text>
                            <front>
                                <titlePage>
                                    <docTitle>
                                        <titlePart>Title of digial edition</titlePart>
                                    </docTitle>
                                    <docAuthor>Author of digital edition</docAuthor>
                                    <docEdition>Document edition</docEdition>
                                    <docImprint>
                                        <pubPlace>Publication place</pubPlace>
                                        <docDate>Publication date</docDate>
                                    </docImprint>
                                    <graphic url="url_of_cover_page_image.jpg"/>
                                </titlePage>
                                <div type="preface" xml:id="prf-01">
                                    <!-- Introductory chapter -->
                                </div>
                            </front>
                            <body>
                                <div type="chapter" xml:id="ch01">
                                    <!-- Chapter with main content -->
                                </div>
                            </body>
                            <back>
                                <div type="bibliogr" xml:id="bibl01">
                                    <!-- Bibliography -->
                                </div>
                                <div type="appendix" xml:id="app01">
                                    <!-- Appendix -->
                                </div>
                                <div type="summary" xml:id="sum01">
                                    <!-- Summary -->
                                </div>
                            </back>
                        </text>
                    </egXML>
                </figure>
                <p>Only <gi>titlePage</gi> is obligatory, because it is converted to the default
                    start page (index.html) and, as such, accessible through the navigation bar – at
                    the very top, as the Title Page. The <gi>front</gi> element may contain one or
                    several <gi>div</gi> elements, which represent the introductory chapters section
                    in the navigation. The <gi>back</gi> element includes three possible content
                    sections (bibliographies, annexes, summaries), which is why they must always be
                    assigned the appropriate <att>type</att> attribute. Each of these sections can
                    consist of one or more chapters. In most cases, the conversion of the content of
                    these divisions is based on the standard XSLT stylesheets of the TEI Consortium,
                    which I have only partly adapted to the needs of our own digital editions. I
                    have written the transformations for the generated <gi>divGen</gi> divisions
                    from scratch. All of them have been included in the SIstory TEI profile. These
                    generated divisions can be included in the <gi>front</gi> (<ref
                        target="#figure6">Figure 6</ref>) or the <gi>back</gi> element (<ref
                        target="#figure7">Figure 7</ref>), and each of the <gi>divGen</gi> elements
                    must include a <gi>head</gi> with an arbitrary division title. These titles are
                    then included in the digital edition's navigation.</p>
                <figure xml:id="figure6">
                    <head>Figure 6: The list of all possible generated <gi>divGen</gi> divisions,
                        contained in the <gi>front</gi> element</head>
                    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                        <front>
                            <divGen type="cip" xml:id="cip">
                                <head>Colophon</head>
                            </divGen>
                            <divGen type="teiHeader" xml:id="teiHeader">
                                <head>TEI header</head>
                            </divGen>
                            <divGen type="toc" xml:id="id-toc">
                                <head>Table of contents</head>
                            </divGen>
                            <divGen type="toc" xml:id="id-images">
                                <head>List of images</head>
                            </divGen>
                            <divGen type="toc" xml:id="id-charts">
                                <head>List of charts</head>
                            </divGen>
                            <divGen type="toc" xml:id="id-tables">
                                <head>List of tables</head>
                            </divGen>
                            <divGen type="toc" xml:id="id-titleAuthor">
                                <head>Table of contents where the name 
                                    of the author is also displayed</head>
                            </divGen>
                            <divGen type="toc" xml:id="id-titleType">
                                <head>Simplified table of contents</head>
                            </divGen>
                            <divGen type="search" xml:id="search">
                                <head>Search</head>
                            </divGen>
                        </front>
                    </egXML>
                </figure>
                <p>Unlike the aforementioned <gi>div</gi> elements, where the use of
                        <att>xml:id</att> identifiers is merely recommended (the HTML files that
                    contain these divisions are named after these identifiers), in case of generated
                    divisions they are obligatory and also have a semantic meaning that is of key
                    importance for their conversion. The <att>type</att> attribute defines the main
                    category, which is particularly highlighted in the horizontal navigation. The
                        <att>xml:id</att> attribute more precisely defines the subcategory, shown in
                    the navigation drop-down menu. The most extensive category is the Table of
                    Contents (TOC) group, which, apart from the various tables of the contents of
                    chapters and subchapters, also contains a list of tables, figures, and charts.
                    In reality, the list of charts is merely a separate group of list of figures
                        (<gi>figure</gi>), which includes figures with the <att>type</att> attribute
                    and <val>chart</val> value.</p>
                <p>The <gi>back</gi> element involves only a single category of generated divisions
                    that includes various lists of persons, places, and organisations. The generated
                    divisions include all of the persons mentioned in the TEI document, encoded with
                    the <gi>persName</gi> element, all places encoded with <gi>placeName</gi>, or
                    all organisations encoded with orgName. All of the named entities, encoded in
                    this manner, must also be assigned the <att>ref</att> attribute, in order to
                    refer to the appropriate canonical element in the list of entities
                        (<gi>listPerson</gi> for persons, <gi>listOrg</gi> for organisations, and
                        <gi>listPlace</gi> for places) in the TEI header (<gi>teiHeader</gi>). The
                        <gi>placeName</gi> element's <att>ref</att> attribute may also contain a
                    reference to the GeoNames<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn10" n="9">
                        <hi rend="italic">GeoNames</hi>, accessed April 15, 2019, <ref
                            target="http://www.geonames.org/">http://www.geonames.org/</ref>.</note>
                    or DBpedia<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn11" n="10">
                        <hi rend="italic">DBpedia</hi>, accessed April 15, 2019, <ref
                            target="http://wiki.dbpedia.org/">http://wiki.dbpedia.org/</ref>.</note>
                    URI, where the SIstory profile can process the geographical coordinates and
                    display them in the list of places.</p>
                <figure xml:id="figure7">
                    <head>Figure 7: The list of all possible elements for automatically generated
                        text division <gi>divGen</gi>, contained in the <gi>front</gi>
                        element</head>
                    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                        <back>
                            <divGen type="index" xml:id="id-persons">
                                <head>List of persons</head>
                            </divGen>
                            <divGen type="index" xml:id="id-places">
                                <head>List of places</head>
                            </divGen>
                            <divGen type="index" xml:id="id-organizations">
                                <head>List of organizations</head>
                            </divGen>
                        </back>
                    </egXML>
                </figure>
                <p>As it is also possible to use the SIstory profile to convert the TEI documents
                    from the TEI corpus, the <gi>divGen</gi> elements from the various TEI documents
                    cannot possess the same <att>xml:id</att> identifiers. Therefore the
                    subcategories of the generated divisions are specified in such a manner that the
                    subcategory's identifier is stated after the final hyphen of this identifier's
                    value (see <ref target="#figure6">Figures 6</ref> and <ref target="#figure7"
                        >7</ref>, where the <hi rend="italic">id</hi> before the hyphen in
                        <att>xml:id</att> attribute defines the arbitrary identifier, while the
                    subcategory is stated after the hyphen).</p>
                <p>The SIstory profile also allows for the display of dynamic contents. The Tipue
                    Search engine is included as a basic functionality.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn12" n="11">
                        <hi rend="italic">Tipue Search</hi>, accessed April 15, <ref
                            target="http://www.tipue.com/search/"
                        >http://www.tipue.com/search/</ref>.</note> It can be included with a
                    generated division (<gi>divGen</gi>) of the <val>search</val> type in the
                        <gi>front</gi> element. Tipue Search is an open source jQuery plugin, which
                    can be relatively easily integrated even in static sites. In the graphical user
                    interface, the search bar is located immediately below the bottom navigation,
                    while the element <gi>divGen</gi> generates a <hi rend="italic">search.html</hi>
                    web page that includes a dynamic display of search results. The content of the
                    TEI document is indexed, as a JavaScript object (JSON), in the file <hi
                        rend="italic">tipuesearch_content.js</hi>, which needs to be located in the
                    same folder as the <hi rend="italic">search.html</hi> file. Content indexation
                    takes place at the level of paragraphs (<gi>p</gi>), lists (<gi>list</gi>),
                    tables (<gi>table</gi>), figures (<gi>figure</gi>), and all other possible TEI
                    elements, which are direct child elements of the text division <gi>div</gi>.
                    Therefore, all of these elements must include a <att>xml:id</att> attribute for
                    unique identifier. Lists are the only exception: when they do not possess the
                        <att>xml:id</att> attribute, whereas their child elements do, then the
                    latter are indexed.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Configuring and Upgrading the SIstory TEI Profile</head>
                <p>Much like the main XSL Stylesheets of the TEI Consortium, the SIstory profile has
                    been created to allow for its adaptation to the requirements of any individual
                    project. To this end, it includes a few original parameters of the TEI
                    Consortium's XSLT stylesheets which affect the default stylesheet output, to
                    which I have added a few new SIstory parameters. All of these parameters can be
                    set up anew for each conversion, but it is more appropriate that new project
                    profiles be created for each individual project. The conversion usually proceeds
                    in the following manner: the project's custom profile imports the SIstory
                    profile, which, in turn, imports the TEI XSLT transformations, and adds
                    overrides (see <ref target="#figure8">Figure 8</ref>).</p>
                <figure xml:id="figure8">
                    <head>Figure 8: Chained XSLT conversions with additional profiles</head>
                    <graphic url="figure_8.jpg" height="400px"/>
                </figure>
                <p>For example, during conversion, the default SIstory profile thus expects every
                    chapter or the first <gi>div</gi> text division to become a separate HTML web
                    page. In this case, navigation through forward and back buttons is added to the
                    web pages automatically. Unlike the original TEI transformations, this
                    navigation also includes the <gi>divGen</gi> generated divisions. However, by
                    changing the <ident>splitLevel</ident> parameter (originally a parameter
                    included in the TEI conversions), it is possible to specify that subchapters
                    also become separate HTML web pages. The forward/back and up/down navigation
                    between the web pages has now been appropriately adapted. The current SIstory
                    profile only supports a depth of three text divisions.</p>
                <p>The <ident>documentationLanguage</ident> parameter may currently be used to
                    specify the Slovenian, English, or Serbian navigation (in the Latin or Cyrillic
                    script). By adding new translations to the <hi rend="italic">myi18n.xml</hi>
                    document, it is possible to further expand this localisation. The localisation
                    of the Tipue Search engine has been suitably taken care of as well.</p>
                <p>The SIstory profile also allows for the parallel display of the texts' various
                    language versions. In this case, all of the main <gi>div</gi> text divisions and
                        <gi>divGen</gi> generated divisions must contain <att>xml:lang</att>
                    attributes with the appropriate language code as well as <att>corresp</att>
                    attributes pointing at all the other language versions of the text in question
                    (see <ref target="#ftn9">Figure 9</ref>). Simultaneously, the
                        <ident>languages-locale</ident> parameter must be set to the value
                        <val>true</val>, while the <ident>languages-locale-primary</ident> parameter
                    must specify the language code of the starting <hi rend="italic">index.html</hi>
                    file.</p>
                <figure xml:id="figure9">
                    <head>Figure 9: Localization and language setting in TEI document</head>
                    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                        <body>
                            <div type="chapter" xml:id="ch01"  xml:lang="sl"
                                corresp="#en-ch01">
                                <!-- Slovenian chapter with main content -->
                            </div>
                            <div type="chapter" xml:id="en-ch01" xml:lang="en"
                                corresp="#ch01">
                                <!-- English chapter with main content -->
                            </div>
                        </body>
                    </egXML>
                </figure>
                <p>The display of the TEI document's metadata from the <gi>teiHeader</gi> element is
                    similarly adaptable. This transformation can be initially specified by including
                    the generic division (<gi>divGen</gi>), whose <att>type</att> attribute value
                    should be set to <gi>teiHeader</gi> (see <ref target="#figure6">Figure 6</ref>).
                    The entire content of the <gi>teiHeader</gi> element is converted to <gi>dl</gi>
                    (definition list HTML element), where <gi>dt</gi> (description term element)
                    defines the name of the TEI element as well as the names and attribute values
                    (element [attribute = value | attribute = value]), while <gi>dd</gi> (definition
                    description element) defines the text contents of the TEI element. Of course,
                    the definitions are appropriately nested. With additional parameters, this
                    transformation can be configured in such a way as to display the descriptive
                    names of elements and attributes in the English or Slovenian language instead of
                    their names.</p>
                <p>Apart from this simple SIstory profile configuration, any additional XSLT
                    transformation that can be completely adapted to the needs of an individual
                    digital edition can be included during the conversion of a project.
                    Simultaneously, by using various JavaScript libraries and plugins as well as web
                    applications, it is also possible to enable additional dynamic content display.
                    For example, in the case of the SIstory portal's digital editions, I have
                    successfully used DataTables<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn13" n="12">
                        <hi rend="italic">DataTables: Table plug-in for jQuery</hi>, accessed April
                        15, 2019, <ref target="https://datatables.net/"
                            >https://datatables.net/</ref>.</note> to display large quantities of
                    tabled data, Highcharts<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn14" n="13">
                        <hi rend="italic">Highcharts</hi>, accessed April 15, 2019, <ref
                            target="https://www.highcharts.com/products/highcharts/"
                            >https://www.highcharts.com/products/highcharts/</ref>. </note> for
                    charts, Google Maps for maps, and ImageViewer<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn15"
                        n="14">
                        <hi rend="italic">ImageViewer</hi>, accessed April 15, 2019, <ref
                            target="http://ignitersworld.com/lab/imageViewer.html"
                            >http://ignitersworld.com/lab/imageViewer.html</ref>.</note> and
                    Viewer.js for images.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn16" n="15"> Viewer.js,
                        JavaScript image viewer, accessed April 15, 2019, <ref
                            target="https://fengyuanchen.github.io/viewerjs/"
                            >https://fengyuanchen.github.io/viewerjs/</ref>.</note> These are merely
                    examples: there are alternatives, and every year many new possibilities
                    emerge.</p>
                <p>Simultaneously, in 2017, with the publication of Saxon-JS<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn17" n="16">“Saxon-JS,” <hi rend="italic">Saxonica</hi>, accessed
                        April 15, 2019, <ref target="http://www.saxonica.com/saxon-js/index.xml"
                            >http://www.saxonica.com/saxon-js/index.xml</ref>.</note>, the
                    possibilities of dynamically displaying the contents of XML documents in static
                    web pages have even improved. Saxon-JS is an XSLT 3.0 run-time written in pure
                    JavaScript. It could contribute to XSLT once again becoming a client-side
                    technology that works in a browser (<ref target="#Lumley.2017">Lumley et al.
                        2017</ref>). For digital editions, I have thus started to successfully use
                    an Saxon extension function <ident>ixsl:query-params</ident>, which parses the
                    query parameters of the HTML page URI. In the case of the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Kapelski pasijon</hi> (The Železna Kapla Passion Play) digital edition, I
                    have thus created and used the following parameters to generate a dynamic
                    parallel display of facsimiles as well as the diplomatic and critical
                    transcription: <ident>type</ident>, <ident>mode</ident>, <ident>page</ident>,
                    and <ident>lb</ident> (line break). These parameters have allowed me to
                    construct a dynamic display of extremely complex contents (<ref
                        target="#figure10">Figure 10</ref>), which can still be optionally upgraded
                    in the future digital editions.</p>
                <figure xml:id="figure10">
                    <head>Figure 10: The simultaneous display of facsimiles, diplomatic
                        transcription, and critical transcription of the <hi rend="italic">Kapelski
                            pasijon</hi> passion play.</head>
                    <graphic url="figure_10.jpg" height="600px"/>
                    <p>Source: Kapelski pasijon, GitHub pages, <ref
                            target="https://dariah-si.github.io/Kapelski-pub/"
                            >https://dariah-si.github.io/Kapelski-pub/</ref></p>
                </figure>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Publishing Digital Editions</head>
                <p>The default SIstory profile transformation generates all the HTML, JS, and any
                    other files in a single folder. As the digital editions generated in this manner
                    consist solely of static web pages, they can also be used on personal computers.
                    In this manner it is possible to effectively test the digital editions even
                    before publishing them online, where we can swiftly and simply publish them on
                    any accessible servers. Additionally, the GitHub repository web pages are a free
                    option that can also ensure an efficient version control.</p>
                <p>However, the main purpose of SIstory profiles is to include digital editions
                    directly into the SIstory portal's repository and its digital library. Thus we
                    can efficiently store all of the digital editions' files by adding persistent
                    Handle System identifiers and checksums for all the relevant files, as well as
                    flexibly organise digital editions as one or several digital objects with one or
                    several intellectual entities. Each intellectual entity has its own Handle
                    identifier and metadata. It can include several files or none at all. The files
                    belonging to an individual intellectual entity are located in the same folder.
                    The path to this folder also includes the suffix of the Handle persistent
                    identifier, which is, in the case of the SIstory portal, always a numerical
                    value (e.g., for the suffix 555, the relative path would be <hi rend="italic"
                        >/cdn/publikacije/1-1000/555/file</hi>). Therefore, the SIstory XSLT profile
                    must know the values of these identifiers in advance. Thus we can precisely
                    determine, even in advance, whether the entire contents of a digital edition
                    should be contained in a single intellectual entity of the SIstory portal, or
                    whether various digital edition files should be included in various intellectual
                    entities. These identifiers can be recorded among the rest of the metadata in
                        <gi>teiHeader</gi>, within the <gi>publicationStmt</gi> element, as a value
                    of one or more <gi>idno</gi> elements. This element requires that the value of
                    the <att>type</att> attribute be specified as <val>sistory</val> or
                        <val>si4</val>, while the <att>corresp</att> attribute should point at all
                    the appropriate <gi>div</gi> and <gi>divGen</gi> divisions whose content will be
                    included in the intellectual entity with this identifier.</p>
                <p>The SIstory XSLT profile is open source and available in the GitHub repository.
                        (<ref target="#Pančur.2019a">Pančur 2019a</ref>) Another GitHub repository
                    also contains all of the digital editions currently kept on the SIstory portal.
                    The project upgrades of the SIstory XSLT profile for each of these editions are
                    available as well. (<ref target="#Pančur.2018">Pančur 2018</ref>) I regularly
                    expand and maintain the SIstory profile in accordance with the changes of the
                    TEI XSLT stylesheets.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Conclusion</head>
                <p>There are several advantages to a digital editions infrastructure organised in
                    this manner:</p>
                <list type="unordered">
                    <item>using format that is most common in digital humanities: TEI XML (Neuefeind
                        2019, 221);</item>
                    <item>using a single XML technology (XSLT) for various sorts of digital
                        editions, which enjoys a wide support in the TEI community;</item>
                    <item>the possibility of simply including JavaScript libraries and
                        plugins;</item>
                    <item>flexibly adding dynamic contents with Saxon-JS;</item>
                    <item>in comparison with other technologies (dynamic sites), static sites ensure
                        a relative sustainability and simple maintenance of digital editions;</item>
                    <item>using Git version control to store the various versions of digital
                        editions together with the software used to generate static websites;</item>
                    <item>open access to the complete digital editions code in the GitHub and GitLab
                        software development platforms; </item>
                    <item>the possibility of sharing digital editions on the GitHub Pages and GitLab
                        Pages, and, last but not least, the possibility of including them in the
                        History of Slovenia – SIstory portal.</item>
                </list>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Acknowledgements</head>
                <p>The work presented in this paper was supported by the Slovenian historiography
                    research infrastructure (I0- 0013), and the Slovenian ESFRI infrastructures
                    DARIAH- SI which are financially supported by the Slovenian Research Agency.</p>
            </div>

        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="bibliography">
                <head>Sources and Literature</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Datasets and Academic Software:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="Pančur.2018">Pančur, Andrej. 2018. <hi rend="italic">Electronic
                            publishing on SIstory.</hi> Distributed by GitHub. <ref
                            target="https://github.com/SIstory/publications"
                            >https://github.com/SIstory/publications</ref>.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="Pančur.2019a">Pančur, Andrej. 2019a. <hi rend="italic">SIstory TEI
                            Stylesheets.</hi> Distributed by GitHub. <ref
                            target="https://github.com/SIstory/Stylesheets"
                            >https://github.com/SIstory/Stylesheets</ref>.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="Pančur.2019b">Pančur, Andrej. 2019b. <hi rend="italic">SIstory:
                            additional CSS and JS.</hi> Distributed by GitHub. <ref
                            target="https://github.com/SIstory/themes"
                            >https://github.com/SIstory/themes</ref>.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Literature:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="Andorfer.2016">Andorfer, Peter, Matej Ďurčo, Thomas Stäcker,
                        Christian Thomas, Vera Hildenbrandt, Hubert Stigler, Sibylle Söring, and
                        Lukas Rosenthaler. 2016. “Nachhaltigkeit technischer Lösungen für digitale
                        Editionen: Eine kritische Evaluation bestehender Frameworks und Workflows
                        von und für Praktiker_innen.” In <hi rend="italic">DHd 2016: Modellierung –
                            Vernetzung – Visualisierun: Die Digital Humanities als
                            fächerübergreifendes Forschungsparadigma: Konferenzabstracts</hi>,
                        36–39. Universität Leipzig. <ref target="http://www.dhd2016.de/"
                            >http://www.dhd2016.de/</ref>.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="Andrews.2016">Andrews, Tara, and Joris van Zundert. 2016. “What
                        Are You Trying to Say? The Interface as an Integral Element of Argument.” In
                            <hi rend="italic">Digital Scholarly Editions as Interfaces,
                            International Symposium at the University of Graz, Austria</hi>, 31–32.
                        Graz: Centre for Information Modelling – Austrian Centre for Digital
                        Humanities. <ref
                            target="https://static.uni-graz.at/fileadmin/gewi-zentren/Informationsmodellierung/PDF/dse-interfaces_BoA21092016.pdf"
                            >https://static.uni-graz.at/fileadmin/gewi-zentren/Informationsmodellierung/PDF/dse-interfaces_BoA21092016.pdf</ref>.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="Daengeli.2017">Daengeli, Peter, and Simon Zumsteg. 2017. “Hermann
                        Burgers Lokalbericht: Hybrid-Edition mit digitalem Schwerpunkt.” In <hi
                            rend="italic">DHd 2017: Digitale Nachhaltigkeit:
                        Konferenzabstracts</hi>, 151–55. Universität Bern. <ref
                            target="http://www.dhd2017.ch/">http://www.dhd2017.ch/</ref>.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="DHd-AG.2017">DHd-AG Datenzentren. 2017. <hi rend="italic"
                            >Geisteswissenschaftliche Datenzentren im deutschsprachigen Raum:
                            Grundsatzpapier zur Sicherung der langfristigen Verfügbarkeit von
                            Forschungsdaten.</hi> Hamburg. DOI: 10.5281/zenodo.1134760.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="Erjavec.2011">Erjavec, Tomaž, Jan Jona Javoršek, Matija Ogrin, and
                        Petra Vide Ogrin. 2011. “Od biografskega leksikona do znanstvenokritične
                        izdaje: vprašanje trajnosti elektronskih besedil.” <hi rend="italic"
                            >Knjižnica</hi> 55, No. 1: 103–14. <ref
                            target="https://knjiznica.zbds-zveza.si/knjiznica/article/view/6004"
                            >https://knjiznica.zbds-zveza.si/knjiznica/article/view/6004</ref>.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="Diaz.2018">Diaz, Chris. 2018. “Using Static Site Generators for
                        Scholarly Publications and Open Educational Resources.” <hi rend="italic"
                            >Code4Lib Journal</hi>, No. 44. <ref
                            target="https://journal.code4lib.org/articles/1386"
                            >https://journal.code4lib.org/articles/1386</ref>.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="Fechner.2018">Fechner, Martin. 2018. “Eine nachhaltige
                        Präsentationsschicht für digitale Editionen.” In <hi rend="italic">DHd 2018:
                            Kritik der digitalen Vernunft: Konferenzabstracts</hi>, edited by Georg
                        Vogeler, 203–7. Universität zu Köln. <ref
                            target="http://dhd2018.uni-koeln.de/"
                        >http://dhd2018.uni-koeln.de/</ref>.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="Flanders.2016">Flanders, Julia, Syd Bauman, and Sarah Connell.
                        2016. “XSLT: Transforming our XML data.” In <hi rend="italic">Doing Digital
                            Humanities: Practice, Training, Research</hi>, edited by C. Crompton, R.
                        J. Lane and R. Siemens, 255–72. Oxon and New York: Routledge.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="Gašparič.2014">Gašparič, Jure. 2014. <hi rend="italic">Slovenski
                            parlament: Politično zgodovinski pregled od začetka prvega do konca
                            šestega mandata (1992-2014).</hi> Ljubljana: Inštitut za novejšo
                        zgodovino. <ref target="http://hdl.handle.net/11686/26950"
                            >http://hdl.handle.net/11686/26950</ref>.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="Kraetke.2016">Kraetke, Martin, and Gerrit Imsieke. 2016. “XSLT as
                        a Modern, Powerful Static Website Generator: Publishing Hogrefe's Clinical
                        Handbook of Psychotropic Drugs as a Web App.” In <hi rend="italic"
                            >Proceedings of XML in, Web Out: International Symposium on sub rosa
                            XML</hi>, Balisage Series on Markup Technologies, vol. 18. <ref
                            target="https://doi.org/10.4242/BalisageVol18.Kraetke02"
                            >https://doi.org/10.4242/BalisageVol18.Kraetke02</ref>.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="Lumley.2017">Lumley, John, Debbie Lockett, and Michael Kay. 2017.
                        “Compiling XSLT3, in the browser, in itself.” In <hi rend="italic"
                            >Proceedings of Balisage: The Markup Conference 2017</hi>, Balisage
                        Series on Markup Technologies, vol. 19. <ref
                            target="https://doi.org/10.4242/BalisageVol19.Lumley01"
                            >https://doi.org/10.4242/BalisageVol19.Lumley01</ref>.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="Moeller.2018">Moeller, Katrin, Matej Ďurčo, Barbara Ebert, Marina
                        Lemaire, Lukas Rosenthaler, Patrick Sahle, Urlike Wuttke, and Jörg
                        Wettlaufer. 2018. Die “Summe geisteswissenschaftlicher Methoden?
                        Fachspezifisches Datenmanagement als Voraussetzung zukunftsorientierten
                        Forschens.” In <hi rend="italic">DHd 2018: Kritik der digitalen Vernunft:
                            Konferenzabstracts</hi>, edited by Georg Vogeler, 89–93. Universität zu
                        Köln. <ref target="http://dhd2018.uni-koeln.de/"
                            >http://dhd2018.uni-koeln.de/</ref>.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="Neuefeind.2019">Neuefeind, Claes, Philip Schildkamp, and Brigitte
                        Mathiak. 2019. “Technologienutzung im Kontext Digitaler Edition – eine
                        Landschaftsvermessung.” In <hi rend="italic">DHd 2019: Digital Humanities:
                            multimedial &amp; multimodal. Konferenzabstracts</hi>, 219–22.
                        Universität Mainz, Universität Frankfurt. <ref target="https://dhd2019.org/"
                            >https://dhd2019.org/</ref>.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="Ogrin.2009">Ogrin, Matija, and Tomaž Erjavec. 2009. “Ekdotika in
                        tehnologija: Elektronske znanstvenokritične izdaje slovenskega slovstva.”
                            <hi rend="italic">Jezik in slovstvo</hi> 54, No. 6 (2009): 57–72. <ref
                            target="http://www.dlib.si/?URN=URN:NBN:SI:doc-BOC8BANS"
                            >http://www.dlib.si/?URN=URN:NBN:SI:doc-BOC8BANS</ref>.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="Ogrin.2005">Ogrin, Matija, ed. 2005. <hi rend="italic">Znanstvene
                            razprave in elektronski mediji: razprave</hi>. Ljubljana: Založba ZRC,
                        ZRC SAZU. <ref target="http://nl.ijs.si/e-zrc/bib/eziss-knjiga.pdf"
                            >http://nl.ijs.si/e-zrc/bib/eziss-knjiga.pdf</ref>.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="Pančur.2016">Pančur, Andrej. 2016. “History of the Holocaust in
                        Slovenia.” In <hi rend="italic">Between the House of Habsburg and Tito: A
                            Look at the Slovenian Past</hi>, edited by Jurij Perovšek and Bojan
                        Godeša. Ljubljana: Inštitut za novejšo zgodovino. <ref
                            target="http://hdl.handle.net/11686/36294"
                            >http://hdl.handle.net/11686/36294</ref>.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="Rinaldi.2015">Rinaldi, Brian. 2015. <hi rend="italic">Static Site
                            Generators: Modern Tools for Static Website Development.</hi>
                        Sebastopol, CA: O'Reilly Media.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="Robinson.2016">Robinson, Peter. 2016. “Why Interfaces Do Not and
                        Should Not Matter for Scholarly Digital Editions.” In <hi rend="italic"
                            >Digital Scholarly Editions as Interfaces, International Symposium at
                            the University of Graz, Austria</hi>, 29–30. Centre for Information
                        Modelling – Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities. <ref
                            target="https://static.uni-graz.at/fileadmin/gewi-zentren/Informationsmodellierung/PDF/dse-interfaces_BoA21092016.pdf"
                            >https://static.uni-graz.at/fileadmin/gewizentren/Informationsmodellierung/PDF/dse-interfaces_BoA21092016.pdf</ref>.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="RosselliDelTurco.2016">Rosselli Del Turco, Roberto. 2016. “The
                        Battle We Forgot to Fight: Should We Make a Case for Digital Editions?” In
                            <hi rend="italic">Digital Scholarly Editing: Theories and
                        Practices</hi>, edited by Matthew James Driscoll and Elena Pierazzo, 19–238.
                        Cambridge: Open Book Publishers. <ref
                            target="http://dx.doi.org/10.11647/OBP.0095"
                            >http://dx.doi.org/10.11647/OBP.0095</ref>.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="Romary.2017">Romary, Laurent, Piotr Banski, Jack Bowers, Emiliano
                        Degl'innocenti, Matej Ďurčo, Roberta Giacomi, Klaus Illmayer, Adeline
                        Joffres, Fahad Khan, Mohamed Khemakhem, et al. 2017. <hi rend="italic"
                            >Report on Standardization (draft)</hi>. [Technical report] 4.2 Inria.
                            <ref target="https://hal.inria.fr/hal-01560563"
                            >https://hal.inria.fr/hal-01560563</ref>.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="Schaffner.2014">Schaffner, Jennifer and Ricky Erway. 2014. <hi
                            rend="italic">Does Every Research Library Need a Digital Humanities
                            Center?</hi> Dublin, Ohio: OCLC Research. <ref
                            target="https://www.oclc.org/content/dam/research/publications/library/2014/oclcresearch-digital-humanities-center-2014.pdf"
                            >https://www.oclc.org/content/dam/research/publications/library/2014/oclcresearch-digital-humanities-center-2014.pdf</ref>.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="TEIConsortium.2019">TEI Consortium, ed. 2019. <hi rend="italic"
                            >TEI P5: Guidelines for Electronic Text Encoding and Interchange
                            3.5.0.</hi> TEI Consortium. <ref
                            target="http://www.tei-c.org/Guidelines/P5/"
                            >http://www.tei-c.org/Guidelines/P5/</ref>.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="Turska.2016">Turska, Magdalena, James Cummings, and Sebastian
                        Rahtz. 2016. “Challenging the Myth of Presentation in Digital Editions.” <hi
                            rend="italic">Journal of the Text Encoding Initiative</hi>, No. 9. DOI:
                        10.4000/jtei.1453.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="Viglianti.2017">Viglianti, Raffaele. 2017. “Your own
                        Shelley-Godwin Archive: An off-line strategy for an on-line publication
                        (poster).” In <hi rend="italic">TEI 2017 Victoria</hi>. <ref
                            target="https://hcmc.uvic.ca/tei2017/abstracts/t_126_viglianti_shelleygodwin.html"
                            >https://hcmc.uvic.ca/tei2017/abstracts/t_126_viglianti_shelleygodwin.html</ref>.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="Visconti.2016">Visconti, Amanda. 2016. “Building a static website
                        with Jekyll and GitHub Pages.” <hi rend="italic">The Programming Historian,
                            5</hi>. <ref
                            target="https://programminghistorian.org/lessons/building-static-sites-with-jekyll-github-pages"
                            >https://programminghistorian.org/lessons/building-static-sites-with-jekyll-github-pages</ref>.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="Williams.2019">Williams, Martin. 2019. <hi rend="italic">Web
                            Development Trends 2019</hi> (blog). March 14, 2019. Accessed April 12,
                        2019. <ref target="https://www.keycdn.com/blog/web-development-trends-2019"
                            >https://www.keycdn.com/blog/web-development-trends-2019</ref>.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
            <div type="summary">
                <docAuthor>Andrej Pančur</docAuthor>
                <head>SUSTAINABILITY OF DIGITAL EDITIONS: STATIC WEBSITES OF THE HISTORY OF SLOVENIA
                    – SISTORY PORTAL</head>
                <head rend="subheader">SUMMARY</head>
                <p>The contribution is based on the position that, with regard to digital editions,
                    the highest possible degree of digital sustainability of data, presentations,
                    functionalities, and programme code should be ensured. This represents a
                    significant challenge, especially in case of smaller digital humanities projects
                    with limited financing, which does not allow for the long-term maintenance of
                    technically-demanding digital editions. The alternative solutions facilitated by
                    the swift development of static web pages in the recent years are presented in
                    the contribution.</p>
                <p>Static websites enjoy numerous advantages in comparison with dynamic websites:
                    efficiency, hosting, security, maintenance, and versioning. These reasons are
                    particularly important to ensure the sustainability of digital editions. These
                    reasons, however, are less convincing in case we expect digital editions to
                    contain user-generated contents as well. Therefore, static websites are not
                    appropriate for all digital editions in the field of digital humanities. On the
                    other hand, countless digital projects do not call for very complex content and
                    its display. In such cases the existing solutions provided by static websites
                    can be more than satisfactory, especially because modern static websites do not
                    completely lack the option of adding dynamic contents. Modern static websites
                    are generated by employing static website generators. Humanities texts are most
                    often encoded with Extensible Markup Language (XML). Extensible Stylesheet
                    Language for Transformation (XSLT) is used as a tool for XML conversion: also in
                    static websites. Digital editions based on the TEI have been successfully
                    included in the SIstory portal repository as static web pages, employing basic
                    XML (XSLT) and web technologies (HTML, CSS, JavaScript). All the static web
                    pages also have the possibility of displaying dynamic content.</p>
                <p>In the case of SIstory portal, we have decided to upgrade the basic XSLT
                    Stylesheets of the TEI Consortium. In the <hi rend="italic">SIstory TEI
                        Profile</hi> chapter, I will present generic upgrade of the TEI Stylesheets.
                    In the chapter <hi rend="italic">Configuring and Upgrading the SIstory TEI
                        Profile</hi> I will outline the project-specific options for upgrading this
                    profile. In both these chapters, I will also discuss the various options of
                    adding dynamic contents to static websites. In the chapter <hi rend="italic"
                        >Publishing Digital Editions</hi> I will outline how these static websites
                    can be made available to the public, in particular by their inclusion in the
                    SIstory portal's digital repository. In the <hi rend="italic">Conclusion</hi>, I
                    will also mention a few more general findings.</p>
                <p>There are several advantages to a digital editions infrastructure organised in
                    this manner: using format that is most common in digital humanities (TEI XML);
                    using a single XML technology (XSLT) for various sorts of digital editions,
                    which enjoys a wide support in the TEI community; the possibility of simply
                    including JavaScript libraries and plugins; flexibly adding dynamic contents
                    with Saxon-JS; in comparison with other technologies (dynamic sites), static
                    sites ensure a relative sustainability and simple maintenance of digital
                    editions; using Git version control to store the various versions of digital
                    editions together with the software used to generate static websites; open
                    access to the complete digital editions code in the GitHub and GitLab software
                    development platforms; the possibility of sharing digital editions on the GitHub
                    Pages and GitLab Pages, and, last but not least, the possibility of including
                    them in the History of Slovenia – SIstory portal.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="summary">
                <docAuthor>Andrej Pančur</docAuthor>
                <head>TRAJNOST DIGITALNH IZDAJ: STATIČNE SPLETNE STRANI PORTALA ZGODOVINA SLOVENIJE
                    – SISTORY</head>
                <head rend="subheader">POVZETEK</head>
                <p>Prispevek izhaja iz stališča, da je pri digitalnih izdajah potrebno poskrbeti za
                    čim bolj celovito digitalno trajnost tako podatkov kot prezentacij,
                    funkcionalnosti in programske kode. To je velik izziv predvsem za manjše
                    digitalno humanistične projekte z omejenim financiranjem, ki ne omogoča
                    dolgoročnega vzdrževanja tehnično zahtevnih digitalnih izdaj. Kot alternativno
                    rešitev so v prispevku predstavljene rešitve, ki jih v zadnjih letih ponuja
                    hiter razvoj statičnih spletnih strani.</p>
                <p>Statične spletne strani imajo v primerjavi s dinamičnimi številne prednosti:
                    zmogljivost, gostovanje, varnost, vzdrževanje in kontrola verzij. Ti razlogi so
                    zlasti pomembni zaradi trajnosti digitalnih izdaj. Vendar so ti razlogi manj
                    prepričljivi, če glede digitalnih izdaj pričakujemo, da bodo vsebovale tudi
                    uporabniško generirano vsebino. Zato statične spletne strani niso primerne za
                    vse digitalne izdaje s področja digitalne humanistike. Po drugi strani pa je
                    zelo veliko digitalnih projektov, kjer vsebina in njen prikaz nista tako zelo
                    zahtevni. V teh primerih bi bile obstoječe rešitve, ki jih prinašajo statične
                    spletne strani, več kot zadovoljive, predvsem zaradi tega, ker moderne statične
                    strani niso povsem brez možnosti dodajanja dinamičnih vsebin. Moderne statične
                    spletne strani generiramo s pomočjo generatorjev statičnih spletnih strani.
                    Besedila v humanistiki večinoma kodiramo z XML označevalnim jezikom. XSLT pa
                    uporabljamo kot orodje za pretvorbo XML: tudi v statične spletne strain.
                    Digitalne izdaje, ki temeljijo na TEI, so s pomočjo osnovnih XML (XSLT) in
                    spletnih tehnologij (HTML, CSS, JavaScript) kot statične spletne strani uspešno
                    vključene v repozitorij portala SIstory. Vse statične spletne strani imajo tudi
                    možnost dinamičnega prikazovanja vsebine.</p>
                <p>V primeru portala SIstory smo se odločili za nadgradnjo osnovnih pretvorb XSLT
                    konzorcija TEI. V poglavju SIstory TEI profil bom predstavil svojo generično
                    nadgradnjo pretvorb XSLT konzorcija TEI. V poglavju Konfiguracija in nadgradnja
                    SIstory profila bom nato predstavil projektno specifične možnosti nadgradnje
                    tega profila. V obeh teh poglavjih bom predstavil še različne možnosti dodajanja
                    dinamične vsebine statičnim spletnim stranem. V poglavju Publiciranje digitalnih
                    izdaj bom omenil, kako te statične spletne strani damo na razpolago javnosti,
                    predvsem z vključitvijo v digitalni repozitorij portala SIstory. V Sklepu
                    naposled dodam še nekaj pomembnejših splošnih ugotovitev.</p>
                <p>Tako vzpostavljena infrastruktura za digitalne izdaje ima več prednosti: uporaba
                    podatkov, ki so v digitalni humanistiki najbolj razširjeni (TEI-XML); uporaba
                    enotne XML tehnologije (XSLT) za različne vrste digitalnih izdaj, ki ima široko
                    podoro v TEI skupnosti; možnost enostavnega vključevanja JavaScript knjižnic in
                    vtičnikov; fleksibilno dodajanje dinamične vsebine s Saxon-JS; statične spletne
                    strani zagotavljajo v primerjavi z ostalimi tehnologijami (dinamične spletne
                    strani) relativno trajnost digitalnih izdaj ter relativno enostavno vzdrževanje;
                    uporaba Git kontrole verzij za shranjevanje različnih izdaj digitalnih izdaj,
                    skupaj s programsko opremo, ki smo jo uporabili pri generiranju statičnih
                    spletnih strani; odprti dostop do celotne kode digitalnih izdaj v platformah za
                    razvoj programske opreme GitHub in GitLab; možnost gostovanja digitalnih izdaj v
                    GitHub Pages in GitLab Pages in nenazadnje možnost vključitve v portal Zgodovina
                    Slovenije – SIstory.</p>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
