<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>On the Global Impact of the Russian October Revolution of
                1917</title>
            <author>
                <name>
                    <forename>Anton</forename>
                    <surname>Bebler</surname>
                </name>
                <roleName>Professor Emeritus</roleName>
                <affiliation>Faculty of Social Sciences, University of Ljubljana</affiliation>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Kardeljeva ploščad 5</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>SI – 1000 Ljubljana</addrLine>
                </address>
                <email>anton.bebler@fdv.uni-lj.si</email>
            </author>
        </titleStmt>
        <editionStmt>
            <edition><date>2018-03-30</date></edition>
        </editionStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
                <orgName xml:lang="sl">Inštitut za novejšo zgodovino</orgName>
                <orgName xml:lang="en">Institute of Contemporary History</orgName>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Kongresni trg 1</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>SI-1000 Ljubljana</addrLine>
                </address>
            </publisher>
            <pubPlace>http://ojs.inz.si/pnz/article/view/260</pubPlace>
            <date>2018</date>
            <availability status="free">
                <licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</licence>
            </availability>
        </publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title xml:lang="sl">Prispevki za novejšo zgodovino</title>
            <title xml:lang="en">Contributions to Contemporary History</title>
            <biblScope unit="volume">58</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
            <idno type="ISSN">2463-7807</idno>
        </seriesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <p>No source, born digital.</p>
        </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc xml:lang="en">
                <p>Contributions to Contemporary History is one of the central Slovenian scientific
                    historiographic journals, dedicated to publishing articles from the field of
                    contemporary history (the 19th and 20th century).</p>
                <p>The journal is published three times per year in Slovenian and in the following
                    foreign languages: English, German, Serbian, Croatian, Bosnian, Italian, Slovak
                    and Czech. The articles are all published with abstracts in English and
                    Slovenian as well as summaries in English.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <projectDesc xml:lang="sl">
                <p>Prispevki za novejšo zgodovino je ena osrednjih slovenskih znanstvenih
                    zgodovinopisnih revij, ki objavlja teme s področja novejše zgodovine (19. in 20.
                    stoletje).</p>
                <p>Revija izide trikrat letno v slovenskem jeziku in v naslednjih tujih jezikih:
                    angleščina, nemščina, srbščina, hrvaščina, bosanščina, italijanščina, slovaščina
                    in češčina. Članki izhajajo z izvlečki v angleščini in slovenščini ter povzetki
                    v angleščini.</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="sl"/>
                <language ident="en"/>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords xml:lang="en">
                    <term>Russian Revolution</term>
                    <term>communism</term>
                    <term>Lenin</term>
                    <term>Comintern</term>
                    <term>Soviet Union</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords xml:lang="sl">
                    <term>ruska revolucija</term>
                    <term>komunizem</term>
                    <term>Lenin</term>
                    <term>kominterna</term>
                    <term>Sovjetska zveza</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change>
                    <date>2018-04-05</date>
                    <name>Neja Blaj Hribar</name>
                    <desc>Pretvorba iz DOCX v TEI, dodatno kodiranje</desc>
                </change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <docAuthor>Anton Bebler<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn1" n="*">
                    <hi rend="bold">Professor Emeritus, Faculty of Social Sciences,
                        University of Ljubljana, Kardeljeva ploščad 5, SI-1000,
                        Ljubljana, Slovenia.
                        anton.bebler@fdv.uni-lj.si</hi></note></docAuthor>
            <docImprint>
                <idno type="cobissType">Cobiss type: 1.01</idno>
                <idno type="UDC">UDC: 323.272(47)"1917":327(100)”1918/2018”</idno>
            </docImprint>
            <div type="abstract" xml:lang="sl">
                <head>IZVLEČEK</head>
                <head>O GLOBALNEM UČINKU RUSKE OKTOBRSKE REVOLUCIJE IZ LETA 1917</head>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Ruska Oktobrska revolucija leta 1917 je pretresla politični red v
                    Evropi, povzročila pomembne geopolitične spremembe na dveh celinah in več
                    desetletij bolj ali manj intenzivno vplivala na politiko na šestih celinah.
                    Vendar pa ji ni uspelo uresničiti najpomembnejšega razglašenega strateškega
                    cilja – uničiti in ukiniti svetovni kapitalizem. Poleg tega je v lastni državi
                    in večini Evrope postala diskreditirana, kar pa se ni zgodilo v številnih
                    neevropskih državah, zlasti v Aziji.</hi>
                </p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Ključne besede: ruska revolucija, komunizem, Lenin, kominterna,
                    Sovjetska zveza</hi></p>
            </div>
            <div type="abstract">
                <head>ABSTRACT</head>
                <p><hi rend="italic">The 1917 Russian October Revolution upset the political order in Europe, causing a significant geopolitical change on two continents and exerting various degrees of influence on the politics on six continents for several decades. However, the Revolution failed in its primary declared strategic objective – to destroy and abolish world capitalism. Moreover, it became discredited in its own country of origin and in most of Europe – much more than in many non-European countries, particularly Asia. </hi></p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Keywords: Russian Revolution, communism, Lenin, Comintern, Soviet
                    Union</hi></p>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <p>The Great Russian Revolution of 1917, popularly called the October Revolution, was
                preceded by the short-lived February Revolution. The latter brought about the
                replacement of the imperial government, the abdication of the head of one of the
                oldest European monarchies, and the introduction of a dual rule of the “Provisional
                Committee of the State Duma” (provisioned government) and of the “Soviets of
                Workers’ and Soldiers’ Deputies”. In the following months the Provisional government
                lost control of the capital and its military garrison. The state takeover was
                declared by the Military Revolutionary Committee of the Petrograd Soviet, at 10 in
                the morning on 25 October 1917. By then, Prime and Defense Minister A. Kerensky had
                already escaped from the besieged Winter Palace in a car provided by the US Embassy,
                masquerading as a Serbian officer. The unopposed arrest of most ministers of the
                already powerless Provisional government took place in the following night, on 26
                October, at 2:30 a.m. It was actually a rather unimportant episode accompanied by a
                mob looting the Winter Palace.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn2" n="1"> Richard Pipes, <hi rend="italic">The Russian
                            Revolution</hi> (New York: Alfred Knopf, 1991), 489-99.</note> The
                blank salvo from the cruiser Aurora and the storming of the Winter Palace were later
                magnified by the Bolshevik propaganda into the symbols of the glorious October
                Revolution. </p>
            <p>Led by the Russian left-wing social democrats (the Bolsheviks), the barely successful
                October Revolution called for the termination of World War I with a “just and
                democratic peace” without any annexations and reparations; for the complete
                abolition of world capitalism and imperialism; as well as for its replacement with
                the dictatorship of proletariat in the classless societies of the world federation
                of Soviet republics. According to the Bolsheviks, this was to be a step towards the
                abolition of the state as such.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn3" n="2"> Vladimir
                        J. Lenin, <hi rend="italic">Država in revolucija in drugi spisi iz l.
                            1917</hi> (Ljubljana: Studia Humanitatis, 2017), 38‒49,
                    169‒76.</note> The October Revolution also contained a strong antireligious
                and anticlerical component.</p>
            <p>The Russian October Revolution could not put a stop to the savagery of World War I –
                in fact it even prolonged it, possibly by several months. The breakdown of the
                Imperial Russian Army and the conclusion of the hugely rewarding and separate peace
                treaty with the Soviet Russia in March 1918 allowed Germany and Austro-Hungary to
                continue fighting until November 1918. In the following decades, the Russian
                Revolution upset the existing political order in Europe. This order had been already
                badly destabilised by the ravages of World War I, soon to be followed by the
                abolition of three more empires (Austro-Hungarian, German, and Ottoman). The impact
                of the Russian Revolution on the world was significant: it influenced it in a myriad
                of ways and with varying intensities on six continents. It generated a deep
                ideological and political conflict between the new communist state and other powers
                whose troops invaded the territory of the defunct Russian Empire in 1918. This
                conflict contributed to the outbreak of World War II, during which the Soviet Union
                fought in a temporary alliance with the liberal “Western” powers. After 1945 the
                same conflict re-emerged and constituted the declared key ingredient of the “Cold
                War” between the liberal “West” and the communist “East”. However, the subsequent
                resumption of the conflicting relations between the “West” and post-Soviet Russia
                reveals that the main component of the ideological clash between liberalism and
                communism actually disguised its basic component: the struggle for power, influence,
                and domination, essentially between the Americans and the Russians. </p>
            <p>The Russian Revolution has tangibly influenced the course of human history in the
                20th century as well as contributed to considerable changes on the political map of
                two continents – Europe and Asia. The most immediate impact of the Russian
                Revolution was expressed (1) by the geographic expansion of Soviet or Soviet-like
                political, economic and social systems imposed on other countries by the Russian
                Bolsheviks and later by the Soviet communists. The Russian Revolution also exerted
                (2) a notable political, ideological, as well as cultural influence on other
                countries on all continents. The Russian example served as (3) an inspiration in a
                number of countries where the local communists managed to take over the power in the
                state predominantly or exclusively through their own efforts. Having declared the
                people's right to self-determination, the Russian Revolution strongly challenged
                imperialism and national oppression in a number of multinational states, including
                those in Europe. Its proclamations echoed in the colonies as well as in the
                semi-colonial dependencies of the European powers on other continents, notably in
                India, China, and Vietnam. Lenin’s proclaimed slogan of people’s self-determination
                preceded Woodrow Wilson’s Fourteen Points by several months and was more
                far-reaching and universal – applicable to the colonies and semi-colonies of the
                “Western” powers as well. </p>
            <p>Unlike in Petrograd, the takeovers in Moscow and in other parts of the already
                disintegrated Empire took much longer and were more difficult and bloody. The armed
                continuation of the October Revolution was concluded in 1921 with the termination of
                the Russian Civil War. Having defeated their armed opponents in Russia (Yudenich,
                Denikin, Kolchak, Wrangel et. al.), the Bolsheviks succeeded in imposing – by the
                Red Army – the Soviet system on most of the former territory of the Russian Empire
                and in reintegrating Ukraine, Transcaucasia, Central Asia, and the Far East into a
                huge multinational state. The Russian Bolsheviks were more successful in this effort
                than the elites of the two other multinational empires – the Austro-Hungarian and
                the Ottoman. However, they did fail in several other territories formerly ruled by
                the Russians, which allowed for the restoration of Poland’s independence and for the
                creation of new independent states in Finland, Estonia, Latvia, and Lithuania. In
                1919, the attempts at revolutions, inspired by the Russian October, were crushed in
                Germany, Hungary, and Slovakia. Several other communist revolts elsewhere in Europe
                (including in Yugoslavia in 1929) also failed. In the 1920s, the Soviet system
                expanded, by means of military force, in Asia – to two peripheral Chinese
                territories bordering on the Soviet Union: Tuwa and Mongolia. Tuwa was later annexed
                by the Soviet Union, while the People’s Republic of Mongolia became formally an
                independent, later internationally recognised state and a member of Organisation of
                the United Nations.</p>
            <p>In the 1920s and 1930s, the ideas and slogans of the Russian Revolution generated a
                considerable political impact in the war-ravaged Europe. Its messages of peace,
                social justice, equality, and of peoples’ self-determination had attracted and
                motivated many leftists on all continents. On the other hand, the Bolshevik victory
                indirectly contributed to internal divisions in the socialist and social-democratic
                parties, which used to belong to the dissolved Second Socialist International. In
                many European countries, communist parties sprung from their left wings. </p>
            <p>In the 1920s – 1930s, the strongest communist parties in Europe outside the Soviet
                Union developed in Germany, France and Spain; and after World War II also in Italy.
                However, none of them were able to stage a communist revolution on their own or to
                take over the power through elections. On the other side of the political spectrum,
                the October Revolution provoked strong anti-communist reactions in the rest of
                Europe and in Northern America. It affected a number of mainstream political
                parties, the extreme right, and the established churches, particularly the Roman
                Catholic Church. Russian Bolshevism and the Soviets of workers influenced the
                development of the German system of <hi rend="italic">Mitbestimmung</hi> and the
                ideology of the German National Socialist Workers’ Party (NSDAP). Moreover, the fear
                of communism contributed significantly to the emergence of several varieties of
                European fascism, including Catholic clero-fascism. </p>
            <p>For about a quarter of a century, the Third (Communist) International (Comintern) was
                the main instrument for spreading the universal message of the Russian Revolution
                and communist ideology worldwide. This was intended to be the central organisation
                of the global communist movement, a unified international party with national
                communist parties as “sections”, led from the centre in Moscow. Established in March
                1919 at its first congress in Moscow, the Comintern continued to operate for more
                than two decades. It was officially dissolved in 1943. Its central bodies would
                confirm the mandate, appoint the leadership, or dissolve the communist parties
                outside the Soviet Union; provide them with general political guidelines and
                financial subsidies; decide on their strategy; offer to the communists who were
                persecuted elsewhere with political refuge and hospitality in the Soviet Union, new
                Soviet papers or forged foreign identity and documents; as well as provide medical
                care, general and political education, and ideological training. The Comintern
                maintained two universities, both located in Moscow – the “Communist University of
                the National Minorities in the West” (KUNMZ), and the “Communist University of the
                Toilers in the East” (KUTV). The Comintern also had a specialised publishing house
                that printed books and brochures in numerous languages and a theoretical journal
                with a free worldwide distribution. The Comintern combined its promotion of
                communist ideology, mostly through printed media, with the preparations for
                potential future communist takeovers in the “bourgeois” world. </p>
            <p>Some foreign communists, including the prospective future leaders in their countries,
                were also provided with military, security, and intelligence training by the Red
                Army and by the Soviet security services. Prominent future communist leaders,
                presidents, prime ministers, ministers, and other high-ranking officials in Poland,
                East Germany, Czechoslovakia, Hungary, Romania, Bulgaria, and Yugoslavia were among
                these students. The list included also the future Yugoslav communist leader Josip
                Broz –Tito. The Comintern also used emissaries, advisers and controllers, who
                oversaw groups of countries and their communist parties. One of the best known among
                them was Mikhail Borodin, who operated as a Comintern representative in China,
                Scandinavia, the United States, Mexico, Spain, and Turkey. He and a number of other
                Russian lecturers were vital for the establishment in 1924 as well as for the
                subsequent functioning of the Whampoa Military Academy in Guangzhou, Guangdong
                Province, China. Since the 1920s, the Comintern’s educational, ideological,
                organisational and security training was provided in the Soviet Union to future
                leading communists from China, Vietnam, and Korea. The future leader of the Korean
                communists, first Prime Minister and later President of the People’s Democratic
                Republic of Korea Kim Ilsung was educated and trained in Soviet military schools,
                and by 1945 rose to the rank of a major in the Soviet Army. </p>
            <p>On the other hand, during Stalin’s insane orgy of purges in the late 1930s, numerous
                communist refugees, including the leaders of Polish, Yugoslav, and Korean communist
                parties perished in the Soviet Union. Between 1937 and 1938, nineteen prominent
                Yugoslav communist emigrants were arrested in Moscow and executed on fabricated
                charges. Among them were five former Secretaries General (including Milan Gorkić)
                and nine current or former members of the Central Committee of the Communist Party
                of Yugoslavia. The estimated total number of Yugoslav communists executed in the
                Soviet Union in 1938 is around sixty.</p>
            <p>The Soviet Bolsheviks (officially renamed to communists) considered and justified
                these activities (and the expense for USSR) as crucial for the active defence of the
                first socialist state “of workers and peasants” in history. In most countries
                outside the Soviet Union, the Comintern’s activities were officially considered as
                politically subversive, even seditious and criminal (including in the Kingdom of
                Yugoslavia). The Comintern’s internal security service and the OMS (International
                Liaison Department) played an important role in the Comintern’s clandestine
                activities. Both partly overlapped with and were controlled by the Soviet civilian
                and military security and intelligence services (OGPU, GRU). A considerable part of
                the Comintern’s political activities was channelled through an extensive network of
                international “transmission” associations, such as the Communist Youth
                International, Red Trade Union International, Peasant International, Red Mutual
                Assistance, the corresponding women’s organisation, etc. The Comintern’s activities,
                including its clandestine operations, were supported by the Soviet diplomatic and
                consular missions abroad. </p>
            <p>The World War II and its aftermath provided new opportunities for the geographic
                spreading of Soviet-like communist regimes. Between 1939 and 1940, three Baltic
                republics and parts of Poland and Romania were occupied and annexed by the USSR in
                accordance with the secret clauses of the Molotov-Ribbentrop Pact. The defeat of the
                Axis in 1945 was followed by the imposition of Soviet-like systems in seven
                “people’s democracies” in Eastern Europe and North Korea. Moreover, in 1945 the
                victorious communists in Yugoslavia and Albania implemented their own versions of
                the Soviet system. In 1946 the Soviets attempted to create a similar regime in
                Northern Iran as well, but had to abandon the attempt under the British and American
                pressure. In 1979 the Soviet Army invaded Afghanistan in order to prop up a
                crypto-communist regime in that Asian country, but later had to give up this attempt
                after considerable expenses and losses. </p>
            <p>The spreading of Soviet-like systems into the Eastern Europe and Asia corresponded to
                two key strategic objectives of the Soviet leadership. These included: (1) the
                declared goal of advancing “socialism” worldwide; and (2) making the Soviet Union a
                global political and military superpower. Joseph Stalin made use of the appeal of
                the Russian Revolution in order to advance and satisfy the Soviet Union's
                (essentially Russian) great power ambitions. Achieving these two objectives was
                costly and not always compatible. On a number of occasions they collided, and then
                the latter would always prevail. The non-aggression pact with Hitler in 1939 was
                among such examples.</p>
            <p>Following its official dissolution in 1943, a number of the Comintern’s functions
                continued in the form of mostly bilateral relations between the Communist Party of
                the Soviet Union and other communist parties. In 1947 the Communist Information
                Bureau (Cominform) was established at a conference in Poland, mostly tasked with
                guiding and disciplining the East European communist parties. It was also joined by
                the two largest West European communist parties (the Italian and the French).
                Originally the seat of the Bureau and the editorial office of its newspaper were
                located in Belgrade. The editor-in-chief of the newspaper was a Soviet citizen with
                a diplomatic status, while a representative of the Communist Party of Yugoslavia
                Boris Ziherl served as his deputy. However, in June 1948 the Yugoslav Communist
                Party was expelled from the Cominform and its office was consequently relocated to
                Bucharest. </p>
            <p>Outside the territory of the former Russian Empire, Russian Bolshevism decisively
                influenced the destiny of two Asian and two European states. The Republic of
                Mongolia and the People's Democratic Republic of Korea owe their very existence as
                independent states to the Soviet Union. In the past this was also true of the German
                Democratic Republic (GDR). The ideological impact of Bolshevism was crucial for the
                rebirth and forty-five years later for the violent demise of Yugoslavia, as well as
                for the peaceful dissolution of the GDR and Czechoslovakia.</p>
            <p>Banned in December 1920, the Communist Party of Yugoslavia (the CPY) suffered greatly
                from the police and judicial repression in Yugoslavia as well as elsewhere. In
                addition to the underground membership in the country, its leadership and about a
                thousand of its adherents operated abroad, as migrants or political refugees (mostly
                in the Soviet Union, France, Austria, and during the civil war also in Spain). The
                Soviet organisational, logistic and financial support helped the severely weakened
                and politically marginalised party to survive. In the late 1930s, with a new
                generation of young members and a new leadership, the Yugoslav communists abandoned
                their sectarianism and started cooperating with other anti-fascists. However, under
                normal peacetime conditions – without the tremendous upheaval and the profound
                social and political dislocation caused by the World War II – the Yugoslav
                communists would have probably never assumed power in the state by means of
                elections.</p>
            <p>Financially self-sustaining without any Soviet subsidy since 1939, under the
                conditions of World War II and of the foreign occupation as well as at a
                considerable distance from Moscow, the Yugoslav communists managed to emancipate and
                free themselves from outside control. Their leadership did continue to report to
                Moscow by radio, but adopted its own political strategy and managed its affairs
                independently. At several junctions, the actions of the Yugoslav leadership deviated
                from the Soviet positions and tactics regarding the Western Allies. As a centralised
                and disciplined Party without internal fractions and with motivated adherents and
                supporters, the Yugoslav communists, in spite of the initially modest membership,
                proved to be the best organised armed resistance force on the territory of the
                defunct Yugoslav monarchy. The line of resolute resistance that was adopted by the
                communists resulted in large numbers of non-communists joining on patriotic grounds
                the Yugoslav Partisan movement. The organisational legacy of the Russian Bolsheviks,
                transmitted through the Comintern, as well as the appeal of an egalitarian ideology
                contributed to the Yugoslav communists’ ending up on the winning side of the war. As
                of 1943, the British and the Americans recognised the Yugoslav Partisans as the most
                effective Allied force in the Balkans. In the autumn of 1944 the Soviet Army
                liberated part of Yugoslavia’s territory, but unlike elsewhere in occupied Europe
                (except in Albania), in the final stages of World War II the Yugoslav Partisans
                succeeded in liberating most of their country on their own. The war’s outcome
                allowed the communists to defeat, drive away or eliminate the internal adversaries
                who had collaborated with the occupiers. In resolutely and often brutally dealing
                with them, the Yugoslav communists employed the methods of their role models – the
                Russian Bolsheviks. </p>
            <p>Imitating the Soviet system and adhering to Marxist-Leninist ideological precepts
                became a general rule in post-1945 Yugoslavia. A significant part of the first
                constitution of the new Yugoslav state, adopted in 1946, was merely a translation of
                the Soviet (“Stalin’s”) Constitution of 1936. The Yugoslav communists adopted thus
                the Soviet system of fake ethno-federalism, with often artificial administrative
                lines separating the federal units. In many respects, the Yugoslav communists
                strived to be and indeed were more orthodox and Stalinist in terms of their
                “revolutionary” approach than the other European communist parties. The Yugoslav
                adaptation of the Russian Bolshevik ideology replaced the pre-war ideological
                foundation of the Kingdom of Yugoslavia and became the first and foremost adhesive
                element of the newly stitched-together multinational state called the Federal
                People’s Republic of Yugoslavia. </p>
            <p>Initially the Yugoslav communists responded to the sharp conflict with Stalin in June
                1948 and to the insulting expulsion from the Eastern European “camp of people’s
                democracies” with an even more Marxist orthodoxy and Stalinism in internal political
                and economic matters. Only after 1951 did the political shock resulting from the
                conflict with Moscow led to gradual and partial liberalisation of Yugoslavia and its
                distancing from the Soviet system. The hallmarks of the Yugoslav “revisionist”
                system included workers’ self-management, semi-market economy, relatively open
                borders, and non-alignment in international affairs. However, the Yugoslav communist
                leaders, like the Soviets, continued to wrongly believe that the “socialist
                revolution” had resolved forever the national problem in their multinational state.
                Because of the pressure from below, in 1963 and in 1974 the Yugoslav authorities
                made concessions to the centrifugal forces and allowed for the transformation of the
                centralised quasi-federation into a malfunctioning hybrid of a federal – confederal
                institutional structure and authoritarian one-party rule. With the waning attraction
                of the egalitarian communist ideology, the “revisionist” deviations from the Soviet
                model proved to be insufficient to keep the Yugoslav state in one piece. Not
                accidentally, the modified imitation of the Soviet system in Yugoslavia went down
                the drain of history roughly at the same time as its original form in the Soviet
                Union. </p>
            <p>The dissolution of the Warsaw Pact in 1991 marked the end of the Soviet hegemony in a
                significant part of Eastern-Central and South-Eastern Europe. It was accompanied by
                the crumbling of European communist regimes and the end of the “Cold War”. These
                dramatic developments allowed for an important geopolitical transformation and
                realignment on the European continent. Four communist-ruled “real-socialist” states
                disappeared from the European map. Among them were three “socialist federations”
                (the Union of Soviet Socialist Republics, the Socialist Federal Republic of
                Yugoslavia, and the Czechoslovak Socialist Republic). <hi rend="bold">Nowadays,
                    twenty-four new European states exist on the territories of the three defunct
                    federations. Of these, seven republics on the territory of the former SFR
                    Yugoslavia have become independent also due to the delayed political and
                    ideological impact of the Russian October Revolution.</hi></p>
            <p>Between the 1920s and the 1930s, the Russian October Revolution and the Comintern
                contributed significantly to the development of Chinese communism. The popularity of
                the Bolsheviks in the semi-colonial China was enhanced by their anti-imperialist
                pronouncements and the declared intention to renounce Russia’s extraterritorial
                rights. In the spring of 1920, Grigorii Voytinski, a Comintern emissary, helped to
                establish the Communist Party of China and drafted its manifesto, which was adopted
                at the first party congress. In the 1920s and 1930s, the future important communist
                functionaries like Deng Xiaoping, Zhou Enlai and others attended the ideological and
                organisational training in Moscow, at the Communist University of the Toilers in the
                East. The adopted Bolshevik organisational format and internal rules of a
                centralised and disciplined party as well as the Comintern’s annual subsidy greatly
                helped the Chinese communists to survive persecution and eventually to emerge
                victorious in the guerrilla warfare against the Japanese occupiers and in the civil
                war that lasted for two decades. The Whampoa Military Academy, Soviet advisors and
                instructors in China, and military schools in the Soviet Union contributed to the
                military education and training of some generals of the Chinese People’s Liberation
                Army (PLA) who became later quite famous. In the final stage of the civil war, the
                strength of the PLA was enhanced by the captured weapons of the Japanese Kwantuing
                Army in Manchuria, crushed by the Soviet Army in August 1945. </p>
            <p>Having gained the state power on the mainland in 1949, the Chinese communists adopted
                and largely followed the Soviet model of state organisation as well as economic and
                social development. There have been several notable exceptions. Mao Zedong disagreed
                with the Russian Bolshevik concept of a “workers’ revolution” and opted instead for
                the strategy of a “peasants’ revolution”. Moreover the Chinese communists eschewed
                the Soviet model of ethno-federalism, granted only limited cultural autonomy to
                ethnic minorities and organised mass relocations of the Han population to the
                strategically-important peripheral provinces. In addition they, unlike the Soviets,
                allowed the continued existence and controlled legal functioning of eight “fellow”
                and “patriotic“ parties, small by the Chinese standards. After two disastrous
                experiments in the 1950s, 1960s and 1970s – with Mao Zedong’s “Great Leap Forward”
                and the “Cultural Revolution” – the Chinese communist leadership under Deng Xiaoping
                abandoned the Marxist economic dogmas. Moreover, unlike in the Soviet Union, the
                Chinese leadership introduced and, until 2018, maintained a system of regular
                mandatory rejuvenation of the top personnel in the state, based on the criteria of
                proved competence, managerial ability, and personal achievements. </p>
            <p>V. Lenin, the spiritual leader of the October Revolution, was feared that the Soviet
                Russia will not survive without a global socialist revolution<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn4" n="3"> Louis Fischer, <hi rend="italic">The Life of Lenin</hi>
                        (New York: Harper &amp; Row, 1964), 309‒13, 528, 622.</note>. The
                Revolution's militry leader L. Trotsky claimed, in his work “The Permanent
                Revolution”, that a socialist revolution could not be accomplished in a national
                    framework<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn5" n="4"> Lav Trocki, <hi rend="italic">Permanentna revolucija</hi> (Rijeka: Otokar Keršovani,
                        1972), 131.</note>. For more than three decades, the prospect of a world
                revolution seemed unattainable. However, the future of world communism became
                brighter by the 40<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> anniversary of the October
                Revolution, which was solemnly celebrated in November 1957 in Moscow. Conspicuously
                present at the event were the leaders of the territorially largest and the most
                populous states on the globe (the USSR and the People's Republic of China) as well
                as of a dozen “people’s democracies”. During the following two and a half decades,
                the pseudo-communists rose to power on Cuba, in Kampuchea, South Vietnam, Laos,
                Angola, Mozambique, Ethiopia, South Yemen, Afghanistan, Grenada, and Nicaragua. All
                these achievements seemed to foreshadow the communist future of mankind. However,
                soon after the 70<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> anniversary Lenin’s premonition
                turned out to be correct. </p>
            <p>Lenin and Trotsky were wrong in their assumption that the communist system could only
                be defeated if crushed militarily from the outside by “bourgeois” imperialism.
                Instead the communist systems in the Soviet Union and in Eastern Europe broke down
                because of internal reasons. Ultimately, the demise of the Soviet system and the
                systems of Eastern European “people’s democracies” has resulted from flawed economic
                strategies, inflexible authoritarian political systems, and the challenges posed by
                nationalism (which was supposed to disappear in the communist societies). The Soviet
                Union collapsed also due to its leadership’s grossly excessive global superpower
                ambitions, to the ensuing economic exhaustion, the cancer of the ethno-federalist
                façade, and a conflict within the Russian political elite. In the last decade of the
                20th century, all communist-led or dominated “real socialist” systems in Eastern
                Germany, Central Eastern and South Eastern Europe, in Russia itself, in all other
                former republics of the Soviet Union (with the possible exception of Belarus), and
                in Mongolia experienced ostensibly liberal, mostly non-violent counter-revolutions.
                They were replaced by very different systems, ranging from multiparty
                parliamentarian democracies to various kinds of autocracies and personal or family
                dictatorships behind the imitations of liberal constitutional façades. All these
                regimes deny any continuity with the heritage of the Russian Revolution.</p>
            <p>Lenin and Trotsky did not believe that Soviet-like systems would still survive
                elsewhere, if defeated in Russia. Once again, it turned out that they were wrong.
                Communist systems inspired directly or indirectly by the Russian Revolution, partly
                copied from the Soviet model but developed indigenously, have been created “through
                the barrel of the gun” and have developed in Eastern Asia. Today, one of them – a
                radical totalitarian and militarised replica of the Soviet system in the People’s
                Democratic Republic of Korea – does not capture the world’s attention with the
                wellbeing of its population, but rather with its successful development of nuclear
                weapons and long-range missiles. The list of geographically more distant followers
                also include the current systems in the Republics of Laos and Cuba. An aberrant,
                brutal imitation of wartime Bolshevism by the “Khmer Rouge” existed for several
                years in Kampuchea, but was crushed militarily by the Vietnamese communists.</p>
            <p>The economically and politically most successful “socialist” state – the People’s
                Republic of China and to a lesser degree the Socialist Republic of Vietnam – have
                developed and maintained several essential elements of the systems inspired by the
                Russian revolution: a ruling communist party, an official Marxist – Leninist
                ideology, mass rituals, red flags, five-pointed stars, and other communist symbols.
                Having abandoned however the Marxist economic dogmas, the Chinese and Vietnamese
                communists combined the Soviet-like political features of their political systems
                with a considerably open and controlled market economy, a large share of private
                domestic and foreign capitalism, and gross economic inequality. These deviations
                from the Soviet model released the energy of hundreds of millions of Chinese. In
                three decades they have transformed the still communist China into the second
                largest world economy and a great political and military power. Since the
                implementation of reforms inspired by Deng Xiaoping, the Chinese communists could be
                considered as followers of the Soviet “New Economic Policy” (NEP) in the 1920s,
                which could be observed first-hand by Deng Xiaoping, at the time a student of the
                Communist University in Moscow. However, this policy was soon abandoned by the
                frightened and dogmatic Soviet officialdom. In retrospect, that turnabout and the
                ensuing suppression of private economic activities in the Soviet Union was one of
                the fatal errors committed by the Russian Bolsheviks. </p>
            <p>The Russian October Revolution was much more radical in its proclaimed goals and much
                more violent than the American Revolution of 1775–1783. It also lacked the latter’s
                main secessionist element. However, when constructing the Soviet Union, the Russian
                Bolsheviks copied some institutional features of the American federalism. In a
                number of respects, the Russian Revolution could be more appropriately compared with
                the Great French Revolution of 1789–1792. The storming of Bastille in Paris and of
                the Winter Palace in Petrograd became the symbols of these revolutions, both of
                which occurred in the largest European states of that time and shook profoundly the
                existing social and political orders in Europe. The French Revolution abolished
                feudalism in France and contributed to its gradual abolition in the rest of Europe.
                The Russian Revolution, on the other hand, swept away the remnants of feudalism in
                Russia. Unlike the American revolution, both anticlerical revolutions soon
                degenerated into dictatorships. The liberating appeal of both of them was abused by
                the two dictators for conquests and domination in considerable parts of the European
                continent. The two dictators who came from minorities – Napoleon Bonaparte and
                Joseph Stalin – thus betrayed the declared goals of the two revolutions. </p>
            <p>Both revolutions were eventually defeated in the countries of their origin (and in
                their satellite states), but left deep impact on their societies. For more than a
                century, the ideas of the French Revolution would inspire reformers and
                revolutionaries in Europe and the Americas, and would be subsequently built into the
                political and social orders of liberal democratic states on five continents. The
                French Revolution also contributed to the decolonisation of North and South America,
                while the French Jacobins influenced many radical leftists around the globe,
                including the Russian Bolsheviks. </p>
            <p>The Russian October Revolution failed in its declared primary strategic objective: to
                destroy and abolish capitalism all around the world. Contrary to their original
                promise of “the complete abolition of the state”, the Russian communists developed a
                bureaucratic monstrosity. On the other hand, the fear of communism, helped to reform
                the crude capitalist systems in the West in the direction of more democratic and
                human social states. The first communist state – the Soviet Union – contributed
                decisively to the military defeat of the German-Austrian Third Reich and to the
                victory of the Allies in the World War II. The Russian Revolution also contributed
                to the decolonisation in Asia and Africa, and indirectly to the rebirth of China as
                a global superpower. </p>
            <p>On the other hand, certain features and symbols of the Russian Revolution have become
                discredited in many countries with authoritarian communist regimes. Geographically,
                this discreditation was rather random. During the last three decades in addition to
                30 European, Transcaucasian and Central Asian countries, communist parties have lost
                state power in four Asian countries (Afghanistan, Kampuchea, Southern Yemen, Nepal);
                six African countries (Ethiopia, Somalia, Benin, Angola, Mozambique, Congo,
                Brazzaville); and in two states in the Americas (Grenada, Nicaragua). Nowadays
                communist parties rule only in four East Asian and one Latin American state. In
                addition, the communist parties in Asia (India, Bangladesh, Nepal, Syria and
                Palestine); Africa (South Africa) and Latin America (Chile, Ecuador, Uruguay, Guyana
                and Venezuela) have participated in the ruling leftist coalitions. The Communist
                Party of Japan currently holds 14 seats in the upper house of the Japanese National
                Assembly. Most European communist parties have either been dissolved or reformed,
                reorganised and renamed, usually into socialist or social-democratic parties. Three
                small communist parties participate today in the ruling coalitions in Greece, Serbia
                and San Marino while notable non-ruling communist parties function in the Russian
                Federation, Czech Republic, Portugal, Spain, Italy, France and Cyprus. 15 deputies
                of the European Parliament (out of 751) have been elected from the lists of seven
                European communist parties<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn6" n="5">
                        <hi rend="italic">List of communist parties – Wikipedia.</hi></note>. </p>
            <p>The discreditation of the October Revolution in its country of origin explains why
                the post-Soviet Russian regime has stopped celebrating the 7<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> of November and removed it from the list of official holidays. The
                Americans and the French, on the other hand, continue to joyfully celebrate every
                year the 4<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> and
                14<hi rend="superscript" xml:space="preserve">th </hi>of July as their main state
                events. The Russian October Revolution has thus primarily become intellectual food
                for historians and other social scientists, as well as a topic for writers, film and
                television producers, and for other media. </p>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="bibliography">
                <head>Sources and Literature</head>
            <listBibl>
                <head>Literature</head>
                <bibl>Fischer, Louis. <hi rend="italic">The Life of Lenin. </hi>New York: Harper
                    &amp; Row, 1964.</bibl>
                <bibl>Lenin, Vladimir J. <hi rend="italic">Država in revolucija in drugi spisi iz l.
                    1917</hi>. Ljubljana: Studia Humanitatis, 2017.</bibl>
                <bibl>Pipes, Richard. <hi rend="italic">The Russian Revolution</hi>. New York:
                    Alfred Knopf, 1991.</bibl>
                <bibl>Trocki, Lav. <hi rend="italic">Permanentna revolucija</hi>, Rijeka: Otokar
                    Keršovani, 1972.</bibl></listBibl>
            
            <listBibl>
                <head>E-Sources</head>
            <bibl><hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">List of communist parties – Wikipedia. </hi>Accessible
                    at: <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_communist_parties">https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_communist_parties</ref>, 19 March
                    2018. </bibl></listBibl>
            </div>
            <div type="summary" xml:lang="sl">
                <docAuthor>Anton Bebler</docAuthor>
            <head>O GLOBALNEM ODTISTU RUSKE OKTOBRSKE REVOLUCIJE IZ LETA 1917</head>
            <head>POVZETEK</head>
            <p>Ruska revolucija, se je dejansko začela februarja –marca l. 1917 z ukinitvijo ene od
                najstarejših monarhij v Evropi in z uvedbo deljene vladavine začasnega odbora Dume
                (»Začasna vlada«) in »Sovjetov odposlancev delavcev in vojakov.« Do sredine oktobra
                1917 je Vojaškorevolucionarni odbor Petrograjskega sovjeta že nadzoroval rusko
                prestolnico. Aretacija večine ministrov nemočne Začasne vlade v Zimski palači v
                Petrogradu ponoči 26. oktobra in strel s slepim nabojem s križarke »Avrora« sta bila
                le epizoda, ki so ju propagandno napihnili v simbola slavne Oktobrske revolucije v
                največji evropski državi. Prevzem oblasti v Moskvi in drugod po državi pa je bil
                veliko težji, bolj nasilen in krvav. Ruska revolucija se je zaključila šele l. 1921
                z zmagami ruskih »boljševikov« in Rdeče armade v krvavi državljanski in drugih
                vojnah. Te vojne, drugo nasilje, lakota in epidemije na ozemlju propadlega cesarstva
                so terjali v štirih letih nekaj milijonov smrtnih žrtev.</p>
            <p>Ruska revolucija je pretresla tedanjo politično ureditev v Evropi, ki jo je že pred
                tem hudo razmajala prva svetovna vojna, kar se je izrazilo tudi v propadu še treh
                velikih cesarstev –avstroogrskega, nemškega in otomanskega. Za razliko od drugih
                prevratov je Ruska revolucija pozivala k popolni odpravi svetovnega kapitalizma in
                imperializma ter k uvedbi brezrazrednih družb v svetovni federaciji sovjetskih
                republik kot koraka k odpravi države. Ruska revolucija je odmevala v svetu na več
                načinov. Njen najbolj neposredni mednarodni odtis se je v naslednjih treh
                desetletjih izrazil: v (1) nastanku političnih, ekonomskih in družbenih sistemov,
                podobnih sovjetskemu, ki so jih na druge dežele razširili predvsem ruski oz.
                sovjetski komunisti; (2) v vplivu na politično sceno v več drugih državah, ki se je
                izražal, med drugim, v nastanku komunističnih partij in v protikomunistični
                reakciji; (3) v vzpostavitvi nekaj avtohtonih komunističnih režimov, ki so delno
                posnemali sovjetski sistem.</p>
            <p>V sedmih desetletjih od zmage v svoji domovini Ruska revolucija ni odpravila ne
                svetovnega kapitalizma in ne same države, povzročila pa je velike geopolitične
                spremembe, predvsem v Evropi in Aziji. Strah pred komunizmom je posredno pomagal
                reformirati grobi kapitalizem na Zahodu v smeri bolj humane in demokratične socialne
                države. Število »socialističnih« držav, seštevek njihovih ozemelj in prebivalstva so
                dosegli svoje vrhunce kmalu po 40. obletnici Ruske revolucije, ki so jo v novembru
                1957 slovesno obeležili v Moskvi. Ruska revolucija je poleg tega prispevala k
                dekolonizaciji v Aziji in Afriki. </p>
            <p>Po sedmih desetletjih od zmage pa so bili v zadnjem desetletju 20. stoletja, večinoma
                po mirni poti, odpravljeni komunistični sistemi v sami Rusiji, vseh drugih nekdanjih
                republikah Sovjetske zveze (z morebitno izjemo Belorusije), vseh drugih
                vzhodnoevropskih državah (vključno z Vzhodno Nemčijo) ter Mongoliji. V primerjavi z
                vrhuncem okrog l. 1960 se je število »socialističnih« držav v svetu tako skrčilo za
                dve tretjini na sedanjih pet, od teh na štiri v Aziji in eno v Latinski Ameriki. </p>
            <p>Kot posnemovalci ruskih komunistov so se izkazali predvsem komunisti v Vzhodni Aziji.
                Svojevrstna, močno militarizirana imitacija sovjetskega sistema v Severni Koreji
                priteguje danes pozornost svetovne javnosti predvsem s svojim razkazovanjem jedrske
                in raketne oborožitve. Veliko bolj politično in gospodarsko uspešni kitajski
                komunisti so povezali politične poteze, povzete po sovjetskem sistemu (vladavino
                komunistične partije, uradno marksistično ideologijo, množične rituale, rdeče
                zastave, peterokrake zvezde in druge simbole), s tržno ekonomijo, veliko vlogo
                zasebnega domačega in tujega kapitala ter visoko ekonomsko neenakostjo. </p>
            <p>Za ruske in druge vzhodnoevropske režime pa je bilo usodno, da se niso odrekli
                protitržnim marksističnim dogmam in vztrajanju na avtoritarnem oblastem monopolu.
                Razpadu Sovjetske zveze, ČSSR in SFRJ sta botrovala tudi od zgoraj vsiljeni model
                fasadnega etnofederalizma in zgrešeno verovanje, da socializem odpravlja nacionalna
                protislovja. Še posebej v Evropi so dediščino in simbole Ruske revolucije politično
                diskreditirali avtoritarni vzhodnoevropski komunistični režimi in še posebej
                totalitarni režim v Sovjetski zvezi, katere gospodarstvo ni zdržalo tekme z razvitim
                Zahodom. To je bil temeljni razlog, zakaj so v Ruski federaciji odpravili
                praznovanje 7. novembra. Ruska revolucija je tako postala predvsem tema za
                zgodovinarje, druge družboslovce in umetnike. </p></div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>