<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Editorial Remarks</title>
                <author>Igor Vobič</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>2022-04-11</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>
                    <orgName xml:lang="sl">Inštitut za novejšo zgodovino</orgName>
                    <orgName xml:lang="en">Institute of Contemporary History</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Privoz 11</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>SI-1000 Ljubljana</addrLine>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>http://ojs.inz.si/pnz/article/view/</pubPlace>
                <date>2021</date>
                <availability status="free">
                    <licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title xml:lang="sl">Prispevki za novejšo zgodovino</title>
                <title xml:lang="en">Contributions to Contemporary History</title>
                <biblScope unit="volume">62</biblScope>
                <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
                <idno type="ISSN">2463-7807</idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source, born digital.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc xml:lang="en">
                <p>Contributions to Contemporary History is one of the central Slovenian scientific
                    historiographic journals, dedicated to publishing articles from the field of
                    contemporary history (the 19th and 20th century).</p>
                <p>The journal is published three times per year in Slovenian and in the following
                    foreign languages: English, German, Serbian, Croatian, Bosnian, Italian, Slovak
                    and Czech. The articles are all published with abstracts in English and
                    Slovenian as well as summaries in English.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <projectDesc xml:lang="sl">
                <p>Prispevki za novejšo zgodovino je ena osrednjih slovenskih znanstvenih
                    zgodovinopisnih revij, ki objavlja teme s področja novejše zgodovine (19. in 20.
                    stoletje).</p>
                <p>Revija izide trikrat letno v slovenskem jeziku in v naslednjih tujih jezikih:
                    angleščina, nemščina, srbščina, hrvaščina, bosanščina, italijanščina, slovaščina
                    in češčina. Članki izhajajo z izvlečki v angleščini in slovenščini ter povzetki
                    v angleščini.</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change>
                    <date>2022-05-09T08:08:43Z</date>
                    <name>Mihael Ojsteršek</name>
                    <desc>Pretvorba iz DOCX v TEI, dodatno kodiranje</desc>
                </change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <docAuthor>Igor Vobič</docAuthor>
        </front>
        <body>
            <p>The position of the media vis-à-vis the state and the Communist Party, varying
                between coercion and liberalisation in different periods of socialist Yugoslavia,
                was continuously re-shaped by the way the communication system(s) were developing,
                in turn re-articulating the role(s) of journalism in political and cultural life. As
                social institutions, the media and journalism in Yugoslavia were re-configured in
                the dynamics between the one-party state political system, the ‘pluralism of
                self-managing interests’ and the market economy, whereas the dominant concepts and
                corresponding policies of intercultural and international communication emerged amid
                imbalances in international news flows and inequalities and tensions among social
                groups, regions and republics of the federation. This thematic issue of the journal
                    <hi rend="italic">Contributions to Contemporary History</hi> views this history
                as a flow of discontinuities and new beginnings rather than linear progress or
                demise, acknowledging the relevance held by social history, cultural traditions,
                particularities of economic development, the (inter)national configurations of power
                and the development of state policies for studying the contradictions of media and
                journalism in socialist Yugoslavia. </p>
            <p>Against this backdrop, the thematic issue considers theoretical and empirical voids
                in the scarce scholarly research that can be found, exploring certain
                discontinuities in Yugoslav media and journalism’s contemporary history by analysing
                rich historical materials from a variety of sources, chiefly archival materials,
                scholarly documentation, media content, and oral history interviews. The invited
                contributions reappraise some of the key ideas and communication research in the
                SFRY period, examine tensions in international and intercultural communication, with
                a focus on the Tanjug news agency and the Non-Aligned news agency pool, reconsider
                the normative foundations of Yugoslav journalism and investigate what former
                journalists remember about their roles as socio-political workers, analyse
                journalistic discourse concerning pressing issues of the collapsing state, and
                explore the place of the media in forming collective and individual memories of
                socialist Yugoslavia. </p>
            <p>The studies in this thematic issue are the result of cooperation between the Social
                Communication Research Centre at the Faculty of Social Sciences, University of
                Ljubljana, and the Institute for Contemporary History as part the basic research
                project <hi rend="italic">The Role of Communication Inequalities in Disintegration
                    of a Multinational Society</hi> (J5-1793) financed by ARRS – Slovenian Research
                Agency. Both the project and this thematic issue promote the disciplinary
                integration of history and communication science by exploring and explaining the
                complexities of material and symbolic re-configurations of the media and journalism
                in Yugoslavia while also gathering and analysing the memories of journalism
                professionals and media audiences of the socialist past. Although the studies
                investigate only some of the past discontinuities in the media and journalism and
                their re-imaginings today, it is vital that such interdisciplinary research continue
                if we are to ensure a more nuanced picture of of Yugoslav media and journalism
                history and overcome the simplified images of that socialist society that prevail in
                contemporary public life in Slovenia and in other countries of the region. </p>
            <p>Ljubljana, 10 April 2022</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
