<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Twenty-five Years of the Republic of Slovenia – Challenges, Dilemmas
                    and Expectations. Ljubljana, 15 and 16 June 2016</title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename>Filip</forename>
                        <surname>Čuček</surname>
                    </name>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>2016-10-05</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>
                    <orgName xml:lang="sl">Inštitut za novejšo zgodovino</orgName>
                    <orgName xml:lang="en">Institute of Contemporary History</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Kongresni trg 1</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>SI-1000 Ljubljana</addrLine>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>http://ojs.inz.si/pnz/article/view/180</pubPlace>
                <date>2016</date>
                <availability status="free">
                    <licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title xml:lang="sl">Prispevki za novejšo zgodovino</title>
                <title xml:lang="en">Contributions to Contemporary History</title>
                <biblScope unit="volume">56</biblScope>
                <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
                <idno type="ISSN">2463-7807</idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source, born digital.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc xml:lang="en">
                <p>Contributions to Contemporary History is one of the central Slovenian scientific
                    historiographic journals, dedicated to publishing articles from the field of
                    contemporary history (the 19th and 20th century).</p>
                <p>The journal is published three times per year in Slovenian and in the following
                    foreign languages: English, German, Serbian, Croatian, Bosnian, Italian, Slovak
                    and Czech. The articles are all published with abstracts in English and
                    Slovenian as well as summaries in English.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <projectDesc xml:lang="sl">
                <p>Prispevki za novejšo zgodovino je ena osrednjih slovenskih znanstvenih
                    zgodovinopisnih revij, ki objavlja teme s področja novejše zgodovine (19. in 20.
                    stoletje).</p>
                <p>Revija izide trikrat letno v slovenskem jeziku in v naslednjih tujih jezikih:
                    angleščina, nemščina, srbščina, hrvaščina, bosanščina, italijanščina, slovaščina
                    in češčina. Članki izhajajo z izvlečki v angleščini in slovenščini ter povzetki
                    v angleščini.</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change>
                    <date>2016-10-18</date>
                    <name>Neja Blaj Hribar</name>
                    <desc>Pretvorba iz DOCX v TEI, dodatno kodiranje</desc>
                </change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <front>
            <docAuthor>Filip Čuček</docAuthor>
        </front>
        <body>
            <p> The Institute of Contemporary History organised a symposium detailing (the first) 25
                years of Slovenia as a state, thus commemorating the 25<hi rend="superscript"
                    >th</hi> anniversary of the independent Republic of Slovenia. Even though 25
                years is a relatively short period from the historical perspective, it poses a
                special challenge to researchers of contemporary history, since many events took
                place in the young country from 1991 to 2016 and there are many things that require
                a systematic analysis. </p>
            <p>Two and a half decades after Slovenia became independent, some of the
                well-established researchers detected and defined issues related to the study of the
                independent Slovenia. The issues regarding archival and other documentary materials
                were usually at the forefront; these were followed by methodological issues relating
                to time distance, the issue of various sources and those concerning the options for
                presenting this period, and the need to attract reviews and studies from other
                fields that dealt with contemporariness. </p>
            <p>A diplomat at the Ministry of Foreign Affairs and historian, Dr Janez Šumrada, was
                the first author to treat the subject of Slovenian independence; he wrote a paper
                called <hi rend="italic">Foreign Policy – International Recognition, UN, EU, NATO,
                    and OECD</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Zunanja politika – mednarodno priznanje, OZN,
                    EU, NATO in OECD</hi>). In this work, he summarised and to a certain extent
                questioned some issues related to the politics of the most important countries with
                regard to the recognition of the independent Republic of Slovenia. In light of the
                infrastructure of the Social Science Data Archives, Chairman of the Social Science
                Data Archives, Dr Janez Štebe, dealt with the legitimacy of the international
                recognition of Slovenia, having written a paper titled <hi rend="italic">Legitimacy
                    of the International Recognition of the Republic of Slovenia: the Use of the
                    Social Science Data Archives</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Legitimnost mednarodnega
                    pridruževanja države Slovenije: primer izkoriščanja Arhiva družboslovnih
                    podatkov</hi>). In the paper, he introduced a few possibilities for the use of
                data available in the Social Science Data Archives and at providers, which are
                associated with the Archives, for the purpose of analysing the issue of Slovenia's
                international recognition. Dr Jure Gašparič from the Institute of Contemporary
                History dealt with the issue of how to tackle the research and records from recent
                history by writing the paper <hi rend="italic">The Writing of the Political History
                    of the Republic of Slovenia</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Pisati politično zgodovino
                    RS</hi>). He discovered that people mistrusted politicians and parties from the
                very beginning, and asked the questions of how the political institutions acted, how
                they developed, and how they adapted themselves to the world and the times that
                changed considerably over the twenty years. Dr Simona Kustec Lipicer from the
                Faculty of Social Sciences, who is currently a Member of Slovenian Parliament,
                evaluated modern party-based and parliamentary democracies in her paper titled <hi
                    rend="italic">Evaluation of Modern Party-based and Parliamentary Democracy: a
                    Prediction Based on Past Experience</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Vrednotenje
                    strankarske in parlamentarne demokracije današnjega časa: pogled naprej skozi
                    pretekle izkušnje</hi>). This work chronologically shows and evaluates the
                political situation in parliamentary democracy since the first parliamentary
                elections in the independent Slovenia in 1992.</p>
            <p>Afterwards, Dr Zdenko Čepič from the Institute of Contemporary History showed how
                Slovenian statehood had been formed even prior to gaining independence in his paper
                titled <hi rend="italic">Before That – the Formation of Slovenian Statehood in the
                    Period before its Independence</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Pred tem – nastajanje
                    slovenske državnosti pred samostojno državo</hi>). In the form of an essay, he
                discussed the issue of the formation of Slovenia in the “brief” 20<hi
                    rend="superscript">th</hi> century as the predecessor of the independent
                Republic of Slovenia. Dr Aleksander Lorenčič, the Director of the Ptuj-Ormož
                Regional Museum, stressed the key issues of researching Slovenia's economic
                transition in his paper <hi rend="italic">Studying Economic Transition – Challenges,
                    Dilemmas and Results</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Proučevanje gospodarske tranzicije
                    – izzivi, zagate in rezultati</hi>), which showed the challenges, dilemmas, and
                findings that he faced when researching and studying Slovenia’s economic transition.
                On the other hand, Dr Damijan Guštin wrote about the security aspect of the young
                Slovenia in a paper titled <hi rend="italic">Security and Defence of the Republic of
                    Slovenia – Dilemmas and Solutions</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Varnost in obramba
                    Republike Slovenije – dileme in rešitve</hi>). The defence system of the young
                state was established in 1991 and was formed under the influence of war and the
                instability of regional security. Slovenia developed its national security system,
                it developed its Territorial Defence into a regular army in 2004, and abolished the
                selective service system and restructured its army into a professional army while in
                the process of joining NATO between the years 2000 and 2004. Dr Tomaž Pavlin from
                the Faculty of Sport presented Slovenian sports in light of the transition in a
                paper titled <hi rend="italic">“Sports Story Woven by Thousands” (The Independence
                    and Sport &amp; Transition and Dilemmas) (“Športna zgodba, stkana iz dejavnosti
                    tisočev” (Osamosvojitev in šport, tranzicija in dileme))</hi>, revealing key
                moments that came before independence and the first preparations for sports
                independence. The first day of the conference was concluded by Dr Jurij Perovšek
                from the Institute of Contemporary History with his paper <hi rend="italic">What to
                    Say?</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Kaj reči?</hi>) and his thoughts on the “Slovenian”
                    20<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> century and independent Slovenia. In his paper,
                the author pointed out the negative aspects of the social, political and economic
                development in the Republic of Slovenia following its attainment of independence. </p>
            <p>On the second day of the conference, Vesna Gotovina from the Archives of the Republic
                of Slovenia discussed the issue of archival materials of state authorities from the
                period of fighting for independence in the Archives of the Republic of Slovenia in
                her paper titled <hi rend="italic">National Authorities' Archival Materials on the
                    Process of the Slovenian Independence</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Arhivsko gradivo
                    državnih organov o procesih osamosvajanja Slovenije</hi>), and she came to the
                conclusion that the majority of archival materials about the democratisation process
                and the process of gaining independence of the Republic of Slovenia is still held by
                those who created or own the archival materials. Dr Kaja Širok, the Director of the
                National Museum of Contemporary History, emphasised the collection management
                policies at the museum after 1991 and the materials of the National Museum of
                Contemporary History in her paper titled <hi rend="italic">The Object and the
                    Memory: A Perspective on Museums' Collection Management Policy and Acquisition
                    of Historical Materials in the Past 25 Years</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Predmet in
                    spomin: Pregled na muzejske zbiralne politike in pridobivanje historičnega
                    gradiva zadnjega četrt stoletja</hi>). She mainly discussed the restatement of
                the mission and collection management policies of museums after 1991. Dr Andrej
                Pančur and Dr Mojca Šorn from the Institute of Contemporary History presented the
                use of National Assembly materials in digital humanities in a paper titled <hi
                    rend="italic">Digital Approach to Parliamentary History: the use of the
                    Slovenian National Assembly Materials in Digital Humanities</hi> (<hi
                    rend="italic">Digitalni pristop k parlamentarni zgodovini: uporaba gradiva
                    Državnega zbora v digitalni humanistiki</hi>) and warned about the issue of
                comprehensive amounts of digital historical sources, which will be encountered by
                those researching the history of the Republic of Slovenia. Dr Bojan Godeša from the
                Institute of Contemporary History discussed the issue of the significance of World
                War II in the independent state of Slovenia in his paper titled <hi rend="italic"
                    >Instead of Reconciliation, a Cultural War– Significance of World War II in
                    Slovenian Society in the Independent State</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Namesto
                    sprave kulturni boj – mesto druge svetovne vojne v slovenski družbi po
                    osamosvojitvi</hi>). His paper also discussed the issue of reconciliation, the
                presence of which has been growing in Slovenian society since the mid-1980s. Dr
                Jurij Hadalin from the Institute of Contemporary History studied the historiographic
                discourse about the second Yugoslavia after 1991 in a paper titled <hi rend="italic"
                    >Unwanted Heritage? Historiographic Discourse about (the Second) Yugoslavia</hi>
                    (<hi rend="italic">Nezaželena dediščina? Historiografski diskurz o (drugi)
                    Jugoslaviji</hi>). In his paper, he tried to show the understanding of the
                second Yugoslav state in Slovenian historiography and in society, as Yugoslav
                history had remained an entirely political and not so much a professional topic in
                Slovenia. As the final paper at the conference, Dr Janez Markeš, a reporter for the
                Delo newspaper, presented his paper <hi rend="italic">The 25 years of Slovenian
                    Statehood: does History Repeat itself as a Farce?</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Četrt
                    stoletja slovenske države: se zgodovina ponavlja kot farsa?</hi>), in which he
                discussed the repetition of history from mid-18<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>
                century until now. </p>
            <p>The authors attempted to show the issues of the first 25 years of Slovenian
                statehood, each from their own perspective. The papers, when suitably extended and
                adapted scientifically, were recently published in a book with the same title as the
                symposium – <hi rend="italic">Twenty-five Years of the Republic of Slovenia –
                    Challenges, Dilemmas and Expectations</hi>. </p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
