<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Remembering Media and Journalism in Socialist Yugoslavia: Oral History
                    Interviews with Audiences<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn3" n="*">This work
                        received financial support from the Slovenian Research Agency – ARRS (grant
                        No. J5-1793).</note></title>
                <author>
                    <forename>Jernej</forename>
                    <surname>Kaluža</surname>
                    <roleName>Researcher</roleName>
                    <affiliation>Social Communication Research Centre, Faculty of Social Sciences,
                        University of Ljubljana</affiliation>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Kardeljeva ploščad 5</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>SI-1000 Ljubljana</addrLine>
                    </address>
                    <email>Jernej.Kaluza@fdv.uni-lj.si</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <forename>Jernej</forename>
                    <surname>Amon</surname>
                    <surname>Prodnik</surname>
                    <roleName>Researcher</roleName>
                    <affiliation>Social Communication Research Centre, Faculty of Social Sciences,
                        University of Ljubljana</affiliation>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Kardeljeva ploščad 5</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>SI-1000 Ljubljana</addrLine>
                    </address>
                    <email>Jernej.Amon-Prodnik@fdv.uni-lj.si</email>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>2022-04-21</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>
                    <orgName xml:lang="sl">Inštitut za novejšo zgodovino</orgName>
                    <orgName xml:lang="en">Institute of Contemporary History</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Privoz 11</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>SI-1000 Ljubljana</addrLine>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>http://ojs.inz.si/pnz/article/view/3988</pubPlace>
                <date>2021</date>
                <availability status="free">
                    <licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title xml:lang="sl">Prispevki za novejšo zgodovino</title>
                <title xml:lang="en">Contributions to Contemporary History</title>
                <biblScope unit="volume">62</biblScope>
                <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
                <idno type="ISSN">2463-7807</idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source, born digital.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc xml:lang="en">
                <p>Contributions to Contemporary History is one of the central Slovenian scientific
                    historiographic journals, dedicated to publishing articles from the field of
                    contemporary history (the 19th and 20th century).</p>
                <p>The journal is published three times per year in Slovenian and in the following
                    foreign languages: English, German, Serbian, Croatian, Bosnian, Italian, Slovak
                    and Czech. The articles are all published with abstracts in English and
                    Slovenian as well as summaries in English.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <projectDesc xml:lang="sl">
                <p>Prispevki za novejšo zgodovino je ena osrednjih slovenskih znanstvenih
                    zgodovinopisnih revij, ki objavlja teme s področja novejše zgodovine (19. in 20.
                    stoletje).</p>
                <p>Revija izide trikrat letno v slovenskem jeziku in v naslednjih tujih jezikih:
                    angleščina, nemščina, srbščina, hrvaščina, bosanščina, italijanščina, slovaščina
                    in češčina. Članki izhajajo z izvlečki v angleščini in slovenščini ter povzetki
                    v angleščini.</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en"/>
                <language ident="sl"/>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords xml:lang="en">
                    <term>memory studies</term>
                    <term>themed life-story interviews</term>
                    <term>socialist Yugoslavia</term>
                    <term>media use</term>
                    <term>history of journalism</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords xml:lang="sl">
                    <term>spominske študije</term>
                    <term>tematizirane življenjske zgodbe</term>
                    <term>socialistična Jugoslavija</term>
                    <term>uporaba medijev</term>
                    <term>zgodovina novinarstva</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change>
                    <date>2022-05-04T07:21:24Z</date>
                    <name>Mihael Ojsteršek</name>
                    <desc>Pretvorba iz DOCX v TEI, dodatno kodiranje</desc>
                </change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <docAuthor>Jernej Kaluža<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn1" n="**"><hi rend="bold"
                        >Researcher, Social Communication Research Centre, Faculty of Social
                        Sciences, University of Ljubljana, Kardeljeva ploščad 5, SI-1000
                            Ljubljana; <ref target="mailto:Jernej.Kaluza@fdv.uni-lj.si"
                            >Jernej.Kaluza@fdv.uni-lj.si</ref></hi></note>
            </docAuthor>
            <docAuthor>Jernej Amon Prodnik<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn2" n="***"><hi rend="bold"
                        >Researcher, Social Communication Research Centre, Faculty of Social
                        Sciences, University of Ljubljana, Kardeljeva ploščad 5, SI-1000
                            Ljubljana; <ref target="mailto:Jernej.Amon-Prodnik@fdv.uni-lj.si"
                            >Jernej.Amon-Prodnik@fdv.uni-lj.si</ref></hi></note>
            </docAuthor>
            <docImprint>
                <idno type="cobissType">Cobiss tip: 1.01</idno>
                <idno type="DOI">doi: https://doi.org/10.51663/pnz.62.1.6</idno>
            </docImprint>
            <div type="abstract" xml:lang="sl">
                <head>IZVLEČEK</head>
                <head><hi rend="italic">SPOMIN NA MEDIJE IN NOVINARSTVO V SOCIALISTIČNI JUGOSLAVIJI:
                        USTNI ZGODOVINSKI INTERVJUJI Z OBČINSTVI</hi></head>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Spominske študije so se v zadnjih desetletjih razvile v
                        plodovito interdisciplinarno raziskovalno področje, ki je veliko analitične
                        pozornosti posvetilo tudi socialistični Jugoslaviji in njenemu razpadu.
                        Kljub obstoju večjega števila študij o Jugoslaviji pa je vloga medijev in
                        novinarstva v svojem delovanju bila deležna občutno manj raziskovalne
                        pozornosti. V študiji raziskujeva, kakšno vlogo so te osrednje družbene
                        institucije igrale v vsakodnevnih življenjih prebivalcev Jugoslavije, v
                        kolikšni meri so jim zaupali in kako so vplivale na procese tvorjenja
                        individualnega in kolektivnega spomina. Te problematike se lotevava prek
                        analize 96 polstrukturiranih ustnih intervjujev z medijskimi občinstvi.
                        Intervjuvanci so v socialistični Jugoslaviji živeli večino svojega življenja
                        in so imeli nanjo osebne spomine, zaradi česar so lahko prispevali
                        edinstvene in dragocene vpoglede v to zgodovinsko obdobje, ki bi jih le
                        stežka pridobili na druge načine. Interpretativna analiza intervjujev je
                        temeljila na deduktivnem kodiranju intervjujev, razdelila pa sva jo na tri
                        dele: vsakodnevno uporabo medijev; zaupanje v medije in novinarstvo; ter
                        dojemanje jugoslovanske družbe. Študija predstavlja prvi celosten kratek
                        pregled zbranih podatkov in poudarja potencialno vrednost teh podatkov tudi
                        za prihodnje raziskave. Zbrani podatki razkrivajo tudi, kako intervjuvanci
                        razumejo in vrednotijo jugoslovanski režim, in na splošno zagotavljajo
                        veliko pestrejši pogled na socialistično preteklost, kot ga je ta
                        najpogosteje deležna v danes pogosto polarizirani javni razpravi. </hi></p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Ključne besede: spominske študije, tematizirane življenjske
                        zgodbe, socialistična Jugoslavija, uporaba medijev, zgodovina
                        novinarstva</hi></p>
            </div>
            <div type="abstract" xml:lang="en">
                <head>ABSTRACT</head>
                <p><hi rend="italic">In recent decades, memory studies have become a prominent
                        interdisciplinary field of research, with several studies focusing on the
                        specifics of socialist Yugoslavia and its demise. Less attention, however,
                        has been paid to the media and journalism in the life and functioning of the
                        state. This study explores what role these central social institutions
                        played in everyday lives of the population, what level of trust they enjoyed
                        amongst them, and how they influenced the processes of forming collective
                        and individual memory in socialist Yugoslavia. We consider these issues by
                        analysing 96 semi-structured oral history interviews with media audiences.
                        The interviewees had personal recollections of this era since they lived in
                        socialist Yugoslavia for most of their lives and could thus provide unique
                        and valuable insights not available by other means. Interpretative analysis
                        was performed with deductive coding of the interviews and was separated into
                        three parts: everyday media use; trust in the media and journalism; and
                        perceptions of socialist Yugoslavia. This paper presents a short overview of
                        the dataset and indicates its potential value for future research. The
                        gathered data also reveal the interviewees' understanding and evaluation of
                        the Yugoslav regime and, in general, provide a much more nuanced view of the
                        socialist past than is most often found in today's polarised public
                        debates.</hi></p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Keywords: memory studies; themed life-story interviews;
                        socialist Yugoslavia; media use; history of journalism</hi></p>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div>
                <head>Introduction</head>
                <p>In the last two decades, memory studies have become one of the most burgeoning
                    fields of research, often bringing together a variety of disciplines and with
                    them diverse perspectives on a range of historical issues. One such topic is
                    socialist Yugoslavia, which has received ample attention in the broader field of
                    cultural and media studies as an important source of memory and nostalgia of a
                    bygone era. Similarly, there has been extensive historiographical research
                    focusing on the specifics of Yugoslav socialism and the reasons for its
                    collapse. In both cases, however, little attention has been paid to how media
                    and journalism functioned in the socialist system, what role they played in the
                    everyday lives of its population, and what level of trust they enjoyed amongst
                    them. It is therefore hardly surprising that only a few studies have analysed
                    how audiences remember these arguably central social institutions.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn4" n="1">For exceptions, see Maruša Pušnik, <hi
                            rend="italic">Kulturna zgodovina elektronskih medijev</hi> (Ljubljana:
                        FDV, 2019), Ch. 3. Sabina Mihelj and Simon Huxtable, <hi rend="italic">From
                            Media Systems to Media Cultures </hi>(Cambridge: Cambridge University
                        Press, 2018), Ch. 8.</note>
                </p>
                <p>In the article, we explore how the memory of socialist Yugoslavia was created
                    through the past use of media and especially how audiences used and perceived
                    media and journalism in their everyday lives during the existence of Yugoslavia.
                    We address these issues by analysing 96 semi-structured interviews with media
                    audiences, where emphasis was placed on how the interviewees perceived
                    journalistic reporting in socialist Yugoslavia, how they used various types of
                    media, and whether they trusted these social institutions. Even though the focus
                    of the interviews was on the media and journalism, their overall scope was
                    wider. We wanted the interviewees to embed their memories in the broader context
                    and provide an evaluation of the socialist system as a whole. We were thus also
                    interested in the question of how the memory of the media in socialism
                    influenced the processes of collective and individual identity formation in
                    Yugoslavia.</p>
                <p>The article is divided into three parts. In the following section, section 2, we
                    present a brief synthesis of the key dilemmas that have emerged in memory
                    studies and how they can be linked to our research. In the second part of the
                    paper, section 3, we present the way the empirical material was collected, the
                    framework used for conducting the interviews, and details of the method used. We
                    gave considerable attention to these methodological and epistemological aspects
                    because of both the largely experimental nature of the research and the sheer
                    quantity of the unstructured data already gathered and which continues to grow.
                    The last part of the article, which incorporates sections 4, 5 and 6, overviews
                    some of the most notable topics addressed by the interviewees. Interpretative
                    analysis of the interviews was done with deductive coding and leads to some
                    general observations that may serve as an entry point for further analysis of
                    the material.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Memory Studies and Media Remembering</head>
                <p>Recent decades have seen remarkable interest in memory as a topic of public
                    discussion as well as a field of research. In an overview of the field, Erll
                    emphasises that “the practice of remembering and reflection on that practice
                    have become an all-encompassing sociocultural, interdisciplinary, and
                    international phenomenon”.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn5" n="2">Astrid Erll,<hi
                            rend="italic">Memory in Culture </hi>(London: Palgrave Macmillan, 2011),
                        1.</note> She therefore notes both the political and cultural prominence of
                    memory in the public sphere and the fact it must necessarily be treated as a
                    transdisciplinary research problem, bridging otherwise established academic
                    fields.</p>
                <p>There is a consensus on at least two interrelated assumptions made in memory
                    studies. First, memories are socially constructed by nature. They “are not
                    objective images of past perceptions, even less of a past reality. They are
                    subjective, highly selective reconstructions, dependent on the situation in
                    which they are recalled”.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn6" n="3">Erll,<hi
                            rend="italic">Memory in Culture</hi>, 8.</note> A related assumption was
                    already made by Halbwachs, a founding father of what later came to be called
                    memory studies. He stated that “a remembrance is in very large measure a
                    reconstruction of the past achieved with data borrowed from the present”.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn7" n="4">Maurice Halbwachs, <hi rend="italic">The Collective Memory</hi>
                        (New York: Harper Colophon Books, 1980), 69.</note> Second, the distinction
                    between individual and collective memory is unclear and often blurred, with a
                    constant interplay between them a prerequisite. Collective memory depends on
                    individual remembering, but that remembering happens in a socio-cultural context
                    where media and other institutions establish and shape knowledge of the
                        past.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn8" n="5">Erll, <hi rend="italic">Memory
                            in Culture</hi>, Ch. 4. </note> The past is always shared, making it
                    therefore debatable whether our own memories exist at all since “there are
                    social dimensions to the apparently most individual memories”.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn9" n="6">Jérôme Bourdon, “Media Remembering: The Contributions of
                        Life-Story Methodology to Memory/Media Research,” in: <hi rend="italic">On
                            Media Memory: Collective Memory in a New Media Age</hi>, eds. Motti
                        Neiger, Oren Meyers, and Eyal Zandberg (Basingstoke, New York: Palgrave
                        Macmillan, 2011), 64.</note> A similar observation was also made by
                    Halbwachs when noting that “our memories remain collective” even when we were
                    the only participants in certain events, since “in reality, we are never
                        alone”.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn10" n="7">Halbwachs, <hi rend="italic"
                            >The Collective Memory</hi>, 23.</note>
                </p>
                <quote>A man must often appeal to others’ remembrances to evoke his own past. He
                    goes back to reference points determined by society, hence outside himself.
                    Moreover, the individual memory could not function without words and ideas,
                    instruments the individual has not himself invented but appropriated from his
                    milieu. Nevertheless, it is true that one remembers only what he himself has
                    seen, done, felt, and thought at some time.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn11"
                        n="8">Ibidem, 21.</note></quote>
                <p>These two assumptions are also very important for our empirical study. Since it
                    is based on interviews with individuals, their recollections must be seen as
                    interpretations, not statements of fact. Memory is deceptive and prone to
                    various falsifications, with some authors observing that “talk is cheap”.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn12" n="9">Colin Jerolmack and Shamus Khan, “Talk Is
                        Cheap: Ethnography and the Attitudinal Fallacy,” <hi rend="italic"
                            >Sociological Methods &amp; Research</hi> 43, No. 2 (2014):
                        178–209.</note> Similarly to other cases, the recollections of our
                    interviewees were also shaped by the wider context in which they developed, by
                    the groups they formed part of, and by the intersubjective micro-context in
                    which they were uttered. Collective memory constructs history and typically
                    depends on interpretative struggles,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn13" n="10">
                        Todor Kuljić, <hi rend="italic">Kultura spominjanja</hi> (Ljubljana:
                        Filozofska Fakulteta, 2012).</note> which naturally extends to our
                    interviewees and their own recollections. This can be likened to the approach of
                    social constructivism, which explores “lived experiences and interactions with
                        others”.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn14" n="11">John W. Creswell, <hi
                            rend="italic">Qualitative Inquiry and Research Design</hi> (Thousand
                        Oaks: Sage, 2007), 36.</note>
                </p>
                <p>It must be stressed that collective memory is not necessarily the same as the
                    memory of the nation. Criticism of “methodological nationalism”, which posits a
                    nation as “the natural social and political form of the modern world” became
                    prominent in memory studies.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn15" n="12">Chiara De
                        Cesari and Ann Rigney, “Introduction,” in: <hi rend="italic">Transnational
                            Memory</hi>, eds. Chiara De Cesari and Ann Rigney (Berlin, Boston: De
                        Gruyter, 2014), 1. See also Andreas Wimmer and Nina Glick Schiller,
                        “Methodological Nationalism and Beyond,” <hi rend="italic">Global
                            Networks</hi> 2, No. 4 (2002).</note> Many authors based their criticism
                    on Anderson’s foundational study on the emergence of nationalisms.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn16" n="13">Benedict Anderson, <hi rend="italic"
                            >Imagined Communities </hi>(London, New York: Verso, 2006/1983).</note>
                    For Anderson, nations as communities could be viewed as something that is
                    necessarily imagined through various forms of mediated communication, which can
                    bring about specific solidarities. A similar claim can certainly be made about
                    memory since practices of remembrance can both create and preserve communities
                    and identities.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn17" n="14">Maja Breznik and Rastko
                        Močnik, “Organized memory and popular remembering: The encounter of
                        Yugonostalgia theories with socialism,” <hi rend="italic">Memory
                            Studies</hi> (October 2021): 2.</note> Another point of reference was
                    Hobsbawm, who pointed out that nationalisms are a result of the past, which is
                    necessarily made by people, often professional historians.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn18" n="15">Eric J. Hobsbawm “Ethnicity and Nationalism in Europe
                        Today,” in: <hi rend="italic">Mapping the Nation</hi>, ed. Gopal
                        Balakrishnan (London, New York: Verso), 255.</note> They are the ones who
                    are actively producing histories of particular nations, making any notion of
                    them being somehow ‘natural’ impossible. Močnik’s analysis demonstrates that a
                    similar logic of production of national histories was in place amongst prominent
                    Slovenian historians. <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn19" n="16">Rastko Močnik,
                            <hi rend="italic">O pisanju zgodovine</hi> (Ljubljana: Založba/*cf.,
                        2015), Ch. 4.</note> Furthermore, Hobsbawm also noted that, contrary to
                    common beliefs, modern traditions are typically invented and then ritualised to
                    inculcate specific social values and norms in nations.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn20" n="17">Eric J. Hobsbawm “Introduction: Inventing Traditions,”
                        in: <hi rend="italic">The Invention of Tradition</hi>, ed. Eric Hobsbawm and
                        Terence Ranger (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1983), 1–14.</note>
                </p>
                <p>We believe these issues are especially relevant for the post-socialist context
                    where memory of the socialist past does not necessarily correspond with the
                    national memory, which has usually been established by the mainstream official
                    discourse in transitional societies. Even more, in these narratives the entire
                    history of communism is often “reduced to its totalitarian dimension”,<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn21" n="18">Enzo Traverso, <hi rend="italic"
                            >Left-Wing Melancholia</hi> (New York: Columbia University Press, 2017),
                        2.</note> reproducing a binary, black-and-white understanding of history. As
                    Velikonja argues, Slovenia is today often perceived as the antipode of
                    Yugoslavia, and this “ideological binarism” is further upgraded through an
                    identity transformation: “We have transformed from former Yugoslavs into
                    contemporary Slovenes”.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn22" n="19">Mitja Velikonja,
                        “New Yugoslavism in contemporary popular music in Slovenia,” in: <hi
                            rend="italic">Post-Yugoslavia</hi>, eds. Dino Abazović and Mitja
                        Velikonja (Basingstoke, New York: Palgrave Macmillan, 2014), 62.</note> Even
                    if this transformation is suppressed in the nationalistic discourse, which bets
                    on the idea of stability of the national identity throughout history,<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn23" n="20">Jernej Kosi, “Je bil proces formiranja
                        slovenskega naroda v 19. stoletju res zgolj končni nasledek tisočletne
                        slovenske kontinuitete?,” <hi rend="italic">Zgodovinski časopis </hi>64, No.
                        1–2 (2010), 154–75.</note> processes of modern identity formation, as it is
                    also clear in our analysis of the interviews, were very turbulent even in recent
                        history.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn24" n="21">See Aleida Assmann and
                        Linda Shortt, eds., <hi rend="italic">Memory and Political Change</hi>
                        (London: Palgrave Macmillan, 2012).</note> Similarly, the aforementioned
                    binary opposition is rarely emphasised by the interviewees themselves.</p>
                <p>As a structural consequence of this suppression of the socialist past, the memory
                    of this period became part of the “underground” discourse, excluded from
                    mainstream discourses or what can also be called “official memory engineering”,
                    where retrospective remembering is highly selective in the quest for shared
                        memories.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn25" n="22">Breznik and Močnik,
                        “Organized memory and popular remembering.” Compare to Hobsbawm,
                        “Introduction: Inventing Traditions.”</note> These alternative practices of
                    remembering were mainly reflected in the rise of Yugonostalgia on a cultural
                    level, in informal settings, and in the non-institutionalised practices of
                        remembering.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn26" n="23">Velikonja, “New
                        Yugoslavism,” 57–95.</note> This is one of the main reasons that oral
                    history interviews concerning the socialist past have become one of the methods
                    most frequently used in the regional development of memory studies.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn27" n="24">See for example Valeria Kasamara and Anna
                        Sorokina, “Post-Soviet collective memory,« <hi rend="italic">Communist and
                            Post-Communist Studies</hi> 48, No. 2–3 (2015), 137–45.</note> After
                    1989, namely, socialism remains present in this region generally in the form of
                    a memory which “captures the meaning of the past as a lived experience”, or,
                    more exactly, in the form of a “testimony of an experience related to history by
                    an emotional link”.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn28" n="25">Traverso, <hi
                            rend="italic">Left-Wing Melancholia</hi>, 97. </note> The popularity of
                    Yugonostalgia was followed by extensive research into post-socialist nostalgia,
                    which differentiated itself from traditional political historiography, but also
                    largely avoided any direct confrontations with their portrayals of history.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn29" n="26">Breznik and Močnik, “Organized memory and
                        popular remembering,” 6–9.</note></p>
                <p>The binary opposition between the (national, Slovenian) present and the
                    (multinational, Yugoslav) past, which is specific to the post-socialist
                        context,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn30" n="27">Maruša Pušnik, “Media
                        memorial discourses and memory struggles in Slovenia,” <hi rend="italic"
                            >Memory Studies</hi> 12, No. 4 (2017), 433–50.</note> was already etched
                    deeply into the framework for conducting the interviews, in which the binarism
                    between the interviewer (grandchild) and interviewee (grandparent) structurally
                    corresponded with the opposition between capitalism and socialism, together with
                    a series of related oppositions and transitions.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn31" n="28">Mitja Velikonja, “Lost in Transition: Nostalgia for
                        Socialism in Post-socialist Countries,” <hi rend="italic">East European
                            Politics and Societies</hi>, 23 No. 4 (2009), 536.</note> Even if such
                    a "bi-polar vision" is an unavoidable structural necessity in research on memory
                    of the socialist past, it has often been acknowledged as an epistemological
                        obstacle.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn32" n="29">Anikó Imre, <hi
                            rend="italic">TV Socialism</hi> (Durham: Duke University Press, 2016),
                        3.</note> In recent years, an increasing amount of literature has focused
                    specifically on the memory of media consumption in socialism<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn33" n="30">See Imre, <hi rend="italic">TV Socialism</hi>. Mihelj
                        and Huxtable, <hi rend="italic">From Media Systems to Media Cultures.</hi>
                        Pušnik, <hi rend="italic">Kulturna zgodovina elektronskih
                        medijev</hi>.</note> and that research – especially because the memory on
                    media consumption is associated with the memory of leisure time, fun and
                    relaxation – also reveals the complex and non-binary nature of the interviewees’
                    evaluation of the past.</p>
                <p>Research on media consumption in socialism is important not simply because it
                    constitutes an important source for memory studies, but also for media and
                    communication studies that aim to analyse the perception of socialist media by
                    audiences, which was rarely an object of concurrent empirical research in the
                    socialist regimes.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn34" n="31">See Slavko Splichal
                        and France Vreg, <hi rend="italic">Množično komuniciranje in razvoj
                            demokracije</hi> (Ljubljana: Komunist, 1986). Gertrude J. Robinson,
                            <hi rend="italic">Tito’s Maverick Media</hi> (Chicago: University of
                        Illinois Press, 1977). </note> Therefore, oral history interviews represent
                    a basic source for understanding how public life functioned in socialism.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Methodology: Oral History Interviews with Audiences</head>
                <p>People who followed the media in a certain historical period may be seen as
                    valuable sources of insights into the past. They can provide explanations and
                    interpretations concerning the everyday use of different media types, while also
                    addressing the issue of trust in these institutions and subsequently the wider
                    social system. Since such personal insights are hardly available using other
                    means – and with the availability of suitable interviewees naturally diminishing
                    over time – our longer-term research goal was to build a comprehensive archive
                    of oral history interviews. Projects like this may prove to be even more
                    important given that the “everyday practices of readers, viewers and listeners
                    are typically beyond the remit of sources found in institutional archival
                        collections”.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn35" n="32">Sabina Mihelj and
                        Jérôme Bourdon, “Doing audience history,” <hi rend="italic">European Journal
                            of Communication</hi> 30, No. 1 (2015): 3. </note>
                </p>
                <p>All of the interviews were transcribed for the purposes of future analysis and
                    are continually being archived in the Social Science Data Archive located at the
                    Faculty of Social Sciences (University of Ljubljana),<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn36" n="33">See: Jernej Amon Prodnik, <hi rend="italic"
                            >Novinarstvo v socialistični Jugoslaviji in imaginariji medijev skozi
                            občinstvo</hi>, <hi rend="italic">2019 </hi>(Ljubljana: Arhiv
                        družboslovnih podatkov, 2020). Jernej Amon Prodnik and Jernej Kaluža, <hi
                            rend="italic">Novinarstvo v socialističnih Jugoslaviji in imaginarij
                            medijev skozi občinstvo 2020 </hi>(Ljubljana: Arhiv družboslovnih
                        podatkov, 2021). Jernej Amon Prodnik and Jernej Kaluža, <hi rend="italic"
                            >Novinarstvo v socialističnih Jugoslaviji in imaginarij medijev skozi
                            občinstvo 2021</hi> (Ljubljana: Arhiv družboslovnih podatkov,
                        2022).</note> which ensures their future unavailability does not simply turn
                    them into “dead knowledge”.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn37" n="34">Erll, <hi
                            rend="italic">Memory in Culture,</hi> 4. </note> The empirical dataset
                    currently consists of 96 semi-structured interviews performed in-person in
                    Slovenian. We first constructed a general-purpose framework for conducting the
                    interviews, with thematic areas defined very broadly so as not to miss certain
                    phenomena with too narrow a focus. This opens up many possible avenues for
                    future analysis of the archived material (e.g. by using focus groups) and means
                    these interviews can serve as an initial exploratory step for studying more
                    specific phenomena that here might only be mentioned in passing. Yet, a downside
                    of this broadness is that the overarching insights into the material in the
                    sections below are inevitably sketchy and introductory and thus call for further
                    exploration.</p>
                <div>
                    <head><hi rend="italic">Ethical dilemmas and framework of the
                            interviews</hi></head>
                    <p>The interviews were conducted by first-year undergraduate students attending
                        the History of Journalism course (Journalism study programme at the Faculty
                        of Social Sciences). During this course, students received hands-on training
                        and thorough instructions on how to carry out the interviews and transcribe
                        the audio recordings, with attention paid to the possible ethical issues
                            involved.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn38" n="35">See Jernej Amon
                            Prodnik “Nekaj etičnih dilem pri vključevanju študentov v raziskovalno
                            delo,” <hi rend="italic">Arhiv družboslovnih podatkov</hi>, <ref
                                target="http://www.adp.fdv.uni-lj.si/blog/2021/blog/nekaj-eticnih-dilem-pri-vkljucevanju-studentov-v-raziskovalno-delo%20(20"
                                >http://www.adp.fdv.uni-lj.si/blog/2021/blog/nekaj-eticnih-dilem-pri-vkljucevanju-studentov-v-raziskovalno-delo
                                (20</ref>. 3. 2022).</note> We aimed for complete transparency and
                        tried to clear up any pitfalls of doing this kind of research as quickly as
                        they appeared. Even though conducting interviews was part of the students’
                        study obligations, archiving and thereby making them available for future
                        research was entirely optional and had no influence on their grade. An
                        informed consent form, which detailed the research project and future access
                        to the interviews, was a prerequisite. In the form, interviewees had an
                        option to remain anonymous.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn39" n="36">
                            Pseudonyms are used for those interviewees who opted for anonymity, as
                            indicated by the use of quotation marks, for instance ‘<hi rend="italic"
                                >Prijazna Gospa’</hi> (Eng. <hi rend="italic">Kind Lady</hi>). In
                            all other cases, interviewees are referred to by the first letter of
                            their first name and surname, for instance <hi rend="italic">P.
                                Bezjak</hi>. In the majority of cases, the pseudonyms were chosen by
                            interviewees themselves if they had decided on anonymity.</note> They
                        could also retract statements they deemed too personal or sensitive for the
                        archived version of the interview. Where appropriate, strict anonymisation
                        was applied throughout the interviews to avoid third parties being
                        identified.</p>
                    <p>We developed a framework for conducting the interviews that assured a
                        standardised structure for the future comparability of the interviews, while
                        providing the interviewers with a general direction and an overview of the
                        topics to be covered. This interview matrix included three broad thematic
                        areas: 1) Media use; 2) Trust in the media and journalism; and 3) Perception
                        of Yugoslav society. We provided the interviewers with a description of
                        these areas and several sample questions. This gave them a sense of the
                        topics that could be addressed, but also left them with enough leeway to
                        have a genuine in-depth conversation with their interlocutors.</p>
                    <p>To provide more control and a tidier structure, the interview matrix further
                        divided interviews into four stages of life: childhood, youth, adulthood,
                        and senior years. All of the thematic areas mentioned above were to be
                        discussed separately in these stages of life, which – depending on when
                        interviewees were born – broadly corresponded with different historical
                        periods of socialist Yugoslavia. Adulthood, for instance, in most cases
                        overlapped with the peak of Titoist Yugoslavia in the 1970s, while senior
                        years largely corresponded with the rise of nationalisms and disintegration
                        processes. We also added “events of reference”, where the aim was to help
                        interviewees remember particular historical periods better. These included
                        the Vietnam War, the Space Race, or Tito's death amongst others. It was up
                        to the interviewers to sensibly connect these events to a specific stage of
                        an interviewee’s life.</p>
                    <p>The interview matrix was also followed in the textual analysis of the
                        interviews performed in NVivo, software for organising and analysing
                        qualitative (unstructured) data. Such a deductive coding strategy is common
                        while analysing interview transcripts.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn40"
                            n="37">See, for example, Creswell, <hi rend="italic">Qualitative Inquiry
                                and Research Design</hi>. </note> In the analysis, the qualitative
                        approach of life history was combined with the methods used in oral history
                        and memory studies of media consumption.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head><hi rend="italic">Properties of the sample</hi></head>
                    <p>Our aim was to encompass as many time periods of media use in socialist
                        Yugoslavia as possible, ranging from the early 1950s up to the independence
                        of Slovenia in 1991. This is why the students were instructed to choose
                        interviewees born between 1940 and 1955 (the arithmetic mean and median of
                        the sample are both 1947, the mode is 1946). It was recommended they spend
                        approximately 1 hour speaking to their interviewees. The lengths of the 96
                        archived interviews vary between 29 minutes and 180 minutes, with the
                        arithmetic mean for the interviews being 59 minutes, the median 54 minutes,
                        and a standard deviation of 25 minutes.</p>
                    <p>Even though this was not intentional, since we had limited control over the
                        sampling process and could not aim for true representativeness, the
                        demographic characteristics of the interviewees in our study do not deviate
                        significantly from those of the general population in the same age bracket
                        (65 and older). Men are slightly overrepresented in the sample (53.1%) and
                        the interviewees also seem to have a better education since one-third hold
                        at least a high school degree. The large majority of our informants (around
                        95%) were already retired at the time of the interview. About 30% of them
                        were living in urban areas and 70% in rural ones, which more or less
                        overlaps with the shares in the general population (in Slovenia, two-thirds
                        of the population lives in places with fewer than 10,000 inhabitants<note
                            place="foot" xml:id="ftn41" n="38">See Ana Vučina Vršnak, “Slovenija
                            ostaja ruralna dežela,” <hi rend="italic">Dnevnik </hi>9. 6. 2012, <ref
                                target="http://www.dnevnik.si/1042534899"
                                >www.dnevnik.si/1042534899</ref> (20. 3. 2022).</note>). If we were
                        to consider the place of birth and where the interviewees grew up, the
                        number of people living in rural areas would be even higher.</p>
                    <p>We could expect overrepresentation of the informants coming from central
                        Slovenia because they were chosen by students who study in Ljubljana, but
                        this bias was in fact not so pronounced: 28 interviewees for instance came
                        from the Central Slovenia statistical region, 20 from the Drava region, 11
                        from the Savinja region, 9 from the Southeast Slovenia statistical region, 8
                        from the Gorizia region etc. Apart from the Coastal-Karst and Mura
                        statistical regions, which are underrepresented, these numbers roughly
                        correspond to the general shares in the population.</p>
                    <p>In the majority of cases, students chose their grandparents or other older
                        relatives as their interviewees, meaning the sample was generally based on
                        convenience and ease of accessibility. It must therefore be stressed that
                        people who were living a family life and had children and grandchildren are
                        very likely to be overrepresented in the sample. Another source of imbalance
                        was the explicit recommendation that talkativeness, accessibility, good
                        memory, and openness to discussion should be considered while choosing
                        interviewees so as to make the interviews richer in content.</p>
                    <p>Finally, it must be noted that the vast majority of interviews was conducted
                        in the month of May in 2019, 2020 and 2021, when the summer semester was
                        coming to a close. Although this was not the topic of the interviews,
                        contemporary socio-political events such as SARS-CoV-2 pandemic, the
                        illiberal turn in politics and the continuous conflicts between the Slovenian
                        government and the media were at least implicitly addressed by the
                        interviewees and contrasted with examples from the past.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Everyday Media Use in Socialist Yugoslavia</head>
                <p>Media use was the central topic of the interviews but, unlike some other research
                    based on oral media history,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn42" n="39">Pušnik, <hi
                            rend="italic">Kulturna zgodovina elektronskih medijev</hi>.</note> the
                    focus was solely on the (journalistic) mass media, namely television, radio, and
                    the press. Use of personal communication channels, for instance telephones, or
                    storage media formats, such as LP records or cassettes, was not addressed. The
                    development of the mass media was closely linked to the general development of
                    socialist Yugoslavia and corresponds to the accelerated modernisation of
                    socialist society between the 1950s and 1980s. In that time frame, a transition
                    from rural to urban areas and the general transformation from a predominantly
                    agricultural to an industrial society occurred.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn43"
                        n="40">Eric D. Gordy, <hi rend="italic">The Culture of Power in Serbia</hi>
                        (University Park PA: The Pennsylvania State University Press, 1999): 9.
                    </note> The availability of the media thus saw considerable growth in
                    Yugoslavia: in 1950 a total of 357 newspapers was published, while in 1974 this
                    figure had risen to 1,988 newspapers, with monthly magazines seeing the biggest
                    growth, from 61 to 633. In the same time frame, the number of radio sets rose
                    more than tenfold, from 336,000 to 4,081,000, with a similar change happening
                    with television sets, from 9.2 households per TV subscription in 1965 to 1.7 in
                        1980.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn44" n="41">Robinson, <hi rend="italic"
                            >Tito’s Maverick Media</hi>, 20, 21. Splichal and Vreg, <hi rend="italic"
                            >Množično komuniciranje in razvoj demokracije</hi>, 72, 80–84.
                    </note></p>
                <p>The rise of the media accompanied broader socio-political processes, with radical
                    changes also occurring in individual lifestyles. Even though this was not the
                    topic of the interviews, these changes were implicitly or explicitly addressed.
                    This is not surprising because remembering the media implies “remembering
                    contacts with a certain world ‘out there’, which comes to exist through the
                    television screen” (or, we might add, other types of media) and “generates a
                    variety of interactions that cannot be reduced to simple viewing”.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn45" n="42">Jérôme Bourdon, “Some sense of time:
                        Remembering television.” <hi rend="italic">History and Memory </hi>15, No. 2
                        (2003): 13. See also Alice Bardan, “Remembering socialist entertainment:
                        Romanian television, gestures and intimacy.” <hi rend="italic">European
                            Journal of Cultural Studies</hi> 20, No. 3 (2017): 10. </note>
                </p>
                <div>
                    <head><hi rend="italic">Everyday use of the radio and the role of the
                            press</hi></head>
                    <p>The post-war situation in the early 1950s was a starting point for most of
                        the interviews, with radio often mentioned as the most important medium in
                        the childhood and youth of the interviewees. In 1963, namely, more than 90%
                        of people living in Yugoslavia listened to the radio.<note place="foot"
                            xml:id="ftn46" n="43">Splichal and Vreg, <hi rend="italic">Množično
                                komuniciranje in razvoj demokracije</hi>, 84. </note> Radio was thus
                        perceived as the most important media, even though newspapers also played an
                        influential role in certain households. As one interviewee notes: “Radio was
                        always in the kitchen; it was the centre of everything” (‘Športni
                        navdušenec’). Similar domestication of radio can be observed in other
                        interviews. Its use was often described as an event that unified the whole
                        family: “Radio was a sacred thing, it was turned on only at certain times of
                        the day, when daily reports or music shows were broadcasted; the whole
                        family – and sometimes even some neighbours and friends – gathered on such
                        occasions” (‘Planinski Sokol’).</p>
                    <p>Especially popular were radio programmes, which were suitable for group
                        listening: radio broadcasts with folk-pop music such as <hi rend="italic"
                            >Četrtkov večer</hi> [Eng. <hi rend="italic">Thursday evening</hi>],
                        testimonies of the Partisans fighting in the Second World War anti-fascist
                        movement in <hi rend="italic">Še pomnite tovariši?</hi> [Eng. <hi
                            rend="italic">Do You Still Recall, Comrades?</hi>], and the Sunday noon
                        broadcast. “We gathered in the evenings after we had finished our work /…/
                        and we listened to the radio, especially to music shows. When I was a child,
                        we sang a lot. In the evening one could hear singing in almost every house,
                        particularly when people were busy with the tasks that were usually done
                        together like pumpkin peeling or the husking of corn” (‘Prijazna
                        Gospa’).</p>
                    <p>Listening to radio, therefore, fitted in quite smoothly with the existing
                        social practices in the post-war period. Even though radio played an
                        important role on various occasions and in specific social settings, media
                        consumption was often restricted since it was regarded as something that
                        encourages idleness. It was thus opposed to the urge to work as much as
                        possible, as especially pronounced in the 1950s, a time characterised by
                        modest living conditions in a mainly agrarian society. Interviewees who were
                        still children at the time often described how their parents limited their
                        media use: “There was not a lot of time for fun /…/ we had to work in the
                        fields with our parents, we only relaxed in the evening or if it was
                        raining” (A. Golež).</p>
                    <p>Like radio, print was often associated with a particular social function of
                        connecting the community in this early period: “I still remember how my
                        mother said: ‘the neighbour brought the newspaper!’ We didn’t buy our own
                        newspapers, of course” (I. Markič). Newspapers, magazines and books were
                        often shared or stored after reading so they could be re-used, and the
                        topics appearing in them were often discussed by people. Reading was also
                        regularly considered as part of leisure time: “We had time to read on Sunday
                        afternoon, when we had fights over the newspapers from the previous week”
                        (F. R. Steiner).</p>
                    <p>The interviewees often recalled their parents reading the press. In these
                        memories, on most occasions the newspaper belonged to the <hi rend="italic"
                            >pater familias</hi>: “My father was somewhat politically educated, and
                        he sometimes read for us from the newspapers” (I. Trotovšek). Everyday
                        socialisation typically occurred in a common physical space in local
                        environments and the interviewees often perceived their life as being
                        separated from the topics discussed in the press, especially when it came to
                        politics. One respondent stated: “Those were the years when I was not
                        interested in political stuff /…/ I mostly struggled with my own things,
                        with work, friends, and women” (‘Lojtra’).</p>
                    <p>Many interviewees recalled the role of the magazines, such as popular
                        magazine <hi rend="italic">Tedenska Tribuna</hi> (Eng. <hi rend="italic"
                            >Weekly Tribune</hi>, popularly called <hi rend="italic">TT</hi>), which
                        gained in popularity because their approach adapted to their audiences’
                        needs and was lighter in nature. Magazines devoted to specific audience
                        profiles also became more prominent in the 1960s, for example <hi
                            rend="italic">Življenje in tehnika</hi> (Eng. <hi rend="italic">Life and
                            Technology</hi>) for technically engaged people, or <hi rend="italic"
                            >Ciciban</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Pionirski list</hi> for children and
                        youth. Religious books published by Mohorjeva družba and the (bi)weekly
                        Catholic magazine <hi rend="italic">Družina</hi> (Eng. <hi rend="italic"
                            >Family</hi>) were also popular and were not prohibited in Yugoslavia,
                        as some might assume.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head><hi rend="italic">Television reigns supreme</hi></head>
                    <p>Certain interviewees, especially those who had lived in an urban environment,
                        were already familiar with the moving image format that television brought
                        to their lives early on as they had experienced it in the cinema. In most
                        cases, the first memories of TV were very detailed and usually referred to
                        the early 1960s when collective watching was common. This occurred in either
                        the richer households of a village or town that could afford to buy a
                        television set and allowed their neighbours (notably children) to join in
                        watching or in semi-public spaces like community halls:</p>
                    <quote>I was in seventh grade when our village got its first television set /…/
                        we had a club in the cooperative house [Slo. zadružni dom]. People bought a
                        TV set together, with common funds. /…/ Adults watched daily reports and
                        talk shows, and we watched movies and music. /…/ Later, my father came to
                        the idea that we should buy our own TV set, but my brother and I were
                        against it – we were afraid that we wouldn’t be allowed to go into that club
                        anymore. (‘Rumena Magnolija’) </quote>
                    <p>As the above anecdote reveals, socialising was an important aspect of this
                        ritual for many, but only the early experiences were collective. Towards the
                        end of the 1960s and later, television became an essential item in most
                        households, while the practice of watching TV became either individualised
                        or at least reserved for members of the nuclear family. In this period, most
                        interviewees moved out of their parents' houses and completed their
                        education. They began to establish their own families, usually in their own
                        dwelling. A living room with a TV set became the main venue for consuming
                        media and replaced the rural kitchen where large families had gathered to
                        listen to the radio. A predominantly rural lifestyle, related to the cycles
                        of nature and farm work, was in many interviewees’ stories replaced by a
                        modern working lifestyle in which TV often represented the biggest source of
                        evening relaxation, especially for men: “This is like a chronic disease or
                        addiction /…/ I have always watched the evening news programme. At that
                        hour, there had to be peace in the house” (D. Rajtmajer). Women, in
                        contrast, were not so accustomed to watching the evening news and preferred
                        movies or TV shows, which often started after the children had gone to bed.
                        Of course, one can also find notable exceptions to this stereotypical
                        pattern in the sample.</p>
                    <p>Television was crucial in the popularisation of sports fan culture in
                        Yugoslavia, with interviewees mentioning ski jumping, skiing, the Olympic
                        Games, football World Cups, and basketball World Cups as examples. There is
                        little doubt that the most prominent example of a televised event was Tito’s
                        death in 1980, as announced by the TV anchor Tomaž Terček. With his
                        recognisable and memorable voice and always serious manner, most
                        interviewees could recall exactly what they were doing and how they felt
                        when he uttered those famous words: “Comrade Tito has died”. When the
                        interviewees were asked which journalists they could recall from Yugoslavia,
                        most remembered TV anchors and announcers, which goes far to demonstrate the
                        role of TV in producing celebrities, even in a non-Western context. Memories
                        of the most important public events – from the first moon landing in 1969 to
                        the war for Slovenian independence in 1991 – were in one way or another
                        connected to television watching, but often quite vaguely, which confirms
                        Bourdon’s point that “much of our media experience, especially in an
                        increasingly mediated world, is not encoded (or not primarily) as specific
                        ‘media experience’”.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn47" n="44">Bourdon, “Media
                            Remembering,” 61. </note>
                    </p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Trust in the Media and Journalism</head>
                <quote>There was no dilemma concerning whether “to believe or not”. I would say that
                    we trusted what we were watching and listening to<hi rend="italic">.</hi> (A.
                    Žabjek)</quote>
                <p>Memories connected to people’s feelings and attitudes regarding the past are
                    especially prone to falsification since emotions, opinions and beliefs we have
                    of certain phenomena today can easily affect the perception of our past
                    attitudes to them.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn48" n="45">Michael Ross,
                        “Relation of implicit theories to the construction of personal histories,”
                            <hi rend="italic">Psychological Review</hi> 96, No. 2 (1989):
                        341–57.</note> While these issues must be taken into account, the
                    interviewees’ responses seem unambiguous: most conceded that they believed in
                    the information transmitted, particularly before Tito’s death in 1980, and were
                    generally not critical of journalistic reporting in socialist Yugoslavia. They
                    did not look for alternative sources of information, but also did not regard
                    themselves as being deprived of different worldviews. Statements like “We
                    trusted the media, there was no alternative” (‘Bela Lilija’) or “We believed
                    everything, there was only one TV channel” (A. Žener), were common in the
                    sample.</p>
                <p>Comparisons between trust in the media and the absence of diverse sources is one
                    of the most frequent topics the interviewees noted, especially in their
                    childhood and youth. When asked about their belief in the news, they often made
                    comparisons with today’s overabundance of information from many different – and
                    often opposing – sources. It is only in such an environment that the question of
                    belief in the news could even be raised. One interviewee for instance mentioned
                    that her first doubts about credibility appeared when the media became similar
                    to what it is today: “People who were supposed to inform us started to insult
                    each other /…/, the same event has many different interpretations, I don’t know
                    what is right anymore” (‘Lepa gospa’).</p>
                <p>The everyday influence of the wider social context was frequently acknowledged by
                    the interviewees as an important reason for them trusting the media and the
                    Yugoslav system in general: “That’s how we were raised” (P. Bezjak); “My father
                    told me not to criticise /…/ I didn’t like it when people were criticising
                    things” (J. Krek); “We trusted the media because of the ‘brotherhood and unity’,
                    we were unified: one for all, all for one” (D. Borovnik). Particularly for the
                    earlier periods, it seems that criticism was often considered rude and
                    unnecessary, as something tearing apart the social cohesion. That is why
                    criticism of journalistic reporting did not form part of usual small talk, as is
                    often the case today.</p>
                <div>
                    <head><hi rend="italic">(Lack of) Information diversity and sources of
                            criticism</hi></head>
                    <p>The absence of information plurality was often mentioned while describing the
                        media situation in the 1950s, when radio was the main source of daily news
                        for many households. In this historical period, a diversity of political
                        views was generally seen as a threat to social cohesion due to the
                        devastating consequences of ideological differences during the Second World
                        War. Older people who had lived through that epoch often discouraged any
                        kind of political debate, even in private settings. Those in search of
                        different worldviews frequently used foreign media and depended on the radio
                        signals coming from across the borders. The influence of Western media was
                        especially important for people living in the border regions: <hi
                            rend="italic">Radio Trst</hi> (Eng. <hi rend="italic">Trieste</hi>) was followed in the Upper
                        Carniola region and <hi rend="italic">Radio Graz</hi> in Carinthia and some
                        parts of the Styria region. Slovenian programmes broadcast on <hi
                            rend="italic">Radio Vatican</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Voice of
                            America</hi> were also often mentioned as sources of information with
                        alternative, 'Westernised' political views, while <hi rend="italic">Radio
                            Luxembourg</hi> was important for introducing Yugoslavia to Western pop
                        culture in the early 1960s.</p>
                    <p>At least to some extent, journalists could criticise specific local problems
                        and flaws, but as the interlocutors realise today it was not possible to
                        doubt the social system’s foundations. For instance, one interviewee noted:
                        “There would be a special kind of problem if someone tried to criticise the
                        ideal of brotherhood and unity among different nations /…/, this ideal had
                        to be preserved and respected” (H. Molan).</p>
                    <p>The first signs of criticism usually corresponded with youthful stubbornness
                        and disobedience. In some cases, this was related with the reading of comics
                        (Miki Muster and his famous comic <hi rend="italic">Zvitorepec</hi> were
                        mentioned many times) and satirical magazines like <hi rend="italic"
                            >Pavliha</hi>, which enjoyed high circulation and popularity. In this
                        context, Fran Miličinski – Ježek (Eng. <hi rend="italic">The Little
                            Hedgehog</hi>), the award-winning satirist, comedian, director, writer,
                        chansonnier and self-proclaimed clown, was often mentioned as a figure whose
                        jokes were seen as an implicit critique of the system. Similarly to how
                        Bardan describes the New Year’s Eve television programme in socialist
                            Romania<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn49" n="46">Bardan, “Remembering
                            Socialist Entertainment,” 11.</note>, it seems that what contributed to
                        the popularity of Ježek’s performances was its mildly subversive nature,
                        ambiguous expressions, and “the structure of feeling” describing the
                        bittersweet life of an ordinary little man in the socialist reality, with
                        whom audiences could easily identify. The structure of jokes circulating in
                        non-formal environments (usually directed against important members of The
                        Party, such as Stane Dolanc) followed the same recipe.</p>
                    <p>The rise of liberal politics and student social movements in Yugoslavia in
                        the late 1960s and early 1970s was not perceived as a turning point for most
                        of the interviewees, who also paid scant attention to the political crisis
                        related to the Croatian Spring (also known as Maspok) between 1967 and 1971.
                        They usually saw this as a conflict between the Croats and Serbs, which was
                        not as important for the situation in Slovenia. Expressions of nationalistic
                        tendencies were often recognised as a classic example of forbidden content
                        in the media sphere of socialist Yugoslavia, but the interviewees often
                        perceived this censorship as a positive side-effect of stricter control of
                        the media content, particularly when they took account of the consequences
                        of such nationalistic discourse later in the 1990s. Even the first memories
                        concerning the diversity and pluralism of political views in the media are
                        often associated with the rise of conservativism and nationalism during the
                        1980s, when, for instance, “Slovenian and Serbian views on the situation in
                        Yugoslavia began to diverge radically” (‘Dušan Anon’).</p>
                    <p>The male interviewees’ experience of military service was often described as
                        a paradigmatic example of the actual solidarity existing among the different
                        Yugoslav nations where the principle of “brotherhood and unity” was, on one
                        hand, manifested in practice, but where on the other any expressions of
                        disobedience or rebelliousness were also strictly rejected. One interviewee
                        mentioned that his hair had to be shortened due to the military rules,
                        another had minor problems after criticising the quality of weapons, while
                        many of them remembered the mandatory daily practice of group watching the
                        evening news on television, which they regarded as a typical example of the
                        authoritarian tendencies of the system.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head><hi rend="italic">Censorship and contradictions of freedom of
                            speech</hi></head>
                    <p>While discussing criticism and censorship, the interviewees often related
                        these phenomena to interpersonal relationships. This seemed a bigger concern
                        for them than potential control of the media content. Instances of
                        undercover agents monitoring discussions in pubs and inns were frequently
                        mentioned. Similarly, anecdotes were given about encounters with police or
                        customs officers. Both were perceived as incarnations of the non-democratic
                        system since they could act strictly if not treated properly. Problems that
                        emerged with the work environment and career development due to the public
                        expression of political opinions, religious affiliation or a controversial
                        family history are another common theme discussed in the interviews. Still,
                        these anecdotal cases were not very pronounced and were told almost as
                        trivia that rarely had a defining influence on the interviewees’ lives or
                        their overall attitude to the system. They should therefore be evaluated
                        systematically against other historical sources, which lies beyond the scope
                        of this article.</p>
                    <p>In general, answers regarding freedom of speech vary widely. Some
                        interviewees stated they did not dare to be critical even in a private
                        setting, especially in the 1950s. Others mentioned there were no particular
                        issues attracting such criticism among friends or co-workers. Some
                        interviewees did not regard themselves as being in any way deprived of free
                        speech, while others noted they did not even have a need for any such
                        criticism. This was explained as an outcome of their relative happiness,
                        satisfaction with individual and social life, and feeling of social
                        security: “As kids, we lived in a bubble, without problems, without deep
                        considerations as to what was going on in the media” (H. Molan). “There were
                        no [political] parties, no questions as to who to believe. I got my first
                        job and went there immediately. Everything was pleasant” (R. M. Perlič).</p>
                    <p>Such favourable social circumstances not only led to a lack of interest in
                        criticism, but also a broader absence of interest in journalistic reporting:
                        “I wasn’t deeply interested in the reporting by the media. When you are
                        young, you are not interested in that, but I never doubted whether it was
                        true. /…/ We were living our lives, socialising, playing games /…/ we didn’t
                        ask ourselves whether we trusted the media” (‘Cvetoča orhideja’). Especially
                        news about domestic politics – a prime example being summaries of various
                        Party meetings – were considered boring and separate from the interviewees’
                        actual lives.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Perceptions of Socialist Yugoslavia</head>
                <quote>“To some extent, you’ll always be limited, remember that. Always!”. (F.
                    Mastnak)</quote>
                <p>As observed in the literature, self-consistency in identity presentation is a
                    general tendency among the interviewees.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn50" n="47"
                        > See Joshua Kaldor-Robinson, “The Virtual and the Imaginary,” <hi
                            rend="italic">Oxford Development Studies</hi> 30, No. 2 (2002):
                        177–87.</note> In our study, where the relationship between interviewer and
                    interviewee also corresponds to the seemingly contradictory binary opposition
                    between the present and the past (and simultaneously between capitalism and
                    socialism), this tendency was even more pronounced: the interviewee’s perception
                    of their own identity was in fact rarely caught in two paradigms opposed to each
                    other. They did not regard themselves as being subjected to some radical
                    transformation, such as what happened to the socio-political system in the
                    transition years.</p>
                <p>The interviewees’ opinions of the socialist regime and quality of the media
                    reporting offer insights that reject simple and unambiguous black-and-white
                    narratives of the past. They also partially reveal the complex logic of the
                    identity-formation process during (and after) socialist Yugoslavia, while
                    serving as a good illustration of why unequivocal anti-communism and demonising
                    of the socialist past have difficulties becoming an attractive ideology in
                    Slovenia with mass political appeal. As emphasised by Wilmer, “people living in
                    Yugoslavia identified themselves in terms of multiple, intersecting, and
                    sometimes overlapping identities”.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn51" n="48">
                        Frankie Wilmer, <hi rend="italic">The Social Construction of Man, the State
                            and War Identity, Conflict, and Violence in Former Yugoslavia</hi>
                        (London: Routledge, 2002), 81. </note> Even if their Slovenian identity was
                    always important and not necessarily suppressed, people also identified as
                    Yugoslavs, as workers, and as active builders of society.</p>
                <div>
                    <head><hi rend="italic">Opinion on the regime and identity
                        formation</hi></head>
                    <p>The Yugoslav identity based on the “normative foundations of anticapitalist
                        Marxism”, which is also “anti-Stalinist” in nature, “emphasized the
                        ‘socialist’ rather than communist basis for Yugoslav society,
                        ‘self-management’ in the economy, and the coexistence, however uneasy, of
                        national ethnic and socialistic civic identities”.<note place="foot"
                            xml:id="ftn52" n="49">Ibid., 86.</note> This identity was expressed and maintained through many
                        public rituals, for instance <hi rend="italic">the Relay of Youth</hi>
                        (Slo. <hi rend="italic">Štafeta mladosti</hi>) or the <hi rend="italic"
                            >Train of Brotherhood and Unity</hi>, and especially through admiration
                        of the figure of the leader of Yugoslavia, Josip Broz – Tito. It was also
                        related to the feelings of pride that emanated from the country’s
                        international reputation as a unique, powerful and independent entity, that
                        was neither East nor West. Even the Yugoslav communication system was unique
                        and significantly different from the stereotypical image of the state-owned
                        and centralised Eastern European media. <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn53"
                            n="50">See Slavko Splichal, “Media Research in Socialist
                            Slovenia/Yugoslavia: Some Afterthoughts,” <hi rend="italic">Triple-C
                            </hi>18, No. 1 (2020): 350–59.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>In this sense, it is no surprise that regrets about the collapse of
                        Yugoslavia, which the interviewees viewed as a respected society (and not on
                        the periphery of the First world), were often present in the interviews.
                        Similar arguments appeared when some interviewees tried to explain the
                        quality of Yugoslav journalism. It was typically seen as a very respected
                        profession and its interpretations of world events were mostly considered to
                        be neutral. Yugoslavia was not part of the Western or Eastern bloc and
                        Yugoslav audiences were supposedly receiving objective information about
                        world events. One interviewee, for instance, stated that “reporting was
                        objective /…/ Yugoslavia was not a fan of Russia, /…/ We were freer, we were
                        not as repressed as people living in Hungary or Czechoslovakia” (A.
                        Zupančič). One question many interviewees lacked an exact answer for was how
                        and when this Yugoslav identity disappeared, or indeed, whether today it is
                        still somehow present.</p>
                    <p>Even though the period of socialist Yugoslavia is often presented as a
                        repressed and somewhat rejected part of Slovenian history – an obstacle to
                        realisation of the 1,000-year-old dream that finally came true upon
                        Slovenian independence – our interviewees’ memories of Yugoslavia were
                        rarely marked by any significant traumas. As one interviewee noted: “None of
                        our generation – in contrast with those born in the 1930s – experienced any
                        atrocities” (‘Lojtra’). Even though the interlocutors had varying
                        evaluations of the socialist regime – with many mentioning negative aspects
                        of the system, for instance the Goli otok concentration camp for political
                        prisoners – they had not undergone a radical experience (such as war) in
                        their lifetime. A certain sense of reconciliation with the past can thus be
                        discerned from the responses: “That’s how the system was. It was a one-party
                        system and we agreed with that /.../ we thought it was just right back then.
                        That’s how they taught us /…/ and that’s what we taught our children. /…/ It
                        was considered normal” (‘Prijazna Gospa’). Even though such a stance
                        dominates, some interviewees mentioned the discomfort they felt when they
                        retrospectively realised the regime’s problematic aspects or the post-war
                        killings of local collaborators with the Nazi regime.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head><hi rend="italic">The past is a foreign country? Comparisons and
                            (dis)continuities</hi></head>
                    <p>The conversations ended with questions concerning how the interviewees view
                        the past regime today. It seems that the students had often implicitly
                        anticipated that their interviewees would emphasise the radical otherness of
                        the past. Yet, on the contrary, they often rejected such simplistic
                        assumptions and argued that the change might not be so radical after all.
                        One interviewee for example said: “Some of us are satisfied and others are
                        not. Those who are dissatisfied now, were also dissatisfied back then and
                        will be dissatisfied in 10 years time” (A. Zupančič). Another stated
                        similarly: “It was hard back then for working people like us, but it is the
                        same today, we are living in difficult times” (‘Julijana’).</p>
                    <p>Such a stance, which stresses that ‘nothing ever changes’, is probably
                        generally characteristic for the perspective of ‘ordinary people’ whose
                        lives are not necessarily dramatically affected by the regime change.
                        However, the reason for the frequency of this view in our sample might also
                        be attributed to the fact that Yugoslav self-managed socialism was
                        significantly more democratic and open than in the Eastern European regimes,
                        which is why the transition to market capitalism was not necessarily seen as
                        such a radical event. Similarly, differences between contemporary journalism
                        and journalism of the past were often relativised by the interviewees, as
                        evidenced by several similar statements: “The media is always the same /…/
                        you can never believe it 100%” (M. Martinšek). “The journalistic profession
                        has always been under pressure” (J. Maj). “There have always been good
                        journalists /…/ and there have always been poor journalists acting on the
                        behest of someone” (S. Mlakar).</p>
                    <p>The idea of historical continuity is also seen in political opinions
                        regarding the regime. The majority of interviewees were completely devoted
                        to the unity of Titoist Yugoslavia before 1980, while the same people later
                        also unanimously supported the Slovenian independence movement. This
                        transition seems to hold a deep structural influence on the interviewees’
                        understanding of their individual and group identity. Memory regarding the
                        gradual change in worldviews is especially murky. In general, the
                        interviewees’ responses fail to provide deep insights into the precise
                        course of historical development throughout the 1980s when this change was
                        underway. They sometimes mentioned the influence of dissident media like <hi
                            rend="italic">Mladina</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Nova Revija</hi>, and
                        events that added to the liberalisation of civil society (the rise of
                        alternative culture, the punk movement, JBTZ court proceedings etc.).</p>
                    <p>Yet, the interviewees even more often explained the beginning of the
                        disintegration of Yugoslavia with anecdotes from their own lives. These
                        examples often describe the rise of banal nationalism on the level of
                        everyday life. They also involve simplified economic reasoning, with claims
                        that Slovenia put proportionally more funds into the common Yugoslav budget
                        than it received from it, while combining this with the supposed laziness of
                        the ‘southerners’. Many jokes circulating at the time illustrate this well:
                        “In Slovenia, a concrete mixer is spinning, while ‘in the south’, a piglet
                        on a spit is spinning [Slo. <hi rend="italic">V Sloveniji se vrtijo
                            mešalci, na jugu pa odojki</hi>]” (H. Molan). This narrative seems to be
                        so effective because it corresponds with two main arguments for Slovenian
                        independence: first, with the idea that Slovenians are culturally different
                        from the other nations of Yugoslavia and, second, that independence would be
                        accompanied by rising economic prosperity, as implied by the notion of
                        Slovenia as “The Switzerland of the Balkans”. It is therefore not surprising
                        that the criticism of contemporary politics often referred to the failure to
                        realise these hopes: “They promised us another Switzerland /…/, but now we
                        are closer to the Visegrad Group” (D. Pernek).</p>
                    <p>The other reason it is difficult to locate the exact point of the transition
                        might relate to the fact that in both the period of Titoist Yugoslavia and
                        the times of Slovenian independence public opinion was very homogeneous. In
                        contrast to this, when the interviewees tried to explain the biggest
                        difference between the past and the present, they often used the dichotomy
                        between the homogenous society with a unified will (as something not
                        necessarily negative) and the divided society in which we are currently
                        living: “We experienced brotherhood and unity, and I miss that today” (V.
                        Štiglic). “I am quite confused by the media reporting today – the news is so
                        diverse /…/ as it suits the actor which supports or funds certain media.
                        Today, it is difficult to know what the real truth is” (‘Bela Lilija’).</p>
                    <p>Individualism, which replaced unity and uniformity, was often presented as
                        the main structural reason for the polarisation of society in which everyone
                        has their own truth. Even if most interviewees agreed that they once missed
                        plurality and diversity, they often still described the situation today as
                        democratisation that “has gone too far”. As one interviewee noted: “There is
                        only one truth, there cannot be many truths” (‘Želimir Anon’).</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Conclusion</head>
                <p>Many aspects of socialist Yugoslavia continue to be under-researched and deserve
                    more attention in the future. Our aim in the empirical part was to add a small
                    piece to this puzzle. We paid special attention to the influence media use has
                    on the process of creating collective and individual memory, identities, and
                    ideological positioning through time, and the evaluation of the Yugoslav regime
                    compared to today’s post-socialist Slovenia. We necessarily had to resort to
                    certain generalisations when it came to the insights provided by the
                    interviewees. Our study should hence be seen as an initial exploration, a
                    roadmap presenting possible directions for other researchers, who should probe
                    these topics further. The conducted interviews enable unique insights into the
                    everyday use of the media by ordinary people, which often go missing in other
                    approaches that, for instance, merely analyse institutional changes or use
                    typical archival material. The interviews can thus serve as an inductive entry
                    point for new ideas and possible avenues for research or as a supplementary
                    source for other empirical material.</p>
                <p>Since we were forced to make broad generalisations, we treated the sample in a
                    homogenous manner. Still, all of the archived interviews include basic
                    demographic data, which makes it possible to further analyse the sample from
                    this point of view and construct different profiles based on gender, level of
                    education, or geographical location. Generalisations made from a few individuals
                    to the whole population always carry risks and possible problems and thus it
                    makes sense to put more focus on specific social subgroups and their
                        memories.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn54" n="51">Bourdon, “Media
                        Remembering,” 64–67. </note> Further segmentation of the sample or profiling
                    of the interviewees could offer a possible solution in this regard, especially
                    because we aim to continue with this project in the future and thereby expand
                    the archive with additional interviews.</p>
                <p>The drawing of firm generalisations seems especially tricky when it comes to the
                    issues of legitimacy and questions concerning trust in relation to particular
                    institutions. This is very much the case when opinions are polarised, at least
                    among some groups and individuals.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn55" n="52">See
                        Breznik and Močnik, “Organized memory and popular remembering,” 6.</note> To
                    a considerable extent, socialist Yugoslavia remains such a contested and
                    emotionally charged historical era, and significant differences might exist
                    between the memories of certain social groups. Digging deeper into the dataset
                    therefore seems necessary to provide an unbiased interpretation.</p>
                <p>In our opinion, there seems little doubt, however, that the interviews provide a
                    substantially more nuanced understanding of a contradictory social system than
                    is usually afforded in public discussion. For a long time, this system enjoyed
                    remarkable legitimacy amongst the general population and these interviews can
                    help give some answers about why that was the case, and why – at least to an
                    extent – it still remains so. The interviewees address many of these issues, yet
                    in the broadest sense they also provide insights into how political opinions in
                    the most general sense are formed, developed, solidified, entrenched and
                    self-justified through an individual’s personal history.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="bibliography">
                <head>Sources and Literature</head>
                <list type="unordered">
                    <head>Archive sources</head>
                    <item>Amon Prodnik, Jernej. “Novinarstvo v socialistični Jugoslaviji in
                        imaginariji medijev skozi občinstvo, 2019” [podatkovna datoteka]. Ljubljana:
                        Univerza v Ljubljani, Arhiv družboslovnih podatkov, 2020. ADP - IDNo:
                        MEDJUG19. <ref target="https://doi.org/10.17898/ADP_MEDJUG19_V1"
                            >https://doi.org/10.17898/ADP_MEDJUG19_V1</ref>.</item>
                    <item>Amon Prodnik, Jernej and Jernej Kaluža. “Novinarstvo v socialistični
                        Jugoslaviji in imaginariji medijev skozi občinstvo, 2020” [podatkovna
                        datoteka]. Ljubljana: Univerza v Ljubljani, Arhiv družboslovnih podatkov,
                        2021. ADP - IDNo: MEDJUG20. <ref
                            target="https://doi.org/10.17898/ADP_MEDJUG20_V1"
                            >https://doi.org/10.17898/ADP_MEDJUG20_V1</ref>.</item>
                    <item>Amon Prodnik, Jernej and Jernej Kaluža. “Novinarstvo v socialistični
                        Jugoslaviji in imaginariji medijev skozi občinstvo, 2021” [podatkovna
                        datoteka]. Ljubljana: Univerza v Ljubljani, Arhiv družboslovnih podatkov,
                        2022. ADP - IDNo: MEDJUG21. <ref
                            target="https://doi.org/10.17898/ADP_MEDJUG21_V1"
                            >https://doi.org/10.17898/ADP_MEDJUG21_V1</ref>.</item>
                </list>
                <list type="unordered">
                    <head>Literature</head>
                    <item>Anderson, Benedict. <hi rend="italic">Imagined Communities: Reflections on
                            the Origin and Spread of Nationalism</hi>. London, New York: Verso,
                        2006/1983.</item>
                    <item>Assmann, Aleida and Linda Shortt, eds.. <hi rend="italic">Memory and
                            Political Change. </hi>London: Palgrave Macmillan, 2012.</item>
                    <item>Bardan, Alice. “Remembering socialist entertainment: Romanian television,
                        gestures and intimacy.” <hi rend="italic">European Journal of Cultural
                            Studies</hi> 20, No. 3 (2017): 341–58.</item>
                    <item>Bourdon, Jérôme. “Media Remembering: The Contributions of Life-Story
                        Methodology to Memory/Media Research.” In: <hi rend="italic">Media Memory:
                            Collective Memory in a New Media Age</hi>. Eds. Motti Neiger, Oren
                        Meyers and Eyal Zandberg, 62–73. London: Palgrave Macmillan, 2011. </item>
                    <item>Bourdon, Jérôme. “Some sense of time: Remembering television.” <hi
                            rend="italic">History and Memory </hi>15, No. 2 (2003): 5–35.</item>
                    <item>Breznik, Maja and Rastko Močnik. “Organized memory and popular
                        remembering: The encounter of Yugonostalgia theories with socialism.” <hi
                            rend="italic">Memory Studies</hi> (October 2021). doi:
                        <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1177/17506980211049899">10.1177/17506980211049899</ref>.</item>
                    <item>Creswell, John W. <hi rend="italic">Qualitative Inquiry and Research
                            Design</hi>. Thousand Oaks: Sage, 2007.</item>
                    <item>De Cesari, Chiara and Ann Rigney. “Introduction.” In: <hi rend="italic"
                            >Transnational Memory: Circulation, Articulation, Scales. </hi>Eds.
                        Chiara De Cesari and Ann Rigney, 1–25. Berlin, Boston: De Gruyter,
                        2014.</item>
                    <item>Erll, Astrid.<hi rend="italic"> Memory in Culture. </hi>London: Palgrave
                        Macmillan, 2011. </item>
                    <item>Gordy, Eric D. <hi rend="italic">The Culture of Power in Serbia:
                            Nationalism and the Destruction of Alternatives</hi>. University Park
                        PA: The Pennsylvania State University Press, 1999.</item>
                    <item>Halbwachs, Maurice. <hi rend="italic">The Collective Memory</hi>. New
                        York: Harper Colophon Books, 1980.</item>
                    <item>Hobsbawm, Eric J. “Ethnicity and Nationalism in Europe Today.” In: <hi
                            rend="italic">Mapping the Nation</hi>. Ed. Gopal Balakrishnan, 255–66.
                        London, New York: Verso.</item>
                    <item>Hobsbawm, Eric J. “Introduction: Inventing Traditions.” In: <hi
                            rend="italic">The Invention of Tradition</hi>. Eds. Eric Hobsbawm and
                        Terence Ranger, 1–14. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1983.</item>
                    <item>Imre, Anikó. <hi rend="italic">TV Socialism</hi>. Durham: Duke University
                        Press, 2016.</item>
                    <item>Jerolmack, Colin and Shamus Khan. “Talk Is Cheap: Ethnography and the
                        Attitudinal Fallacy.” <hi rend="italic">Sociological Methods &amp;
                            Research</hi> 43, No. 2 (2014): 178–209.</item>
                    <item>Kaldor-Robinson, Joshua. “The Virtual and the Imaginary: The Role of
                        Diasphoric new Media in the Construction of a National Identity during the
                        Break-Up of Yugoslavia.” <hi rend="italic">Oxford Development Studies</hi>
                        30, No. 2 (2002): 177–87.</item>
                    <item>Kasamara, Valeria and Anna Sorokina. “Post-Soviet collective memory:
                        Russian youths about Soviet past.” <hi rend="italic">Communist and
                            Post-Communist Studies</hi> 48, No. 2–3 (2015): 137–45.</item>
                    <item>Kosi, Jernej. “Je bil proces formiranja slovenskega naroda v 19. stoletju
                        res zgolj končni nasledek tisočletne slovenske kontinuitete?.” <hi
                            rend="italic">Zgodovinski časopis</hi> 64, No. 1–2 (2010):
                        154–75.</item>
                    <item>Kuljić, Todor. <hi rend="italic">Kultura spominjanja</hi>. Ljubljana:
                        Filozofska fakulteta, 2012. </item>
                    <item>Mihelj, Sabina and Jérôme Bourdon. “Doing audience history: Questions,
                        sources, methods.” <hi rend="italic">European Journal of Communication</hi>
                        30, No. 1 (2015): 3–6.</item>
                    <item>Mihelj, Sabina and Simon Huxtable. <hi rend="italic">From Media Systems to
                            Media Cultures: Understanding Socialist Television. </hi>Cambridge:
                        Cambridge University Press, 2018.</item>
                    <item>Močnik, Rastko. <hi rend="italic">O pisanju zgodovine</hi>. Ljubljana:
                        Založba/*cf., 2015.</item>
                    <item>Pušnik, Maruša. “Media memorial discourses and memory struggles in
                        Slovenia: Transforming memories of the Second World War and Yugoslavia.” <hi
                            rend="italic">Memory Studies</hi> 12, No. 4 (2017): 433–50.</item>
                    <item>Pušnik, Maruša. <hi rend="italic">Kulturna zgodovina elektronskih
                            medijev</hi>. Ljubljana: FDV, 2019.</item>
                    <item>Robinson, Gertrude J. <hi rend="italic">Tito’s Maverick Media</hi>.
                        Chicago: University of Illinois Press, 1977.</item>
                    <item>Ross, Michael. “Relation of implicit theories to the construction of
                        personal histories.” <hi rend="italic">Psychological Review</hi> 96 No. 2
                        (1989): 341–57.</item>
                    <item>Splichal, Slavko and France Vreg. <hi rend="italic">Množično komuniciranje
                            in razvoj demokracije</hi>. Ljubljana: Komunist, 1986.</item>
                    <item>Splichal, Slavko. “Media Research in Socialist Slovenia/Yugoslavia: Some
                        Afterthoughts.” <hi rend="italic">Triple-C </hi>18, No. 1 (2020):
                        350–59.</item>
                    <item>Traverso, Enzo. <hi rend="italic">Left-Wing Melancholia: Marxism, History,
                            and Memory</hi>. New York: Columbia University Press, 2017.</item>
                    <item>Velikonja, Mitja. “Lost in Transition: Nostalgia for Socialism in
                        Post-socialist Countries.” <hi rend="italic">East European Politics and
                            Societies</hi>, 23 No. 4 (2009): 535–51. </item>
                    <item>Velikonja, Mitja. “New Yugoslavism in contemporary popular music in
                        Slovenia.” In: <hi rend="italic">Post-Yugoslavia: new cultural and political
                            perspectives</hi>. Eds. Dino Abazović and Mitja Velikonja, 57–95.
                        Basingstoke, New York: Palgrave Macmillan, 2014.</item>
                    <item>Wilmer, Frankie. <hi rend="italic">The Social Construction of Man, the
                            State and War Identity, Conflict, and Violence in Former
                        Yugoslavia</hi>. London: Routledge, 2002.</item>
                    <item>Wimmer, Andreas and Nina Glick Schiller. “Methodological Nationalism and
                        Beyond: Nation-State Building, Migration and the Social Sciences.” <hi
                            rend="italic">Global Networks: A Journal of Transnational Affairs</hi>
                        2, No. 4 (2002). </item>
                </list>
                <list type="unordered">
                    <head><hi rend="bold">Online sources</hi></head>
                    <item>Amon Prodnik, Jernej. “Nekaj etičnih dilem pri vključevanju študentov v
                        raziskovalno delo.” <hi rend="italic">Arhiv družboslovnih podatkov</hi> 10.
                        11. 2021. Available at: <ref
                            target="http://www.adp.fdv.uni-lj.si/blog/2021/blog/nekaj-eticnih-dilem-pri-vkljucevanju-studentov-v-raziskovalno-delo"
                            >www.adp.fdv.uni-lj.si/blog/2021/blog/nekaj-eticnih-dilem-pri-vkljucevanju-studentov-v-raziskovalno-delo</ref>
                        (20. 3. 2022). </item>
                    <item>Vučina Vršnak, Ana. “Slovenija ostaja ruralna dežela.” <hi rend="italic"
                            >Dnevnik,</hi> 9. 6. 2012. Available at: <ref
                            target="http://www.dnevnik.si/1042534899"
                            >www.dnevnik.si/1042534899</ref> (20. 3. 2022). </item>
                </list>
            </div>
            <div type="summary" xml:lang="sl">
                <docAuthor>Jernej Kaluža</docAuthor>
                <docAuthor>Jernej Amon Prodnik</docAuthor>
                <head>SPOMIN NA MEDIJE IN NOVINARSTVO V SOCIALISTIČNI JUGOSLAVIJI: USTNI ZGODOVINSKI
                    INTERVJUJI Z OBČINSTVI</head>
                <head>POVZETEK</head>
                <p>Spominske študije so se v zadnjih desetletjih razvile v eno izmed plodovitejših
                    raziskovalnih področij, ki praviloma združuje različne discipline in s tem
                    raznolike vpoglede v vrsto zgodovinskih tematik. V teh analizah je bilo precej
                    pozornosti posvečene socialistični Jugoslaviji in njenemu razpadu, vendar sta
                    bili vloga in funkcija medijev in novinarstva v delovanju te države največkrat
                    spregledani. To je težava, še posebej glede na to, kako pomembno vlogo igrajo te
                    institucije v modernih družbah. V študiji sva se osredotočila na vlogo, ki so jo
                    te institucije igrale v vsakdanjih življenjih prebivalcev Jugoslavije, stopnjo,
                    do katere so jim zaupali, ter na vpliv, ki so ga imeli ti spomini na proces
                    vzpostavljanja identitet in vrednotenje socialističnega sistema kot celote.</p>
                <p>V članku se teh problemov lotevava s pomočjo analize 96 polstrukturiranih ustnih
                    intervjujev z medijskimi občinstvi, ki so jih študenti dodiplomskega programa
                    Novinarstvo na Fakulteti za družbene vede (Univerza v Ljubljani) izvedli v letih
                    2019, 2020 in 2021. Intervjuji so bili izvedeni osebno in so v povprečju dolgi
                    eno uro. V celoti so bili transkribirani in so v takšni obliki tudi arhivirani v
                    Arhivu družboslovnih podatkov, zato so dostopni za nadaljnje analize.
                    Intervjuvanci so po vnaprej postavljenem kriteriju morali biti rojeni med letoma
                    1940 in 1955, študenti in študentke pa so jih izvajali predvsem s svojimi
                    starimi starši, ki so v socialistični Jugoslaviji živeli večino svojega
                    življenja in imajo nanjo torej prvoosebne spomine.</p>
                <p>Interpretativna analiza intervjujev je temeljila na deduktivnem kodiranju
                    intervjujev in je bila zastavljena že z matrico za izvajanje intervjujev, ki so
                    ji morali pri izvedbi pogovora slediti izvajalci intervjujev. Na osnovi matrice
                    sva empirični del razdelila na tri dele. V prvem delu sva se osredotočila na
                    vsakodnevno uporabo medijev, kjer ugotavljava, da je v začetnem povojnem obdobju
                    poleg tiskanih medijev v življenjih intervjuvancev osrednjo vlogo pričakovano
                    odigral predvsem radio. Spremljanje tega medija je bilo pogosto kolektivno,
                    podobno pa je veljalo tudi za prvo obdobje televizije, torej predvsem v
                    šestdesetih letih dvajsetega stoletja. Podobno kot na Zahodu televizija od
                    sedemdesetih let dalje postaja osrednji množični medij. V drugem delu empirične
                    analize sva se osredotočila na zaupanje v medije in novinarstvo in ugotovila, da
                    so posebej v začetnem obdobju intervjuvanci kljub omejeni informacijski
                    raznolikosti do njih gojili visoko stopnjo zaupanja. Novinarstvo kot profesijo
                    so cenili tudi kasneje. Zaupanje je povezano tudi s tretjim delom, ki analizira
                    dojemanje jugoslovanske družbe in poudarja relativno visoko stopnjo legitimnosti
                    tega sistema med sogovorniki. Do prave erozije je pričelo prihajati šele v
                    osemdesetih letih dvajsetega stoletja.</p>
                <p>V študiji sva bila zaradi dolžine in vsebinskih omejitev primorana v nekatere
                    posplošitve, kar nama je omogočilo kratek pregled zbranih podatkov. Kljub
                    omejitvam ti splošni zaključki nakazujejo visoko vrednost teh podatkov za
                    prihodnje raziskave. Prvoosebni intervjuji namreč omogočajo edinstvene in
                    dragocene vpoglede v to zgodovinsko obdobje, ki bi jih le stežka pridobili na
                    druge načine. Omogočajo bistveno pestrejše razumevanje tega protislovnega
                    obdobja, kot pa ga je največkrat deležno v čustveno razvnetih in polariziranih
                    javnih razpravah, ter odpirajo možnosti za razumevanje razlogov, zaradi katerih
                    ta sistem še naprej uživa relativno visoko stopnjo zaupanja. Arhivska dostopnost
                    intervjujev in cilj, da se projekt izvajanja intervjujev nadaljuje tudi v
                    prihodnje, bi morala služiti kot spodbuda za nadaljnje raziskovanje teh
                    empiričnih podatkov, ki je zaradi njihove količine in obsega nujno. Sama sva se
                    lahko dotaknila le osrednjih poudarkov, zato lahko ti podatki služijo tudi kot
                    dopolnilo k drugim osnovnejšim raziskovalnim virom ali kot induktivna vstopna
                    točka za iskanje novih idej in raziskovalnih poti pri preučevanju tega
                    zgodovinskega obdobja.</p>
            </div>

        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
