<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Journalist’s Action in Socialist Yugoslavia: Understanding the
                    Formulation “Journalist as a Socio-political Worker”<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn1" n="*">The author wrote this article as part of a training
                        course for young researchers (Slovenian Research Agency). This article was
                        written as part of a research project <hi rend="italic">The Role of
                            Communication Inequalities in Disintegration of a Multinational
                            Society</hi> (Slovenian Research Agency: grant J5-1793). I would like to
                        thank Martin Mittendorfer and Jernej Kaluža for initial and ongoing
                        discussions on the topic, for help creating the insights and, finally, for
                        support. I also wish to thank Sašo Slaček and Jernej Amon Prodnik for their
                        constructive comments and advice. Finally, thanks to all the transcribers of
                        the interview recordings who made it easier to enter into the analysis of
                        the data obtained.</note></title>
                <author>
                    <surname>Nina</surname>
                    <forename>Žnidaršič</forename>
                    <roleName>Young Researcher</roleName>
                    <affiliation>Faculty of Social Sciences, University of Ljubljana</affiliation>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Kardeljeva ploščad 5</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>SI-1000 Ljubljana</addrLine>
                    </address>
                    <email>nina.znidarsic@fdv.uni-lj.si</email>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>2022-04-21</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>
                    <orgName xml:lang="sl">Inštitut za novejšo zgodovino</orgName>
                    <orgName xml:lang="en">Institute of Contemporary History</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Privoz 11</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>SI-1000 Ljubljana</addrLine>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>http://ojs.inz.si/pnz/article/view/4012</pubPlace>
                <date>2022</date>
                <availability status="free">
                    <licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title xml:lang="sl">Prispevki za novejšo zgodovino</title>
                <title xml:lang="en">Contributions to Contemporary History</title>
                <biblScope unit="volume">62</biblScope>
                <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
                <idno type="ISSN">2463-7807</idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source, born digital.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc xml:lang="en">
                <p>Contributions to Contemporary History is one of the central Slovenian scientific
                    historiographic journals, dedicated to publishing articles from the field of
                    contemporary history (the 19th and 20th century).</p>
                <p>The journal is published three times per year in Slovenian and in the following
                    foreign languages: English, German, Serbian, Croatian, Bosnian, Italian, Slovak
                    and Czech. The articles are all published with abstracts in English and
                    Slovenian as well as summaries in English.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <projectDesc xml:lang="sl">
                <p>Prispevki za novejšo zgodovino je ena osrednjih slovenskih znanstvenih
                    zgodovinopisnih revij, ki objavlja teme s področja novejše zgodovine (19. in 20.
                    stoletje).</p>
                <p>Revija izide trikrat letno v slovenskem jeziku in v naslednjih tujih jezikih:
                    angleščina, nemščina, srbščina, hrvaščina, bosanščina, italijanščina, slovaščina
                    in češčina. Članki izhajajo z izvlečki v angleščini in slovenščini ter povzetki
                    v angleščini.</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="sl"/>
                <language ident="en"/>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords xml:lang="en">
                    <term>journalist</term>
                    <term>socio-political worker</term>
                    <term>socialism</term>
                    <term>self-management</term>
                    <term>Yugoslavia</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords xml:lang="sl">
                    <term>novinar</term>
                    <term>družbeno-politični delavec</term>
                    <term>socializem</term>
                    <term>samoupravljanje</term>
                    <term>Jugoslavija</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change>
                    <date>2022-05-04T07:20:39Z</date>
                    <name>Mihael Ojsteršek</name>
                    <desc>Pretvorba iz DOCX v TEI, dodatno kodiranje</desc>
                </change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <docAuthor>Nina Žnidaršič<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn2" n="**">
                    <hi rend="bold">Young Researcher, Faculty of Social Sciences, University of
                        Ljubljana, Kardeljeva ploščad 5, SI-1000 Ljubljana; </hi><ref
                        target="mailto:nina.znidarsic@fdv.uni-lj.si"><hi rend="bold"
                            >nina.znidarsic@fdv.uni-lj.si</hi></ref>
                </note></docAuthor>
            <docImprint>
                <idno type="cobissType">Cobiss tip: 1.01</idno>
                <idno type="DOI">doi: https://doi.org/10.51663/pnz.62.1.4</idno>
            </docImprint>
            <div type="abstract" xml:lang="sl">
                <head>IZVLEČEK</head>
                <head><hi rend="italic">NOVINARJEVO DELOVANJE V SOCIALISTIČNI JUGOSLAVIJI:
                        RAZUMEVANJE FORMULACIJE “NOVINAR KOT DRUŽBENO-POLITIČNI DELAVEC”</hi></head>
                <p><hi rend="italic">V prispevku analiziramo jezikovno igro 'novinar kot
                        družbeno-politični delavec', ki je bila profesionalna oznaka za novinarjevo
                        delovanje v nekdanji socialistični Jugoslaviji. Besedilo je razdeljeno na
                        dva osrednja dela. V prvem razdelku se z uporabo zgodovinsko-pojmovne metode
                        lotevamo analize izraza v normativnih tekstih, kar zaobjema programska in
                        angažirana besedila, ki so nastajala v takratnem času. S takim pristopom
                        skušamo v pomen izraza vstopiti notranje, v utrip in duh časa, predvsem pa
                        razumeti, kaj so z oznako njeni ustvarjalci želeli doseči in tudi sporočiti.
                        Ugotavljamo, da sta bila novinarstvo in novinarjevo delovanje kot
                        družbeno-političnega delavca razumljena kot pomemben politični dejavnik, kot
                        sila, ki po eni strani prispeva k razvoju in izvedbi novega
                        družbeno-političnega reda, tj. samoupravne socialistične skupnosti, po drugi
                        strani pa novinar z lastnimi izdelki vpliva na širšo zavest množice, kar se
                        izkazuje skozi idejo izobrazbe in vzgoje novega človeka: samoupravljavca.
                        Drugi del prispevka je komplement prvemu, saj s kvalitativno metodo
                        poglobljenega polstrukturiranega intervjuja z nekdanjimi novinarji, ki so
                        profesionalno delovali v Socialistični federativni republiki Jugoslaviji, in
                        skozi njihovo spominjanje nadaljujemo notranjo rekonstrukcijo pomena,
                        razumevanja in rabe izraza v takratnem času. </hi></p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Še posebej smo opazovali odnos s politiko, ki ga koncept
                        esencialno vsebuje. Z empirično analizo smo tako prišli do različnih
                        zaključkov: nekateri intervjuvanci so izraz orisovali afirmativno, da ima
                        novinar posebno poslanstvo, večina od njih pa je do rabe in pomena izraza
                        pristopila s kritično distanco, da je novinar vprežen v potrebe dnevne
                        politike in tako v svojem delovanju viden kot neavtonomen. </hi></p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Ključne besede: novinar, družbeno-politični delavec,
                        socializem, samoupravljanje, Jugoslavija</hi></p>
            </div>
            <div type="abstract" xml:lang="en">
                <head>ABSTRACT</head>
                <p><hi rend="italic">In this paper, we analyse the language game “the journalist as
                        a socio-political worker”, which was the professional label for journalists’
                        action in the former socialist Yugoslavia. The text is divided into two main
                        parts. The first part uses a historical-conceptual method to analyse the
                        mentioned formulation in normative texts, covering programmatic and engaged
                        texts produced at the time. This approach seeks to enter into the meaning of
                        the term from the inside, into the pulse and spirit of the time, and above
                        all to understand what its creators wished to achieve and communicate with
                        this expression. We find that journalism and the journalist’s action as a
                        socio-political worker were understood as an important political factor, as
                        a political force on one hand contributing to the development and
                        implementation of a new socio-political order, i.e., a socialist community
                        based on self-management and, on the other hand, the journalist who through
                        their own products tried to influence the broader consciousness of the
                        masses, as manifested through the idea of the education for the new man: the
                        self-manager. The second part of the paper complements the first since
                        through the qualitative method of in-depth semi-structured interviews with
                        former journalists who had been professionally active in the Socialist
                        Federal Republic of Yugoslavia, and via their recollections, we continue to
                        internally reconstruct the meaning, understanding and use of the formulation
                        at that time. In particular, we observe the relationship with politics that
                        the concept essentially contains. Empirical analysis thus led us to
                        different conclusions: some interviewees (the minority) described the term
                        affirmatively, that the journalist as a socio-political worker had a special
                        mission, while most approached the use and meaning of the expression with a
                        critical distance, namely, that the journalist as a socio-political worker
                        was harnessed to the needs of daily politics and thereby seen as
                        non-autonomous in their labour and actions. </hi></p>
                <p style="text-align:left;"><hi rend="italic">Keyword: journalist, socio-political
                        worker, socialism, self-management, Yugoslavia</hi></p>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div>
                <head>Introduction</head>
                <p>The aim of the article is to analyse the formulation “<hi rend="italic">the
                        journalist as a socio-political worker</hi>” from the <hi rend="italic"
                        >inside</hi>, by entering the particular historical and social moment in
                    which it was present. This formulation, also treated here as a language game,
                    was used during the time of socialist Yugoslavia. The concept undergoes a
                    holistic historical-conceptual analysis and also receives empirical attention.
                    The second part of the expression – ‘a socio-political worker’ – is understood
                    as a way of <hi rend="italic">normatively</hi> marking the journalist’s <hi
                        rend="italic">work</hi> as the creation of journalistic products, the
                    journalist’s <hi rend="italic">labour </hi>as producing daily news/products for
                    audiences, and <hi rend="italic">action</hi> as the journalist enters into the
                    common world/society.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn3" n="1">The triad <hi
                            rend="italic">labour – work – action</hi> follows the tripartite
                        division set out in the work of Hannah Arendt. The division is used
                        throughout her work <hi rend="italic">Vita Activa</hi> [<hi rend="italic"
                            >The Human Condition</hi>] (Ljubljana: Krtina, 1996) in a
                        classical-traditional meaning. This article, however, attempts to unveil the
                        concepts through the meaning and relevance of (<hi rend="italic"
                            >associated</hi>) labour in the socialist political
                    community.</note></p>
                <p>In the field of journalism studies, research explicitly addressing the term is
                    rare. However, the concept is often mentioned in texts that address journalism
                    and the journalist’s actions in socialist Yugoslavia, especially the
                    journalistic normativity of time and space. The wording “the journalist as a
                    socio-political worker” is frequently opened up and interpreted in academic
                    texts by referring to the Yugoslav Journalists’ Code that indeed included<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn4" n="2">The phrase is written in the Codes [<hi
                            rend="italic">Kodeks novinara Jugoslavije</hi>] from 1965, 1973, 1982.
                    </note> it up until 1988, although it is no longer found in the Code.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn5" n="3">
                        <hi rend="italic">Kodeks novinara Jugoslavije</hi>, 1988.</note> The phrase
                    is typically explained as meaning that the journalist, as “a socio-political
                    worker”, is someone who actively contributes to developing and also implementing
                    the self-managed socialism (such as in the article by Sonja Merljak Zdovc and
                    Melita Poler Kovačič,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn6" n="4">Sonja Merljak Zdovc
                        and Melita Poler Kovačič, “The Paradox of Slovenia: Investigative Journalism
                        during Socialism and Democracy,” <hi rend="italic">Journalism </hi>8, No. 5
                        (2007): 522.</note> and in the latest book by Zrinjka Peruško, Dina Vozab
                    and Antonija Čuvalo<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn7" n="5"> Zrinjka Peruško, Dina
                        Vozab and Antonija Čuvalo, <hi rend="italic">Comparing Post-Socialist Media
                            Systems: The Case of Southeast Europe </hi>(Oxon, New York: Routledge,
                        2021), 101.</note>). The Code also states that the journalist, “as a
                    socio-political worker”, ideologically pursues Marxism and Leninism, realises
                    the importance of the working class and its role in socialist society based on
                    self-management. Melita Poler<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn8" n="6">Melita
                        Poler, “Ethics and Professionalisation of Slovene Journalism,” <hi
                            rend="italic">Javnost (The Public) </hi>3, No. 4 (1996): 109.</note>
                    clearly distinguishes these words from “the journalist as a watchdog” who
                    normatively controls and does not cooperate with political authorities. There is
                    also a consensus in these texts that the formulation is closely linked to
                    political power, placing it among political terms, and this is also considered
                    in this discussion.</p>
                <p>Igor Vobič<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn9" n="7">Igor Vobič, “Three paradigms of
                        journalistic objectivity in Slovenian press history,” <hi rend="italic"
                            >Central European Journal of Communication </hi>7, No. 1 (2014): 9–11.
                    </note> shows that the normativity also captured in the expression “the
                    journalist as a socio-political worker” reveals the unique <hi rend="italic"
                        >objectivity</hi> of historical time and space (also see Dina Vozab and
                    Dunja Majstorović<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn10" n="8">Dina Vozab and Dunja
                        Majstorović, “The Transformation of Normative Approaches to Journalism in
                        Croatian Academic Literature from Socialism to Post-Socialism,” <hi
                            rend="italic">Croatian Political Science Review </hi>58, No. 2 (2021):
                        18.</note>). This suggests that phrases which emerged in the chosen
                    historical epoch should be understood according to the political and societal
                    idea of the time – seen in speech/language as an objective disguising of time –
                    which is under research.</p>
                <p>In the paper, we present analysis complementing previous research based on the
                    use of two methods: the historical-conceptual method and the qualitative method
                    of in-depth semi-structured interviews. Both methods are intertwined in the
                    text. Rather than attempt to judge the term from the <hi rend="italic"
                        >outside</hi>, by elaborating and comparing it with contemporary
                    journalistic norms and standards, the article aims to develop an epistemological
                    perspective from the <hi rend="italic">inside</hi>, which was especially
                    possible by using these two methods.</p>
                <p>The discussion is divided into two parts. In part one, we analyse the mentioned
                    expression with the historical-conceptual method, which includes a brief
                    presentation of the journalist’s actions in engaged and programmatic texts
                    written during socialist Yugoslavia, for the purpose of developing the socialist
                    and self-managed community. The second part is dedicated to reconstructing the
                    use and understanding of the formulation “the journalist as a socio-political
                    worker” by interviewing former journalists who were professionally active in
                    socialist Yugoslavia. Most of them were active in the time of the Socialist
                    Federal Republic of Yugoslavia (SFRY), mainly in the former socialist republic
                    of Slovenia.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Interpreting the Language Game Through the Heritage of the Phrase “a
                    Journalist as a Politician”</head>
                <p>The expression “the journalist <hi rend="italic">as</hi> a socio-political
                    worker” after the comparative <hi rend="italic">as</hi> combines two adjectives
                    – <hi rend="italic">social</hi> and <hi rend="italic">political</hi> – that
                    pertain to the noun – <hi rend="italic">worker.</hi><note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn11" n="9">The phrase is not written in a unified way across the
                        texts. Sometimes it is written as one word – <hi rend="italic"
                            >sociopolitical worker – </hi>and other times it is hyphenated – <hi
                            rend="italic">socio-political worker. </hi>Even though the Slovenian
                        language discerns between the meanings of hyphenated and non-hyphenated
                        words, the texts and their subsequent analysis reveals that in this case the
                        phrases <hi rend="italic">sociopolitical worker/socio-political workers
                        </hi>are identical in meaning. In this article, we use the hyphenated
                        version since the hyphen replaces the word <hi rend="italic">and</hi>.
                        Therefore, the meanings of both ‘social’ and ‘political’ are
                        retained.</note> This means the worker is somehow socially and politically
                    engaged/active and therefore the journalist is a socio-political worker. The
                    journalist's professional identity is thus marked by the socio-political
                    imperatives of the Yugoslav socialist system based on self-management.</p>
                <p>The wording is treated as a language game, a concept that reconciles the use of
                    language with forms of human actions; in our case, the use of the term “the
                    journalist as a socio-political worker” with the journalist’s actions in the
                    common socialist and self-managed world. For Ludwig Wittgenstein, the concept
                    “is meant to bring into prominence the fact that the <hi rend="italic">speaking
                    </hi>of language is part of an activity, or of a form of life”.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn12" n="10">Ludwig Wittgenstein, <hi rend="italic"
                            >Philosophical Investigations </hi>(Oxford: Basil Blackwell, 1963),
                        9.</note> As such, it can also be part of a specific historical epoch, idea
                    or use. This discussion attempts to unfold the historical meaning of the wording
                    rather than give it a single black-and-white/universal definition that reduces
                    the journalist as a socio-political worker to an expressive instrument of the
                    political authorities and their ideology. This attempt is based on the
                    understanding that human affairs, and with them the use of language in a chosen
                    form of action, are contingent on and subject to spontaneity,<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn13" n="11">Arendt, <hi rend="italic">Vita activa</hi>, 11, 183,
                        184, 199–202.</note> as well as impossible to capture in a universal
                    definition.</p>
                <p>With the concept of language game we place analysis of the mentioned wording in
                    the historical-conceptual method. Reinhart Koselleck<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn14" n="12">Reinhart Koselleck, <hi rend="italic">Pretekla
                            prihodnost: prispevek k semantiki zgodovinskih časov</hi> [<hi
                            rend="italic">Future Past: on the Semantics of Historical Time</hi>]
                        (Ljubljana: Studia humanitatis, 1999), 110, 111.</note> (see also the text
                    by Gunter Scholtz<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn15" n="13">Gunter Scholtz, “Kaj
                        je pojmovna zgodovina in čemu se z njo ukvarjamo? [What Is
                        Begriffsgeschichte and Why It Deserves Our Attention],” <hi rend="italic"
                            >Phainomena</hi> 11, No. 41/42 (2002).</note>) explains this method as a
                    main and fundamental complement to social history, which analytically enters
                    into the study of socio-political structures and formations, and therefore as a
                    conceptual discussion of the pulse, the spirit of historical time, and its
                    political and ideological purposes. In our case, this means that by interpreting
                    the formulation we observe the structure of the relationship between the
                    political authorities/politics and the journalist’s labour, actions and work in
                    socialist Yugoslavia. The historical-conceptual analysis approach also continues
                    in the second part of the paper through interviews with former journalists and
                    their historical understanding of those words.</p>
                <p>The politician and former editor of <hi rend="italic">Ljudska pravica</hi> [<hi
                        rend="italic">The People’s Right</hi>] Vida Tomšič, at the first press
                    conference held in the liberated territory in 1944, outlined the role and
                    identity of the journalist in the future Yugoslav socio-political system in this
                        manner:<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn16" n="14">Bernard Nežmah, <hi
                            rend="italic">Časopisna zgodovina novinarstva</hi> [<hi rend="italic"
                            >The Newspaper History of Journalism</hi>] (Ljubljana: Študentska
                        založba, 2012), 282.</note> “We are journalists because we are politicians,
                    or we are politicians because we are journalists”. This declaration was aimed at
                    the struggle to construct a new order, which marked the Yugoslav post-war
                    period, but it also regarded the journalist’s identity and actions as an active
                    engagement in the realisation of this new order. Together as a political and
                    socialist community, they were to change the common reality. The previous
                    interpretation of “the journalist as a socio-political worker” (e.g., in the
                    Yugoslav Journalists’ Codes of 1965, 1973 and 1982) also sees the journalist
                    making an active and engaged contribution to the development of self-managed
                    socialism and self-management (level of social and economic relations), which
                    more obviously began to be introduced into the Yugoslav space after 1950.</p>
                <p>Engaged contribution through the identity of journalists as politicians and,
                    later, journalists as socio-political workers may be explained in that
                    journalists, with their products and active recognition of socio-political
                    relevance, actively enter the political community, which is a common space of
                    the people. After revolutions, including after the Yugoslav revolution,<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn17" n="15">Gal Kirn, “Jugoslovanska revolucija skozi
                        tri partizanske prelome [The Yugoslav Revolution Through Three Partisan
                        Ruptures],” <hi rend="italic">Časopis za kritiko znanosti</hi> 45, No. 269
                        (2017).</note> a need had arisen to constitute a new socio-political
                        order<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn18" n="16">Giorgio Agamben, <hi
                            rend="italic">Homo sacer: suverena oblast in golo življenje</hi> [<hi
                            rend="italic">Homo Sacer: Sovereign Power and Bare Life</hi>]
                        (Ljubljana: Študentska založba, 2004), 52–55. See also: Hannah Arendt, <hi
                            rend="italic">O revoluciji</hi> [<hi rend="italic">On Revolution</hi>]
                        (Ljubljana: Krtina, 2017), 19.</note>, which required the participation of
                    all people – in the case of socialist Yugoslavia – all working people who were
                    the central identity of the system at that time.</p>
                <p>In re-constituting the socio-political order, following revolutionary practice,
                    thought is transformed into practical and active thought (practical reason, <hi
                        rend="italic">phrónesis</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn19" n="17"
                        >Aristotel, <hi rend="italic">Nikomahova etika </hi>[<hi rend="italic"
                            >Nicomachean Ethics</hi>] (Ljubljana: Slovenska matica, 2002), 190, 191,
                        194, 195.</note>) that can simply be named action, or in modern vocabulary,
                    activism. The foundations of action are based on human knowledge of speech and
                    its use. It is speech that enables humans, as by nature <hi rend="italic"
                        >politikòn zôon</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn20" n="18">Aristotel, <hi
                            rend="italic">Politika </hi>[<hi rend="italic">Politics</hi>]
                        (Ljubljana: GV, 2010), 112.</note> or just a social animal,<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn21" n="19">Hannah Arendt, <hi rend="italic"
                            >Predavanja o Kantovi politični filozofiji </hi>[<hi rend="italic"
                            >Lectures on Kant’s Political Philosophy</hi>] (Ljubljana: KUD
                        Apokalipsa, 2018), 74.</note> to communicate and collaborate with other
                    humans who can together form and even change a political community and together
                    contribute to its future development. Such journalists, who are part of the
                    creation of a new, socialist, self-management political community and society,
                    may be seen as political animals, agents, who actively enter the public space
                    through their own work, labour and action, which are in turn marked by broader
                    socio-political practice.</p>
                <p>However, the legacy of the previous statement that “a journalist is a politician,
                    and a politician is a journalist” observed in the formulation “the journalist as
                    a socio-political worker”, which is largely focused on the development of
                        self-management<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn22" n="20">Mitja Gorjup, <hi
                            rend="italic">Samoupravno novinarstvo </hi>[<hi rend="italic">Journalism
                            in Self-Management</hi>] (Ljubljana: Delavska enotnost, 1978), 62.
                    </note>, allows two conclusions. First, a manifestation of power that is framed
                    through the one-party system and one main ideology. Yet this also means that while the Party as the political authority is leading, at
                    the same time it also shows that the Party is or should only be partly a leader.
                    Second, as a founder of socialist self-management Edvard Kardelj wrote in one of
                    the fundamental works at the time, <hi rend="italic">Smeri razvoja političnega
                        sistema socialističnega samoupravljanja</hi> [<hi rend="italic">The
                        Developmental Directions of the Political Systems of Socialist
                        Self-Management</hi>] (1977), that a crucial political forces, in addition
                    to other main political forces (e.g., the League of Communists, the Socialist
                    Alliance of Working People, trade unions and other socio-political
                    organisations), of the system is <hi rend="italic">the system of public
                        communication</hi>, in which he listed the press, radio, television and
                    other “media of social life”.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn23" n="21">Edvard
                        Kardelj, <hi rend="italic">Smeri razvoja političnega sistema socialističnega
                            samoupravljanja</hi> (Ljubljana: ČZP Komunist, 1977), 220.</note> These
                    forces are fundamental contributions to developing the socialist political idea
                    and self-management. Kardelj added, “the media of social life” are not “merely
                    media, but a political force that can influence social consciousness in a very
                    progressive or a very reactionary manner”.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn24"
                        n="22">Ibidem.</note></p>
                <p>The introduction of Kardelj's conception of the public media – and thus
                    journalistic activity – as a political (co)force of the socialist system also
                    raises the question of their relationship with other, more central political
                    forces, and the possibility of autonomously implementing the self-management
                    idea and action; in particular, by framing and characterising journalists’
                    activity as a socio-political worker. We address this relationship empirically
                    with in-depth semi-structured interviews in the second part of the paper below.
                </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Methodology</head>
                <p>Using the historical-conceptual method, the concept of research has so far been
                    elaborated and discussed together with programmatic and engaged texts embedded
                    in philosophical/scientific debates. It may be concluded that “the journalist as
                    a socio-political worker” has a close relationship with politics and is
                    connected to political action. This close relationship with politics does
                    however not mean that the journalist is necessarily subordinate to narrow
                    politics, i.e., the Party, or even that they are an instrumental extension of
                    it. Instead, it means the journalist’s action is directed to the construction of
                    an alternative. The building of an alternative modernity is reflected on one
                    hand by an appeal to the socialist political idea and the individual’s committed
                    contribution to a shared political community and, on the other, it is
                    demonstrated that the journalist as “a socio-political worker” is part of the
                    authorities, especially of the power of united workers, which precisely in
                    socialist Yugoslavia acquires a central role and the role of an engaged member
                    of and contributor to the self-management society.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn25" n="23">Kardelj, <hi rend="italic">Smeri razvoja
                            socialističnega samoupravljanja</hi>, 93. Also in formal acts: e.g., in
                        Article 2 of <hi rend="italic">Zakon o združenem delu</hi> [<hi
                            rend="italic">The Associated Labour Act</hi>] (Ljubljana: Gospodarska
                        založba, 1976), 23. And in fundamental principles (part II) in <hi
                            rend="italic">Integralno besedilo ustave Socialistične federativne
                            republike Jugoslavije in amandmajev I do XLVIII k ustavi Socialistične
                            federativne republike Jugoslavije</hi> [<hi rend="italic">SFRY
                            Constitution, 1974</hi>] (Ljubljana: Uradni list SR Slovenije, 1989),
                        20.</note>
                </p>
                <p>The overall exploration of the formulation and understanding of the relationship
                    between politics and journalism whose meaning this language game offers is
                    complemented by the use of in-depth-semi-structured interviews conducted with
                    former journalists who were professionally active and worked in the SFRY. The
                    interviews saw the following research question emerge: <hi rend="italic">What
                        kind of relationship with political power and the authorities was expressed
                        by use of the wording “the journalist as a socio-political worker” and how
                        did this relationship affect the journalist’s autonomy?</hi></p>
                <p>As part of the project <hi rend="italic">Vloga komunikacijskih neenakosti v
                        dezintegraciji večnacionalne družbe</hi> [<hi rend="italic">The Role of
                        Communication Inequalities in Disintegration of a Multinational
                    Society</hi>], 37 in-depth semi-structured and non-anonymised qualitative
                    interviews, conducted by Jernej Amon Prodnik and the author of this paper, were
                    held between June and August 2021. A table containing data on the interviews is
                    found in Appendix A. The interviews were designed in several thematic strands;
                    in one of these, we specifically addressed the meaning and use of the researched
                    formulation in the past self-managed socialist society. The sample selected for
                    the analysis includes 34 interviews, where three interviews were excluded
                    because they contained no mention of this wording.</p>
                <p>The choice of a qualitative method of this type was dictated by the tendency to
                    look at the formulation’s use from the <hi rend="italic">inside</hi>, by those
                    journalists who had been professionally active in the SFRY and generally in
                    socialist Yugoslavia. This approach ultimately serves to complement the
                    historical-conceptual method and reveals the ‘facticity’ of use of the wording,
                    as well as the journalists’ point of view: how they used, understood and saw the
                    formulation, especially at the time. Here we may add that both methods are
                    approaches that open up intersecting perspectives and entail different ways of
                    internal thinking about the expression according to the then socio-political
                    system.</p>
                <p>By interviewing former journalists, we entered into their recollection and
                    interpretation of the time, and – in a historically interpretative and
                    reconstructive manner<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn26" n="24">Charles C. Ragin,
                            <hi rend="italic">Družboslovno raziskovanje: enotnost in raznolikost
                            metode</hi> [<hi rend="italic">Constructing Social Research: The Unity
                            and Diversity of Method</hi>] (Ljubljana: Fakulteta za družbene vede,
                        2007), 99.</note> (oral history) – we also grasped the use of the researched
                    language game. The latter shows the forms of action in the SFRY and the
                    journalist’s relationship with the political authorities and specifically what
                    they wanted to glue onto the journalist’s identity in the socialist
                    socio-political system precisely in the wording of the formulation. Namely,
                    through dialogue with the former journalists, and therefore by using the method
                    of in-depth semi-structured interviewing, we also clarified<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn27" n="25">Ragin, <hi rend="italic">Družboslovno
                            raziskovanje</hi>, 98. Steinar Kvale, <hi rend="italic">Doing
                            Interviews</hi> (London: Sage, 2007), 13, 14.</note> some of the
                    judgements, dilemmas, even prejudices about the formulation, which have arisen
                    following the SFRY’s dissolution, and instead adopted an analytical, <hi
                        rend="italic">internal</hi> view of the expression.</p>
                <p>The main limitation of this method is that the interviewees’ personal and
                    professional histories are memories, and hence we cannot exclude the possibility
                    that their description of the past – and thus use of the phrase “journalist as a
                    socio-political worker” – is imbued with the language of the present and with
                    (professional) normative ideals adapted to the contemporary time and place. It
                    is 30 years since the collapse of the SFRY, although tendencies to move away
                    from the Yugoslav socialist political system were already evident in the 1980s.
                    We are also aware of the fact that the interviewees are remembering and
                    reconstructing the time, place and the formulation on the phenomenological level
                    of experience and thus on the level of plural particularity, i.e., their insight
                    is just one element of views on the language game in the larger puzzle of time
                    and space. This also explains why their words are not taken as the ‘main’ or
                    ‘only’ truth, but as a complement to other relevant and possible perspectives.
                </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Empirical Analysis: The Embedding of “the Journalist as a Socio-political
                    Worker” in Their Relationship with Politics and Reflecting on their
                    Autonomy</head>
                <p>The data obtained offer several possible perspectives on the understanding and
                    meaning of the mentioned wording.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn28" n="26">The
                        interviewers presented preliminary results of the interviews in the paper
                            <hi rend="italic">The Journalist as a Socio-political Worker: Ideology
                            and Practice of Slovenian Journalists in Socialist Yugoslavia </hi>at
                        the Central and Eastern European Communication and Media Conference
                        (CEECOM), which took place between 22 and 23 October 2021.</note> Some
                    interviews approached the term affirmatively, in line with the interpretation
                    presented in the first part of the paper. Yet, most approached the expression in
                    a highly critical way, understanding it as a way the political authorities tried
                    to limit and restrict the journalist’s autonomy and their mission to their own
                    political purposes and interests.</p>
                <p>The revealed polarisation once again gives the impression that the formulation
                    and its meaning cannot be seen in any univocal way, or even be packaged into a
                    single semantic definition. The interviewees’ divergences also suggest that the
                    life forms of social and political action, including that of the journalist (as
                    a socio-political worker), in socialist Yugoslavia were complex and not
                    unambiguous, and ultimately call for further research to explain the alternative
                    on which the socialist Yugoslav revolution and system were built. The findings
                    presented here also – at least in part – bridge interpretations of the
                    formulation that are products of the conflicts emerging in contemporary
                    political discussions.</p>
                <div>
                    <head><hi rend="italic">Affirmative Interpretations and Identifying with the
                            Expression</hi></head>
                    <p>Whether the interviewees identify with the formulation is not entirely clear.
                        An affirmative and positive understanding of the wording does not mean these
                        ex-journalists associated their own professional action at the time with
                        broader socio-political activity and saw it as contributing to the creation
                        of the socialist self-management community and society. They tried to see
                        and explain these words consistently for the special historical context and
                        time in which it was used, which shows at least the partial
                        self-identification and association of one’s own journalistic identity with
                        socio-political action at that time.</p>
                    <p>We estimate that seven of the interviewees held such an attitude to the
                        language game: they understood their own action through use of it as being
                        equal to higher political decision-makers, as socio-political workers they
                        actively contributed to the (re)construction of self-managed socialism –
                        seeing their journalistic labour and work as one of the main forces of the
                        system. Two of them understood the second part of the term –
                        ‘socio-political workers’ – as a manifestation of the opinion leaders and
                        engaged agents in their own right, through their journalistic pieces and
                        products their readers showing listeners and viewers different perspectives
                        on social problems. Being an opinion leader and an engaged agent also meant
                        being like a sort of a teacher of the audience. Many, however, saw the
                        formulation as a generic label for their role and status as a journalist in
                        the SFRY.</p>
                    <quote><p>Socio-political workers were politicians, that is the equation. It was used,
                        but not in a pejorative sense. /…/ We journalists wanted to change social
                        relations. It was conscious. That is why we are journalists. (Branko
                        Maksimovič)</p>
                    <p>We informed people. We broadened their knowledge, their horizons, and
                        directed them with our ideas. That is why it used to be said then – and I
                        agreed with it – that a journalist is a socio-political worker. /.../ Today,
                        the phrase is taken out of context. (Miloš Ivančič)</p>
                    <p>If someone told me “you are a socio-political worker”, I naturally told them
                        that I was a journalist, but our status at the time was such that there was
                        no need to pretend otherwise. (Stane Grah)</p></quote>
                    <p>For these interviewees, as we can also see in the above quote from Miloš
                        Ivančič, there was a strong emphasis on the fact that today the formulation
                        is seen outside of the context in which it was coined and used. Today, it is
                        generally used as a way of expressing how journalists’ action and journalism
                        at that time could be discredited in the sense that it was an extension of
                        propaganda and merely an instrument of the one-party rule. And that
                        journalists did not have the possibility of autonomous thinking, reflection
                        and action. It is precisely by using the historical-conceptual method in the
                        first part that we have sought to unpack the formulation contextually and to
                        look at it through the interpretations of texts written and produced during
                        socialist Yugoslavia. Interviewee Bernarda Jeklin contextualised the wording
                        as follows:</p>
                    <quote>Today, the phrase sounds terrible, but it sounded completely different back
                        then. At the time, it was self-evident [that journalists were
                        socio-political workers]. The fact that we were building socialism was
                        entirely fine. To provide a better life for everyone, what was wrong with
                        that? Nothing.</quote>
                    <p>Interviewee Stane Grah also viewed the general status of “journalists as
                        socio-political workers” in the way that the narrower political power, by
                        using this term – purely on a linguistic level – gave journalists some kind
                        of trust, leaving them close to narrow political circles and also to the
                        information that was circulating in these closed spheres. Here we recall
                        Kardelj’s assumption that <hi rend="italic">the system of public
                            communication</hi> is one of the political forces adding to the
                        development of the socialist system and influencing the social and political
                        consciousness of the masses.</p>
                    <quote>That was our status and they [politicians] treated us in this way when we
                        were talking to the League, the Socialist Alliance or those like them. /.../
                        In essence, we were an integral component of politics for politicians. /.../
                        There was mutual trust that was very dear to us, I was grateful and so were
                        others; we appreciated being better-informed, this was very useful for us.
                        (Stane Grah)</quote>
                    <p>This statement can be interpreted in two ways. First, more generally, the
                        political authorities that coined and used the term probably wanted to show
                        and give recognition that journalism is the (co)power of the system and the
                        developer of those political ideas that have yet to see their day of full
                        realisation. Further, they also tried to symbolically represent the
                        unification of working people, who are political agents too. By using the
                        formulation, they wished to establish relations between various fundamental
                        political forces of the system, and journalists as “socio-political workers”
                        are therefore one of them. Second, by establishing a closer relationship by
                        using the formulation with journalists, the political authorities also
                        sought to ensure the easier and more direct promotion of the ideas,
                        positions and reforms they had developed in spaces removed from the general
                        public. They tried to eliminate journalists from <hi rend="italic">the watch
                            dog</hi> role, which was also not a plan of the system at the time.</p>
                    <p>The affirmative attitude to the concept did not mean they did not feel
                        autonomous in their work and action. They characterised their action as
                        largely autonomous, although their autonomous – i.e., independent setting of
                        the rules of governing their own action (<hi rend="italic">autós</hi>,
                            self,<hi rend="italic"> – nómos</hi>, law) – action was dictated and
                        made meaningful by the self-management and socialist socio-political system
                        in which they were existentially and professionally situated. Thus, certain
                        topics like self-management, socialism as a broader political idea, the
                        leading political functionaries (e.g., Tito and Kardelj) and the Non-Aligned
                        Movement were sacrosanct and could not be openly or publicly questioned and
                        challenged.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head><hi rend="italic">Distancing from and Non-identification with the
                            Formulation</hi></head>
                    <p>Two interviewees stated they had never thought about the formulation and
                        engaged with it in any meaningful way. Although they had heard of it, it did
                        not preoccupy them. One of them explained this was because he had been a
                        foreign correspondent and mainly professionally active abroad.</p>
                    <quote>I personally think that we did not pay too much attention to it. I only know
                        that we used to say we would not make for great socio-political workers.
                        /.../ [When asked whether she understood the phrase as a pejorative, she
                        responds:] Not really a pejorative, no, but that we are not socio-political
                        workers because we are journalists. (Nadja Pengov)</quote>
                    <p>Some interviewees who were critical of the phrase, even back then, also
                        expressed that they did not put more emphasis on the expression as a way of
                        distancing themselves from it. However, we estimate that 25 interviewees
                        were extremely and clearly critical of the expression and did not associate
                        their own professional action with it in any way. They saw the coining and
                        use of the wording primarily as a political manner, how political
                        authorities tried to direct them in line with their goals, interests and
                        positions. By appointing journalists as “socio-political workers”, they were
                        attempting to intervene in journalists’ autonomous action and mission. For
                        these interviewees, it is not very clear whether they entered into the
                        interpretation of the formulation through contemporary journalistic norms
                        and ideals. Despite this, it is clear that they see the professional
                        identity of the journalist and the professional field of journalism as
                        matters that should be independent of narrow political power, regarding
                        which they as journalists must be critical and attentive to the problems it
                        causes.</p>
                    <p>Distancing from the term, or being critical of it, was shown in narrow
                        association with political power, with the Party and other socio-political
                        organisations. This notion was applied by interviewees mainly to those
                        journalists who saw their professional mission and their professional
                        identity in line with ‘socio-political working’ and to journalists who gave
                        the impression of being socio-political workers because they had visibly
                        close relationships with the political authorities and collaborated with
                        them in various ways (serving politics and its interests). The large
                        majority of interviewees stated that otherwise a minority of journalists in
                        editorial offices and journalistic organisations equated their professional
                        action/work with the essence of the formulation. Those who identified with
                        it were principally those who had a stronger intention to climb up the
                        political ladder or had other political interests and thought it would make
                        it easier for them to obtain information from the inside, from the closed
                        circles.</p>
                    <quote>Many of us stayed kilometres away from this phrase. From the very beginning.
                        It only meant a close relationship to and dependence on politics. Some were
                        even proud of this phrase, proclaiming themselves to be socio-political
                        workers, but we often thought it was a slur. That, in this way, you are
                        selling your independence. (Gojko Bervar)</quote>
                    <p>Deliberate non-identification with the formulation “the journalist as a
                        socio-political worker” also meant that they did not want their labour to be
                        associated with political power in any way and thus showed a distance from
                        it. They hence emphasised the fact that they were primarily <hi
                            rend="italic">journalists</hi> and not socio-political workers, which is
                        also seen in some of quotations provided above. With this attitude, our
                        journalists created for themselves the possibility of independent and
                        especially autonomous journalistic action and decision-making within the
                        socio-political system.</p>
                    <quote>That is how we were treated. Even though I never approved of us being called
                        socio-political workers. I always let them know: I am a journalist! I am not
                        a socio-political worker because I would act differently. Even in my opinion
                        pieces, I never ‘religiously’ reported on the decisions that were being
                        made. I always had an independent, critical relationship to things. (Aleks
                        Štakul)</quote>
                    <p>The interviewees also felt that the expression was imposed on them by
                        politics in order to gain <hi rend="italic">a formal ally</hi>, namely,
                        through the use of language and the explicit designation of their
                        professional identity, with which they demonstrated an expectation of who a
                        journalist should be in the SFRY.</p>
                    <quote><p>They [politicians] knew that the press is very important, that it is a factor
                        that can either make politics or break it if it is too critical. With this
                        concept, they wanted to say that we are in this together, we will stay
                        together, you will not stab us in the back with critical writing. (Janez
                        Čuček)</p>
                    <p>[The expression] was present because politics made it present. It said:
                        ‘Journalists are socio-political workers because they are fighting for the
                        ideals of this country’. (Ivan Praprotnik)</p>
                    <p>I understood it as a yoke. As a way to use journalists for the purposes of
                        daily politics. (Marjan Sedmak)</p></quote>
                    <p>A few interviewed journalists felt that anyone who was a member of the League
                        of Communists of Yugoslavia, i.e., the Party, or other socio-political
                        organisations was automatically seen as a socio-political worker who was
                        implementing the self-managed socialist society. A contradiction arising
                        here is that although the vast majority of former journalists were by their
                        own accounts mostly passive members of the League of Communists, they felt
                        no special affinity with the expression.</p>
                    <quote>Those [socio-political workers] were mainly functionaries and members of five
                        socio-political organisations: the Socialist Alliance of the Working People,
                        the League of Communists, trade unions, youth, and fighters. And those who
                        were involved in these organisations were socio-political workers. They were
                        not merely functionaries, they also sat in county communities,
                        municipalities, and so on. (Ivan Praprotnik)</quote>
                    <p>This interpretation can be expanded by some interviewees’ observations who
                        stressed that ‘the journalist as a socio-political worker’ was simply
                        someone who uncritically and faithfully transmitted the conclusions,
                        opinions and positions of the Central Committee, which they saw as
                        propaganda, and was thus completely subordinated to politics in thought.
                        Such journalists were not seen as autonomous in socio-political action.</p>
                    <quote><p>The closest definition of this concept would be that a socio-political worker
                        is someone aware of the responsibilities expected of him by the League, in
                        line with their politics, the current politics. (Alenka Puhar)</p>
                    <p>[Journalists as socio-political workers] obtained their opinions at the
                        Central Committee. (Tone Hočevar)</p></quote>
                    <p>Interviewee Ervin Hladnik Milharčič interestingly noted that the emergence
                        and inflation of this kind of engaged and programmatic expression meant that
                        the alienated political power was trying to build a closer relationship with
                        the working people. According to the interviewees’ statements, the inflation
                        of this kind of expressions had the opposite effect: they distanced
                        themselves from the expressions and hence from the ideas that such an
                        expression represented. The formulation “the journalist as a socio-political
                        worker” was also seen by most journalists as a programmatic and bureaucratic
                        platitude found in a variety of formal documents. Accordingly, they did not
                        attribute deeper meanings to it.</p>
                    <quote><p>If you were to go back and search for these resolutions, documents, you would
                        find them in abundance. But everyday people did not know what this is. /…/
                        These platitudes were flying around. Why did they even think of a journalist
                        being a socio-political worker apart from it being a propagandistic
                        platitude. (Jože Poglajen)</p>
                    <p>[The Code of Yugoslav Journalists] existed, yet it was useless. Full of
                        platitudes. They used to say the journalist is a socio-political worker and
                        similar stupidities. (Mojca Drčar Murko)</p></quote>
                    <p>A few interviewees who were critical and distanced themselves from the
                        expression sometimes took a pragmatic approach to identifying with it: they
                        identified with the wording only when the status built around it brought
                        them existential and professional benefits, e.g., the possibility of a
                        higher salary, promotion and also the kind of symbolic possibility of
                        transforming socio-political organisations, especially the Party, from the
                        inside. Interviewee Ivan Praprotnik very ironically described this
                        claim:</p>
                    <quote>We liked this idea of a journalist as a socio-political worker, but for one
                        reason only, not politics. It was because the salaries of socio-political
                        workers at the time were twice the level of journalists. And so, we said,
                        well then, we, too, shall be [socio-political workers] and have better
                        salaries.</quote>
                    <p>Statements like this again link socio-political workers in particular with
                        those who were active in the Party or in the narrower political power and
                        organs, and hence obtained some existential benefits. This also leads to the
                        conclusion that the designation of journalists as “socio-political workers”
                        was chiefly on a symbolic level of the socialist system.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head><hi rend="italic">The Expression Discredits Journalism</hi></head>
                    <p>Some interviewees perceived the formulation as an obvious humiliation of
                        journalistic labour and its mission. They mentioned that the authorities
                        used the term to discredit the journalist, as they should embody the role of
                        a <hi rend="italic">watch dog</hi> and be perceived as such, and tried to
                        humiliate their labour precisely by reducing the noun <hi rend="italic"
                            >worker </hi>to the level of merely labour. One interviewee even felt
                        that use of the word <hi rend="italic">worker </hi>was partly inappropriate
                        because journalists in those days already held advanced degrees and
                        diplomas.</p>
                    <p>Again, this attitude contradicts a system supposed to be built on the power
                        of all workers and the associated labour through which workers could realise
                        their own political potential.</p>
                    <quote><p>I even stated publicly at a meeting then that we [journalists] were not
                        socio-political workers. /.../ Because the label socio-political worker
                        degrades the journalistic profession. The term implied that a journalist, as
                        a socio-political worker, was serving the socio-political system. Not that
                        he is a watchdog. /.../ This label was made to imply that journalists [as
                        socio-political workers] were supposed to make a constructive, positive
                        contribution to the development of society as such. But this label was at
                        the same time degrading to the journalistic profession. (Mitja Meršol)</p>
                    <p>[With this term] politics was trying to put us on the same level as workers.
                        To humiliate [journalists] in a way. (Lada Zei)</p></quote>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Discussion and Conclusion</head>
                <p>The paper and previous empirical analysis allow the conclusion that the
                    formulation, treated here as a language game, which revels the journalistic
                    professional form of action in the SFRY, is closely related to politics and
                    broader political action, which in turn leads to three possible
                    sub-interpretative concise meanings:</p>
                <list rend="ordered:A">
                    <item><p>The affirmative conception of the formulation showed that the
                            journalist, as a socio-political worker, was one of the forces of a
                            system that was actively, committedly and perhaps even activistically
                            contributing to the development and emergence of the new socio-political
                            order, namely, the socialist community based on self-management. With
                            such an interpretation, the journalist is not seen as subordinated in
                            thought and action to politics, but their autonomy is intersected with
                            the higher goals of contributing to the community, society, suggesting
                            an Aristotelian <hi rend="italic">use of practical reason </hi>together
                            with the <hi rend="italic">political action</hi> of equal agents in the
                            public sphere and in the broader political community. Especially through
                            associated labour and the importance of a worker – which includes a
                            socio-political worker – as an engaged agent of the community, there is
                            a significant political potential, inspired by the idea of creating a
                            socialist society that would be the starting point for a <hi
                                rend="italic">good</hi> and fair life for all people.<note
                                place="foot" xml:id="ftn29" n="27">Franck Fischbach, <hi
                                    rend="italic">Kaj je socialistična vlada? Kar je živo in kar je
                                    mrtvo v socializmu</hi> [<hi rend="italic">What is a Socialist
                                    Government? What is Alive and What is Dead in Socialism</hi>]
                                (Ljubljana: Krtina, 2019), 12, 14, 24, 38, 40, 69. See also: Franck
                                Fischbach, “Delo in možnost demokratičnega javnega prostora [<hi
                                    rend="italic">Labour and the Possibility of a Democratic Public
                                    Space</hi>],” <hi rend="italic">Filozofski vestnik</hi> XXXIV,
                                No. 3 (2013): 30–32.</note></p>
                        <p>This kind of understanding the formulation is consistent with the
                            interpretation presented in the first part of the paper, and it is
                            precisely with this explanation that we bridge the prejudices and
                            judgements attached to journalism and the journalist’s action in this
                            historical timeframe. With this interpretation, we also recognise the
                            huge possibilities for further research since it offers us a more
                            complex reflection and understanding of a form of journalistic action,
                            especially in line with the alternatives on which the Yugoslav
                            revolution and system were built.</p>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <list rend="ordered:1">
                            <item><p>The second, frequent interpretation that emerges from the
                                    analysis is that, through the use and conception of the
                                    expression, the Party and the other main socio-political
                                    organisations sought to mark the journalist’s action with their
                                    own goals and purposes, also including the simulated pretension
                                    of the common struggle in the construction and development of,
                                    on one hand the self-management society and on the other the
                                    socialist political community. Use of the formulation was also
                                    an attempt to control journalists in their actions. The
                                    interviewees thus noted that the designation “socio-political
                                    workers” denoted their autonomous action and thought, and above
                                    all their professional identity, which they already then
                                    understood as meaning that the journalist's labour had to be
                                    independent of political power and its intentions.</p>
                                <p>The interpretation of this strand is linked to a statement by
                                    Rastko Močnik, who in 1984 wrote that the journalist as “a
                                    socio-political worker” was “an agent of bureaucratic class
                                        struggle”,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn30" n="28">Rastko
                                        Močnik, “V boju za svobodo javne besede – danes [In the
                                        Fight for Freedom of Public Expression – Today],” [foreword]
                                        in <hi rend="italic">Cenzura in svoboda tiska</hi> [<hi
                                            rend="italic">Censorship and Press Freedom</hi>], Karl
                                        Marx and Friedrich Engels (Ljubljana: Univerzitetna
                                        konferenca ZSMS: Republiška konferenca ZSMS, 1984), 18.
                                    </note> which sheds light on the following: although the
                                    authorities wished to construct the active and engaged power of
                                    all working people, including by declaring journalists as
                                    socio-political workers, in a way they failed to do so. Thus,
                                    for most interviewees this kind of designation was either a mere
                                    programmatic and bureaucratic phrase purposely invented by the
                                    authorities to ‘simulate’ or ‘fake’ a common struggle for a new
                                    order, or was simply intended to show that the journalist’s
                                    identity in this system must only be somehow linked to narrow
                                    political power, even if in terms of the <hi rend="italic"
                                        >common good.</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn31" n="29">
                                        Aristotel, <hi rend="italic">Nikomahova etika</hi>,
                                        47–51.</note></p></item>
                            <item>This explanation is related to the previous one. Some interviewees
                                saw a minority of journalists as socio-political workers completely
                                subordinated to the authorities, implying that those journalists
                                were direct transmitters of opinions and positions that were formed
                                in closed, internal political circles. Namely, they were in a sense
                                propagandists for the Party and its interests.</item>
                        </list></item>
                </list>
                <p>However, through the paper we wanted to show the complexity of use of the
                    language game “the journalist as a socio-political worker”. We addressed the
                    formulation in the first part with the historical-conceptual method and in the
                    second part with the qualitative method of in-depth semi-structured interviews
                    with former journalists. With both methods, we tried to approach the Yugoslav
                    time and space in a distanced way, by entering into the understanding of the
                    expression internally and adapting to the normative ideas of the time: who the
                    journalist “as a socio-political worker” should be. The two methods led us to
                    several possible perspectives for explaining the term, which confirms the basic
                    point that the formulation cannot be explained by a single universal definition.
                    What is ‘universal’ in the expression is precisely its concrete connection to
                    politics.</p>
                <p>The multiple possible perspectives of understanding show that language and its
                    usage are components of human affairs, of the intersubjective world, which in
                    essence is spontaneous, contingent, plural and unpredictable. Through their own
                    particular perspectives, use of language and the outline of their professional
                    and personal histories/(auto)biographies, the interviewees interpreted and
                    explained one of the most important concepts in Yugoslav journalism and
                    presented the different possibilities of journalistic actions and practice
                    which, alongside possible interpretations of the formulation, also give an
                    incentive to research and explore the complexities of the Yugoslav
                    socio-political system, possible alternative forms of journalistic activity and
                    an alternative liveness in a manner of Catherine Samary,<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn32" n="30">Catherine Samary, <hi rend="italic">Komunizem v
                            gibanju: zgodovinskih pomen jugoslovanskega samoupravljanja</hi> [<hi
                            rend="italic">Communism in Motion: The Historical Significance of
                            Yugoslav Self-management</hi>] (Ljubljana: /*cf, 2017).</note> who sees,
                    e.g., in the Yugoslav self-management socialism subversive potential to
                    transform society and political communities and generally in the area of human
                    affairs.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="bibliography">
                <head>Sources and Literature</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl>Agamben, Giorgio. <hi rend="italic">Homo sacer: suverena oblast in golo
                            življenje</hi>. Ljubljana: Študentska založba, 2004. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Aristotel. <hi rend="italic">Nikomahova etika</hi>. Ljubljana: Slovenska
                        matica, 2002. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Aristotel. <hi rend="italic">Politika</hi>. Ljubljana: GV, 2010. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Arendt, Hannah. <hi rend="italic">O revoluciji</hi>. Ljubljana: Krtina,
                        2017. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Arendt, Hannah. <hi rend="italic">Predavanja o Kantovi politični
                            filozofiji</hi>. Ljubljana: KUD Apokalipsa, 2018.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Arendt, Hannah. <hi rend="italic">Vita activa</hi>. Ljubljana: Krtina,
                        1996.</bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="italic">Integralno besedilo ustave Socialistične federativne
                            republike Jugoslavije in amandmajev I do XLVIII k ustavi Socialistične
                            federativne republike Jugoslavije</hi>. Ljubljana: Uradni list SR
                        Slovenije, 1989. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Fischbach, Franck. “Delo in možnost demokratičnega javnega prostora.” <hi
                            rend="italic">Filozofski vestnik</hi> XXXIV, No. 3 (2013): 23–33.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Fischbach, Franck. <hi rend="italic">Kaj je socialistična vlada? Kar je
                            živo in kar je mrtvo v socializmu. </hi>Ljubljana: Krtina, 2019. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Gorjup, Mitja. <hi rend="italic">Samoupravno novinarstvo. </hi>Ljubljana:
                        Delavska enotnost, 1978. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Kardelj, Edvard. <hi rend="italic">Smeri razvoja političnega sistema
                            socialističnega samoupravljanja</hi>. Ljubljana: ČZP Komunist, 1977. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Kirn, Gal. “Jugoslovanska revolucija skozi tri partizanske prelome.” <hi
                            rend="italic">Časopis za kritiko znanosti</hi> 45, No. 269 (2017):
                        316–32.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Koselleck, Reinhart. <hi rend="italic">Pretekla prihodnost: prispevek k
                            semantiki zgodovinskih časov. </hi>Ljubljana: Studia humanitatis, 1999. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Kvale, Steiner. <hi rend="italic">Doing Interviews. </hi>London: Sage,
                        2007. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Merljak Zdovc, Sonja and Melita Poler Kovačič. “The Paradox of Slovenia:
                        Investigative Journalism during Socialism and Democracy.” <hi rend="italic"
                            >Journalism </hi>8, No. 5 (2007): 522–29.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Močnik, Rastko. “V boju za svobodo javne besede – danes.” [foreword] In:
                            <hi rend="italic">Cenzura in svoboda tiska, </hi>Karl Marx and Friedrich
                        Engels, 7–22. Ljubljana: Univerzitetna konferenca ZSMS: Republiška
                        konferenca ZSMS, 1984. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Nežmah, Bernard. <hi rend="italic">Časopisna zgodovina novinarstva.
                        </hi>Ljubljana: Študentska založba, 2012. </bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="italic">Novinarstvo</hi> I, No. 2 (1965): 204, 205. “Kodeks
                        novinara Jugoslavije.” </bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="italic">Novinarstvo</hi> IX, No. 1-2 (1973): 98–102. “Kodeks
                        novinara Jugoslavije.” </bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="italic">Novinarstvo</hi> XVIII, No. 3-4 (1982): 136–40. “Kodeks
                        novinara Jugoslavije.” </bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="italic">Novinarstvo</hi> XXIV, No. 3-4 (1988): 82, 83. “Kodeks
                        novinara Jugoslavije.” </bibl>
                    <bibl>Peruško, Zrinjka, Dina Vozab and Antonija Čuvalo. <hi rend="italic"
                            >Comparing Post-Socialist Media Systems: The Case of Southeast Europe.
                        </hi>Oxon, New York: Routledge, 2021.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Poler, Melita. “Ethics and Professionalisation of Slovene Journalism.” <hi
                            rend="italic">Javnost (The Public) </hi>3, No. 4 (1996): 107–21.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Ragin, Charles C. <hi rend="italic">Družboslovno raziskovanje: enotnost in
                            raznolikost metode</hi>. Ljubljana: Fakulteta za družbene vede, 2007. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Samary, Catherine. <hi rend="italic">Komunizem v gibanju: zgodovinskih
                            pomen jugoslovanskega samoupravljanja</hi>. Ljubljana: /*cf, 2017. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Scholtz, Gunter. “Kaj je pojmovna zgodovina in čemu se z njo ukvarjamo?.”
                            <hi rend="italic">Phainomena</hi> 11, No. 41/42 (2002): 137–58.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Vobič, Igor. “Three Paradigms of Journalistic Objectivity in Slovenian
                        Press History.” <hi rend="italic">Central European Journal of Communication
                        </hi>7, No. 1 (2014): 4–17.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Vozab, Dina and Dunja Majstorović. “The Transformation of Normative
                        Approaches to Journalism in Croatian Academic Literature from Socialism to
                        Post-Socialism.” <hi rend="italic">Croatian Political Science Review
                        </hi>58, No. 2 (2021): 7–32. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Wittgenstein, Ludwig. <hi rend="italic">Philosophical Investigations</hi>.
                        Oxford: Basil Blackwell, 1963. </bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="italic">Zakon o združenem delu</hi> (1976). Ljubljana:
                        Gospodarska založba, 1976. </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
            <div type="appendix">
                <head>APPENDIX A</head>
                <table rend="rules">
                    <head>Table 1: Interview data, including full name of interviewee, their birth
                        year, interview length, date and the type of media interviewee worked
                        at.</head>
                    <row>
                        <cell rend="center"><hi rend="bold">Last name, name</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="center"><hi rend="bold">Interview length [minute]</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="center"><hi rend="bold">Interview date
                            [year-month-date]</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="center"><hi rend="bold">Interviewee birth year</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="center" cols="3"><hi rend="bold">Media type</hi></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell rend="center"/>
                        <cell rend="center"/>
                        <cell rend="center"/>
                        <cell rend="center"/>
                        <cell rend="center"><hi rend="bold">Newspaper</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="center"><hi rend="bold">Television</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="center"><hi rend="bold">Radio</hi></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell rend="center">Ambrožič, Lado</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">127</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">2021-07-22</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">1948</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">X</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">X</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">X</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell rend="center">Bergant, Boris</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">183</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">2021-06-18</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">1948</cell>
                        <cell rend="center"/>
                        <cell rend="center">X</cell>
                        <cell rend="center"/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell rend="center">Bervar, Gojko</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">130</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">2021-06-11</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">1946</cell>
                        <cell rend="center"/>
                        <cell rend="center"/>
                        <cell rend="center">X</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell rend="center">Čuček, Janez</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">124</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">2021-07-15</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">1937</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">X</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">X</cell>
                        <cell rend="center"/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell rend="center">De Corti, Borko</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">139</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">2021-06-17</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">1948</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">X</cell>
                        <cell rend="center"/>
                        <cell rend="center"/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell rend="center">Dobljekar, Nevenka</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">109</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">2021-07-13</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">1952</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">X</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">X</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">X</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell rend="center">Drčar Murko, Mojca</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">252</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">2021-06-22</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">1942</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">X</cell>
                        <cell rend="center"/>
                        <cell rend="center">X</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell rend="center">Golob, Milan</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">112</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">2021-08-11</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">1937</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">X</cell>
                        <cell rend="center"/>
                        <cell rend="center"/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell rend="center">Gorjup, Ada</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">48</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">2021-08-13</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">1943</cell>
                        <cell rend="center"/>
                        <cell rend="center"/>
                        <cell rend="center"/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell rend="center">Grah, Stane</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">192</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">2021-07-19</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">1946</cell>
                        <cell rend="center"/>
                        <cell rend="center">X</cell>
                        <cell rend="center"/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell rend="center">Grizila, Sonja</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">125</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">2021-07-20</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">1951</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">X</cell>
                        <cell rend="center"/>
                        <cell rend="center"/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell rend="center">Grobovšek, Bojan</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">91</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">2021-07-22</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">1949</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">X</cell>
                        <cell rend="center"/>
                        <cell rend="center"/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell rend="center">Hladnik Milharčič, Ervin</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">101</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">2021-08-12</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">1954</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">X</cell>
                        <cell rend="center"/>
                        <cell rend="center">X</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell rend="center">Hočevar, Tone</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">128</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">2021-07-19</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">1946</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">X</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">X</cell>
                        <cell rend="center"/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell rend="center">Ivančič, Miloš</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">171</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">2021-07-21</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">1948</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">X</cell>
                        <cell rend="center"/>
                        <cell rend="center">X</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell rend="center">Jeklin, Bernarda</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">110</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">2021-07-12</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">1936</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">X</cell>
                        <cell rend="center"/>
                        <cell rend="center"/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell rend="center">Kajzer, Janez</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">135</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">2021-08-19</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">1938</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">X</cell>
                        <cell rend="center"/>
                        <cell rend="center"/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell rend="center">Kodrič, Zdenko</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">155</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">2021-07-13</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">1949</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">X</cell>
                        <cell rend="center"/>
                        <cell rend="center">X</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell rend="center">Komparič, Nina</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">129</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">2021-08-13</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">1945</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">X</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">X</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">X</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell rend="center">Kovač, Božo</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">160</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">2021-06-23</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">1935</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">X</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">X</cell>
                        <cell rend="center"/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell rend="center">Kozinc, Željko</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">137</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">2021-07-14</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">1939</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">X</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">X</cell>
                        <cell rend="center"/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell rend="center">Kremžar, Leo</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">171</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">2021-08-17</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">1949</cell>
                        <cell rend="center"/>
                        <cell rend="center"/>
                        <cell rend="center">X</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell rend="center">Lipušček, Uroš</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">106</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">2021-08-20</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">1947</cell>
                        <cell rend="center"/>
                        <cell rend="center">X</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">X</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell rend="center">Maksimovič, Branko</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">151</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">2021-06-16</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">1945</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">X</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">X</cell>
                        <cell rend="center"/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell rend="center">Meršol, Mitja</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">100</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">2021-08-09</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">1945</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">X</cell>
                        <cell rend="center"/>
                        <cell rend="center"/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell rend="center">Pečko, Otmar</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">116</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">2021-06-21</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">1948</cell>
                        <cell rend="center"/>
                        <cell rend="center">X</cell>
                        <cell rend="center"/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell rend="center">Pengov, Nadja</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">82</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">2021-08-16</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">1944</cell>
                        <cell rend="center"/>
                        <cell rend="center"/>
                        <cell rend="center">X</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell rend="center">Poglajen, Jože</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">84</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">2021-06-14</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">1950</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">X</cell>
                        <cell rend="center"/>
                        <cell rend="center"/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell rend="center">Praprotnik, Ivan</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">90</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">2021-08-10</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">1947</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">X</cell>
                        <cell rend="center"/>
                        <cell rend="center"/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell rend="center">Puhar, Alenka</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">142</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">2021-07-14</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">1945</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">X</cell>
                        <cell rend="center"/>
                        <cell rend="center"/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell rend="center">Rupnik, Anton</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">158</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">2021-07-20</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">1937</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">X</cell>
                        <cell rend="center"/>
                        <cell rend="center"/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell rend="center">Sedmak, Marjan</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">129</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">2021-08-09</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">1938</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">X</cell>
                        <cell rend="center"/>
                        <cell rend="center">X</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell rend="center">Štakul, Aleks</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">156</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">2021-08-16</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">1944</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">X</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">X</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">X</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell rend="center">Šuligoj, Boris</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">115</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">2021-06-16</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">1953</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">X</cell>
                        <cell rend="center"/>
                        <cell rend="center"/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell rend="center">Vizovišek, Slavko</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">158</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">2021-06-17</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">1949</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">X</cell>
                        <cell rend="center"/>
                        <cell rend="center"/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell rend="center">Založnik Rustja, Zora</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">78</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">2021-07-16</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">1939</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">X</cell>
                        <cell rend="center"/>
                        <cell rend="center">X</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell rend="center">Zei, Lada</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">159</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">2021-06-21</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">1941</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">X</cell>
                        <cell rend="center"/>
                        <cell rend="center">X</cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
            </div>
            <div type="summary" xml:lang="sl">
                <docAuthor>Nina Žnidaršič</docAuthor>
                <head>POVZETEK</head>
                <head>NOVINARJEVO DELOVANJE V SOCIALISTIČNI JUGOSLAVIJI: RAZUMEVANJE FORMULACIJE
                    »NOVINAR KOT DRUŽBENOPOLITIČNI DELAVEC«</head>
                <p>Prispevek se ukvarja z analizo jezikovne igre 'novinar kot družbenopolitični
                    delavec', ki je bila sicer profesionalna oznaka za novinarjevo delovanje v
                    nekdanji socialistični Jugoslaviji in zapisana v Kodeksu novinarjev Jugoslavije
                    do leta 1988. Analiza izraza je zasnovana z dvema metodama: zgodovinsko-pojmovno
                    metodo in družboslovno kvalitativno metodo poglobljenega polstrukturiranega
                    intervjuja, ki ga lahko imenujemo tudi pristop k oralni zgodovini. Z obema
                    metodama se skuša z analizo vstopiti v čas in prostor notranje, prilagajoče se
                    tedanjosti. Prvi del prispevka je namenjen analizi formulacije skozi programska
                    in angažirana besedila, ki so nastajala prav v socialistični Jugoslaviji.
                    Avtorica prispevka poskuša z metodo zgodovinsko-pojmovne analize zajeti idejo
                    formulacije, hkrati pa predstaviti utrip in duh, ne samo časa, ki ga proučuje,
                    temveč tudi duh, ki veje iz rabe same jezikovne igre. Drugi razdelek prispevka
                    je namenjen empirični analizi 34 poglobljenih polstrukturiranih intervjujev z
                    nekdanjimi novinarji, ki jih je avtorica prispevka skupaj z dr. Jernejem Amonom
                    Prodnikom izvedla med junijem in avgustom 2021. Intervjuvani novinarji se
                    profesionalno-demografsko umeščajo predvsem v obdobje od začetka šestdesetih
                    let, zato je empirična analiza umeščena v analizo rabe fraze v času
                    Socialistične federativne republike Jugoslavije in v prostor nekdanje
                    socialistične republike Slovenije.</p>
                <p>Že zgodovinsko-pojmovna analiza je pokazala, da je proučevana formulacija v
                    tesnem odnosu s politiko in političnostjo, vendar ne na način, da bi bil novinar
                    kot družbenopolitični delavec propagandno gonilo ozke politične oblasti, ampak
                    da naj bi prav prek lastne prakse in političnega delovanja prispeval k izgradnji
                    in razvoju po eni strani samoupravljanja, kar predstavlja družbeno in ekonomsko
                    raven ter idejo podružabljanja, po drugi strani pa socialistične skupnosti, kar
                    predstavlja raven politike, pa tudi političnega delovanja. Sam izraz
                    družbenopolitični (delavec) združuje prav obe ravni delovanja. Tako se
                    identiteta novinarja v tem času normativno izkazuje skozi postavko, da novinar
                    naj ne bi bil »zgolj« poročevalec in opazovalec družbenega dogajanja, temveč naj
                    bi z lastno prakso in izdelki utelešal angažiranega akterja družbe in politike.
                    Branje vizij in idej Edvarda Kardelja razkriva pojmovanje, da je sistem javnega
                    obveščanja, kamor se uvršča komuniciranje po tisku, radiu in televiziji,
                    razumljen kot ena izmed temeljnih političnih sil sistema, kot del širše <hi
                        rend="italic">skupne</hi> oblasti, ki zasleduje vzpostavljanje tistih
                    socialističnih in samoupravnih idej, ki še niso v polni meri ali sploh niso
                    uresničene/izvedene. Prav branje takih besedil daje vtis, da je mogoče na
                    proučevan koncept pogledati tudi skozi drugačne in predvsem kontekstualne
                    perspektive, obenem pa ustvarja kompleksnost novinarske dejavnosti v času in
                    prostoru.</p>
                <p>S poglobljenimi polstrukturiranimi intervjuji z nekdanjimi novinarji je analiza,
                    komplementarno prejšnji metodi, zasledovala notranjost pomena in rabe jezikovne
                    igre 'novinar kot družbenopolitični delavec', kajti vsi intervjuvani novinarji
                    so izkusili prostor in čas, ki ga prispevek naslavlja. Skupaj z njimi se je
                    rekonstruiralo prostor in čas in iskalo morebitne drugačne pomene proučevane
                    formulacije. Pridobljeni podatki intervjujev so podčrtali politično esenco
                    termina, in sicer se je raba termina v odnosu do politike in politične skupnosti
                    izkazovala na različne načine. Manjšinski del intervjuvancev je imel afirmativen
                    odnos do termina oziroma je nanj skušal pogledati skozi kontekst, v katerem je
                    nastal in bil rabljen. Ta pogled se sklada z zgodovinsko-pojmovno analizo. Ti
                    novinarji so novinarja kot družbenopolitičnega delavca videli povsem na isti
                    ravni kot (višje) politične odločevalce, predvsem pa mu pripisali aktivno in
                    angažirano vlogo (mnenjski voditelj), ki vpliva na zavest bralcev, poslušalcev,
                    gledalcev in z lastnim angažmajem prispeva k razvoju in nastajanju samoupravne
                    socialistične skupnosti. Po drugi strani pa je izrazito velik del intervjuvanih
                    novinarjev do pomena in rabe izraza pristopil kritično in distancirano, kar je
                    impliciralo tudi njihovo videnje profesionalnega delovanja novinarja, ki mora
                    biti neodvisen in popolnoma avtonomen v razmerju do politike in politične
                    oblasti. Pojem so videli predvsem kot izrazni način, kako skuša politična oblast
                    novinarje utiriti v lastne cilje, interese in potrebe dnevne politike.</p>
                <p>Prispevek pa ne nazadnje skuša odpreti premislek o alternativni formi
                    novinarskega delovanja, ki jo ponuja prav razumevanje jezikovne igre 'novinar
                    kot družbenopolitični delavec'; takšen novinar naj bi bil primarno aktivist in
                    angažiran akter v družbi in širši politični skupnosti, v aristotelovskem pomenu
                    besede skupnega dobrega.</p>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
