<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Border River Phenomenon: the Example of the River Mura<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn1" n="*">The authors acknowledge the project Phenomenon of Border Rivers (J6-6830) was finacially supported by the Slovenian Research Agency.</note></title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename>Marko</forename>
                        <surname>Zajc</surname>
                        <roleName>Research associate</roleName>
                        <roleName>PhD</roleName>
                        <affiliation>Institute of Contemporary History</affiliation>
                        <address>
                            <addrLine>Kongresni trg 1</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>SI-1000 Ljubljana</addrLine>
                        </address>
                        <email>marko.zajc@inz.si</email>
                    </name>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>2017-10-13</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>
                    <orgName xml:lang="sl">Inštitut za novejšo zgodovino</orgName>
                    <orgName xml:lang="en">Institute of Contemporary History</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Kongresni trg 1</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>SI-1000 Ljubljana</addrLine>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>http://ojs.inz.si/pnz/article/view/246</pubPlace>
                <date>2017</date>
                <availability status="free">
                    <licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title xml:lang="sl">Prispevki za novejšo zgodovino</title>
                <title xml:lang="en">Contributions to Contemporary History</title>
                <biblScope unit="volume">57</biblScope>
                <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
                <idno type="ISSN">2463-7807</idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source, born digital.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc xml:lang="en">
                <p>Contributions to Contemporary History is one of the central Slovenian scientific
                    historiographic journals, dedicated to publishing articles from the field of
                    contemporary history (the 19th and 20th century).</p>
                <p>The journal is published three times per year in Slovenian and in the following
                    foreign languages: English, German, Serbian, Croatian, Bosnian, Italian, Slovak
                    and Czech. The articles are all published with abstracts in English and
                    Slovenian as well as summaries in English.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <projectDesc xml:lang="sl">
                <p>Prispevki za novejšo zgodovino je ena osrednjih slovenskih znanstvenih
                    zgodovinopisnih revij, ki objavlja teme s področja novejše zgodovine (19. in 20.
                    stoletje).</p>
                <p>Revija izide trikrat letno v slovenskem jeziku in v naslednjih tujih jezikih:
                    angleščina, nemščina, srbščina, hrvaščina, bosanščina, italijanščina, slovaščina
                    in češčina. Članki izhajajo z izvlečki v angleščini in slovenščini ter povzetki
                    v angleščini.</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="sl"/>
                <language ident="en"/>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords xml:lang="en">
                    <term>Border rivers</term>
                    <term>River Mura</term>
                    <term>Environmental History</term>
                    <term>River regulations</term>
                    <term>Border Disputes</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords xml:lang="sl">
                    <term>mejne reke</term>
                    <term>Mura</term>
                    <term>okoljska zgodovina</term>
                    <term>rečne regulacije</term>
                    <term>mejni spori</term>
               </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change>
                    <date>2017-10-30</date>
                    <name>Neja Blaj Hribar</name>
                    <desc>Pretvorba iz DOCX v TEI, dodatno kodiranje</desc>
                </change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <docAuthor>Marko Zajc<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn0" n="**">
                <hi rend="bold">Research associate, PhD, Institute of Contemporary History,
                    Kongresni trg 1, SI-1000 Ljubljana, </hi>
                <ref target="mailto:marko.zajc@inz.si"><hi rend="bold">marko.zajc@inz.si</hi></ref></note></docAuthor>
            <docImprint>
                <idno type="cobissType">Cobiss type: 1.01</idno>
                <idno type="UDC">UDC: 341.222(282.24Mura)"1918/2004"</idno>
            </docImprint>
            <div type="abstract" xml:lang="sl">
                <head>IZVLEČEK</head>
                <head>FENOMEN MEJNA REKA: PRIMER MURE</head>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Avtor analizira dva vidika dolgega trajanja fenomena mejne reke na
                    primeru reke Mure: a) razmerje med rečno strugo, mejno črto in antropogenimi
                    učinki na reko; b) odkrivanje historičnih struktur skozi perspektivo mejnih
                    sporov. “Zdravorazumsko” razumevanje mejnih rek predpostavlja ujemanje reke in
                    mejne črte. Kljub temu je lahko v pokrajini in v kartografskih reprezentacijah
                    velika razlika med tema dvema elementoma.</hi></p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Ključne besede: mejne reke, Mura, okoljska zgodovina, rečne
                    regulacije, mejni spori</hi></p>
            </div>
            <div type="abstract" xml:lang="en">
                <head>ABSTRACT</head>
                <p><hi rend="italic">The Author analyses two long-term aspects of the border river
                    phenomenon with the example of the river Mura: a) the relationship between the
                    river bed, the boundaryline, and the anthropogenic effects on the river; b)
                    discovering the historical structures through the perspective of border
                    disputes. The "common sense" ideas about border rivers imply that the river bed
                    and the boundaryline usually match. However, in the actual landscape and
                    cartographic representations, the differences between these elements can be
                    significant.</hi></p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Key words: Border rivers, River Mura, Environmental History, River regulations, Border Disputes</hi></p>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div><p>Rivers were not invented by people. They are natural phenomena with their own
                dynamics, and can never be completely controlled. However, border rivers are
                different: they are social and political concepts that people "assign" to natural
                rivers. The basic goal of the project entitled "The Border River Phenomenon" has
                been to explore the relationship between "natural" rivers and the concept of border
                rivers, using selected examples. According to their classic sociological definition,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn2" n="1">
                        Georg Simmel, ”Der Raum und die räumlichen Ordnungen der Gesellschaft,” in:
                            <hi rend="italic">Grenzsoziologie, die politische Strukturierung des
                            Raumes</hi>, eds. Monika Eigmüller and Georg Vobruba (Wiesbaden: VS
                        Verlag für Sozialwissenschaft, 2006), 22.</note> borders are not a
                spatial fact with social effects, but a social fact manifesting itself in the space.
                Borders have a twofold character: they are a consequence of historical and political
                processes as well as originators of social order.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn3" n="2"> Monika Eigmüller, ”Der duale Character der
                        Grenze. Grenzsoziologie, die politische Strukturierung des Raumes” in: <hi rend="italic">Grenzsoziologie, die politische Strukturierung des
                            Raumes</hi>, eds. Monika Eigmüller and Georga Vobruba (Wiesbaden: VS
                        Verlag für Sozialwissenschaft, 2006), 55.</note> Border rivers are a
                social fact as well, but they are essentially defined by "natural" rivers. Due to
                natural fluvial processes (changing river beds, floods, drying up), border rivers
                function "on their own", "speak for themselves", and their "activities" have social
                consequences. On the other hand, human activities influence rivers as well. In the
                article we will analyse two long-term aspects of the border river phenomenon with
                the example of the river Mura: </p>
            <list type="ordered">
                <item>the relationship between the river bed, the boundaryline, and the
                    anthropogenic effects on the river;</item>
                <item>discovering the historical structures through the perspective of border
                    disputes.</item>
            </list>
                <figure>
                    <head>Picture 1: The wider geographical area.</head>
                    <graphic url="slika1.png" height="300px"/>
                    <p>Source: www.google/maps (November 16, 2017)</p>
                </figure>
            </div>
            <div>
            <head>The Relationship Between the River Bed, the Boundaryline, and the
                    Anthropogenic Effects on the River</head>
            <p>The "common‑sense" ideas about border rivers imply that the river bed and the
                boundaryline usually match. However, in the actual landscape and cartographic
                representations, the differences between these elements can be significant. The
                elements are mutually dependent: boundarylines are usually defined on the basis of
                the river beds. In turn, boundarylines may also influence the river beds (human
                activities on the river). Due to meandering and erosion, the river does not "stick"
                to the river bed as "captured" by the cartographers/geodesists in a certain
                historical moment. Boundarylines may also change due to political/administrative
                changes. </p>
            <p>The proximity of rivers calls for certain human activities. In case of border rivers,
                these activities become even more complicated: who has the jurisdiction to build
                there? Who finances the works? Who carries them out? Such activities require
                communication and coordination between the two entities, separated by the river. We
                can notice an interesting rule in the interaction between people and rivers: the
                rivers that are prone to changing their river beds often due to hydrological and
                geomorphological characteristics (meandering, dead river beds, gravel bars) – which
                means that they are active "in themselves" – call for a more significant human
                response than the rivers with relatively stable river beds. In case of border rivers
                we can underline an additional phenomenon. By changing its river bed often, a border
                river can cause political problems at the level of the two entities it separates.
                The regulation of such a river calls for the cooperation of both sides, which
                involves the coordination of works and expenses. Due to the problems with
                coordination and financing, the authorities from both sides frequently delay the
                works at the detriment of the population on both sides of the border. The history of
                river regulation is also exceedingly significant in the cases where the river has
                only recently gained the status of a border river. In such cases the history of
                regulations may be deemed as typical administrative legacy. </p>
            <p>The history of the river Mura is truly fascinating – in the sense of environmental
                history as well as regarding the delimitation of political entities. It is not
                remarkable in any way that many different disciplines have often focused on Mura and
                its history: political history, environmental history, various fields of geography,
                cartography, and hydrology. Due to the hydrological characteristics and lowlands
                environment, the downstream part of Mura has always kept changing. Mura is a part of
                the Black Sea drainage basin, a left‑bank tributary of the river Drava. It is a
                snow‑fed river system and belongs among lowland rivers, characterised by frequent
                river bed changes on the flood plains, meandering, and frequent floods (the
                frequency and scope of floods have been anthropogenically reduced by means of
                several hydro‑accumulation dams even before this river reaches Slovenia). In its
                totality, Mura is 465 kilometres long. It flows through Slovenia in the total length
                of 95 kilometres, and the section of the Slovenian "internal" Mura is approximately
                33 kilometres long.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn4" n="3">
                        Jožef Novak and Vladimir Vratarič, ”Mura nekoč, danes, jutri,” in: <hi rend="italic">14. Mišičev vodarski dan, zbornik referatov</hi> (Maribor:
                        Vodnogospodarski biro, 2003), 119.</note> Mura represents borders in the
                total distance of 115 km (25 % of the whole river). First it divides Slovenia and
                Austria between the villages of Ceršak and Petanjci (in the distance of over 33 km);
                then Slovenia and Croatia between Gibina and Krka (almost 34 km); and finally,
                Hungary and Croatia in the distance of 48 km between Krka and until it flows into
                the river Drava.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn5" n="4">
                        Simon Balažic, ”Meja na Muri,” in: <hi rend="italic">17. Mišičev vodarski
                            dan, zbornik referatov</hi> (Maribor: Vodnogospodarski biro, 2006),
                        38.</note> This contribution will focus on three sections: the border
                river Mura between Slovenia and Austria; the Slovenian "internal" Mura; and the
                border river Mura between Slovenia and Croatia. </p>
                <figure>
                    <head>Picture 2: The border river Mura between Slovenia and Austria; the Slovenian "internal" Mura; and the border river Mura between Slovenia and Croatia (contemporary situation).</head>
                    <graphic url="slika2.png" height="350px"/>
                    <p>Source: www.geopedia.si (November 16, 2017)</p>
                </figure>
            <p>In the language of political history, Mura's main characteristic could be described
                as "movement". However, the expression is not precise enough. Throughout its
                history, Mura has been creating new river beds and branches. Hydrologists describe
                it as a type of a meandering braided river, whose channel typically consists of a
                network of small channels. The majority of it does flow through its main river bed,
                but its diversion results in new main channels, while the old main channels turn
                into side channels.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn6" n="5">
                        Aleš Lesjak, ”Mura skozi čas,” in: <hi rend="italic">25. Mišičev vodarski
                            dan, zbornik referatov</hi> (Maribor: Vodnogospodarski biro, 2014),
                        183–90.</note> Mura does not only "move", but keeps changing its form as
                well. What was the cohabitation of the river and the people like in the
                circumstances before the modernisation processes? The unpredictable nature of the
                river impeded any permanent cultivation of the area by the river. For example,
                between the 15th and the 19th century, a large area of fallow land was created
                between the towns of Šentilj and Radgona, supposedly resulting predominantly from
                the untameable nature of the river. By the early modern period, the river Mura had
                shaped a large island between two of its branches, where the fortified border town
                of Radgona with its extensive fortification system and two strategically important
                bridges developed. According to the historian Hozjan, south of Radgona the river
                kept creating many new branches, and the Josephine maps reveal all sorts of river
                bed changes.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn7" n="6"> Andrej
                        Hozjan, ”Reka Mura na Slovenskem v novem veku,” <hi rend="italic">Ekonomska
                            i ekohistorija 9</hi> (2013): 17.</note> The rate of flow ratio was
                supposedly, according to the Josephine maps, 40 % of water in the main channel
                versus 60 % of water in the branch.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn8" n="7"> Balažic, ”Meja na Muri,” 40.</note> For centuries,
                the small Prekmurje region village of Dolnja Bistrica had been developing some
                distance away from the river bed. However, by the late 18<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> century Mura captured it into a U-shaped channel.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn9" n="8"> Hozjan, ”Reka Mura,” 22.</note>
                According to hydrologists, in the Middle Ages the river's basin kept changing in
                case of high water in the north, and Mura even destroyed a few villages in the
                Apaško polje plains.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn10" n="9"> Novak, Vratarič, ”Mura nekoč, danes, jutri,” 114.</note></p>
            <p>Until 1918, the section of Mura between Radgona and Gibina was a border river, while
                from Gibina to its mouth it was Hungarian. Regarding the issue at hand, we are
                especially interested in the fact that any human intervention in the river bed or
                river banks, no matter how small, was related to the border river political concept.
                Hydrological literature places the first unsystematic measures addressing the
                river's water regime management into the 16th century. Their goal was to protect the
                settlements and allow for the navigation of the river Mura. Since the late Middle
                Ages, Mura has had the greatest transport potential of all the Styrian rivers. In
                the early modern period, the centres of rafting on Mura were located in Ernovž,
                Cmurek, and Radgona. On the Hungarian side, legislation on securing the banks in
                order to protect the local settlements was already in force in the 17th century. In
                the first period of early modernisation – the Theresian period – Mura's river bed
                was surveyed (1753). On the basis of these surveys, a few meanders were shortened
                and the river banks secured.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn11" n="10"> Ibid.</note></p>
            <p>In this period, the nascent Habsburg state was mostly interested in managing river
                navigation rather than in the border function of Mura. The planned river management
                with the aim of ensuring navigation began in 1770, when a special commission
                inspected the river bed. The works were overseen by Gabrijel Gruber, a Jesuit from
                Ljubljana, while the future mathematician Jurij Vega participated in the project as
                well. The thorough regulation of the river Mura could only be implemented at the
                section before Radgona.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn12" n="11"> Hozjan, ”Reka Mura,” 26.</note> In 1799 the areas
                by the river were visited by a special bilateral commission with a geometer, which
                drew up plans to regulate the flow of Mura from Dokležovje to Veržej and Dolnja
                Bistrica. However, the plans fell through due to the Napoleonic Wars. The Hungarian
                and Styrian commissioners specified precisely which embankments and channels would
                be constructed by Styria and which by Hungary (the Zala County). The document summed
                up by Ivan Zelko reveals that the planned undertaking called for extensive
                coordination of the two political entities. Styrians were also supposed to carry out
                the construction in the Hungarian territory and vice versa.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn13" n="12"> Ivan Zelko, <hi rend="italic">Zgodovina Prekmurja. Izbrane razprave in članki</hi> (Murska Sobota:
                        Pomurska založba, 1996), 68.</note></p>
            <p>In 1810 the meander near Razkrižje was shortened in order to protect the settlement
                from the annual floods. In 1822 Mura created a new water channel near Mursko
                Središče. Thus the bridge found itself on dry land and regulation was necessary in
                order to steer Mura back to its old river bed. The construction of the Ledava – Krka
                relief channel and the relocation of the mouth of Krka's tributary Ledava around
                1850 were important as well. In the second half of the 19th century, large-scale
                regulation took place. In 1874 the government in Vienna adopted a decision to
                finance the regulation of three sections of the river Mura between Graz and Cven
                (the so-called Hohenburg Regulation 1874 – 1891). The majority of the works took
                place at the section between Graz and Wildon as well as between Wildon and
                    Radgona.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn14" n="13"> Novak
                        and Vratarič, ”Mura nekoč, danes, jutri,” 115.</note> The expenses of
                the ambitions construction projects were shared by the central government (40 %),
                the province of Styria (40 %), and the district administrations between Graz and
                Ljutomer (10 %).<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn15" n="14">
                        <hi rend="italic">Slovenski gospodar</hi>, 1. 10. 1874, 345.</note>
                During these works (between 1878 and 1879), high water and damage in the sections
                that had not yet been regulated occurred. The regulation was strengthened and
                expanded to other sections as well, but the works at the section bordering on
                Hungary were carried out very sparsely. The reasons for the Hungarian diminished
                interest in what was then its border river were closely connected with the border
                status of this section of the river. According to the Slovenski gospodar newspaper,
                on 8 October 1878 the Styrian Provincial Diet demanded that the government in Vienna
                persuade the Hungarian government "to take part in the joint regulation of the river
                Mura at the Styrian-Hungarian border.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn16" n="15">
                        <hi rend="italic">Slovenski gospodar</hi>, 8. 10. 1878, 413.</note>
            </p>
                <figure>
                    <head>Picture 3: Mura river near Veržej on the First Military Survey map (1763-1787) and the contemporary situation.</head>
                    <graphic url="slika3.png" height="420px"/>
                    <p>Sources: Rajšp, Vinko et al. (eds.). Slovenija na vojaškem zemljevidu 1763–1787. Band 6. Ljubljana, 2000; www.geopedia.si (November 16, 2017).</p>
                </figure>
            <p>In the beginning of the 20th century, the local large estate owners at the Hungarian
                side of Mura organised themselves and established a river cooperative in Lendava in
                1901. The cooperative was supposed to address the water management problems in
                certain parts of the Zala County. It drew up plans for the regulation of streams and
                draining of certain areas, but the Zala County did not give its concession for the
                construction works until as late as 1907. The cooperative was supposed to broaden
                the river bed of Ledava and maintain the conditions of the following streams:
                Ledava, Krka, Kobiljski potok, Bukovnica, Libenica, Črnec, Lipnica, and Bogojinski
                potok. With the dissolution of the Habsburg Monarchy in 1918, the works at the river
                Mura stopped. Due to the abandonment of maintenance works at the section between
                Špilj and Radgona (after 1919 the new border between the Republic of Austria and the
                Kingdom of SHS), certain sections of Mura broadened significantly (up to 200
                metres). Due to the neglect of its banks, Mura flooded several times between 1918
                and 1926 (Bunčani, Veržej, Dokležovje, Melinci). The interwar period authorities
                only undertook the regulation works at the (new) internal section of Mura after the
                catastrophic floods.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn17" n="16"> Novak and Vratarič, ”Mura nekoč, danes, jutri,” 116.</note> On 12
                November 1925, Ledava and Kučnica flooded Murska Sobota. In just a few hours, the
                city transformed into a "Prekmurje Venice", and the homes of almost a third of its
                citizens were destroyed.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn18" n="17"> Darja Kerec, ”Prekmurske Benetke leta 1925,” <hi rend="italic">Prispevki za novejšo zgodovino</hi> 51, No. 3 (2011):
                        26.</note> Due to the poor state of Mura's river bed, the Interstate
                Commission for the Regulation of Mura was established in Maribor in 1926. It was
                tasked with managing all of the works at the (border) river. The states agreed that
                each of them would restore the extensive embankments on their respective banks of
                the border river Mura, while they would share the expenses for the works required at
                the river bed itself. The works were concluded in 1937/38, and since then Mura's
                rate of flow has increased significantly.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn19" n="18"> Novak and Vratarič, ”Mura nekoč, danes, jutri,”
                        116.</note></p>
            <p>A few fortification works at the (internal) river Mura were carried out in 1928,
                while between 1936 and 1938 it was regulated between Sladki vrh and Apače. Despite
                everything, the 1938 floods were catastrophic. Mura engulfed more than 40 villages
                on both sides, almost flooding the entire Mursko polje plains. In light of this
                disaster, the Prekmurje correspondent of the Slovenski gospodar newspaper complained
                that the authorities neglected the Prekmurje region, and that Mura should have been
                systematically regulated a long time ago. He also underlined that the inhabitants of
                Prekmurje could see clearly how Austria assisted the victims of the floods in its
                territory, and that "this certainly does not contribute to national awareness".<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn20" n="19">
                        <hi rend="italic">Slovenski gospodar</hi>, 1. 6. 1938, 7.</note> After
                these floods, the authorities established an action committee tasked with ensuring a
                comprehensive protection of the area by constructing embankments along a lengthy
                section of the river. However, World War II started before any construction works
                even began. The period of the socialist Yugoslavia was the time of the most
                significant investments into the water infrastructure in the Pomurje region. We
                should also mention the construction of the dry relief channel Ledava-Mura,
                constructed in order to prevent floods in Murska Sobota (the works were initiated in
                1948 and completed in 1958). The other tributaries of the river Mura were gradually
                regulated and dammed as well. In 1966 the regulation of the border river Kučnica
                began in cooperation with Austria. The expropriation, replacement of land plots, and
                new definition of the boundaryline were carried out as well.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn21" n="20"> Novak and Vratarič, ”Mura nekoč,
                        danes, jutri,” 118, 119.</note> At this point we do not have enough
                space to list all of the regulation works in this period. In short, by 1985 the
                river Ledava had been completely regulated (the section bordering on Hungary was not
                regulated until as late as 1997). Due to occasional flooding (for example in 1972),
                experts supported the finding that in addition to strengthening the river bank,
                accumulations and dry reservoirs should be constructed on both sides of the river
                Mura as well. Until the end of the 1980s, three accumulations (lakes) and a single
                dry reservoir were constructed on each side of Mura.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn22" n="21"> Ibid., 120.</note>
            </p>
            <p>By the dissolution of the common state, the Pomurje region had become, in the sense
                of its watercourses, a completely artificially-regulated landscape with channels,
                embankments, and artificial lakes that had not existed previously. The secondary
                river branches and marshes had largely disappeared from the landscape. The estimate
                that the geographical character of the landscape has changed most profoundly
                precisely due to watercourse regulation is not an exaggeration. However, human
                interventions into the nature of the river Mura and its tributaries have also
                resulted in unforeseen consequences. In the period of the so-called "natural" Mura,
                the width of the river and its secondary river beds reached up to 1.2 km, but it was
                narrowed to as little as 60 – 80 metres by means of hydrological interventions.
                These processes have resulted in a greater speed of the river and a more significant
                power of erosion. Due to the fortified banks, the erosion power of the river cannot
                be distributed throughout its bed: instead all of the energy goes toward deepening
                the river bed.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn23" n="22">
                        Lesjak, ”Mura skozi čas,” 188.</note> Consequently the groundwater level
                in the whole Mura drainage basin is decreasing, the groves by the river are drying
                out, and the drinking water reserves are diminishing.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn24" n="23"> Novak and Vratarič, ”Mura nekoč,
                        danes, jutri,” 121.</note> In the study ordered by the Permanent
                Slovenian-Austrian Commission for Mura, the experts proposed the following measures
                in 2001: widening the basin of the border river Mura to 200 metres; constructing
                side branches (or restoring the old ones); and adding gravel.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn25" n="24"> Norbert Baumann, Štefan Fartek,
                        Rudolf Hornich, Jožef Novak and Oliver Rathschüler, <hi rend="italic">Načelna vodnogospodarska zasnova za mejno Muro, I. Faza</hi>
                        (Gradec/Graz: Stalna slovensko-avstrijska komisija za Muro, 2001),
                    5.</note> These measures can thus be interpreted as the very opposite of the
                interventions in the 19th and 20th century. From the viewpoint of environmental
                history, the example of Mura is interesting because of the relationship between the
                river and human interventions in the long run: if repeated attempts had been made to
                "capture" Mura into a single fortified river bed for more than three centuries (and
                regulate its unpredictable tributaries), in the last few decades measures have been
                initiated to undertake a (limited) reconstruction of the pre-regulation
                    conditions.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn26" n="25">
                        Ibid., 17.</note></p>
                <figure>
                    <head>Picture 4: River Mura between Radgona and Ljutomer, 1872.</head>
                    <graphic url="slika4.png" height="450px"/>
                    <p>Source: G Mayr: Südliches Steyermark. Illyrian, Friaul. Küstenland. Gotha 1872.</p>
                </figure>
            <p>According to the findings of hydrologists, after World War II the maintenance and
                construction works at the basin of the river Mura where it borders on Austria have
                been most thorough, while they have been less intensive at the river's internal
                sections and where it borders on Croatia.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn27" n="26"> Novak and Vratarič, ”Mura nekoč, danes, jutri,”
                        119.</note> At the Slovenian-Croatian border, the river is – in
                comparison with the section bordering on Austria – still quite natural and belongs
                among moderately altered watercourses, while a few sections at this part of the
                river have been regulated as well, due to the danger of flooding.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn28" n="27"> Balažic, ”Meja na Muri,”
                    40.</note> The extensive works aimed at systematically regulating the river
                in the territory of Slovenia were carried out between 1972 and 1990, up to the town
                of Bakovci. At a part of the river Mura, located downstream from Mursko Središće (at
                the border between Croatia and Slovenia), individual meanders have been separated
                from the main river bed.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn29" n="28"> Mitja Brilly , Mojca Šraj, Anja Horvat, Andrej Vidmar
                        and Maja Koprivšek, ”Hidrološka študija reke Mure,” in: <hi rend="italic">20. Mišičev vodarski dan 2011, zbornik referatov</hi> (Maribor:
                        Vodnogospodarski biro, 2011), 158.</note> The main works (canals) were
                carried out from the 1960s and until as late as 1990. The works were carried out by
                Slovenia and Croatia, jointly and in accordance with the 50:50 system, regardless of
                the cadastral border. Hydrologists should supposedly observe the rule that the left
                bank is Slovenian and the right bank is Croatian.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn30" n="29"> Balažic, ”Meja na Muri,” 40.</note> The
                Final Award of the Arbitral Tribunal (of 29 June 2017) also quotes a 1967 document
                mentioning the project of regulating Mura with channels near Hotiza.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn31" n="30"> ”PCA CASE NO.
                        2012-04 IN THE MATTER OF AN ARBITRATION UNDER THE ARBITRATION AGREEMENT
                        BETWEEN THE GOVERNMENT OF THE REPUBLIC OF CROATIA AND THE GOVERNMENT OF THE
                        REPUBLIC OF SLOVENIA, SIGNED ON 4 NOVEMBER 2009 BETWEEN THE REPUBLIC OF
                        CROATIA AND THE REPUBLIC OF SLOVENIA, FINAL AWARD, 29 June 2017,” accessed
                        August 5, 2017, <ref target="https://pcacases.com/web/sendAttach/2172">https://pcacases.com/web/sendAttach/2172</ref>. </note>
            </p>
            <p>Rivers as transnational natural phenomena with their unpredictable "lives" tend to
                force political entities to engage in long-term cooperation. We have already
                mentioned the first permanent bilateral commission between Austria and the Kingdom
                of SHS/Yugoslavia, established in 1926. On 16 December 1954, the Federal People's
                Republic of Yugoslavia signed the agreement on the establishment of a permanent
                bilateral commission for the river Mura, and ratified it in 1956. The commission was
                tasked with the joint investigation and resolution of water management issues,
                implementation of measures, and realisation of works at the border section of Mura
                and its branches due to pollution and drainage of water from the river. After it
                attained independence, the Republic of Slovenia ratified this agreement in
                    1993.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn32" n="31"> Aleš
                        Bizjak, ”Transboundary Cooperation of the Republic of Slovenia –
                        Obligations, Good Practices and Benefits, ”<hi rend="italic">2nd Workshop on
                            Assessing the Water-Food-Energy-Ecoystem Nexus and Benefits of
                            Transboundary Cooperation in the Drina River Basin, Belgrade, 8 – 9
                            November 2016</hi>,” accessed August 3, 2017, <ref target="https://www.unece.org/fileadmin/DAM/env/documents/2016/wat/11Nov_08-10_Nexus_2nd-WS_Drinabasin_Belgrade/day_3/ab_UNECE_NEXUS_BELGRADE__Transboundary_Cooperation_091116.pdf">https://www.unece.org/fileadmin/DAM/env/documents/2016/wat/11Nov_08-10_Nexus_2nd-WS_Drinabasin_Belgrade/day_3/ab_UNECE_NEXUS_BELGRADE__Transboundary_Cooperation_091116.pdf</ref>.</note>
                It is relevant for the contemporary history of the border river Mura that after
                their independence, Croatia and Slovenia have not formed any dedicated bilateral
                commissions for this river. However, they did indeed agree (in 1996) to establish a
                Permanent Slovenian-Croatian Commission for Water Management. The rules on the
                activities of this Commission were not ratified by the two states until as late as
                    1998.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn33" n="32"> “Uredba o
                        ratifikaciji Pravilnika stalne slovensko-hrvaške komisije za vodno
                        gospodarstvo,” <hi rend="italic">Uradni list Republike Slovenije</hi>
                        11/1998.</note> The sub-commission for Mura operates in the context of
                this Commission as well. </p></div>
            <div>
            <head>Discovering Historical Structures Through Border Disputes</head>
            <p>How can we "discern" the role and changes of the political structures from the
                example of border rivers? Documents about border disputes represent an excellent
                source for analysing the relations between the state structures and the situation
                "in the field". Border river disputes can drag on for several centuries. In order to
                solve the current border disputes, it is especially important to understand the rich
                pre‑history (a part of the border rivers' administrative legacy). River border
                disputes can also "become obsolete" and calm down due to altered circumstances, or
                can also be created anew as a river acquires the status of a border river. </p>
            <p>At the river Mura between the towns of Radgona and Ljutomer, the border between the
                German part of the Roman Empire or Styria and Hungary had been settled by the middle
                of the 13th century, in so far as that was possible in the medieval
                    circumstances.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn34" n="33">
                        Milko Kos, <hi rend="italic">Srednjeveški urbarji za Slovenijo, Urbarji
                            Salzburške nadškofije</hi> (Ljubljana: Akademija znanosti in umetnosti,
                        1939), 12.</note> In the published medieval sources and older
                historiography we can find several reports on the river Mura border disputes. A more
                detailed analysis of these disputes reveals that one of the reasons for the disputes
                was the combination of this river's twofold role: Mura as a medieval border river
                (in view of the nature of the river, this border could only possess a zoning
                character); and Mura as an economic and geographic factor. The first recorded border
                dispute at the river Mura proves that the medieval actors would also use the natural
                might of the river for strategic and military purposes. If the border at the river
                Mura was relatively calm at the turn of the 12th century (at this time permanent
                settlements were developing there), after 1233 the border disputes reignited for a
                little while. In that year the Hungarian army invaded Styria, but it soon retreated.
                Judging from the Hungarian archive resources, Styrians supposedly used the tactics
                of flooding the river. They dammed the river Mura, and the water flooded several
                villages on the Hungarian side. The situation was remedied by a Hungarian dignitary
                who tore down the dam and restored the previous conditions.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn35" n="34"> László Mayer and András Molnár,
                        eds.,
                        <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Viri za zgodovino Prekmurja 1 / Források a Muravidék történetéhez 1 </hi>(Szombathely
                        – Zalaegerszeg: Arhiv županije Vas in Arhiv županije Zala, 2008),
                    45.</note></p>
            <p>In the first half of the 16th century, disputes between the inhabitants of the two
                river banks would often arise due to Mura's inconstant flow. Tomaž Széchy, a
                landowner with land holdings in Gornja Lendava and Murska Sobota, attempted to
                protect his extensive properties in the Prekmurje region by constructing two river
                beds on his side, steering the flow of Mura towards the Styrian side. There the
                river started eroding the fertile land and getting closer to the settlements.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn36" n="35"> Zelko,
                        <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Zgodovina Prekmurja, </hi>65.</note>
                The Styrian imperial representative contacted the Hungarian feudal landowner, who
                was unwilling to negotiate. In 1511 the Styrian side decided to implement unilateral
                measures. It deployed an engineer and his team of workers to the river Mura in order
                to construct a dam that would benefit Styria. After a few days Széchy attacked them,
                scattering the workers and imprisoning the engineer. Széchy's people strengthened
                the embankments even further, and due to the rushing river several fields and even a
                few villages on the right bank of Mura disappeared. When the Styrian provincial
                government once again sent its commissioners to the river in 1524, Széchy fired on
                them with cannons and rifles. The Styrian subjects attempted to fortify the river
                bank on their own, but the "Hungarians" would not allow them to drive stakes into
                the river. Anton Banffy, owner of land holdings in Dolnja Lendava, would allegedly
                behave in a similar manner. The disputes continued; various commissions would meet
                unsuccessfully; but nothing changed in the field. In 1537 Styrians excavated several
                ditches under military protection in order to prevent Mura from doing so much
                damage. However, Széchy's successor Aleksij Thurzo ordered that the ditches be
                buried immediately. Already next year the Hungarian lord once again repaired the
                embankments to his own benefit. When Styrians attempted to remedy the situation in
                1539, armed conflicts broke out, and according to Kovačič "a Hungarian tax
                collector, who agitated the people, was thrown into the river Mura with his arms and
                legs bound". The disputes could not be appeased. Bloody skirmishes kept occurring,
                and year after year "bloody robbery and violence was reported". Nevertheless,
                towards the end of the 16th century the conflicts gradually cooled down.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn37" n="36"> Fran Kovačič, <hi rend="italic">Ljutomer, Zgodovina trga in sreza</hi> (Maribor:
                        Zgodovinsko društvo, 1926), 24.</note></p>
            <p>According to Kovačič, it could also happen that Mura itself would remedy what
                "Hungarians took from Styrians unjustly". Towards the end of the 17th century, Mura
                changed its flow yet again. The inhabitants of the Styrian village of Hrastje
                acquired a bit of territory that they started using as grazing grounds. In the
                middle of the 18th century, attempts were made to take away the villagers' right to
                grazing, and therefore they complained to the provincial authorities. According to
                the older Slovenian historiography, the border between Hungary and Styria was
                supposedly settled in 1755, during the Theresian consolidation of the Habsburg
                Empire, especially in the upper part of the river Mura between Radgona and
                    Mota.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn38" n="37"> Zelko,
                        <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Zgodovina Prekmurja, </hi>68.</note>
                The subjects built dams and placed border stones in order to mark the border between
                the political entities. The latter would often be removed by the river, which kept
                flooding. However, according to Fran Kovačič, after this regulation major border
                disputes no longer occurred.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn39" n="38"> Kovačič,
                        <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Ljutomer, </hi>25.</note> In the
                19th century, Mura became a "solid" state border for a short time, in 1848 and 1849,
                when the revolutionary Hungary achieved significant autonomy in its relations with
                Vienna. This was followed by a reaction from the Habsburg Court.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn40" n="39"> László Kontler, <hi rend="italic">Madžarska zgodovina</hi> (Ljubljana: Slovenska matica, 2005),
                    203.</note> On 11 September 1848, the Habsburg General and Croatian Ban
                Jelačić invaded Hungary over the river Drava near Varaždin and proceeded into the
                territory of Zala County, which included the south-eastern part of the Prekmurje
                region. On the same day the members of the Zala County National Guard burned the
                bridge over Mura near Lendava. On the basis of the memoirs of a Hungarian National
                Guard member we can identify the basic characteristics of the bridge that was
                destroyed by the defenders. The straw ropes, covered in an abundance of tar
                beforehand, were set on fire. As it was windy, the fire simply "devoured the dry
                planks and beams".<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn41" n="40">
                        Mayer and Molnár, <hi rend="italic">Viri za zgodovino Prekmurja 1</hi>,
                        354.</note></p>
            <p>In the tumultuous times of the establishment of new states in the Central Europe and
                the formation of new state borders between 1918 and 1920, the status of the border
                at the river Mura changed a few times. On 12 August 1919, the Army of the Kingdom of
                SHS occupied the Prekmurje region, and this territory on the left bank of Mura was
                finally annexed to the Yugoslav state with the Treaty of Trianon (4 June 1920). It
                is interesting that during the occupation (between August 1919 and June 1920), the
                border at Mura was not abolished, but rather even strengthened. The passage of the
                inhabitants of Prekmurje over Mura was only possible with permits. In the autumn of
                1920, Prekmurje was still a closed territory, and the Prekmurje press complained
                that soldiers would not let people cross Mura without the permits that were
                difficult to obtain.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn42" n="41"> Vanek Šiftar, ”Prekmurje 1918–1920,” <hi rend="italic">Časopis za
                            zgodovino in narodopisje</hi> 61, No. 1 (1989): 49.</note> At the
                same time, the Hungarian authorities attempted to emphasise the significance of the
                border on the river Mura. On 15 April 1921, the Zala County lodged a complaint
                against the secession of the territories by the river. They emphasised that Mura was
                a broad and quick river that separated the villages on both sides "like the Great
                Wall of China". The inhabitants of the two river banks did not know each other, nor
                did they cooperate or trade. They also emphasised the fact that there were not any
                bridges across Mura throughout the whole border, from Radgona to Mursko
                    središče.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn43" n="42">
                        László Mayer and András Molnár, eds.,
                        <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Viri za zgodovino Prekmurja 2 / Források a Muravidék történetéhez 2 </hi>(Szombathely
                        – Zalaegerszeg: Arhiv županije Vas in Arhiv županije Zala, 2008),
                    330.</note>
            </p>
                <figure>
                    <head>Picture 5: The contemporary situation near Hotiza.</head>
                    <graphic url="slika5.png" height="400px"/>
                    <p>Source: www.geopedia.si (November 16, 2017).</p>
                </figure>
            <p>The National Government in Ljubljana was well-aware of this. On 13 October 1919, the
                Commissioner of Social Welfare reported to Ljubljana that the only road connection
                with Prekmurje was the bridge in Radgona, which, however, now belonged to the
                Republic of Austria.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn44" n="43"> Peter Ribnikar, ed., <hi rend="italic">Sejni zapisniki Narodne vlade
                            Slovencev, Hrvatov in Srbov v Ljubljani in Deželnih vlad za Slovenijo
                            1918–1921, 2. del</hi> (Ljubljana: Arhiv republike Slovenije, 1999),
                        385.</note> The Slovenian political elite strived to ensure that the
                bridge over Mura near Veržej would be built as soon as possible, even though
                complications kept arising regarding the financing of the construction works.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn45" n="44">
                        <hi rend="italic">Slovenec</hi>, 5. 2. 1922, 2.</note> The Veržej bridge
                was opened solemnly on 23 April 1922.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn46" n="45">
                        <hi rend="italic">Jutro</hi>, 25. 4. 1922, 2.</note> That the opening
                was related to the former border river status is also proven by the fact that the
                members of the Yugoslav-Austrian and Yugoslav-Hungarian delimitation commissions
                were invited to the event.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn47" n="46">
                        <hi rend="italic">Slovenec</hi>, 19. 4. 1922, 2.</note></p>
            <p>While the processes of approximation were underway at the former border section of
                the river Mura, at the new Austrian-Yugoslav border disputes and difficulties with
                the delimitation kept arising. The new state border at the river Mura between Cmurek
                and Radgona weighed heavily on the peasants between Drava and Mura. Until the end of
                1921, the Yugoslav authorities allowed access to mills and saws at the border river,
                but in the beginning of 1922 the customs services prohibited the access. After the
                intervention of the Slovenian Members of Parliament in Belgrade, the access to the
                aforementioned mills and saws was included in the agreement on the frontier-zone
                traffic with the Republic of Austria.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn48" n="47"> Franjo Žebot, ”Resnica o mlinih in žagah ob Muri,” <hi rend="italic">Slovenski gospodar</hi>, 24. 8. 1922, 35.</note> The
                paths that the local population could use to cross the border due to economic
                reasons or in emergencies were specified. Newspapers urged people not to transport
                prohibited goods across the Mura border: "Should smuggling start occurring at the
                border, the government will, as it has already threatened, immediately put a stop to
                the whole frontier-zone traffic. In such a case it would be very difficult to
                restore the current concessions".<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn49" n="48"> Franjo Žebot, ”Mali obmejni promet,” <hi rend="italic">Slovenski gospodar</hi>, 28. 12. 1922, 53.</note> The next bridge
                over Mura, near Radenci, was not open until as late as 1940.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn50" n="49">
                        <hi rend="italic">Slovenski gospodar</hi>, 24. 9. 1940, 4.</note></p>
            <p>During the period of World War II (1941–45), Prekmurje was reannexed to Hungary, and
                subsequently (after the Soviet occupation and the arrival of the Yugoslav forces) to
                Yugoslavia or the People's Republic of Slovenia.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn51" n="50"> Metka Fujs, ”Izhodišča madžarske okupacijske
                        politike v Prekmurju,” <hi rend="italic">Prispevki za novejšo zgodovino</hi>
                        37, No. 2 (1997): 175-86.</note> The river Mura
                between Gibina and the triple border with Hungary may have indeed received the
                status of a border between two Yugoslav federal units (People's Republic of Slovenia
                and People's Republic of Croatia). However, no disputes regarding the border at the
                river Mura took place in the post-war period. It is interesting that the biggest
                border dispute between Slovenia and Croatia after World War II took place in the
                vicinity of Mura. The conflict occurred in the former Štrigova municipality, the
                only part of Međimurje that had been included in the "Slovenian" Drava Banate after
                the administrative reorganisation of 1929. After 1945, however, this territory was
                annexed to Croatia. Regardless of the dimensions of the dispute (people would also
                express their discontent with petitions and gatherings) and the proximity of the
                villages involved, the river Mura did not play any role in this particular border
                    dispute.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn52" n="51"> Zdenko
                        Čepič, ”Oris nastajanja slovensko-hrvaške meje po drugi svetovni vojni,” in:
                        Zdenko Čepič, Dušan Nećak and Miroslav Stiplovšek, eds.,
                        <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Mikužev zbornik </hi>(Ljubljana:
                        Oddelek za zgodovino Filozofske fakultete, 1999), 201-16.</note></p>
            <p>In the period between 1945 and 1991, Mura did not "actively" appear in the
                international (or inter-republican) disputes. The nature of the border between two
                Yugoslav federal units did not call for a precise demarcation or division of
                jurisdiction. However, with the dissolution of Yugoslavia in 1991, the relations in
                the Slovenia – Mura – Croatia triangle once again became complicated. The problem of
                the so-called twofold ownership appeared by the Slovenian-Croatian border at the
                river Mura, which had remained in the background before the emancipation of both of
                the states involved, even though even in the Yugoslav period there had been
                differences between the taxation of property in Croatia and Slovenia. In 1992, in
                the Lendava municipality, 2963 landowners from Croatia owned 805 hectares of land or
                3.1 % of the territory. On the other hand, around 800 landowners from the Lendava
                municipality – most of them from Hotiza – owned land in Croatia as well.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn53" n="52"> Borut Belec,
                        ”Hrvaška zemljiška posest v občini Lendava kot sestavina mejne
                        problematike,” <hi rend="italic">Dela</hi> 12 (1997): 186.</note> Near
                the Slovenian village of Hotiza, the border between the Slovenian and Croatian
                cadastre is furthest away from Mura, and therefore the considerable number of land
                property owners in Croatia is not surprising. The cadastral border between the
                states follows the river as it was identified by the creators of the Hungarian
                cadastral measurements in the 19th century. Since then the river has changed its
                flow considerably, while the cadastral municipality borders have remained in the
                ongoing administration of both states as the Habsburg administrative legacy. </p>
            <p>It is important for the future development of the events that the equalisation of the
                Slovenian-Croatian border and the cadastral border took place rather late. The
                border between Slovenia and Croatia might have had an administrative and state-legal
                character (the Yugoslav republics were defined as "states"). However, in the field
                the boundaryline was not defined precisely until as late as 1980. In 1980, the
                legislation on municipalities changed in Slovenia, and now set out that the
                territories of the municipalities should correspond to the cadastral municipalities.
                As the border between Slovenia and Croatia had been defined descriptively as the
                border between the Slovenian and Croatian municipalities, the border between the
                Slovenian and Croatian cadastres de facto became the Slovenian-Croatian
                boundaryline. In the first years of independence, Slovenian geodesists underlined
                that the border according to cadastral municipalities "will not be functional and
                prudent", and saw bilateral harmonisation with the assistance of joint commissions
                as the right way of defining the border.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn54" n="53"> Božo Demšar, ”Ureditev državne meje Slovenije s
                        Hrvaško,” <hi rend="italic">Geodetski vestnik</hi> 36, No. 4 (1992): 298-303. </note></p>
            <p>The discrepancies between the cadastral border and Mura's river bed paved the way for
                the border incidents near Hotiza in 2006. Despite the multiple attempts at
                specifying the border between the states (e.g. the efforts of joint commissions
                between 1993 and 1998 and the so-called "Drnovšek-Račan Agreement" of 2001), the
                Slovenian-Croatian border at the river Mura in 2006 was just as vague as in
                    1991.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn55" n="54">
                        <hi rend="italic">Arbitraža, Vlada Republike Slovenije</hi>, accessed
                        October 10, 2017, <ref target="http://www.vlada.si/teme_in_projekti/arbitraza/">http://www.vlada.si/teme_in_projekti/arbitraza/</ref>. </note> The
                series of incidents began already in May 2005, when the Croatian authorities
                confiscated a river Mura ferry, owned by the inhabitants of Hotiza (internet 1). In
                March 2005, the Croatian side started building a bridge across Mura without any
                agreement with Slovenia, and did not open it for traffic until as late as the summer
                of 2006, due to high water. Because of the bridge, the Slovenian authorities
                protested more than once. According to the opinion of the Slovenian water experts,
                the bridge worsened the local flood safety.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn56" n="55"> Balažic, ”Meja na Muri,” 41.</note></p>
            <p>The considerable flooding potential of the river Mura and the importance of flood
                protection embankments represented an important environmental and historical factor
                in this story.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn57" n="56"> Blaž
                        Komac, Karel Natek and Matija Zorn, <hi rend="italic">Geografski vidiki
                            poplav v Sloveniji</hi> (Ljubljana: Založba ZRC, 2008), 138.</note>
                In August 2005 Mura flooded, and it turned out that new embankments should be
                constructed on both banks of the river in order to improve flood safety. However,
                who would be building in the territory under dispute? Before 1991 it was the
                Slovenian side that would traditionally build embankments on the left bank of Mura.
                Slovenian institutions started constructing the embankments, but only in the
                territory of the Slovenian cadastre.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn58" n="57"> Boris Cipot in Sebastijan Kopušar, ”Hotižani: Dež
                        prehitel diplomacijo,” <hi rend="italic">Dnevnik</hi>, 30. 8.
                    2006.</note> Towards the end of August 2006, the Croatian side started
                building embankments on the left bank of Mura (in the Croatian cadastre) without
                asking the Slovenian government for permission. The developments near Hotiza
                attained significant media dimensions. In Slovenia, the territory around Hotiza
                suddenly became a matter of national interest. After the meeting of both Prime
                Ministers in the disputed territory on 2 September 2006, an agreement was reached on
                the joint construction of embankments at the river Mura, and the issue temporarily
                vanished from the media. Not for long, though. The border dispute culminated on 13
                September 2006, when the Croatian police detained a few Slovenian journalists due to
                their alleged illegal crossing of the state border. The Slovenian authorities
                reacted immediately and demonstrated force, deploying a fully-outfitted special
                police unit at the border.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn59" n="58"> ”Novinarje so pridržali, na meji specialci,” <hi rend="italic">Dnevnik</hi>, 14. 9. 2006.</note> The Slovenian police
                lined up at the cadastral border and crossed it as well. They dug up the
                newly-constructed road and brought down two trees on it. This was a road within the
                borders of the Croatian cadastre, linking the hamlet of Murišče with the Croatian
                side. The miniscule settlement with nine inhabitants was caught in the "limbo" of
                the Slovenian-Croatian dispute. The hamlet has been entered into the Slovenian
                Register of Spatial Units, but within the Croatian cadastre.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn60" n="59"> ”Regulacija Mure izvor
                        nesoglasij,” <hi rend="italic">Dnevnik</hi>, 15. 9. 2006.</note> The
                conflict was appeased after the agreement of the Slovenian-Croatian Commission for
                Water Management of 15 September 2006 on the joint restoration of the high-water
                embankment Kot-Hotiza on the left bank of Mura.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn61" n="60"> “Zapisnik XI. zasedanja Stalne slovensko-hrvaške
                        komisije za vodno gospodarstvo, Ljubljana, 9. in 10. 6. 2015,” accessed
                        August 5, 2017, <ref target="http://gis.arso.gov.si/related/evode/vg_komisije/SLO-CRO_zasedanje%2011_junij%202015.pdf">http://gis.arso.gov.si/related/evode/vg_komisije/SLO-CRO_zasedanje%2011_junij%202015.pdf</ref>.
                    </note></p>
            <p>There is no room here for an additional historical discourse analysis of the dispute.
                However, a short media analysis of the conflict by the border river Mura in 2006
                indicates the importance of the representations of border rivers in various
                environments. Judging from the Croatian response, Croatia completely equalised the
                state border with the cadastral border. Meanwhile, for the Slovenian leadership the
                cadastral border represented merely one of the criteria for defining the borders in
                the future. While the Croatian media reported on the cadastre as the indisputable
                border between the states,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn62" n="61"> ”Balvani na Muri,” <hi rend="italic">Slobodna
                            Dalmacija</hi>, 15. 9. 2006, accessed August 5, 2017, <ref target="http://arhiv.slobodnadalmacija.hr/20060915/novosti03.asp">http://arhiv.slobodnadalmacija.hr/20060915/novosti03.asp</ref>.
                    </note> the Slovenian press would relativise the cadastral border. The
                correspondent of the Dnevnik newspaper claimed that the disputed territory may well
                have been a part of the Croatian cadastre, but that it was nevertheless "sovereign
                Slovenian territory".<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn63" n="62"> Boris Cipot, “Hrvati so si privoščili še eno
                        provokacijo,” <hi rend="italic">Dnevnik</hi>, 28. 8. 2006.</note> The
                Slovenian media would not clarify the complex circumstances by the border river
                until the dispute escalated extremely and the police forces of both states were
                staring down the barrels of their guns.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn64" n="63"> Marjeta Kralj and Mojca Zorko, ”Vrsta pozivov k
                        pomiritvi,” <hi rend="italic">Dnevnik</hi>, 15. 9. 2006, 4.</note></p>
            <p>The activities of the permanent inter-state bodies, which usually take place in the
                background, became inseparable from national interests. Only studying the border
                river discourse allows for the understanding of the relations at the
                landscape–politics–ideology level, and it especially has a role in comprehending the
                mechanisms of nationalist delimitation. Landscape changes (the movement of the
                river, flooding) call for measures to be implemented by both entities. This is
                exploited by various political groups that are looking to further their interests,
                and at the level of ideology and representations various media discourses, involved
                in the reporting/reflecting on the border dispute, are established. Even the mere
                choice of words can have a decisive impact on the main message: is this a cadastral
                border or a state border? In media discourses, however, particularly the outrage and
                feelings of endangerment tend to come to the forefront. If the Slovenian media were
                appalled at the Croatian construction projects on the left bank of Mura, then the
                Croatian media were horrified because of the presence of the Slovenian police in the
                territory of the Croatian cadastre. On the other hand, the media critical of
                nationalism and the contemporaneous leadership were indignant at the border disputes
                in general as well as at the demonstration of force.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn65" n="64"> Ali H. Žerdin: ”Napeti petelini,” <hi rend="italic">MLADINA.SI</hi>, 21. 9. 2006, accessed August 5, 2017, <ref target="http://www.mladina.si/92602/napeti-petelini/">http://www.mladina.si/92602/napeti-petelini/</ref>. </note>
                Meanwhile, the British BBC asked itself (in line with orientalist stereotypes)
                whether a new war might break out in the Balkans.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn66" n="65">
                        <hi rend="italic">STA: BBC: Hotiza povod za nov konflikt na Balkanu? (18. 9.
                            2006),</hi> accessed August 5, 2017, <ref target="https://www.sta.si/1088579/bbc-hotiza-povod-za-nov-konflikt-na-balkanu-18-9">https://www.sta.si/1088579/bbc-hotiza-povod-za-nov-konflikt-na-balkanu-18-9</ref>.
                    </note></p>
            <p>The political elites solved the issue by signing the Arbitration Agreement regarding
                the border in November 2009. Both governments submitted their territorial and
                maritime disputes to arbitration. The Permanent Court of Arbitration in The Hague
                was chosen as the arbitral institution.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn67" n="66"> Marko Zajc, “The slovenian-Croatian border: History,
                        Representations, Inventions,” <hi rend="italic">Acta Histriae</hi> 23, No. 3
                        (2015): 502.</note> The Court of Arbitration announced its Final Award
                on 29 June 2017. However, at the time when this contribution was written, Croatia
                did not acknowledge the Final Award due to the 2015 audio surveillance scandal
                involving a Slovenian arbitrator. How did the Court of Arbitration solve the border
                dispute on the river Mura that had escalated in 2006? Generally it adhered to the
                cadastral border, with the exception of the aforementioned hamlet of Murišče, which
                went to Slovenia. The Slovenian interpretations of Mura as the Slovenian-Croatian
                border river were not successful. The Slovenian side counted predominantly on the
                division of administrative units in the period of the Kingdom of Yugoslavia and the
                fact that the left bank of Mura had been in the hands of the Slovenian side until as
                late as 1991.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn68" n="67"> PCA
                        CASE NO. 2012-04, 125.</note></p></div>
            <div><head>Conclusion</head>
            <p>The "longue durée" border river status indirectly affects the shape and dynamics of
                the river bed. In the time when Mura represented the border between the Austrian and
                Hungarian parts of the Habsburg Empire (in various forms ever since the late 18<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> century), the "internal" Austrian part of the river
                was regulated, while the section of Mura bordering on Hungary was neglected. In the
                historical press we can come across several reports on the demands of the Styrian
                province that the central (Austrian) government in Vienna should demand that Hungary
                co-finance the regulation works at the border river Mura (the today's Slovenian
                "internal" Mura). At the same time, the Hungarian side took its own initiatives to
                regulate the river and its tributaries. After 1918, a different dynamics became
                noticeable. The section of the river at the Yugoslav-Austrian border was
                well-maintained (joint commission after 1926), while its internal part between
                Styria and Prekmurje was neglected (i.e., works would only be initiated after
                catastrophic floods). In the period after World War II, the section of Mura
                bordering on Austria was still the best-maintained part of the river, while
                significant improvement of regulation works was also noticeable at the internal Mura
                and at the section bordering on Croatia, as the border between the republics did not
                impede them. As Mura moved from the cadastral borders, the left‑bank flood
                protection embankments were also constructed in the territory of Croatian cadastral
                municipalities, for example near Hotiza and Petišovci. Until 1991 the rule was that
                both states had to take care of their respective banks, regardless of the location
                of the cadastral border. However, since the border in the area of Hotiza had not
                been defined, after the emancipation of Slovenia and Croatia conflicts arose with
                regard to the administrative jurisdiction.</p>
            <p>Who, then, is responsible for the 2006 border dispute? The answer is simple: the
                river Mura, which has its own life and refuses to stick to its river bed. The
                history of border disputes points out the difficult relationship between the river
                in the landscape and the borders. All the sections of Mura that we have analysed in
                this contribution had the status of a border river in certain periods of time. From
                the longue durée perspective, we can establish that the border disputes by the river
                Mura took place in two periods: in the Middle Ages / early modern period; and in the
                contemporary history. Could we propose a hypothesis that border disputes tend to
                arise when the constellations of the political spaces and borders are not specified?
                Our findings do support this, even though this interaction cannot be completely
                proved. However, we can definitely underline the significant importance of
                administrative legacy. We can also apply the concept of phantom borders, i.e.
                borders that no longer exist, yet continue to structure the political and actual
                    space.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn69" n="68"> Béatrice
                        von Hirschhausen, Hannes Grandits, Claudia Kraft and Dietmar Müller,
                        ”Phantomgrenzen im ostlichen Evropa, Eine wissenschaftliche Positionierung,”
                        in: Béatrice von Hirschhausen, Hannes Grandits, Claudia Kraft, Dietmar
                        Müller and Thomas Serrier, eds., <hi rend="italic">Phantomgrenzen, Räumen
                            und Akteure in der Zeit neu denken</hi> (Göttingen: Wallstein Verlag,
                        2015), 7-13.</note> Administrative legacy also
                includes the types of historical layers of the border that activate in a certain
                socio‑political contexts and function in a phantom manner.</p>
            <p>For the borders in the Slovenian space, the administrative legacy of cadastral
                municipalities is the most significant.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn70" n="69"> Peter Ribnikar, ”Zemljiški kataster kot vir za
                        zgodovino,” <hi rend="italic">Zgodovinski časopis</hi> 36, No. 4 (1982):
                        334.</note> The smallest territorial units of the state, set out by the
                Habsburg officials and geometers in the early 19th century in order to allow for tax
                exploitation and the exertion of general control over the state's territory, are
                still alive. The former river beds, marked on cadastral maps, possess a strong
                "phantom" potential, which can activate itself in the appropriate political
                situation. In case of Mura, this happened during the dissolution of Yugoslavia and
                formation of two independent countries. The administrative legacy of the cadastral
                municipalities, which had merely possessed a "boring" technical character before
                1991, suddenly became a "hot" political (and ideological) instrument
                    afterwards.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn71" n="70"> Marko Zajc, ”Phantom and
                        Possessed borders,” <hi rend="italic">Conference Borders and Administrative
                            legacy, Ljubljana, 24. – 26. 11. 2016</hi>, accessed August 5, 2017,
                            <ref target="http://www.sistory.si/11686/37233">http://www.sistory.si/11686/37233</ref>. </note></p></div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="bibliography"><head>Sources and Literature</head>
            <listBibl>
                <bibl>“Zapisnik XI. zasedanja Stalne slovensko-hrvaške komisije za vodno
                    gospodarstvo, Ljubljana, 9. in 10. 6. 2015.” Accessed August 5, 2017. <ref target="http://gis.arso.gov.si/related/evode/vg_komisije/SLO-CRO_zasedanje%2011_junij%202015.pdf">http://gis.arso.gov.si/related/evode/vg_komisije/SLO-CRO_zasedanje%2011_junij%202015.pdf</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl>”Balvani na Muri.” <hi rend="italic">Slobodna Dalmacija</hi>, 15. 9. 2006.
                    Accessed August 5, 2017. <ref target="http://arhiv.slobodnadalmacija.hr/20060915/novosti03.asp">http://arhiv.slobodnadalmacija.hr/20060915/novosti03.asp</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl>”PCA CASE NO. 2012-04 IN THE MATTER OF AN ARBITRATION UNDER THE ARBITRATION
                    AGREEMENT BETWEEN THE GOVERNMENT OF THE REPUBLIC OF CROATIA AND THE GOVERNMENT
                    OF THE REPUBLIC OF SLOVENIA, SIGNED ON 4 NOVEMBER 2009 BETWEEN THE REPUBLIC OF
                    CROATIA AND THE REPUBLIC OF SLOVENIA, FINAL AWARD, 29 June 2017.” Accessed
                    August 5, 2017. <ref target="https://pcacases.com/web/sendAttach/2172">https://pcacases.com/web/sendAttach/2172</ref>. </bibl>
                <bibl><hi rend="italic">Arbitraža, Vlada Republike Slovenije</hi>. Accessed October
                    10, 2017. <ref target="http://www.vlada.si/teme_in_projekti/arbitraza/">http://www.vlada.si/teme_in_projekti/arbitraza/</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl>Balažic, Simon. ”Meja na Muri.” In: <hi rend="italic">17. Mišičev vodarski
                    dan, zbornik referatov.</hi> Maribor: Vodnogospodarski biro, 2006.</bibl>
                <bibl>Baumann, Norbert, Štefan Fartek, Rudolf Hornich, Jožef Novak and Oliver
                    Rathschüler. <hi rend="italic">Načelna vodnogospodarska zasnova za mejno Muro,
                        I. Faza.</hi> Gradec/Graz: Stalna slovensko-avstrijska komisija za Muro,
                    2001.</bibl>
                <bibl>Belec, Borut. ”Hrvaška zemljiška posest v občini Lendava kot sestavina mejne
                    problematike.” <hi rend="italic">Dela</hi> 12 (1997), 183–93.</bibl>
                <bibl>Bizjak, Aleš. ”Transboundary Cooperation of the Republic of Slovenia –
                    Obligations, Good Practices and Benefits.” Paper on the <hi rend="italic">2</hi><hi rend="italic superscript">nd</hi><hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve"> Workshop on Assessing the Water-Food-Energy-Ecoystem Nexus and Benefits of Transboundary Cooperation in the Drina River Basin, Belgrade, 8 – 9 November 2016</hi>.
                    Accessed 3 August 2017. <ref target="https://www.unece.org/fileadmin/DAM/env/documents/2016/wat/11Nov_08-10_Nexus_2nd-WS_Drinabasin_Belgrade/day_3/ab_UNECE_NEXUS_BELGRADE__Transboundary_Cooperation_091116.pdf">https://www.unece.org/fileadmin/DAM/env/documents/2016/wat/11Nov_08-10_Nexus_2nd-WS_Drinabasin_Belgrade/day_3/ab_UNECE_NEXUS_BELGRADE__Transboundary_Cooperation_091116.pdf</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl>Brilly, Mitja, Mojca Šraj, Anja Horvat, Andrej Vidmar and Maja Koprivšek.
                    ”Hidrološka študija reke Mure.” In: <hi rend="italic">20. Mišičev vodarski dan
                        2011, zbornik referatov.</hi> Maribor: Vodnogospodarski biro, 2011.</bibl>
                <bibl>Čepič, Zdenko. ”Oris nastajanja slovensko-hrvaške meje po drugi svetovni
                    vojni.” In: <hi rend="italic">Mikužev zbornik,</hi> eds. Zdenko Čepič, Dušan
                    Nećak and Miroslav Stiplovšek. Ljubljana: Oddelek za zgodovino Filozofske
                    fakultete, 1999, 201–16.</bibl>
                <bibl>Cipot, Boris and Sebastijan Kopušar. ”Hotižani: Dež prehitel diplomacijo.” <hi rend="italic">Dnevnik</hi>, 30. 8. 2006.</bibl>
                <bibl>Cipot, Boris. “Hrvati so si privoščili še eno provokacijo.” <hi rend="italic">Dnevnik</hi>, 28. 8. 2006.</bibl>
                <bibl>Demšar, Božo. ”Ureditev državne meje Slovenije s Hrvaško.”
                    <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Geodetski vestnik </hi>36, No. 4 (1992):
                    298–303.</bibl>
                <bibl><hi rend="italic">Dnevnik</hi>, 14. 9. 2006. ”Novinarje so pridržali, na meji
                    specialci.”</bibl>
                <bibl><hi rend="italic">Dnevnik</hi>, 15. 9. 2006. ”Regulacija Mure izvor
                    nesoglasij.”</bibl>
                <bibl>Eigmüller, Monika. ”Der duale Character der Grenze. Grenzsoziologie, die
                    politische Strukturierung des Raumes.” In: <hi rend="italic">Grenzsoziologie,
                        die politische Strukturierung des Raumes</hi>, eds. Monika Eigmüller and
                    Georga Vobruba. Wiesbaden: VS Verlag für Sozialwissenschaft, 2006.</bibl>
                <bibl>Fujs, Metka. “Izhodišča madžarske okupacijske politike v Prekmurju.” <hi rend="italic">Prispevki za novejšo zgodovino</hi> 37, No. 2 (1997):
                    175–86.</bibl>
                <bibl>Hirschhausen, Béatrice von, Hannes Grandits, Claudia Kraft and Dietmar Müller.
                    ”Phantomgrenzen im ostlichen Evropa, Eine wissenschaftliche Positionierung.”
                    In<hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Phantomgrenzen, Räumen und Akteure in der Zeit neu denken, </hi>eds.
                    Béatrice von Hirschhausen, Hannes Grandits, Claudia Kraft, Dietmar Müller and
                    Thomas Serrier<hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">. </hi>Göttingen: Wallstein
                    Verlag, 2015.</bibl>
                <bibl>Hozjan, Andrej. ”Reka Mura na Slovenskem v novem veku.” <hi rend="italic">Ekonomska i ekohistorija</hi> 9 (2013):16–27.</bibl>
                <bibl><hi rend="italic">Jutro</hi>, 25. 4. 1922, 2.</bibl>
                <bibl>Kerec, Darja. ”Prekmurske Benetke leta 1925.” <hi rend="italic">Prispevki za
                    novejšo zgodovino</hi> 51, No. 3 (2011): 25–36.</bibl>
                <bibl>Komac, Blaž, Karel Natek and Matija Zorn. <hi rend="italic">Geografski vidiki
                    poplav v Sloveniji</hi>. Ljubljana: Založba ZRC, 2008.</bibl>
                <bibl>Kontler, László. <hi rend="italic">Madžarska zgodovina</hi>. Ljubljana:
                    Slovenska matica, 2005.</bibl>
                <bibl>Kos, Milko. <hi rend="italic">Srednjeveški urbarji za Slovenijo, Urbarji
                    Salzburške nadškofije.</hi> Ljubljana: Akademija znanosti in umetnosti,
                    1939.</bibl>
                <bibl>Kovačič, Fran. <hi rend="italic">Ljutomer, Zgodovina trga in sreza</hi>.
                    Maribor: Zgodovinsko društvo, 1926.</bibl>
                <bibl>Kralj, Marjeta and Mojca Zorko. ”Vrsta pozivov k pomiritvi.” <hi rend="italic">Dnevnik</hi>, 15. 9. 2006.</bibl>
                <bibl>Lesjak, Aleš. ”Mura skozi čas.” In: <hi rend="italic">25. Mišičev vodarski
                    dan, zbornik referatov.</hi> Maribor: Vodnogospodarski biro, 2014.</bibl>
                <bibl>Mayer, László and András Molnár, eds. <hi rend="italic">Viri za zgodovino
                    Prekmurja 1 / Források a Muravidék történetéhez 1</hi>. Szombathely –
                    Zalaegerszeg: Arhiv županije Vas in Arhiv županije Zala, 2008.</bibl>
                <bibl>Mayer, László and András Molnár, eds.
                    <hi rend="italic">Viri za zgodovino Prekmurja 2 / Források a Muravidék történetéhez 2. </hi>Szombathely
                    – Zalaegerszeg: Arhiv županije Vas in Arhiv županije Zala, 2008.</bibl>
                <bibl>Novak, Jožef and Vladimir Vratarič. ”Mura nekoč, danes, jutri.” In: <hi rend="italic">14. Mišičev vodarski dan, zbornik referatov.</hi> Maribor:
                    Vodnogospodarski biro, 2003.</bibl>
                <bibl>Ribnikar, Peter, ed. <hi rend="italic">Sejni zapisniki Narodne vlade
                    Slovencev, Hrvatov in Srbov v Ljubljani in Deželnih vlad za Slovenijo
                    1918-1921, 2. Del</hi>. Ljubljana: Arhiv republike
                    Slovenije, 1999.</bibl>
                <bibl>Ribnikar, Peter. ”Zemljiški kataster kot vir za zgodovino,” <hi rend="italic">Zgodovinski časopis</hi> 36, No. 4 (1982): 321–37.</bibl>
                <bibl>Šiftar, Vanek. ”Prekmurje 1918–1920.” <hi rend="italic">Časopis za zgodovino
                    in narodopisje</hi> 61, No. 1 (1989): 33–53.</bibl>
                <bibl>Simmel, Georg. ”Der Raum und die räumlichen Ordnungen der Gesellschaft.” In:
                    <hi rend="italic">Grenzsoziologie, die politische Strukturierung des
                        Raumes</hi>, eds. Monika Eigmüller and Georg Vobruba. Wiesbaden: VS Verlag
                    für Sozialwissenschaft, 2006.</bibl>
                <bibl><hi rend="italic">Slovenec</hi>, 19. 4. 1922, 2.</bibl>
                <bibl><hi rend="italic">Slovenec</hi>, 5. 2. 1922, 2.</bibl>
                <bibl><hi rend="italic">Slovenski gospodar</hi>, 1. 10. 1874, 345.</bibl>
                <bibl><hi rend="italic">Slovenski gospodar</hi>, 1. 6. 1938, 7.</bibl>
                <bibl><hi rend="italic">Slovenski gospodar</hi>, 24. 9. 1940, 4.</bibl>
                <bibl><hi rend="italic">Slovenski gospodar</hi>, 8. 10. 1878, 413.</bibl>
                <bibl><hi rend="italic">STA: BBC: Hotiza povod za nov konflikt na Balkanu (18. 9.
                    2006)</hi>. Accessed August 5, 2017. <ref target="https://www.sta.si/1088579/bbc-hotiza-povod-za-nov-konflikt-na-balkanu-18-9">https://www.sta.si/1088579/bbc-hotiza-povod-za-nov-konflikt-na-balkanu-18-9</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl><hi rend="italic">Uradni list Republike Slovenije</hi> 11/1998. “Uredba o
                    ratifikaciji Pravilnika stalne slovensko-hrvaške komisije za vodno
                    gospodarstvo.”</bibl>
                <bibl>Zajc, Marko. “Phantom and Possessed borders.” <hi rend="italic">Conference
                    Borders and Administrative legacy, Ljubljana, 24. – 26. 11. 2016</hi>.
                    Accessed August 5, 2017. <ref target="http://www.sistory.si/11686/37233">http://www.sistory.si/11686/37233</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl>Zajc, Marko. “The slovenian-Croatian border: History, Representations,
                    Inventions,” <hi rend="italic">Acta Histriae</hi> 23, No. 3 (2015):
                    499–510.</bibl>
                <bibl>Žebot, Franjo. ”Mali obmejni promet,” <hi rend="italic">Slovenski
                    gospodar</hi>, 28. 12. 1922, 53.</bibl>
                <bibl>Žebot, Franjo. ”Resnica o mlinih in žagah ob Muri,” <hi rend="italic">Slovenski gospodar</hi>, 24. 8. 1922, 35.</bibl>
                <bibl>Zelko Ivan. <hi rend="italic">Zgodovina Prekmurja, Izbrane razprave in
                    članki.</hi> Murska Sobota: Pomurska založba, 1996.</bibl>
                <bibl>Žerdin, Ali H.”Napeti petelini.” <hi rend="italic">MLADINA.SI</hi>, 21. 9.
                    2006. Accessed August 5, 2017. <ref target="http://www.mladina.si/92602/napeti-petelini/">http://www.mladina.si/92602/napeti-petelini/</ref>.</bibl>
            </listBibl></div>
            <div type="summary" xml:lang="sl"><docAuthor>Marko Zajc</docAuthor>
            <head>FENOMEN MEJNA REKA: PRIMER MURE</head>
            <head>POVZETEK</head>
            <p>Avtor analizira dva vidika dolgega trajanja fenomena mejne reke na primeru reke
                Mure: a) razmerje med rečno strugo, mejno črto in antropogenimi učinki na reko; b)
                odkrivanje historičnih struktur skozi perspektivo mejnih sporov. “Zdravorazumsko”
                razumevanje mejnih rek predpostavlja ujemanje reke in mejne črte. Kljub temu je
                lahko v pokrajini in v kartografskih reprezentacijah velika razlika med tema dvema
                elementoma. Vsi odseki reke Mure, ki jih analiziramo v članku, so imeli v določenih
                obdobjih status mejne reke. Status mejne reke dolgem trajanju posredno vpliva na
                obliko i dinamiko rečne struge. Nekdanje rečne struge, ki so “ujete” v katastrskih
                mapah, imajo velik “fantomski” potencial, ki se lahko aktivira v pravem političnem
                trenutku. V primeru Mure se je to zgodilo z razpadom Jugoslavije in vzpostavitvijo
                dveh neodvisnih držav.</p></div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>