<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
             <title>Tourism and Fascism. Tourism Development on the Eastern
                         Italian Border<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn2" n="*">
                         This paper is the result of the research project
                         “Post-Imperial Transitions and Transformations from a Local Perspective:
                         Slovene Borderlands Between the Dual Monarchy and Nation States (1918–1923)”
                         (J6-1801), financially supported by the Slovenian Research Agency.
                     </note></title>
             <author>
                 <name>
                     <forename>Petra</forename>
                     <surname>Kavrečič</surname>
                     <roleName>D.Sc.,</roleName>
                     <roleName>Assistant Professor of History</roleName>
                     <affiliation>Department of History, Faculty of Humanities, University of Primorska</affiliation>
                     <address>
                         <addrLine>Titov trg 5,</addrLine>
                         <addrLine>SI – 6000 Koper</addrLine>
                     </address>
                     <email>petra.kavrecic@fhs.upr.si</email>
                 </name>
             </author>
         </titleStmt>
          <editionStmt>
              <edition>
                  <date>2020-07-29</date>
              </edition>
          </editionStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
              <publisher>
                  <orgName xml:lang="sl">Inštitut za novejšo zgodovino</orgName>
                  <orgName xml:lang="en">Institute of Contemporary History</orgName>
                  <address>
                      <addrLine>Privoz 11</addrLine>
                      <addrLine>SI-1000 Ljubljana</addrLine>
                  </address>
              </publisher>
              <pubPlace>http://ojs.inz.si/pnz/article/view/1027</pubPlace>
              <date>2020</date>
              <availability status="free">
                  <licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</licence>
              </availability>
          </publicationStmt>
          <seriesStmt>
              <title xml:lang="sl">Prispevki za novejšo zgodovino</title>
              <title xml:lang="en">Contributions to Contemporary History</title>
              <biblScope unit="volume">60</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
              <idno type="ISSN">2463-7807</idno>
          </seriesStmt>
          <sourceDesc>
              <p>No source, born digital.</p>
          </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
       <encodingDesc>
           <projectDesc xml:lang="en">
               <p>Contributions to Contemporary History is one of the central Slovenian scientific
                   historiographic journals, dedicated to publishing articles from the field of
                   contemporary history (the 19th and 20th century).</p>
               <p>The journal is published three times per year in Slovenian and in the following
                   foreign languages: English, German, Serbian, Croatian, Bosnian, Italian, Slovak
                   and Czech. The articles are all published with abstracts in English and
                   Slovenian as well as summaries in English.</p>
           </projectDesc>
           <projectDesc xml:lang="sl">
               <p>Prispevki za novejšo zgodovino je ena osrednjih slovenskih znanstvenih
                   zgodovinopisnih revij, ki objavlja teme s področja novejše zgodovine (19. in 20.
                   stoletje).</p>
               <p>Revija izide trikrat letno v slovenskem jeziku in v naslednjih tujih jezikih:
                   angleščina, nemščina, srbščina, hrvaščina, bosanščina, italijanščina, slovaščina
                   in češčina. Članki izhajajo z izvlečki v angleščini in slovenščini ter povzetki
                   v angleščini.</p>
           </projectDesc>
       </encodingDesc>
       <profileDesc>
           <langUsage>
               <language ident="sl"/>
               <language ident="en"/>
           </langUsage>
           <textClass>
               <keywords xml:lang="en">
                   <term>tourism</term>
                   <term>fascism</term>
                   <term>interwar period</term>
                   <term>Venezia Giulia</term>
               </keywords>
               <keywords xml:lang="sl">
                   <term>turizem</term>
                   <term>fašizem</term>
                   <term>obdobje med obema vojnama</term>
                   <term>Furlanija-Julijska krajina</term>
               </keywords>
           </textClass>
       </profileDesc>
       <revisionDesc>
           <listChange>
               <change>
                   <date>2020-09-08</date>
                   <name>Neja Blaj Hribar</name>
                   <desc>Pretvorba iz DOCX v TEI, dodatno kodiranje</desc>
               </change>
           </listChange>
       </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
       <front>
           <docAuthor>Petra Kavrečič<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn1" n="**">
               <hi rend="bold">D.Sc., Assistant Professor of History, Department of
                   History, Faculty of Humanities, University of Primorska, Titov
                   trg 5, 6000 Koper;</hi>
               <ref target="mailto:petra.kavrecic@fhs.upr.si">
                   <hi rend="bold">petra.kavrecic@fhs.upr.si</hi>
               </ref></note></docAuthor>
           <docImprint>
               <idno type="cobissType">Cobiss tip: 1.02</idno>
           </docImprint>
           <div type="abstract" xml:lang="sl">
               <head>IZVLEČEK</head>
               <head>TURIZEM IN
                   FAŠIZEM. TURISTIČNI RAZVOJ NA ITALIJANSKI VZHODNI MEJI</head>
                   <p>
                       <hi rend="italic">Prispevek se osredotoča na obravnavo
                           turističnega razvoja nekdanje italijanske province Julijske krajine (Venezia
                           Giulia). V ospredju zanimanja je torej obdobje med obema vojnama. Območje, ki je
                           predmet analize, predstavlja zanimivo študijo primera, ki še ni bila deležna
                           zadostne historične znanstvene obravnave, vsaj glede področja turističnega
                           razvoja. Zanima me raziskovanje povezave in povezanosti med političnim režimom
                           in nacionalnim diskurzom s turistično panogo oziroma različnimi tipologijami
                           turistične ponudbe. Kako se je posameznim turističnim destinacijam (»starim« ali
                           »novim«) uspelo prilagoditi novim političnim razmeram, ki so nastopile po koncu
                           prve svetovne vojne, in kako se je turizem razvijal v okviru totalitarnega
                           sistema, v tem primeru fašizma. Pri tem bo predstavljena različna turistična
                           ponudba obravnavanega območja.</hi>
                   </p>
               <p>
                   <hi rend="italic">Ključne besede: turizem, fašizem, obdobje
                       med obema vojnama, Furlanija-Julijska krajina</hi>
               </p>
           </div>
           <div type="abstract">
               <head>
                   ABSTRACT
               </head>
               <p>
                   <hi rend="italic">The paper explores tourism development in
                       the Italian region of Venezia Giulia. The territory under discussion represents
                       an interesting but unexplored field of study in historiography, focusing on
                       tourism development during the interwar period. My aim is to study the
                       interrelation between the political regime and the national discourse within the
                       tourism development sector in its various forms. The intent is to study how
                       tourist destinations (“old” and “new”) managed to adjust to the changed
                       political circumstances within a developing totalitarian system – fascism.
                       Different typologies of tourist destinations will be taken into
                       consideration.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                   <hi rend="italic">Keywords: tourism, fascism, interwar period,
                       Venezia Giulia</hi>
               </p>
           </div>
       </front>
      <body>
         <div><head>Introduction</head>
         <p>The main interest of this paper is to explore the
                    relationship between tourism and political ideology with a case study of the
                    Venezia Giulia region,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn3" n="2">
                From the end of World War I to the end of World War
                        II, <hi rend="italic">Venezia Giulia</hi> was an Italian region. Between
                        1923 and 1947, the region was divided into five provinces; Trieste/Trst,
                        Gorizia/Gorica, Pula/Pola (Istra/Istria) and Rijeka/Fiume. After the Treaty
                        of Paris (1947) and the Memorandum of London (1954), parts of the former
                        region were annexed to
                Yugoslavia.
            </note> the easternmost Italian region in the period between the two world wars. The purpose is to conduct a historical analysis of tourism development in the multi-ethnic eastern region of the Kingdom of Italy. 
            </p>
         <p>This study focuses on a period when significant political,
                    economic, social, and cultural changes occurred in Europe – when the population
                    faced the decline of old regimes, creation of new national states, and the
                    radicalisation of national aspirations. This process influenced the tourism
                    sector as well. The proposed research is based on the position that political
                    ideology and tourism are interrelated since a specific ideology also justified
                    and implemented its authority with the help of tourism. Italian fascism in
                    Venezia Giulia has received considerable attention from Slovenian
                    historians,
                <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn4" n="3">
                See e. g. Jože
                        Pirjevec,
                        <hi rend="italic">'Trst je naš!'. Boj Slovencev za morje (1848–1954) </hi>(Ljubljana:
                        Nova revija, 2008). Marta Verginella, <hi rend="italic">Meja drugih.
                            Primorsko vprašanje in slovenski spomin</hi> (Ljubljana: Modrijan,
                        2009). Milica Kacin-Wohinz and Marta Verginella, <hi rend="italic">Primorski
                            upor fašizmu: 1920–1941</hi> (Ljubljana: Društvo Slovenska matica,
                        2008). Marta Verginella, Sandi Volk and Katja Colja, <hi rend="italic">Ljudje v vojni: druga svetovna vojna v Trstu in na Primorskem</hi>
                        (Koper: Zgodovinsko društvo za južno Primorsko, 1995). Egon Pelikan, <hi rend="italic">Tajno delovanje primorske duhovščine pod fašizmom-
                            Primorski krščanski socialci med Vatikanom, fašistično Italijo in
                            slovensko katoliško desnico – zgodovinsko ozadje romana Kaplan Martin
                            Čedermac</hi> (Ljubljana: Nova revija, 2002).
            </note>
                but mostly from the perspective of the fascist repression
                    and the resistance movement of the Slovenian population (which was, after World
                    War II, also used to construct the Slovenian national remembrance). Some studies
                    about tourism development in the region in the interwar period do exist,
                <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn5" n="4">
                See e.g. Olga
                        Janša-Zorn, “Turizem v Sloveniji v času med obema vojnama,” in <hi rend="italic">Razvoj turizma v Sloveniji</hi>, ed. Franc Rozman and
                        Žarko Lazarević (Ljubljana: Zveza zgodovinskih društev Slovenije, 1996),
                        78–95. Metod Šuligoj, ed., <hi rend="italic">Retrospektiva turizma
                            Istre</hi> (Koper: Založba Univerze na Primorskem, 2015).
                    
            </note> but only a few deal with the interrelation between the totalitarian political ideology and tourism as a tool for national affirmation.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn6" n="5">
                For Istria and
                        Dalmatia, see e.g. Maura Hametz, “Replacing Venice in the Adriatic: Tourism
                        and Italian Irredentism 1880–1936,” <hi rend="italic">Journal of Tourism
                            History</hi> 6, No. 2–3 (2014): 107–21. In the Italian perception,
                        especially political, this region represented its now “redeemed” provinces
                        that were associated to the long Venetian presence and heritage, which was
                        used as a justification for their territorial appetites since the 19th century. Hametz’s article focuses on the role
                        of tourism in the identification of the Venetian heritage of Istria and
                        Dalmatia as Italian.
               For Libya and Albania, see
                        e.g. Stephanie Malia Hom, “Empires of Tourism Travel and Rhetoric in Italian
                        Colonial Libya and Albania 1911–1943,” <hi rend="italic">Journal of Tourism
                            History</hi> 4, No. 3 (2012): 281–300.
               For
                        Libya, see e.g. Ester Capuzzo, “”Visitate la Libia”. Il turismo nella Quarta
                        Sponda tra le due guerre mondiali,” <hi rend="italic">Nova Historica</hi>,
                        No. 56 (2016): 3–35.
            </note>
                If we focus on the case of Italy, we can identify such
                    examples also in other Italian regions<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn7" n="6">
                For South Tyrol, see e.g. Stefano Morosini, “I
                        rifugi Alpini dell'Alto Adige/Südtirol dalla fruizione turistica al presidio
                        nazionale (1918–1943),” in <hi rend="italic">Krieg und Tourismus im
                            Spannungsfeld des Ersten Weltkrieges</hi>, ed. Patrick Gasser, Andrea
                        Leonardi and Gunda Barth-Scalmani (Innsbruck: Studien Verlag, 2014),
                        181–207. Annunziata Berrino and Ewa Kawamura, “Grande guerra nell'area
                        Sudtirolese: i mutamenti di una regione turistica e il dibattinto che li
                        accompagna,” in <hi rend="italic">Krieg und Tourismus im Spannungsfeld des
                            Ersten Weltkrieges</hi>, ed. Patrick Gasser, Andrea Leonardi and Gunda
                        Barth-Scalmani (Innsbruck: Studien Verlag, 2014), 271–92. Patrizia
                        Battilani, “L'impatto della guerra sull'immagine turistica dei luoghi: il
                        caso del Trentino e dell'alto Adige,” in <hi rend="italic">Krieg und
                            Tourismus im Spannungsfeld des Ersten Weltkrieges</hi>, ed. Patrick
                        Gasser, Andrea Leonardi and Gunda Barth-Scalmani (Innsbruck: Studien Verlag,
                        2014), 33–54.
            </note>
                and colonies.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn8" n="7">
                See e.g. Hametz, “Replacing Venice in the
                        Adriatic,” 107–21. In the Italian perception, especially political, this
                        region represented its now “redeemed” provinces that were associated to the
                        long Venetian presence and heritage, which was used as a justification for
                        their territorial appetites since the 19th
                        century. Hametz’s article focuses on the role of tourism in the
                        identification of the Venetian heritage of Istria and Dalmatia as
                        Italian.
               For Libya and Albania, see e.g.
                        Stephanie Malia Hom, “Empires of Tourism,” 281–300.
               For Libya, see e.g. Capuzzo, “Visitate la Libia,”
                        3–35.
            </note> The Italian political discourse of this period attributed an important role to tourism, especially when in 1926, the
                <hi rend="italic">Aziende autonome di cura, soggiorno e
                    turismo</hi>
                (Bureau for Health, Holidays and Tourism) – i.e. the
                    tourist management institutions/enterprises – were established by the state in
                    the communities that offered tourist services or already had the status of
                    tourist destinations and were considered as
                <hi rend="italic">“una delle più grandi benemerenze del
                    Regime fascista nei confronti del turismo</hi>”: one
                    of the greatest merits of the fascist regime regarding tourism.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn9" n="8">
                Annunziata Berrino,
                        “La nascita delle Aziende Autonome e le politiche di sviluppo territoriale
                        in Italia tra le due guerre,” <hi rend="italic">Storia del turismo,
                            Annale,</hi> No. 5 (2005): 38. 
               The Aziende
                        Azienda autonoma di cura, soggiorno e turismo were established by the Law,
                        with the RDL (<hi rend="italic">Regio decreto legge) of 15 April 1926, No.
                            765. “Provvedimenti per la tutela e lo sviluppo dei luoghi di cura di
                            soggiorno o di turismo,</hi>” accessed on 15 July 2020, 
               
                  <ref target="http://www.edizionieuropee.it/LAW/HTML/89/zn96_02_001.html">http://www.edizionieuropee.it/LAW/HTML/89/zn96_02_001.html</ref>.
               The Aziende were the administrative organisation of
                        tourism and health localities. In ENIT (Ente nazionale industrie
                        turistiche), <hi rend="italic">L' assetto delle stazioni di cura, di
                            soggiorno e di turismo: R. decreto-legge 15 aprile 1926, n. 765</hi>
                        (Rome: Tipografia del Senato, 1926), 9.
            </note>
                In fact, tourism was considered the second most important
                    industry in the country (after agriculture).<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn10" n="9">
                This was stated by Fulvio Suvich,
                        an important Italian politician and diplomat during the fascist period. He
                        was also the Government Commissioner for the ENIT. – Richard J. B. Bosworth,
                        “Tourist Planning in Fascist Italy and the Limits of a Totalitarian
                        Culture,” <hi rend="italic">Contemporary European History</hi> 6, No. 1
                        (1997): 15. Petra Kavrečič, “'Sacro pellegrinaggio'. Visits of World War I
                        Memorials on the Soča/Isonzo Front in the Interwar Period,” <hi rend="italic">Etnološka tribina</hi> 40, No. 47 (2017): 153, 54.
                    
            </note>
         </p>
         <p>Italian fascism as a political system and especially its
                    leader were aware of the significant potential for economic progress and social
                    well-being (expansion of the social accessibility of tourism supply) that could
                    be accomplished through tourism. At the same time, tourism served as a regime
                    propaganda tool at home and abroad.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn11" n="10">
                Bosworth, “Tourist Planning,” 15.
            </note>
                In the contested areas of the territories newly acquired
                    after World War I (such as Venezia Giulia and South Tyrol), another agenda was
                    related to tourist sites – the construction of the Italian national identity.
                    The presented arguments will be studied in this paper. In fact, the territory
                    under discussion represents an exceptional case study, since it was, during this
                    period, subject to significant changes as it passed from one state and political
                    entity (the Habsburg Monarchy, later Austria-Hungary) to another (the Kingdom of
                    Italy). This drastically changed not only the national “affiliation” but also
                    the attitude towards nationality and consequently towards the national economy
                    and its correlations, ideas, and goals. The theoretical background places the
                    core analysis of tourism development in Venezia Giulia in the framework of the
                    Italian fascist system, which strongly popularised this activity as well. The
                    study is thus faced with a so far mostly neglected topic and the assumption that
                    tourism did not develop in this region. Therefore, in this regard, the present
                    study will attempt to determine how the totalitarian regime in the researched
                    region “used” tourism for the affirmation of its ideology. It will also explore
                    how tourism managed to adjust itself to the new political circumstances; whether
                    it succeeded in improving the supply in light of the new tourist market demand;
                    and how did the various typologies of tourism supply manage to come together. It
                    will also address a new tourism segment in the region; the way in which it
                    managed to position itself in the territory under consideration; and whether it
                    attained any tourist significance. These aspects represent a completely new
                    perspective of the understanding of the economic history in the studied
                    territory as well as of the influence of the economy on the social identity of
                    this territory.
            </p></div>
        <div><head>Tourism as a Regime Propaganda Tool</head>
         <p>In the decades between the two World Wars, certain
                    processes that characterised and encouraged tourism development were present on
                    both the European and global scale. As already stated, tourism trends were
                    gradually moving towards the less privileged social strata of the population.
                    The research of the selected case studies the role of the state – in this
                    instance the fascist regime – in the development of tourism in Venezia Giulia.
                    The goal is to understand the crucial processes and relationships established
                    between tourism and the political ideology in the interwar period when in Italy,
                    even tourism was considered to be subject to the totalitarian state.
                <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn12" n="11">
                Tourism was also
                        seen as a part of the totalitarian system: “everything was for the state,
                        nothing was outside the state, no one was against the state”. – Bosworth,
                        “Tourist Planning,” 9.
            </note> In fact, the studied area offers an excellent background for researching the aforementioned phenomena. In a broader thematic framework, it will help to provide the context regarding the interest of the political authorities in controlling and using tourism to enable a better consolidation and promotion of their regime. Fascism as well as Nazism and communism attempted to create and maintain a loyal population affiliated to the cult of the state or emperor, also through sports and recreation activities. The emphasis was on the youth population (e.g. children colonies;
                <hi rend="italic">Opera Nazionale Balilla</hi>, ONB/Italian Fascist Youth Organisation established in
                    1926) and workers, which is evident from the targeted use of leisure time
                    (<hi rend="italic">Opera Nazionale
                    Dopolavoro</hi>, OND/National Recreational Club
                    established in 1925) where people would gather at sports activities and
                    excursions. Italy employed the same approach to “instrumentalising” tourism in
                    its other provinces (South Tyrol) and colonies (Albania, Libya). In 1933, Nazi
                    Germany established a similar programme or section called Strength through Joy
                    (
                <hi rend="italic">Kraft durch Freude</hi>, KdF),<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn13" n="12">
                KdF was the subsidiary of the Deutsche Arbeitsfront.
                        See: Kristin Semmens, <hi rend="italic">Seeing Hitler's Germany: Tourism in
                            the Third Reich</hi> (Basingstoke: Palgrave Macmillan, 2005). Shelley
                            Baranowski<hi rend="italic">, Strength Through Joy: Consumerism and Mass
                            Tourism in the Third Reich</hi> (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press,
                        2004).
            </note> which organised holidays and sports activities<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn14" n="13">
                Hasso Spode,
                        “Fordism, Mass Tourism and the Third Reich: The ʻStrength through Joyʼ
                        Seaside Resort as an Index Fossil,” <hi rend="italic">Journal of Social
                            History</hi> 38, No. 1 (2004): 149.
            </note>
                and where a considerable potential for spreading
                    innovations in tourism could be seen. The movement’s aim was also to contribute
                    to the growing popularity of group travel.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn15" n="14">
                Semmens, <hi rend="italic">Seeing Hitler’s
                            Germany</hi>,
                    121.
            </note> In fact, the Nazi rhetoric contributed to a greater social “equality”, as on (during) vacation, the workers enjoyed the rights that had once been reserved solely for the upper class.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn16" n="15">
                The aim was to
                        democratise the access to cultural property and practices of Germany’s upper
                        and middle classes. Even though the aim was to popularise this practice
                        among workers, most of the beneficiaries of the KdF offer indeed came from
                        higher social classes. The poorest manual labourers did not really represent
                        the majority of KdF costumers as the Nazi propaganda claimed. In Semmens,
                            <hi rend="italic">Seeing Hitler’s Germany</hi>, 108–9. Baranowski<hi rend="italic">, Strength Through Joy,</hi> 66 and
                    197.
            </note> Holidays were intended to promote the expansion of knowledge and love for the homeland. The organisation’s aim was also to integrate the working class into German society and consequently gain control over consumption in accordance with the political regime. The purpose was also to encourage tourism development and ensure its accessibility among all social strata of the population as well as promote sports activities and the regime abroad.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn17" n="16">
                Spode, “Fordism,
                        Mass Tourism,” 136.
               See also Semmens, <hi rend="italic">Seeing Hitler’s Germany</hi>, 12. In her book, the author
                        claims that “within the field of foreign policy, international tourism had a
                        special role: to convey the ‘truth’ about Germany to guests from abroad.
                        Through tourism, Nazi Germany would persuade the international community of
                        its peaceful intention”.
            </note>
                Fascist Italy employed a similar approach. The 
                <hi rend="italic">Opera Nazionale
                    Dopolavoro</hi> (OND)<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn18" n="17">
                Its aim was “to
                        promote a new national identity”, and it also sponsored tours. In Victoria
                        De Grazia, <hi rend="italic">The Culture of Consent: Mass Organisation of
                            Leisure in Fascist Italy</hi> (Cambridge University Press, 2009),
                        179.
            </note> was established with the purpose of increasing the quality of life of workers and their families. Among other goals, it also took care of the mental and spiritual health of the Italian population through sports activities, excursions, and tourism.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn19" n="18">
                Aldo Agosteo and
                        Antonio Sereno, <hi rend="italic">Fascismo e turismo (politica e storia del
                            turismo sociale)</hi> (Viterbo: Editrice Agnesotti, Collana della SIST,
                        2007),
                    59.
            </note> The regime propaganda and creation of the exemplary citizen contributed to the promotion of vacationing. The introduction of <hi rend="italic">sabato
                    fascista</hi> (fascist Saturday) – free Saturday afternoons for workers – enabled these people to take advantage of their free time, which, of course, played in favour of tourism. The concern was not focused only on workers but also on the youth – the future generations of fascists. The <hi rend="italic">Opera Nazionale
                    Balilla</hi> (ONB) took care of children’s education (along with the schools) and emphasised physical activity. It was also active in the field of youth integration in tourism: sports competitions throughout the country helped expand travel; staying outdoors – camping – was encouraged; and in every community, a Balilla house (<hi rend="italic">Casa
                    Balilla</hi>) was built. The organisation also promoted winter sports (in 1928, the ONB established the <hi rend="italic">Federazione Italiana degli Sport
                    Invernali</hi>/Italian Association of Winter Sports). The ONB (and later, as of 1937, the <hi rend="italic">Gioventù Italiana del Littorio</hi>, GIL) organised colonies for children at the seaside and
                    mountain destinations. In 1927, 420 colonies with 80.000 participating children
                    were organised throughout Italy; while in 1938, already as many as 4.357
                    colonies with 772.000 children all over the country participated. The colonies
                    were also organised in other localities such as lakes, valleys, rivers, and
                    thermal destinations.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn20" n="19">
                Agosteo and Sereno, <hi rend="italic">Fascismo e
                            turismo</hi>, 69.
            </note> In the interwar period, Italy did not only encourage domestic (social) tourism, but also the influx of foreign tourists. Tourism was given important recognition in various fields: in the economic sector as well as the political and national discourse. In a secret report sent to Mussolini in 1931, Suvich, the Government Commissioner for the ENIT, emphasised the important political role played by tourism, as “it constitutes the very best propaganda [of fascism] and the most effective denial of absurd foreign calumnies against our country”.
                <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn21" n="20">
                Bosworth, “Tourist
                        Planning,” 15.
            </note>
                In the present paper, this context will be studied in the case of Venezia Giulia. </p></div>
         <div><head>The “Old” and “New”
                    Tourist Destinations in Venezia Giulia
         </head>
         <p>A decrease in tourist activities was recorded in the first years of the post-war period, especially due to the significant changes regarding the state borders that also affected the territory of the new Italian region Venezia Giulia. In the first years after the war, a decline in tourism was characterised by the lack of “old” tourists from Central Europe, who had not yet been sufficiently replaced by Italian tourists. 
            </p>
         <p>The end of World War I exposed the tourism sector to several changes that determined the end of 
                <hi rend="italic">élite</hi> tourism and the rise of its <hi rend="italic">massivisation</hi>. The period represents a key phase in tourism
                    development, as it gradually acquired a more socially accessible character.
                    Political regimes played an important role in this process as well, especially
                    because they encouraged the development of tourism as a political propaganda
                    tool. On the one hand, tourism development in the interwar period faced changes,
                    upgrades, and the intensification of its accessibility and supply; while, on the
                    other hand, 20
                th-century tourism was also employed by different political systems (fascism, Nazism, and communism) as a tool for the affirmation and promotion of their ideologies. After World War I, the new ideologies steered tourism development in a new direction, distancing it from its previous <hi rend="italic">elite</hi> character. Tourism was becoming increasingly socially accessible, which was also the idea of the post-war regimes that had originated from socialist ideas. These systems attempted to expand the social rights of their populations, also by ensuring the possibility of leisure time playing sports or enjoying vacations. This was also an efficient tool to bolster the popular support for the regime and “control” the population.
            </p>
         <p>Nevertheless, “control” over tourism did not only occur in
                    the 20th century: European countries had interfered with its regulation as of the 19th century – since the very first signs of a positive economic impact. In the former Austria-Hungary, the state (through the responsible Ministries) founded regional associations and societies for the promotion of tourism, which subsequently played their defining roles. In the multi-ethnic territory of Austria-Hungary, we can also identify the role of tourism as a means of national affirmation. This is also implied by Judson, who states that German nationalists “used” tourism to achieve a higher level of the national identity awareness of German-speaking Austrians, which was also facilitated through the establishment of German societies. Similar arguments – in favour of the affirmation of their own national presence – were also used by the Czechs, Slovenians, and Italians who lived in these territories.
                <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn22" n="21">
                Pieter Judson,
                        “'Every German Visitor Has a Völkisch Obligation He Must Fulfill':
                        Nationalist Tourism in the Austrian Empire, 1880–1918,” in: <hi rend="italic">Histories of Leisure</hi>, ed. Rudy J. Koshar (Oxford, New
                        York: Berg, 2002), 150. Pieter M. Judson, <hi rend="italic">Guardians of the
                            Nation. Activists on the Language Frontiers of Imperial Austria</hi>
                        (Harvard: Harvard University Press, 2007).
            </note>
                As pointed out by Wolff regarding the Austro-Hungarian
                    Dalmatia, “…important international exchanges concerning the national
                    aspirations of the South Slavs in Dalmatia took place in the context of the
                    development of modern tourism in ‘delightful’ Dalmatia”,
                <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn23" n="22">
                Larry Wolff, <hi rend="italic">Venice and the Slavs: The Discovery of Dalmatia in the Age
                            of Enlightenment</hi> (Stanford: Stanford University Press, 2001),
                        349.
            </note> which represents another case of tourism used for national affirmation.</p>
         <p>After World War I, the consolidation of the national
                    affiliation “aided” by tourism increased. The present paper tries to determine
                    how strongly the fascist ideology influenced tourism development (or “used”
                    tourism for its political agenda) in the region of Venezia Giulia. Various types
                    of tourism in this region – from the “traditional” seaside, cave, and alpine
                    tourism (which had been, even before World War I, strongly related to the
                    construction and establishment of the national identity, also through alpine
                    societies)
                <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn24" n="23">
                Borut Batagelj,
                        “Odkritje gora: strukturne spremembe v dojemanju gora na Slovenskem do
                        začetka 20. stoletja,” <hi rend="italic">Ekonomska i Ekohistorija</hi> VI,
                        No. 6 (2010): 124–42.
               See also Peter Mikša and
                        Kornelija Ajlec, <hi rend="italic">Slovensko planinstvo = Slovene
                            mountaineering</hi> (Ljubljana: Planinska zveza Slovenije, 2015). Peter
                        Mikša, “Gradnja slovenske nacionalne identitete na podlagi t. i.
                        nacionalnega boja v gorah” in <hi rend="italic">Simpozij v spomin dr. Milanu
                            Ževartu: zbornik povzetkov 2. simpozija v spomin dr. Milanu Ževartu</hi>
                        (Velenje, 15 November 2018),
                19.
            </note> – can be traced to the “new” destinations featuring war monuments and cemeteries related to the construction of the Italian national discourse in this territory.</p>
         <p>In 1919, the <hi rend="italic">Ente nazionale industrie
                    turistiche</hi> (ENIT)/Italian National Tourist Board, financed by the state, was established in Italy.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn25" n="24">
                After the end of
                        World War I, an increased “sense of urgency about the need to formalize a
                        tourist industry” and the idea that “governments should and could interfere,
                        to the national benefit, in commercial enterprise” appeared in Italy. In:
                        Bosworth, “Tourist Planning,” 3 and 8. 
            </note>
                During the interwar period, the ENIT played an important
                    role in the tourism sector, which also included the territories annexed to Italy
                    after World War I. The aim was to promote visits to Italy among both local and
                    international tourists and to establish Italy as a modern tourist destination.
                    The idea was to “bring tourism to the people”.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn26" n="25">
                Ibid., 6.
            </note> Soon after the first years of decline in tourism, visits to Italy by foreign tourists, including those from the former Austria-Hungary (e.g. Czechoslovakia, Yugoslavia, Austria, and Hungary) began to increase. The main concern was to re-establish tourism in the regions of Trentino, South Tyrol, and Venezia Giulia, because while they had become part of Italy, these regions had originally generated significant income from Austrian and German tourists, which was particularly common at the prominent spa and seaside destinations.
                <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn27" n="26">
                Kavrečič, “Sacro
                        pellegrinaggio,” 151, 52. Bosworth, “Tourist Planning,” 3, 4.
            </note>
                The ENIT’s offices were thus opened across the country
                    (and abroad)<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn28" n="27">
                Ibid.,
                7.
            </note> – also in Venezia Giulia (Reka/Fiume, Opatija/Abbazia, Trst/Trieste), where the promotion of seaside destinations, caves, and World War I memorials were prioritised. </p>
         <p>As already mentioned, part of the territory of Venezia
                    Giulia joined the new state as an established tourist destination. In fact, in
                    terms of tourism, it was one of the most developed parts of the former
                    Austro-Hungarian Empire with a well-organised and structured offer and services.
                    However, during the interwar period, the area had not yet been adequately
                    addressed in the context of tourism development.
                <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn29" n="28">
                A significant
                        transformation of seaside resorts in Italy can also be noted in the case of
                        Rimini, where the extensive evolution of tourist facilities (accommodation,
                        entertainment) and increase of tourist visits was present throughout the
                        interwar years. The state leader, who spent his holidays in Rimini, also
                        played an important role in this development. In Patrizia Battilani and
                        Francesca Fauri, “The Rise of a Service-Based Economy and Its
                        Transformation: Seaside Tourism and the Case of Rimini,”
                        <hi rend="italic">Journal of Tourism History </hi>1,
                        No. 1 (2009): 27–48.
            </note> Opatija/Abbazia, Portorož/Portorose, Lošinj/Lussin, Lovran/Laurana, and Brijuni/Brioni were considered the pearls of the Austrian Riviera (the so-called seaside of the Austrian Littoral) and enjoyed considerable popularity amongst tourists.
                <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn30" n="29">
                Petra Kavrečič,
                            <hi rend="italic">Turizem v Avstrijskem primorju: zdravilišča, kopališča
                            in kraške jame (1819–1914)</hi>, 2. dopolnjena izdaja (Koper: Založba
                        Univerze na Primorskem, 2017).
            </note>
                After World War I, the territory faced the loss or change
                    of the tourist market: the once domestic (Austro-Hungarian) tourists had now
                    become foreign tourists. On the other hand, the coastal part of the “redeemed”
                    region (
                <hi rend="italic">terre redenti</hi>) had become just one of the many Italian seaside
                    destinations. However, since this territory represented the Italian eastern
                    multi-ethnic contested province, it is my opinion that this territory was of
                    strategic importance for the “construction” of the Italian national identity. In
                    the previous historical and tourism studies, it is commonly interpreted that
                    Italy was not particularly interested in promoting tourism development in the
                    region. In this study, however, I rely on the assumption that Italy wanted to
                    increase the sense that this territory belonged to the Italians and that tourism
                    was an appropriate tool to achieve this goal.
                <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn31" n="30">
                See also Kavrečič,
                        “Sacro pellegrinaggio,” 151, 52.
            </note>
         </p>
         <p>After World War I, the fashion of leisure in seaside locations increased notably and eventually became one of the most popular leisure activities in the interwar period. During this time, the attitude towards swimming and sunbathing changed in a positive way and now played the central role in the perception of 
                <hi rend="italic">holidays</hi> (also by the middle and lower social class). This enabled the Mediterranean destinations (where the aforementioned locations are situated) to become the most popular sites for leisure activities.
                <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn32" n="31">
                See also Kavrečič,
                            <hi rend="italic">Turizem v Avstrijskem primorju</hi>. Orvar Löfgren,
                            <hi rend="italic">On Holiday. A History of Vacationing</hi> (Berkley,
                        Los Angeles, London: University of California Press, 2002).
            </note>
                In the first post-war years, the seaside tourist
                    locations faced a decrease in tourist visits, yet we can see (from Table 1) that
                    by the mid-1920s, the situation had recovered.
                <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn33" n="32">
                The considerable
                        influx of tourists in 1925 was attributed to the Anno Santo (Holy Year) of
                        1925. See also Petra Kavrečič and Milan Radošević, “Na morje! Izzivi
                        turističnega razvoja v Istri v času Avstro-Ogrske in italijanske uprave s
                        posebnim ozirom na leto 1925,” <hi rend="italic">Zgodovina za vse</hi> 24,
                        No. 2 (2017): 21–40.
            </note>
         </p>
         <p>In order to increase the impact of tourism on the economy, larger investments were needed for the promotion of attractive destinations and localities. The ENIT encouraged various types of marketing activities in this region. In 1925, the 
                <hi rend="italic">Ufficio Viaggi e Turismo/</hi>Office for Travel and Tourism was established in
                    Lovran/Laurana (Croatia). This was the third tourist office in the region (the
                    two existing ones were in Reka/Fiume and Opatija/Abbazia).
                <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn34" n="33">
                ENIT (Ente
                        nazionale industrie turistiche), <hi rend="italic">Relazione sull’attività
                            svolta nell’anno 1925: propaganda, organizzazione, statistica, consorzio
                            degli uffici di viaggio e turismo, bilancio</hi>, (Rome: Tipografia del
                        Senato, 1926), 73.
            </note>
                Another ENIT office, located in Trst/Trieste, covered the
                    whole Venezia Giulia region. Based on the ENIT’s annual reports of tourist
                    income in the region, the Trst/Trieste office reported a lower number of tourist
                    visits in its area with the exception of the “classic” summer season at the
                    seaside resorts of Portorož/Portorose and Brijuni/Brioni islands. Indeed, most
                    of this office’s promotion efforts targeted the summer seaside destinations
                <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn35" n="34">
                Ibid., 85,
                    86.
            </note>
                through its representative/information offices in Portorož/Portorose, Pula/Pola, Grado/Gradež, and Brijuni/Brioni. These offices also cooperated with the 
                <hi rend="italic">Ente provinciale per il turismo per la
                    Provincia d'Istria/</hi>Provincial Tourist Board in
                    Istria, established in 1936.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn36" n="35">
                Metod Šuligoj and Zorana Medarić, “Turistični prevozi,
                        potovanja in izleti na obali severne Istre od 19. stoletja dalje =
                        Turistički prijevozi, putovanja i izleti na obali sjeverne Istre od 19.
                        stoljeća dalje,” in <hi rend="italic">Retrospektiva turizma Istre</hi>, ed.
                        Metod Šuligoj (Koper: Založba Univerze na Primorskem, 2015), 61.
               It is important to emphasise that in 1925, only another
                        14 such boards existed in the whole Kingdom of Italy, which shows how
                        important and strategic the eastern Italian territory was in the opinion of
                        the state. In ENIT, 74. Kavrečič and Radošević, “Na morje!,”
                    21–40.
            </note>
                On the local level, other societies were established, for example the <hi rend="italic">Società per il promovimento dei forestieri
                    nella Venezia Giulia</hi>/Society for the Promotion
                    of Tourist Visits in Venezia Giulia (since 1921). It was important to promote
                    the development of tourism at the seaside resorts for domestic and foreign
                    visitors.</p>
         <p>An important step was taken in 1925 when the decree
                    regarding the standards for hotels was issued. The decree established the
                    mandatory requirements for the implementation of hygiene and health
                    improvements. The ENIT oversaw the promotion and awarding of subsidies or other
                    aid initiatives, aimed at the hotel locations that were insufficiently or
                    inadequately provisioned for the needs of tourism. It also recommended the
                    issuing of opportune agreements with provincial doctors, giving preference to
                    those hotels that had higher standards of sanitation according to the
                    regulations.
                <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn37" n="36">
                RD (<hi rend="italic">Regio decreto) 24 May 1925, No. 1102. “Approvazione del
                            regolamento per le migliorie igieniche negli alberghi,</hi>” accessed on
                        15 July 2020, <ref target="http://www.comune.jesi.an.it/MV/leggi/rd1102-25.htm">http://www.comune.jesi.an.it/MV/leggi/rd1102-25.htm</ref>: <hi rend="italic">L'Ente provinciale per il turismo, nel promuovere o
                            incoraggiare con premi, sovvenzioni od altro ausilio iniziative intese a
                            dotare di alberghi luoghi che ne siano privi o che ne siano provvisti
                            solo in modo inadeguato ai bisogni del turismo, avrà cura, presi gli
                            opportuni accordi col medico provinciale, che sia data la preferenza a
                            quelle atte a conseguire meglio le finalità igieniche a cui intendono le
                            disposizioni del presente regolamento.</hi>
               
            </note>
                The new hotels had to be located in “healthy”
                    environments where the high hygiene and sanitary standards were met. In the case
                    of Istria, the poor supply of clean water and the persistent presence of
                    infectious diseases represented a serious obstacle to tourism development
                    outside the established destinations. Even existing destinations faced
                    challenges stemming from the defamatory news about the alleged spread of malaria
                    in foreign newspapers.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn38" n="37">
                Kavrečič and Radošević, “Na morje!,”
                21–40.
            </note>
         </p>
         <p>The extent to which tourism development was prioritised is
                    also attested to by the initiatives taken by politically influential
                    personalities. The Italian senator (since 1923) and engineer Ugo Ancona
                    emphasised not only the hygiene standards of the accommodation facilities but
                    also the importance of good road infrastructure and transfers. He also pointed
                    out the necessity to provide enough comfort and leisure activities for tourists,
                    since – in his opinion – it was important to attract wealthier visitors.
                <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn39" n="38">
                Ibid.,
                    26.
            </note>
                Although tourism development was oriented towards the
                    less privileged social classes, Ancona’s aim was still to target wealthier
                    visitors, who could bring greater financial benefits to the state. On the other
                    hand, the number of seaside colonies for children increased in this period (e.g.
                    also through associations such as the
                <hi rend="italic">Commissione del Turismo Scolastico nella
                    provincia di Capodistria</hi>/Commision for School
                    Tourism in the Province of Koper),<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn40" n="39">
                Šuligoj and Medarić, “Turistični prevozi,” 60,
                        61.
            </note> which was a sign of tourist supply diversification. Nevertheless, the seaside tourist destinations managed to overcome the first post-war years. The number of visitors gradually increased – especially in 1925, when the number of guests almost reached (and in some cases exceeded) the pre-World War I numbers. However, these destinations did not completely succeed in attracting more domestic visitors, and most of the tourists that visited them still came from the Austrian, Hungarian, Yugoslavian and Anglo-Saxon lands,
                <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn41" n="40">
                ENIT,
                    94.
            </note> which means that the “old” guests were returning here regardless of the changed political situation.</p>
             <p>Table 1: Number of guests at the seaside resorts in Venezia
                 Giulia in 1913 and 1925<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn42" n="41">
                     Kavrečič, “Sacro
                     pellegrinaggio,” 302 and 310. Kavrečič and Radošević, “Na morje!,” 33. Livio
                     Livi<hi rend="italic">, L'economia della Regione Giulia nel 1926.
                         Capitolo V. Il movimento dei forestieri</hi> (Trieste: Istituto
                     statistico-economico annesso alla R. Università degli studi economici e
                     commerciali di Trieste, 1926), 88.
                 </note></p>
             <table rend="rules">
                 <row>
                     <cell rend="both"><hi rend="bold"
                         style="font-size:12pt">Tourist resort</hi></cell>
                     <cell rend="both"><hi rend="bold" style="font-size:12pt">Number of guests in
                         1913</hi></cell>
                     <cell rend="both"><hi rend="bold" style="font-size:12pt">Number of guests in
                         1925</hi></cell>
                 </row>
                 <row>
                     <cell rend="both"><hi style="font-size:12pt">Opatija/Abbazia</hi></cell>
                     <cell rend="right"><hi style="font-size:12pt">49,187</hi></cell>
                     <cell rend="right"><hi style="font-size:12pt">42,723</hi></cell>
                 </row>
                 <row>
                     <cell rend="both"><hi style="font-size:12pt">Portorož/Portorose</hi></cell>
                     <cell rend="right"><hi style="font-size:12pt">7,222</hi></cell>
                     <cell rend="right"><hi style="font-size:12pt">9,093</hi></cell>
                 </row>
                 <row>
                     <cell rend="both"><hi style="font-size:12pt">Lošinj (Mali in
                         Veliki)/Lussin</hi></cell>
                     <cell rend="right"><hi style="font-size:12pt">8,469</hi></cell>
                     <cell rend="right"><hi style="font-size:12pt">5,845</hi></cell>
                 </row>
                 <row>
                     <cell rend="both"><hi style="font-size:12pt">Lovran/Laurana</hi></cell>
                     <cell rend="right"><hi style="font-size:12pt">11,950</hi></cell>
                     <cell rend="right"><hi style="font-size:12pt">8,481</hi></cell>
                 </row>
                 <row>
                     <cell rend="both"><hi style="font-size:12pt">Brioni</hi></cell>
                     <cell rend="right"><hi style="font-size:12pt">2,500</hi></cell>
                     <cell rend="right"><hi style="font-size:12pt">3,908</hi></cell>
                 </row>
             </table>
         <p>Underground caves, which also saw a constant increase in
                    popularity during this period, represented yet another attraction of this
                    region. From the viewpoint of tourism, Postojna Cave was still the most popular
                    and recognised. This period was characterised by the investments in
                    infrastructure (the railway system, enlargement of the cave entrance and paths,
                    bridges) and greater tourist promotion (for the number of guests, see Table 2).
                    In fact, the first Italian national speleological congress after the war took
                    place in Postojna (and Trieste) in 1933.
                <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn43" n="42">
                “Provvedimenti per
                        la tutela”.
            </note>
                After the acquisition of the former Austrian territories
                    (including the cave in Postojna), the cave commission (<hi rend="italic">Commissariato civile distrettuale di
                    Postumia-Commissiorie amministrazione delle Grotte di Postumia</hi>) released the first post-war guidebook (in 1924). It is
                    important to emphasise that the guidebook was not solely meant for tourism
                    promotion, but was also a “tool” for the propaganda spread by the Italian
                    regime: a significant part of the guidebook was dedicated to a historical
                    overview from the Roman period until the repossession and restitution of these
                    lands to its “Roman governance” (
                <hi rend="italic">Roma ritorna</hi>). This was a clear attempt to prove how this territory represented an integral
                    part of the Italian national territory.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn44" n="43">
                Franc Habe, “Vodniška literatura Postojnske
                        jame,” <hi rend="italic">Naše jame, Glasilo društva za raziskovanje jam
                            Slovenije</hi> 10/1968, No. 1–2 (1969): 26.
            </note>
         </p>
         <p>During this period, tourism was present in Škocjan Caves
                    as well. After the end of World War I, the administration passed from the German
                    and Austrian Alpine Society (
                <hi rend="italic">Deutsches und Österreichisches
                    Alpenverein</hi>, DuÖAV) to the Italian Alpine
                    Society (
                <hi rend="italic">Società Alpina delle Giulie, Sezione di
                    Trieste</hi>, SAG, under the national <hi rend="italic">Club Alpino Italiano</hi>, CAI). At this point, new regulations regarding the
                    alpine and cave guides were implemented, specifying that guides could only
                    register through the Italian Alpine Society.
                <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn45" n="44">
                Matjaž Puc, <hi rend="italic">Škocjanske jame pri Divači: kronika raziskovanj in
                            turističnega obiska</hi> (Škocjan: PŠJ, 2015), 94.
            </note>
                The cave was not reopened until 1923 (while tourist
                    visits were not made possible until as late as 1925). The Society invested
                    significant efforts into facilitating tourist visits (see Table 2) and
                    furthering the underground research activities. To date, the tourism development
                    of Škocjan Caves in the interwar period has been poorly studied. In 2018, Trevor
                    Shaw released a new study, which provides insight into the development of cave
                    tourism and management in the period between 1920 and 1940
                <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn46" n="45">
                See also Trevor
                        Shaw, <hi rend="italic">Škocjanske jame 1920–1940</hi> (Ljubljana: Zalozba
                        ZRC, 2018).
            </note>
                and points out the unknown aspects of tourism development
                    of the caves in this period. In this study, Shaw presents the changes and
                    challenges faced by the new cave administration (SAG CAI) during the interwar
                    period. Besides the promotion of tourism, the Alpine Society also drew up plans
                    for the modernisation of the cave infrastructure (organisation of paths in the
                    caves, placement of new signs and names of cave sections now named by Italian
                    speleologists, placement of signposts from Divača towards the attraction, car
                    parks, etc.). The new manager also envisioned new infrastructure such as the
                    construction of a new bridge, footpaths, better lightning, and an elevator. Due
                    to insufficient finances, the financial crisis in the 1930s, and the onset of
                    World War II, not all of these plans were realised during this period
                <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn47" n="46">
                Ibid<hi rend="italic">.</hi>
               
            </note> (Shaw 2018).</p>
         <p>Table 2: The number of guests at
                    the
                Venezia Giulia
                caves in 1913 and
                    1925.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn48" n="47">
               
                        Kavrečič, <hi rend="italic">Turizem v Avstrijskem primorju,</hi> 314.
                            Livi<hi rend="italic">, L'economia della Regione Giulia</hi>, 95. Puc,
                            <hi rend="italic">Škocjanske jame pri Divači,</hi> 88 and 96.
            </note>
         </p>
             <table rend="rules">
                 <row>
                     <cell rend="both"><hi rend="bold" style="font-size:12pt">Cave</hi></cell>
                     <cell rend="both"><hi rend="bold" style="font-size:12pt">Number of guests in
                         1913</hi></cell>
                     <cell rend="both"><hi rend="bold" style="font-size:12pt">Number of guests in
                         1925</hi></cell>
                 </row>
                 <row>
                     <cell rend="both"><hi style="font-size:12pt">Postojna cave/Grotte di
                         Postumia</hi></cell>
                     <cell rend="right"><hi style="font-size:12pt">40,971</hi></cell>
                     <cell rend="right"><hi style="font-size:12pt">155,711</hi></cell>
                 </row>
                 <row>
                     <cell rend="both"><hi style="font-size:12pt">Škocjan caves/Grotte di San
                         Canziano</hi></cell>
                     <cell rend="right"><hi style="font-size:12pt">3,312</hi></cell>
                     <cell rend="right"><hi style="font-size:12pt">4,580</hi></cell>
                 </row>
             </table>
         <p>The relatively “new” tourist offers in the region were
                    related to the attractions associated with “disaster, suffering, violence, or
                    death”.
                <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn49" n="48">
                Metod Šuligoj,
                        “Memories of War and Warfare Tourism in Croatia,” <hi rend="italic">Annales,
                            Ser. Hist. sociol.</hi> 26, No. 2 (2016): 260.
            </note> This type of tourism is most commonly associated with dark tourism (as described by Lennon and Foley) or considered a form of thanatourism (as described by Seaton)
                <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn50" n="49">
                Jennifer Iles,
                        “Exploring Landscapes after Battle. Tourists at Home on the Old Front
                        Lines,” in <hi rend="italic">Writing the Dark Side of Travel</hi>, ed.
                        Jonathan Skinner (New York – Oxford: Berghahn Books, 2012), 183.
            </note>
                in “which issues such as remembrance, nationhood, family,
                    honour and respect are regarded as integral aspects of tourist motivation and
                    activity”.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn51" n="50">
               
                        Caroline Winter, “Battlefield Visitor Motivations. Explorations in the Great
                        War Town of Ieper, Belgium,” <hi rend="italic">International Journal of
                            Tourism Research</hi> 13 (2011): 173.
            </note>
                In the territory of Venezia Giulia, tourism also turned
                    towards World War I battlefields of the former Soča/Isonzo front
                    (1915–1917).
            </p>
         <p>The first known large-scale visits to battlefields were
                    recorded after the battle of Waterloo, which is considered to have changed the
                    British trips to Europe,
                <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn52" n="51">
                See also A. V.
                        Seaton, “War and Thanatourism: Waterloo 1815–1914”, <hi rend="italic">Annals
                            of Tourism Research</hi> 26, No. 1 (1999):
                    130–58.
            </note> “although intensive development of battlefield tourism was initiated no earlier than the end of World War I”.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn53" n="52">
                Šuligoj, “Memories
                        of War and Warfare Tourism in Croatia,” 260. Patrizia Battilani, “L’impatto
                        della guerra sull’immagine turistica dei luoghi: il caso del Trentino e
                        dell’alto Adige,” in <hi rend="italic">Krieg und Tourismus im Spannungsfeld
                            des Ersten Weltkrieges: Guerra e Tourismo nell’area di tensione della
                            Prima Guerra Mondiale</hi>, ed. Patrick Gasser, Andrea Leonardi and
                        Gunda Barth-Scalmani (Innsbruck: Studien Verlag, 2014), 249, 50.
            </note>
                During this period, the tourist industry was in search of
                    new potential markets, and considerable efforts were made in the area of
                    battlefield tourism, although the promotion of these visits was strongly related
                    to (secular) pilgrimages to war sites.
                <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn54" n="53">
                See also Kavrečič,
                        “Sacro pellegrinaggio,”
                    141–60.
            </note> The intention was to stir up emotions among the potential Italian tourists and encourage them to visit these war sites.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn55" n="54">
                Andrea Leonardi, “La
                        prima guerra mondiale e la vulnerabilità del fenomeno turistico,” in <hi rend="italic">Krieg und Tourismus im Spannungsfeld des Ersten
                            Weltkrieges: Guerra e Tourismo nell’area di tensione della Prima Guerra
                            Mondiale</hi>, ed. Patrick Gasser, Andrea Leonardi and Gunda
                        Barth-Scalmani (Innsbruck: Studien Verlag, 2014), 82, 83.
               Leonardi analyses the case of tourism in the Alpine
                        area of the new Italian (former Austrian/Austro-Hungarian) territories and
                        the effort made by the Italian state to influence visits to this area where
                        World War I battles also took place.
            </note>
                In the new political atmosphere, Italy was interested in
                    affirming and justifying its presence in the region, which it accomplished
                    through various institutions such as the national tourist organisation. The
                    emphasis was on selected memories of Italian victories and on promoting the
                    commemoration and glorification of sacrifice for the nation.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn56" n="55">
                Kavrečič, “Sacro
                        pellegrinaggio,” 148.
            </note>
                Questions such as “Who were these memorials for? Who were the visitors to war cemeteries and memorials (at Sredipolje/Redipuglia, Oslavje/Oslavia, Kobarid/Caporetto, and others)?” should be raised and addressed. 
            </p></div>
         <div><head>“Italianisation” of
                    the Redeemed Lands
         </head>
         <p>As already explained, we need to consider that the area
                    under consideration was subject to significant changes in this period. First,
                    World War I devastated the region where the battles between the Italian and
                    Austro-Hungarian armies took place at the Soča/Isonzo Front. After the war, this
                    region was annexed to Italy (in line with the 1920 Treaty of Rapallo), which
                    symbolised not only the transition from one state to another but was also
                    strongly marked by the Italian national ambitions to “Italianise” the region. In
                    order to make this region ethnically Italian, the immigration of Italian
                    teachers and officials into this territory was encouraged. The purpose was the
                    so-called
                <hi rend="italic">“ethnic bonification”</hi> – the settlement of Italians in the regions populated by Slovenians (and Croatians) as well as assisting these settlers in the confiscation of Slovenian land (economic structure) for Italian colonisation (through associations such as 
                <hi rend="italic">Ente per la Rinascita Agraria delle Tre
                    Venezie</hi>).<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn57" n="56">
                Jože Prinčič, “Primorsko in postojnsko
                        gospodarstvo v času med obema vojnama,”
                        <hi rend="italic">Prispevki za novejšo </hi>zgodovino
                        49, No. 1 (2009): 173.
            </note>
                The process of Italianising this territory took place in
                    different areas, focusing on the political, economic, social, and cultural life.
                    Efforts were also made in the tourism sector. In order to “make” this land
                    Italian, much attention was paid to the particular segment of tourism related to
                    World War I battlefields. A new market niche – the so-called ‘dark tourism’ –
                    was introduced, related to the visits of battlefields (the Soča/Isonzo Front,
                    the myth of the fallen soldier, sacred sites). The primary reason for these
                    visits had nothing to do with tourism, but rather exhibited a memorial and
                    commemorative character (secular pilgrimage of veterans and bereaved families)
                    with a strong national note as well as patriotic and educational aspects.
                    Gradually, these types of visits were integrated into the offers of tourist
                    organisations,
                <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn58" n="57">
                The ENIT
                        supervised the tours to World War I battlefield sites since 1923. In:
                        Bosworth, “Tourist Planning,” 7.
            </note>
                which had a significant role in the creation of national
                    identity in the contested border region of the easternmost Italian
                    province.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn59" n="58">
               
                        Issues that were addressed in Kavrečič, “Sacro pellegrinaggio,”
                    141–60.
            </note>
                The war memorial visits garnered much attention from
                    historiographers,
                <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn60" n="59">
                Foreign and
                        Slovenian: Gaetano Dato, “Lineamenti storiografici, memorie pubbliche e miti
                        all’origine del sacrario di Redipuglia. La fondazione di un tempio della
                        nazione,” <hi rend="italic">Acta Histriae</hi> 18, No. 3 (2014): 399–424.
                        Borut Klabjan, “Nation and Commemoration in the Adriatic: the Commemoration
                        of the Italian Unknown Soldier in a Multinational Area: the Case of the
                        Former Austrian Littoral,” <hi rend="italic">Acta Histriae</hi> 22, No. 3
                        (2010): 695–714. Leonardi, “La prima guerra mondiale,” 57–98. George L.
                        Mosse, <hi rend="italic">Le guerre mondiali. Dalla tragedia al mito dei
                            caduti</hi> (Rome; Bari: Edizioni Laterza, 2007). Kaja Širok, “Spomin in
                        pozaba na obmejnem območju: predstave o Goriški preteklosti,” <hi rend="italic">Acta Histriae</hi> 18, No. 1–2 (2010): 337–57. Kaja Širok,
                        “Identitete, zgodovina in dediščina prostora – prakse spominjanja in
                        komemoracije na Goriškem v XX. stoletju,” <hi rend="italic">Acta
                            Histriae</hi> 20, No. 4 (2012): 631–46. Fabio Todero, “Il culto del
                        soldato caduto nella Venezia Giulia dalla Grande guerra al fascism,” in <hi rend="italic">Regime fascista, nazione e periferie</hi>, ed. Anna Maria
                        Vinci (Udine: Studi e documenti, 2010, 30), 51–68. Angelo Visintin, “Dalla
                        Grande guerra al fascismo. L’ ipotesi della Vittoria sui campi di battaglia
                        dell’Isonzo,” in <hi rend="italic">Regime fascista, nazione e
                        periferie</hi>, ed. Anna Maria Vinci (Udine: Studi e documenti, 2010, 30),
                        69–87.
            </note> but with no references or studies of the impact of tourism and these visits or the transition from “pilgrimage” to “tourist” sites (more studies have been carried out by ethnologists and anthropologists, e.g. Eade and Katić).
                <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn61" n="60">
                See e.g. John Eade
                        and Mario Katić, ed., <hi rend="italic">Military Pilgrimage and Battlefield
                            Tourism. Commemorating the Dead</hi> (London, New York: Routledge,
                        Taylor and Francis Group, 2017).
            </note>
                So far, greater attention has been paid to the
                <hi rend="italic">battlefield</hi> tourism related to the World War I Western Front memorial sites,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn62" n="61">
                See e.g. Jennifer
                        Iles, “Encounters in the Fields – Tourism to the Battlefields of the Western
                        Front,” <hi rend="italic">Journal of Tourism and Cultural Change</hi> 6/2
                        (2008), 138–54. David William Lloyd, <hi rend="italic">Battlefield Tourism.
                            Pilgrimage and the Commemoration of the Great War in Britain, Australia
                            and Canada, 1919–1939</hi> (Oxford, New York: Berg, 1998). Tony Walter,
                        “War Grave Pilgrimage,” in <hi rend="italic">Pilgrimage in Popular
                            Culture</hi>, ed. Ian Reader and Tony Walter (London: Palgrave,
                        Macmillan, 1993), 63–91. Winter, “Battlefield Visitor
                    Motivations.”
            </note> but the territory of the today’s western Slovenia still needs to be taken into consideration. The Italian War Front (Tyrol and Soča/Isonzo) and the memorial sites in this territory seem to “represent a more nationally-oriented case of ‘tourism’ development, since the sacred sites were mostly visited by Italians for memorial purposes – as part of a (secular) pilgrimage for the bereaved families and sometimes ex-servicemen – as well as for patriotic and educational purposes”.
                <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn63" n="62">
                Kavrečič, “Sacro
                        pellegrinaggio,” 158.
            </note>
                “These sites seem to have kept a more ‘local’
                    influence”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn64" n="63">
               
                        Ibid.
            </note> and it seems that the state was not able to supervise the battlefield tours effectively.
                <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn65" n="64">
                Bosworth, “Tourist
                        Planning,” 15.
            </note>
         </p>
         <p>The different aspects of tourism development should be
                    considered (both chronologically and by type of tourism) and appointed
                    adequately. During this period, the “old” tourist destinations (the seaside, the
                    caves) with a tourist infrastructure put in place before World War I needed an
                    incentive in terms of a promotional strategy. On the other hand, a plan of
                    tourist development and promotion of the “new” segment of tourism (battlefields)
                    still needed to be implemented (related to infrastructure, facilities,
                    connections, etc.). Naturally, that required more extensive financial input.
                    Nevertheless, we need to take into account that these destinations attracted a
                    different type of visitor. All these aspects should be approached with an
                    appropriate methodology, considering various typologies of sources (e.g.
                    statistical data and tourist records can be used for seaside resorts and partly
                    for caves; while memorial sources, war diaries, and registers kept by the
                    societies that managed war graves and monuments are more suitable for World War
                    I battlefields sites).
            </p></div>
         <div><head>The Easternmost
                    Italian Region, Further Investigation
         </head>
         <p>The area of Venezia Giulia, the easternmost Italian
                    region, represents a distinctive case study of the adaptation of tourism to new
                    trends and political systems – in particular the transition from one state to
                    another. This caused several changes in the political structure as well as from
                    the national perspective, leading to migrations of the Slovenian (and Croatian)
                    population from the region as well as to the immigration of Italians from other
                    regions. The role of tourism in the fascist regime; the way in which it was
                    interpreted and used as a tool for regime propaganda;
                <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn66" n="65">
                Although, as
                        argued by Bosworth, the question is whether the <hi rend="italic">fascistisation</hi> of the tourist industry was entirely accomplished
                        and whether tourism managed to become an obedient “body” of the totalitarian
                        state? In Bosworth, “Tourist Planning,” 20.
            </note> and the affirmation of the Italian national character of the border region of Venezia Giulia has not been thoroughly studied yet. I intend to analyse how the aforementioned tourism organisations operated in this territory. I am interested in how social tourism expanded here and whether the tourism industry – which had, until World War I, mostly targeted the 
                <hi rend="italic">elite</hi> – adjusted to the new circumstances and demand.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn67" n="66">
                As mentioned above
                        (for example regarding Ugo Ancona and his efforts to attract wealthier
                        tourists), this period was characterised by the diversification of tourist
                        supply.
            </note>
         </p>
         <p>The Adriatic seaside destinations from the Austrian period
                    – such as Opatija/Abbazia, Portorož/Portorose, Lošinj/Lussin, Lovran/Laurana and
                    Brijuni/Brioni – were well-known and acclaimed destinations of the upper class.
                    My interest is to explore how these localities managed to offer different types
                    of supply on the tourist market (foreign guests still in search of “fashionable”
                    destinations vs workers and children). In this sense, different aspects of
                    tourism development will be underlined.
            </p>
         <p>An important tourist activity – cave tourism – shows
                    continuity since the preindustrial period, while successful development has also
                    been evident in the period of modern tourism development. The Karst underground
                    had enjoyed a long tradition of visits from foreign travellers, but intensive
                    development – both in terms of cave research as well as tourist visits – took
                    place during the 19
                th century. Postojna Cave, the most recognised cave boasting the largest number of visitors, kept improving its visibility in the Italian period (see Table 2). Other caves such as Vilenica, Škocjan, and Divača experienced significant changes from the administrative point of view. With the exception of Vilenica, which had been administrated by the Italian Alpine Society even before World War I, the caves came under the jurisdiction of the Alpine Society, which was an important factor of regime propaganda and national affirmation. One of the measures implemented by the Society after its acquisition of the Škocjan Caves was to change the denominations of the cave sections.
                <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn68" n="67">
                Shaw, <hi rend="italic">Škocjanske jame</hi>,
                25.
            </note> Similar to seaside tourism, the development of cave tourism during the two World Wars has not yet been the subject of extended scientific research from the perspective discussed in this study.</p>
         <p>As mentioned above, apart from the seaside and underground
                    tourist destinations, another tourist segment will also be taken into
                    consideration: the study of the former World War I battlefield visits. The
                    Italian authorities promoted this activity, as the battlefields possessed a
                    strong symbolic value and role in the construction or consolidation of the
                    Italian national consciousness in the territory under consideration (e. g. the
                    involvement of the youth population in this process – in the construction of
                    national identity through memorial and educational visits of war
                sites).</p>
         <p>The question of the main target groups of tourists will be
                    addressed in the selected case studies of seaside locations, caves, and the
                    former battlefield sites of the Soča/Isonzo Front. The study of tourism
                    development will shed entirely new light on the history of the first half of the
                    20
                th century in the studied territory as well as provide a valuable new starting point for new research in the context of other disciplines, e.g. urbanism (influence of tourism on spatial planning, urban expansion, regulation of water and sea, etc.), architectural history (introduction of new modern building types and thus also the introduction of the first examples of modernist architecture in this area), heritage studies (the importance of cultural heritage and monuments in tourist offer), anthropology of tourism (ongoing research in the context of the World War I anniversary at the Soča/Isonzo Front), etc. </p></div>
         <div><head>Final Remarks</head>
         <p>The paper proposes an analysis of tourist development in
                    Venezia Giulia during the Italian fascist regime. Throughout history, the
                    studied region has been subject to border changes and migration processes, as it
                    represented a strategic interest zone of different, usually opposing political
                    powers. Even if we only consider the 20th century, drastic border changes occurred in this area, reflected in the territory itself as well as in its population. World War I (the Soča/Isonzo Front) has left its mark on this area as well. After the war, this territory was once again subject to many changes in light of the collapse of the old regime (Austria-Hungary) and the onset of a new political reality, brought about by the Italian state. Additionally, the change of the state structure was subject to a new national structure, which was, in this period, characterised by a greater radicalisation of national ideas. 
            </p>
         <p>The development of tourism after World War I can be placed in the context of the political events and processes that took place during that period. Similarly to the political arena, the tourism industry faced crucial transitions. The end of the war marked the conclusion of the contemporaneous 
                <hi rend="italic">elite</hi> tourism – which had developed as a significant economic industry after the industrial revolution. The interwar period brought about a slow but efficient transition of the tourist industry. Despite the difficult post-war circumstances, Italy soon began to organise the field of tourism. The 1920s are even considered as the most important period for tourism development: a period of transition that changed the history of Italian tourism.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn69" n="68">
                Berrino, “La nascita
                        delle Aziende Autonome,”
                38.
            </note> In fact, tourism development during these years is considered to have had a positive impact on the expansion of social accessibility, which means that also the lower social strata started to benefit from tourism services (mainly through the OND and the ONB). The accessibility and popularity of tourism gradually “expanded”.</p>
         <p>This paper refers to a case study that investigates the
                    extensive relationship between political power and ideology as well as between
                    the economy and society. Within the study of the significant economic activity
                    in which social and cultural relations are strongly integrated, it raises new
                    research questions about the development processes described in the case study
                    of the border and the disputed territory of Venezia Giulia during the interwar
                    period. Such a study will outline the wider context of the social and economic
                    development of the region and simultaneously recognise the influence of the
                    fascist regime on tourism development. This means that the fascist doctrine will
                    be explored from a new perspective.
            </p>
         <p>The research questions – for example, how the regime
                    managed to “shape” the tourist sector during the post-war period in Venezia
                    Giulia; which target groups of tourists did it focus on; and how or whether the
                    tourism industry managed to adjust to the new circumstances; and in what way and
                    how did it (if it actually did) upgrade the tourist offer with new content (e.g.
                    visits of World War I battlefields) – also open up entirely new thematic
                    horizons in Slovenian historiography.</p>
         <p>The results involved in such a study will contribute to a
                    better understanding of the historical development of one of the most important
                    and constantly growing economic industries in the world. The emphasis will be on
                    analysing the efforts for the “nationalisation” of tourism and promotion of
                    Italian tourist destinations in the new provinces as a direct reflection of the
                    fascist ideology. Due to the need for the integration of the newly acquired
                    territories into the Italian reality, the state aimed to prove the level of
                    the
                <hi rend="italic">Italianisation</hi>
                of this area and the continuity of its presence. In the
                    Italian perception, especially political, this region represented the final
                    “redemption” of the provinces that had been associated with the long Venetian
                    presence and heritage, which was used as a justification for the Italian
                    territorial appetites since the 19th century (especially by the <hi rend="italic">irredentist</hi> movement). Such an in-depth study will thus offer a different evaluation of the studied period, which is, in the Slovenian historiography, mostly considered from the perspective of the national assimilation politics carried out by the fascist regime and the resistance movement of the Slovenian (and Croatian) population. The study aims to show the multiplicity of the Italian fascist system and its impact on the social and economic fields. It addresses these phenomena in a comprehensive analysis of the different typologies of tourist destinations, present in this area during the interwar period. It thus poses questions about the involvement of the radical national political ideology propaganda in the economic sector (tourism) in the region of Venezia Giulia.
            </p></div>
      </body>
       <back>
           <div type="bibliography">
               <head>Literature and
                   Sources
           </head>
           <listBibl>
               <head>Literature</head>
               <bibl>Agosteo, Aldo and Antonio Sereno.
                   <hi rend="italic">Fascismo e turismo (politica e storia
                       del turismo sociale)</hi>. Viterbo: Editrice
                   Agnesotti, Collana della SIST, 2007.</bibl>
               <bibl>Baranowski, Shelley.
                   <hi rend="italic">StrengthTthrough Joy: Consumerism and
                       Mass Tourism in the Third Reich</hi>. Cambridge:
                   Cambridge University Press, 2004.
               </bibl>
               <bibl>Batagelj, Borut. “Odkritje gora: strukturne spremembe v dojemanju gora na Slovenskem do začetka 20. stoletja.” <hi rend="italic">Ekonomska i
                   Ekohistorija</hi> VI, No. 6 (2010): 124–42.</bibl>
               <bibl>Battilani, Patrizia. “L'impatto della guerra sull'immagine turistica dei luoghi: il caso del Trentino e dell'alto Adige.” In <hi rend="italic">Krieg und Tourismus im Spannungsfeld
                   des Ersten Weltkrieges: Guerra e Tourismo nell'area di tensione della Prima
                   Guerra Mondiale</hi>, edited by Patrick Gasser,
                   Andrea Leonardi and Gunda Barth-Scalmani, 249–70. Innsbruck: Studien Verlag,
                   2014.</bibl>
               <bibl>Battilani, Patrizia and Francesca Fauri. “The Rise of a Service-based Economy and Its Transformation: Seaside Tourism and the Case of Rimini.” <hi rend="italic">Journal of Tourism
                   History</hi> 1, No. 1 (2009): 27–48.</bibl>
               <bibl>Berrino, Annunziata. “La nascita delle Aziende Autonome e le politiche di sviluppo territoriale in Italia tra le due guerre.” <hi rend="italic">Storia del turismo,
                   Annale</hi>, No. 5 (2005): 33–54. </bibl>
               <bibl>Berrino, Annunziata and Ewa Kawamura. “Grande guerra nell'area Sudtirolese: i mutamenti di una regione turistica e il dibattinto che li accompagna.” In <hi rend="italic">Krieg und Tourismus im Spannungsfeld
                   des Ersten Weltkrieges</hi>, edited by Patrick
                   Gasser, Andrea Leonardi and Gunda Barth-Scalmani, 271–92. Innsbruck: Studien
                   Verlag, 2014.</bibl>
               <bibl>Bosworth, Richard J. B. “Tourist Planning in Fascist Italy and the Limits of a Totalitarian Culture.” <hi rend="italic">Contemporary European
                   History</hi> 6, No. 1 (1997): 1–25.</bibl>
               <bibl>Capuzzo, Ester. “”Visitate la Libia”. Il turismo nella Quarta Sponda tra le due guerre mondiali.” <hi rend="italic">Nova Historica</hi>, No. 56 (2016): 3–35.</bibl>
               <bibl>Dato, Gaetano. “Lineamenti storiografici, memorie pubbliche e miti all’origine del sacrario di Redipuglia. La fondazione di un tempio della nazione.” <hi rend="italic">Acta
                   Histriae</hi> 18, No. 3 (2014): 399–424. </bibl>
               <bibl>De Grazia, Victoria. <hi rend="italic">The Culture of Consent: Mass
                   Organisation of Leisure in Fascist Italy</hi>.
                   Cambridge University Press, 2009.
               </bibl>
               <bibl>Eade, John and Mario Katić, eds., 
                   <hi rend="italic">Military Pilgrimage and Battlefield
                       Tourism. Commemorating the Dead</hi>. London, New
                   York: Routledge, Taylor and Francis Group, 2017.</bibl>
               <bibl>ENIT (Ente nazionale industrie turistiche). <hi rend="italic">L' assetto delle stazioni di cura, di
                   soggiorno e di turismo: R. decreto-legge 15 aprile 1926, n. 765</hi>. Roma: Tipografia del Senato, 1926.</bibl>
               <bibl>ENIT (Ente nazionale industrie turistiche). <hi rend="italic">Relazione sull’attività svolta
                   nell’anno 1925: propaganda, organizzazione, statistica, consorzio degli
                   uffici di viaggio e turismo, bilancio</hi>. Roma:
                   Tipografia del Senato, 1926.</bibl>
               <bibl>Habe, Franc. “Vodniška literatura Postojnske jame.” <hi rend="italic">Naše jame, Glasilo društva za
                   raziskovanje jam
                   Slovenije</hi> 10/1968, No. 1–2 (1969): 15–32.</bibl>
               <bibl>Hametz, Maura. “Replacing Venice in the Adriatic: Tourism and Italian Irredentism 1880–1936.” <hi rend="italic">Journal of Tourism
                   History</hi> 6, No. 2–3 (2014): 107–21. </bibl>
               <bibl>Hom, Stephanie Malia. “Empires of Tourism Travel and Rhetoric in Italian Colonial Libya and Albania 1911–1943.” <hi rend="italic">Journal of Tourism History 4</hi>, No. 3 (2012): 281–300.</bibl>
               <bibl>Iles, Jennifer. “Encounters in the Fields – Tourism to the Battlefields of the Western Front.” <hi rend="italic">Journal of Tourism and Cultural
                   Change</hi> 6/2 (2008): 138–54. </bibl>
               <bibl>Iles, Jennifer. “Exploring Landscapes after Battle. Tourists at Home on the Old Front Lines.” In <hi rend="italic">Writing the Dark Side of Travel</hi>, edited by Jonathan Skinner, 182–202. New York –
                   Oxford: Berghahn Books, 2012.</bibl>
               <bibl>Janša-Zorn, Olga. “Turizem v Sloveniji v času med obema vojnama.” In <hi rend="italic">Razvoj turizma v Sloveniji</hi>, edited by Franc Rozman and Žarko Lazarević, 78–95.
                   Ljubljana: Zveza zgodovinskih društev Slovenije, 1996.</bibl>
               <bibl>Judson, Pieter M. <hi rend="italic">Guardians of the Nation. Activists on
                   the Language Frontiers of Imperial Austria</hi>.
                   Harvard: Harvard University Press, 2007.</bibl>
               <bibl>Judson, Pieter. “'Every German Visitor Has an
                   Völkisch Obligation He Must fFulfil': Nationalist Tourism in the Austrian
                   Empire, 1880–1918.” In
                   <hi rend="italic">Histories of Leisure</hi>, edited by Rudy J. Koshar, 147–68. Oxford, New York:
                   Berg, 2002</bibl>
               <bibl>Kacin-Wohinz, Milica and Marta Verginella. <hi rend="italic">Primorski upor fašizmu:
                   1920–1941</hi>. Ljubljana: Društvo Slovenska
                   matica, 2008.</bibl>
               <bibl>Kavrečič, Petra and Milan Radošević. “Na morje! Izzivi turističnega razvoja v Istri v času Avstro-Ogrske in italijanske uprave s posebnim ozirom na leto 1925.” <hi rend="italic">Zgodovina za vse, vse za
                   zgodovino</hi> 24, No. 2 (2017): 21–40.</bibl>
               <bibl>Kavrečič, Petra. “'Sacro pellegrinaggio'. Visits of World War I Memorials on the Soča/Isonzo Front in the Interwar Period.” <hi rend="italic">Etnološka
                   tribina</hi> 40, No. 47 (2017): 141–60. </bibl>
               <bibl>Kavrečič, Petra.
                   <hi rend="italic">Turizem v Avstrijskem primorju:
                       zdravilišča, kopališča in kraške jame (1819</hi>–<hi rend="italic">1914)</hi>, 2. dopolnjena izdaja. Koper: Založba Univerze na
                   Primorskem, 2017.</bibl>
               <bibl>Klabjan, Borut. “Nation and Commemoration in the Adriatic: the Commemoration of the Italian Unknown Soldier in a Multinational Area: the Case of the Former Austrian Littoral.” <hi rend="italic">Acta
                   Histriae</hi> 22, No. 3 (2010): 695–714. </bibl>
               <bibl>Leonardi, Andrea. “La prima guerra mondiale e la
                   vulnerabilità del fenomeno turistico.” In
                   <hi rend="italic">Krieg und Tourismus im Spannungsfeld
                       des Ersten Weltkrieges: Guerra e Tourismo nell'area di tensione della Prima
                       Guerra Mondiale</hi>, edited by Patrick Gasser,
                   Andrea Leonardi and Gunda Barth-Scalmani, 57–98. Innsbruck: Studien Verlag,
                   2014.</bibl>
               <bibl>Livi, Livio. <hi rend="italic">L'economia della Regione Giulia nel
                   1926. Capitolo V. Il movimento dei forestieri</hi>. Trieste: Istituto statistico-economico annesso alla R. Università degli
                   studi economici e commerciali di Trieste, 1926.</bibl>
               <bibl>Löfgren, Orvar. <hi rend="italic">On Holiday. A History of
                   Vacationing</hi>. Berkley, Los Angeles, London:
                   University of California Press, 2002.</bibl>
               <bibl>Lloyd, David William. <hi rend="italic">Battlefield Tourism. Pilgrimage and the
                   Commemoration of the Great War in Britain, Australia and Canada,
                   1919–1939</hi>. Oxford, New York: Berg, 1998. </bibl>
               <bibl>Mikša, Peter. “Gradnja slovenske nacionalne identitete na podlagi t. i. nacionalnega boja v gorah.” In <hi rend="italic">Simpozij v spomin dr. Milanu Ževartu:
                   zbornik povzetkov 2. simpozija v spomin dr. Milanu Ževartu</hi>, 19. Velenje, 15 November 2018.</bibl>
               <bibl>Mikša, Peter and Kornelija Ajlec. <hi rend="italic">Slovensko planinstvo = Slovene
                   mountaineering</hi>. Ljubljana: Planinska zveza
                   Slovenije, 2015.</bibl>
               <bibl>Morosini, Stefano. “I rifugi Alpini dell'Alto Adige/Südtirol dalla fruizione turistica al presidio nazionale (1918–1943).” In <hi rend="italic">Krieg und Tourismus im Spannungsfeld
                   des Ersten Weltkrieges</hi>, edited by Patrick
                   Gasser, Andrea Leonardi and Gunda Barth-Scalmani, 181–207. Innsbruck:
                   Studien Verlag, 2014.</bibl>
               <bibl>Mosse, George L. <hi rend="italic">Le guerre mondiali. Dalla tragedia al
                   mito dei caduti</hi>. Roma; Bari: Edizioni
                   Laterza, 2007.</bibl>
               <bibl>Pelikan, Egon. <hi rend="italic">Tajno delovanje primorske duhovščine
                   pod fašizmom – Primorski krščanski socialci med Vatikanom, fašistično
                   Italijo in slovensko katoliško desnico – zgodovinsko ozadje romana Kaplan
                   Martin Čedermac</hi>. Ljubljana: Nova revija,
                   2002.</bibl>
               <bibl>Pirjevec, Jože. <hi rend="italic">'Trst je naš!'. Boj Slovencev za morje
                   (1848–1954)</hi>. Ljubljana: Nova revija, 2008. </bibl>
               <bibl>Prinčič, Jože. “Primorsko in postojnsko gospodarstvo v času med obema vojnama.” <hi rend="italic">Prispevki za novejšo
                   zgodovino</hi> 49, No. 1 (2009): 171–84.</bibl>
               <bibl>Puc, Matjaž.
                   <hi rend="italic">Škocjanske jame pri Divači: kronika
                       raziskovanj in turističnega obiska</hi>. Škocjan:
                   PŠJ, 2015.</bibl>
               <bibl>Seaton, A. V. “War and Thanatourism: Waterloo 1815–1914.” 
                   <hi rend="italic">Annals of Tourism
                       Research</hi> 26, No. 1 (1999): 130–58.</bibl>
               <bibl>Semmens, Kristin.
                   <hi rend="italic">Seeing Hitler's Germany: Tourism in the
                       Third Reich</hi>. Basingstoke: Palgrave
                   Macmillan, 2005.</bibl>
               <bibl>Shaw, Trevor. <hi rend="italic">Škocjanske jame 1920–1940</hi>. Ljubljana: Zalozba ZRC, 2018.</bibl>
               <bibl>Spode, Hasso. “Fordism, Mass Tourism and the Third Reich: The ʻStrength Through Joyʼ Seaside Resort as an Index Fossil.” <hi rend="italic">Journal of Social
                   History</hi> 38, No. 1 (2004): 127–55.</bibl>
               <bibl>Širok, Kaja. “Identitete, zgodovina in dediščina prostora – prakse spominjanja in komemoracije na Goriškem v XX. stoletju.” <hi rend="italic">Acta
                   Histriae</hi> 20, No. 4 (2012): 631–46. </bibl>
               <bibl>Širok, Kaja. “Spomin in pozaba na obmejnem območju: predstave o Goriški preteklosti.” <hi rend="italic">Acta
                   Histriae</hi> 18, No. 1–2 (2010): 337–57.</bibl>
               <bibl>Šuligoj, Metod. “Memories of War and Warfare Tourism in Croatia.” <hi rend="italic">Annales, Ser. Hist.
                   sociol.</hi> 26, No. 2 (2016): 259–70.</bibl>
               <bibl>Šuligoj, Metod and Medarić, Zorana. “Turistični prevozi, potovanja in izleti na obali severne Istre od 19. stoletja dalje=Turistički prijevozi, putovanja i izleti na obali sjeverne Istre od 19. stoljeća dalje.” In <hi rend="italic">Retrospektiva turizma Istre</hi>, edited by Metod Šuligoj, 49–110. Koper: Založba
                   Univerze na Primorskem, 2015).</bibl>
               <bibl>Todero, Fabio “Il culto del soldato caduto nella Venezia Giulia dalla Grande guerra al fascism.” In <hi rend="italic">Regime fascista, nazione e
                   periferie</hi>, edited by Anna Maria Vinci,
                   51–68. Udine: Studi e documenti, 2010.</bibl>
               <bibl>Verginella, Marta. <hi rend="italic">Meja drugih. Primorsko vprašanje in
                   slovenski spomin</hi>. Ljubljana: Modrijan,
                   2009.</bibl>
               <bibl>Verginella, Marta, Sandi Volk and Katja Colja. <hi rend="italic">Ljudje v vojni: druga svetovna vojna v
                   Trstu in na Primorskem</hi>. Koper: Zgodovinsko
                   društvo za južno Primorsko, 1995.</bibl>
               <bibl>Visintin, Angelo. “Dalla Grande guerra al fascismo. L’ ipotesi della Vittoria sui campi di battaglia dell’Isonzo.” In <hi rend="italic">Regime fascista, nazione e
                   periferie</hi>, edited by Anna Maria Vinci,
                   69–87. Udine: Studi e documenti, 2010, 30.</bibl>
               <bibl>Walter, Tony. “War Grave Pilgrimage”. In <hi rend="italic">Pilgrimage in Popular Culture</hi>, edited by Ian Reader and Tony Walter, 63–91.
                   London: Palgrave, Macmillan, 1993.</bibl>
               <bibl>Winter, Caroline. “Battlefield Visitor Motivations. Explorations in the Great War Town of Ieper, Belgium.” <hi rend="italic">International Journal of Tourism
                   Research</hi> 13 (2011): 164–76.</bibl>
               <bibl>Wolff, Larry. <hi rend="italic">Venice and the Slavs: The Discovery of
                   Dalmatia in the Age of Enlightenment</hi>.
                   Stanford: Stanford University Press, 2001.</bibl>
           </listBibl>
           <listBibl>
               <head>Online Sources</head>
               <bibl>RD<hi rend="italic"> (Regio decreto) 24. 5. 1925, n. 1102. “Approvazione del regolamento per le migliorie igieniche negli alberghi</hi>.” Accessed July 15, 2020. <ref target="http://www.comune.jesi.an.it/MV/leggi/rd1102-25.htm">http://www.comune.jesi.an.it/MV/leggi/rd1102-25.htm</ref>.  </bibl>
               <bibl>RDL <hi rend="italic">(Regio decreto legge) 15. 4. 1926 n. 765.
                   “Provvedimenti per la tutela e lo sviluppo dei luoghi di cura di soggiorno o
                   di turismo.</hi>” Accessed July 15, 2020.<ref target="http://www.edizionieuropee.it/LAW/HTML/89/zn96_02_001.html">http://www.edizionieuropee.it/LAW/HTML/89/zn96_02_001.html</ref>. 
               </bibl>
           </listBibl></div>
           <div type="summary" xml:lang="sl">
           <docAuthor>Petra Kavrečič</docAuthor>
           <head>TURIZEM IN FAŠIZEM. TURISTIČNI
               RAZVOJ NA ITALIJANSKI VZHODNI MEJI</head>
           <head>POVZETEK</head>
           <p>Prispevek se osredotoča na obravnavo turističnega razvoja
               nekdanje italijanske province Julijske krajine (<hi rend="italic">Venezia Giulia</hi>). V
               ospredju zanimanja je torej obdobje med obema vojnama. Območje, ki je predmet
               analize, predstavlja zanimivo študijo primera, ki še ni bila deležna zadostne
               historične znanstvene obravnave, vsaj glede področja turističnega razvoja. Namen
               prispevka je analiza povezave med ukrepi za konsolidacijo političnega režima in
               težnjo po nacionalni afirmaciji na eni ter turističnim sektorjem na drugi
               strani. Obravnavan je turistični razvoj današnje zahodne Slovenije, to je
               območje, ki je po prvi svetovni vojni prešlo iz ene politične strukture
               (Avstro-Ogrska) v drugo (Kraljevina Italija). Pri tem se je teritorij (oziroma
               njegovo prebivalstvo) v okviru nove države kmalu moral soočiti z naraščajočim
               totalitarnim političnim režimom, fašizmom, ki je tudi uradno stopil na oblast
               leta 1922. V ospredju zanimanja je ugotoviti, kako je posameznim turističnim
               krajem (»starim« in »novim« destinacijam) uspelo prilagoditi svojo ponudbo v
               spremenjenih političnih okoliščinah. Obmorske turistične destinacije in podzemne
               jame so bile prepoznavne in uveljavljene turistične točke že v avstrijskem
               obdobju. Zanima me, ali je na njihov nadaljnji razvoj močno vplivala nova
               politična doktrina. Poleg že uveljavljenih, »starih« turističnih atrakcij so se
               na območju, pogorišču bitk prve svetovne vojne, razvijale tudi »nove« oblike
               turistične ponudbe. Slednje so bile povezane s sekularnim romanjem, žalovanjem
               in spominom na gloriozno žrtvovanje za nacijo. V okviru praks, ki so se na
               območju nekdanjih bojišč pojavile po koncu vojne (spomeniki neznanim junakom,
               pokopališča, grobišča in monumentalni spomeniki ali cone spomina), se je razvila
               tudi nova tipologija turistične ponudbe (temni turizem, turizem obiskovanja
               bojišč).</p></div>
       </back>
   </text>
</TEI>