<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">“The Case of Comrade Dragiša Pavlović”<lb/>The Yugoslav Media Space and Its Perception Through the Example of
                    the Main Political Weeklies’ Coverage of the Eighth Session of the Central
                    Committee of the League of Communists of Serbia<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn1"
                        n="*">The article was written in the framework of the basic research project
                        J5-1793: <hi rend="italic">Vloga komunikacijskih neenakosti v dezintegraciji
                            večnacionalne družbe</hi> (The Role of Communication Inequalities in the
                        Disintegration of the Multinational Society) and the research programme
                        P6-0281: <hi rend="italic">Politična zgodovina</hi> (Political History),
                        co-financed by the Slovenian Research Agency (ARRS) from the state
                        budget.</note></title>
                <author>
                    <forename>Jurij</forename>
                    <surname>Hadalin</surname>
                    <roleName>PhD</roleName>
                    <roleName>Research Associate</roleName>
                    <affiliation>Institute of Contemporary History</affiliation>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Privoz 11</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>SI-1000 Ljubljana</addrLine>
                    </address>
                    <email>jurij.hadalin@inz.si</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <forename>Marko</forename>
                    <surname>Zajc</surname>
                    <roleName>PhD</roleName>
                    <roleName>Research Associate</roleName>
                    <affiliation>Institute of Contemporary History</affiliation>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Privoz 11</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>SI-1000 Ljubljana</addrLine>
                    </address>
                    <email>marko.zajc@inz.si</email>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>2022-04-21</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>
                    <orgName xml:lang="sl">Inštitut za novejšo zgodovino</orgName>
                    <orgName xml:lang="en">Institute of Contemporary History</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Privoz 11</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>SI-1000 Ljubljana</addrLine>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>http://ojs.inz.si/pnz/article/view/</pubPlace>
                <date>2021</date>
                <availability status="free">
                    <licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title xml:lang="sl">Prispevki za novejšo zgodovino</title>
                <title xml:lang="en">Contributions to Contemporary History</title>
                <biblScope unit="volume">62</biblScope>
                <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
                <idno type="ISSN">2463-7807</idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source, born digital.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc xml:lang="en">
                <p>Contributions to Contemporary History is one of the central Slovenian scientific
                    historiographic journals, dedicated to publishing articles from the field of
                    contemporary history (the 19th and 20th century).</p>
                <p>The journal is published three times per year in Slovenian and in the following
                    foreign languages: English, German, Serbian, Croatian, Bosnian, Italian, Slovak
                    and Czech. The articles are all published with abstracts in English and
                    Slovenian as well as summaries in English.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <projectDesc xml:lang="sl">
                <p>Prispevki za novejšo zgodovino je ena osrednjih slovenskih znanstvenih
                    zgodovinopisnih revij, ki objavlja teme s področja novejše zgodovine (19. in 20.
                    stoletje).</p>
                <p>Revija izide trikrat letno v slovenskem jeziku in v naslednjih tujih jezikih:
                    angleščina, nemščina, srbščina, hrvaščina, bosanščina, italijanščina, slovaščina
                    in češčina. Članki izhajajo z izvlečki v angleščini in slovenščini ter povzetki
                    v angleščini.</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en"/>
                <language ident="sl"/>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords xml:lang="en">
                    <term>Slovenia</term>
                    <term>Yugoslavia</term>
                    <term>media</term>
                    <term>political discourse</term>
                    <term>political history</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords xml:lang="sl">
                    <term>Slovenija</term>
                    <term>Jugoslavija</term>
                    <term>mediji</term>
                    <term>politični diskurz</term>
                    <term>politična zgodovina</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change><date>2022-05-04T07:22:12Z</date>
                    <name>Mihael Ojsteršek</name>
                    <desc>Pretvorba iz DOCX v TEI, dodatno kodiranje</desc></change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <docAuthor>Jurij Hadalin<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn2" n="**"><hi rend="bold">PhD,
                        Research Associate, Institute of Contemporary History, Privoz 11, SI-1000
                        Ljubljana; </hi><ref target="mailto:jurij.hadalin@inz.si"><hi rend="bold"
                            >jurij.hadalin@inz.si</hi></ref></note></docAuthor>
            <docAuthor>Marko Zajc<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn3" n="***"><hi rend="bold">PhD,
                        Research Associate, Institute of Contemporary History, Privoz 11, SI-1000
                        Ljubljana; </hi><ref target="mailto:marko.zajc@inz.si"><hi rend="bold"
                            >marko.zajc@inz.si</hi></ref></note></docAuthor>
            <docImprint>
                <idno type="cobissType">Cobiss tip: 1.01</idno>
                <idno type="DOI">doi: https://doi.org/10.51663/pnz.62.1.8</idno>
            </docImprint>
            <div type="abstract" xml:lang="sl">
                <head>IZVLEČEK</head>
                <head><hi rend="italic">»PRIMER TOVARIŠA DRAGIŠE PAVLOVIĆA«</hi></head>
                <head><hi rend="italic">JUGOSLOVANSKI MEDIJSKI PROSTOR IN NJEGOVO DOJEMANJE NA
                        PRIMERU POROČANJA OSREDNJIH POLITIČNIH TEDNIKOV O OSMEM PLENUMU CENTRALNEGA
                        KOMITEJA ZVEZE KOMUNISTOV SRBIJE</hi></head>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Prispevek obravnava vprašanje homogenosti jugoslovanske
                        medijske krajine, ki je že v sodobni literaturi in časopisju bila
                        obravnavana kot izrazito republiško usmerjena. Za vsebinski okvir analize
                        sta avtorja iz množice tem v politično razgretih osemdesetih letih
                        prejšnjega stoletja odbrala poročanje o dogajanju na osmem plenumu
                        Centralnega komiteja Zveze komunistov Srbije. O tej temi so najobširneje in
                        najbolj poglobljeno poročali redki jugoslovanski politični tedniki, ki so v
                        prispevku predstavljeni, analiziran pa je tudi njihov diskurz. Iz analize se
                        nakazuje zaključek, da so politični tedniki sicer bili usmerjeni v
                        republiško okolje, vendar pa so zaradi široke mreže povezav med
                        obravnavanimi mediji in novinarji bili bistveno bolj jugoslovansko
                        usmerjeni, kot so to menili v času njihovega izhajanja.</hi></p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Ključne besede: Slovenija, Jugoslavija, mediji, politični
                        diskurz, politična zgodovina</hi></p>
            </div>
            <div type="abstract" xml:lang="en">
                <head>ABSTRACT</head>
                <p><hi rend="italic">The article deals with the question of the homogeneity of the
                        Yugoslav media landscape, which is already considered to be distinctly
                        republican in modern literature and newspapers. From a variety of topics in
                        the politically heated 1980s, the authors chose reports on events at the
                        Eighth Plenum of the Central Committee of the League of Communists of Serbia
                        as the basis for analysis. The rare Yugoslav political weeklies reported on
                        this issue most extensively and in detail, and article deals with presenting
                        and analyzing their discourse. The analysis suggests that the political
                        weeklies focused on the republican environment but, because of the extensive
                        network of connections between the media outlets and journalists in
                        question, were significantly more Yugoslav-oriented than they were thought
                        at the time of publication.</hi></p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Keywords: Slovenia, Yugoslavia, media, political discourse,
                        political history</hi></p>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div>
                <head>The Unity of the Yugoslav Media Space?</head>
                <p>In the Slovenian historical memory of the media landscape of socialist Yugoslavia
                    during the 1980s, the period between 1987 and 1991 has made the most prominent
                    impression. At that time, the tensions between the Slovenian and Serbian
                    political leadership led to the outbreak of the so-called “media war”, which put
                    a heavy strain on the mutual relations and did not come to an end until the very
                    disintegration of the common state. On the other hand, this war was distinctly
                    unequal, as, on the Serbian side, we can observe the silent takeover of the most
                    important media players, which then allowed for the consolidation of the new
                    Serbian Party leadership; while on the Slovenian side, the Party leadership
                    attempted to control the social unrest mainly by implementing technical measures
                    (occasional seizures of the individual issues of the disobedient press). In
                    response to the critical articles coming from Serbia, Jože Smole, the president
                    of the Republic Conference of the Socialist Alliance of Working People at the
                    time, asked in the daily newspaper <hi rend="italic">Borba</hi>: “Why are
                    certain objectionable texts published in the Slovenian press, being responded to
                    with prominent commentaries that reach millions of readers and are thus provided
                    with unacceptable publicity?”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn4" n="1">Krste
                        Bijelić, “Slovenija i Jugoslavija: zašto (1): Sindrom ‘paralelnog toka’,”
                            <hi rend="italic">Duga</hi> 359, 28 November – 11 December 1987,
                        67.</note></p>
                <p>However, this process – popularly called the “Slovenian syndrome” in the “newly
                    composed journalism”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn5" n="2">The term stems from a
                        somewhat pejorative expression for the so-called newly composed folk music,
                        a type of popular music that was becoming increasingly loaded with
                        nationalist symbols. – Rory Archer, “Assessing Turbofolk Controversies:
                        Popular Music between the Nation and the Balkans,” <hi rend="italic"
                            >Southeastern Europe</hi> 36, No. 2 (2012): 179.</note> of the second
                    half of the 1980s – was not a novelty: it had dominated the Yugoslav media
                    landscape for a decade or more before the escalation of the problems<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn6" n="3">In 1974, the editor of the <hi
                            rend="italic">Delo</hi> daily newspaper addressed this issue in an
                        editorial: “During the festive days leading up to the New Year, the Yugoslav
                        press focused on ‘Slovenian topics’ a lot. One of the most interesting of
                        these was the recruitment of workers from the other republics in Slovenia.”
                        Thus, the Slovenian syndrome started becoming apparent already very early
                        on: “And precisely because the problem exists and because it is serious –
                        and because we should write about it and discuss it rather than ignoring it
                        – we should also underline that just as quickly as writing or speaking
                        carelessly and insensitively can leave a bad taste, it can also create
                        dilemmas in people, introduce a kind of an intimate agitation which, if
                        abused, can become political, to which we must pay particular attention to
                        in Yugoslavia…/… In its famous series of articles about Slovenia, <hi
                            rend="italic">NIN</hi> from Belgrade has already…/… What worries me most
                        is the undertone that can be felt in some of the Yugoslav press. Perhaps the
                            <hi rend="italic">NIN</hi> magazine expresses it most evidently.” –
                        Mitja Gorjup, “Da bi se bolje razumeli,” <hi rend="italic">Delo</hi>, 4
                        September 1974, 7.</note> and processes of differentiation,<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn7" n="4">“Not everything in Yugoslavia can be made
                        uniform. We would be happy if we had many more alternative solutions to all
                        of the important issues than we have now. We cannot accuse everyone who
                        disagrees of being anti-communist.” – Ibidem.</note> which became a constant
                    in the Yugoslav politics and society after the Eighth Session of the Central
                    Committee of the League of Communists of Serbia. Even before, this issue had
                    been a part of ideological campaigns, and the individual republics’ policies
                    towards the opposition were very different. “In the second half of the 1980s,
                    the attempts at all-Yugoslav ideological campaigns became uncommon, mostly due
                    to the interest in exposing particular environments to criticism – especially
                    Kosovo and Slovenia, and by the end of the 1980s Croatia as well.”<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn8" n="5">Božo Repe, <hi rend="italic">Slovenci v
                            osemdesetih letih</hi> (Ljubljana: Zveza zgodovinskih društev Slovenije,
                        2001), 22.</note> In this context, it can be argued that no single media
                    space existed in Yugoslavia, although the processes taking place in the
                    environments of the various republics and media companies were essentially quite
                    similar. In his pioneering work on the position of Slovenians in
                        Yugoslavia,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn9" n="6">Božo Repe, “Zakaj so
                        Slovenci vstopili v Jugoslavijo in zakaj so iz nje odšli?,” in: <hi
                            rend="italic">Jugoslavija v času: devetdeset let od nastanka prve
                            jugoslovanske države</hi>, ed. Bojan Balkovec (Ljubljana: Znanstvena
                        založba Filozofske fakultete, 2009), 36.</note> Božo Repe thus stated: “In
                    the 1980s, cultural and economic differences, poor mutual familiarity and
                    stereotypical ideas about each other – despite living together for decades –
                    started to increase in the 1980s. News systems functioned mainly within the
                    individual republics.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn10" n="7">Precisely this
                        theme was underlined in the report about the 10<hi rend="superscript"
                            >th</hi> Congress of the League of Communists of Slovenia in the
                        political weekly <hi rend="italic">NIN</hi>. “The differences in the
                        development of Slovenia and the rest of Yugoslavia is completely obvious,
                        but, on the other hand, the gap between Slovenia and its western neighbours
                        has been increasing in recent years.” – Šćepan Rabrenović, “Slovenija na
                        jugu,” <hi rend="italic">NIN</hi> 1843, 27 April 1986, 9.</note></p>
                <p>Such observations were nothing new: Mitja Gorjup, a prominent expert on the
                    Yugoslav journalism and editor-in-chief of the newspaper <hi rend="italic"
                        >Delo</hi>, had already addressed these issues in the 1970s: “To sum all of
                    this up, I will focus on the basic problems of the Yugoslav press in general,
                    which can be reduced to a single predominant theme: the entire Yugoslav press is
                    essentially not Yugoslav enough. It does not nurture the Yugoslav dimension
                    enough in terms of information and the political presentation of events and
                        trends.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn11" n="8">Mitja Gorjup, “Preveč vase
                        zaprta kultura (Iz razprave na sestanku osnovne organizacije ZKS ‘Delo’ –
                        časopisi), 16. januarja 1974,” in: Mitja Gorjup, <hi rend="italic"
                            >Samoupravno novinarstvo</hi> (Ljubljana: Delavska enotnost, 1978),
                        96.</note> This question was on the minds of the journalists themselves: in
                    1985, a consultation of Yugoslav journalists was held in Novi Sad, titled
                    “Yugoslav Contents in the Public Press”, which saw the unity of politics as the
                    precondition for the unity of the Yugoslav news system. In this regard, Jug
                    Grizelj, an exceedingly Yugoslav-oriented journalist of the Serbian magazine <hi
                        rend="italic">NIN</hi>, pointed out that this did not refer to the
                    statistical calculations of Yugoslav contents in the individual media (these
                    averaged between twenty and thirty percent – a piece of information that the
                    speakers at the conference kept pointing out as proof of disunity). However, the
                    fact remained that various environments perceived the same process differently,
                    even though Grizelj justified it with the globally present processes of
                    decentralisation, democratisation, and personalisation of information.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn12" n="9">Jug Grizelj, “Jedinstvo nije u rukama
                        novinara,” <hi rend="italic">NIN</hi> 1832, 2 February 1986, 19.</note></p>
                <p>In 1977, Gorjup also raised the question of the Yugoslavianisation of the
                    newspapers of the individual republics. “I think we are too narrowly focused on
                    the republics. Of course, we are primarily republican newsletters, but we need
                    to provide our readers with as much information about Yugoslavia as possible. We
                    are not succeeding, though. In addition, a kind of mentality is spreading that
                    the affairs of the individual republics should only be discussed in the
                    newspapers of those republics…” Thus, he underlined the problem related both to
                    the “Slovenian syndrome” and later to the media war, as “the notion that one
                    should only mind one’s own business and leave one’s neighbours alone”<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn13" n="10">Thus, the President of the Slovenian
                        Assembly Miran Potrč gave a lengthy interview for the weekly magazine <hi
                            rend="italic">Nin</hi>, which came across as a justification in front of
                        the Serbian public, as it was essentially devoted to his previous statement
                        for the British BBC regarding the issue of the distribution of
                        foreign-exchange assets in the Yugoslav federation. – Šćepan Rabrenović,
                        “Čije su devize: predsednik Skupštine SR Slovenije Miran Potrč govori za
                        NIN,” <hi rend="italic">NIN</hi> 1864, 21 September 1986, 13–16.</note> was
                    also a problem.</p>
                <p>“I believe that this issue is taking on very problematic proportions. Such
                    behaviour inevitably leads to closing ourselves within the republican borders,
                    which is certainly not beneficial. Another issue I think is problematic is the
                    over-sensitivity of the Yugoslav environments to what is written about them
                    elsewhere. What is happening now is that we often write about events in the
                    other republics unproblematically and uncritically. Thus a kind of an idyllic
                    image of Yugoslavia is being created in the mass media, suggesting that there
                    are no problems, difficulties, or misunderstandings. This is, of course, at odds
                    with reality…/… The public media simply avoid any ‘non-idyllic’ information,
                    leading to a paradox: because of this, people often refuse to believe us. We
                    need to shape the public opinion in such a way that people know that the state,
                    through its constitutional mechanisms, is capable of resolving all the objective
                    socio-economic and political contradictions without any political drama and
                        scandals.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn14" n="11">Mladen Pleše, “Pravi
                        pogum je povezan z znanjem,” in: Mitja Gorjup, <hi rend="italic">Samoupravno
                            novinarstvo</hi>, 145, 146.</note></p>
                <p>Therefore, the critical Serbian journalist Ivan Torov describes the period before
                    the process under consideration as one of relative media freedom: “The first
                    five or six years after Tito’s death – after an initial lull due to the
                    uncertainty inevitably provoked by the departure of a great leader – will
                    certainly be remembered as a period of a more notable liberation of news outlets
                    from the political shackles they had been subjected to. Critical analyses of the
                    economic and political realities were approached more and more courageously,
                    many scandals and abuses were exposed, and free professional journalism was
                    increasingly successful in filling the empty space resulting from the lack of
                    cohesion in Serbia and Yugoslavia. Already in the first half of 1985, it was
                    believed that Serbian journalism, along with many other newspapers in the other
                    republics, was experiencing a democratic development that would be difficult to
                    stop. Publications such as <hi rend="italic">Borba</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
                        >Duga</hi>, <hi rend="italic">NIN</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Mladost</hi>, and
                        <hi rend="italic">NON</hi> dictated the rhythm in this new wave and
                    doubtlessly had a significant impact on the increasingly visible changes in the
                    leading media companies…”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn15" n="12">Ivan Torov,
                        “Sunovrat srpskog novinarstva (delovi iz knjige),” in: <hi rend="italic"
                            >“Antibirokratska revolucija”: (1987–1989)</hi>, eds. Bojana Lekić,
                        Zoran Pavić, Slaviša Lekić and Imre Sabo (Beograd: Statusteam in Službeni
                        glasnik, 2009), 270.</note> A similar trend could also be attributed to the
                    developments in the Slovenian media, most prominently among weeklies. After
                    1984, the previously benign if not almost boring newsletter of the Socialist
                    Youth League of Slovenia <hi rend="italic">Mladina</hi> became clearly
                        radicalised.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn16" n="13">Sonja Merljak Zdovc,
                        “Slovenska revija Tovariš in njeni revialni ‘tovariši’ v drugi polovici
                        dvajsetega stoletja,” <hi rend="italic">Prispevki k zgodovini slovenskih
                            medijev</hi>, ed. Maruša Pušnik (Ljubljana: Fakulteta za družbene vede,
                        2008), 535.</note> Along with the magazine <hi rend="italic">Teleks</hi>
                    from the <hi rend="italic">Delo</hi> newspaper company, it developed into the
                    most important Slovenian political weekly.</p>
                <p>When asked about it, Jure Apih, the first editor of <hi rend="italic"
                    >Teleks</hi>, agreed that at the time, this magazine represented a medium
                    through which the society communicated with itself since the only official
                    newsletter of the League of Communists, <hi rend="italic">Komunist</hi>, simply
                    adhered to the Party directives, while in the daily newspaper <hi rend="italic"
                        >Delo</hi>, reporting was restricted to what had been agreed upon with its
                    official founder, the Socialist Alliance of Working People.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn17" n="14">Ervin Hladnik Milharčič, “#intervju Jure Apih,
                        časnikar: prej so se časopisi delali za partijo, mi smo ga delali za
                        bralce,” <hi rend="italic">Dnevnik.si</hi>, 24 October 2020, <ref
                            target="https://www.dnevnik.si/1042941784"
                            >https://www.dnevnik.si/1042941784</ref>, accessed on 1 March
                        2022.</note> Thus, he actually responded to a claim made by the former
                    editor of <hi rend="italic">Delo</hi> Mitja Gorjup when the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Teleks</hi> weekly was being conceived: “With the advancement of technical
                    possibilities and the increasing flow of information, journalistic work is
                    starting to influence the public opinion more and more, while the public opinion
                    also keeps gaining more and more influence on the political decisions. On the
                    one hand, this offers the information media greater opportunities and power,
                    but, on the other hand, it also confronts them with greater responsibility, as
                    by highlighting and interpreting information, the press can make a significant
                    contribution to the creation of a certain public climate.”</p>
                <p>As Ljubomir Tadić wrote, the task of the press was therefore clear because “under
                    socialism, the public opinion appears as a form of social consciousness for the
                    purpose of coordinating the interests in tackling social issues or as the
                    qualified, competent, clear, and understandable reasoning of the working people
                    regarding the general activities of the community.“ In this sense, it is a
                    permanent and important mental presupposition of socialist democracy.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn18" n="15">Ljubomir Tadić, <hi rend="italic">Javno
                            mnenje u savremenom društvu, javno mnenje o Prednacrtu novog Ustava</hi>
                        (Institut društvenih nauka: Beograd, 1964), 31.</note> The activities of the
                    Socialist Alliance of Working People (SZDL), officially the broadest
                    socio-political organisation in Yugoslavia that represented a much wider forum
                    than the League of Communists, was thus one of the forms of public opinion – a
                    place where the public gathered and was shaped, and where the common consensus
                    of the self-managers was being developed. On the other hand, the SZDL was
                    simultaneously the factor of the broadest social control. “The organisational
                    structure of the SZDL and the way in which it operates allow it to initiate,
                    discuss, propose, and agree on solutions to various social issues. Meanwhile,
                    the mass media as a form of shaping and expressing the public opinion is of
                    particular significance. Moreover, the SZDL also formally possesses ‘its own’
                    daily press ( <hi rend="italic">Borba</hi> as the newsletter of the Socialist
                    Alliance of Working People of Yugoslavia, <hi rend="italic">Vjesnik</hi> as the
                    newsletter of the Socialist Alliance of Working People of Croatia, etc.). The
                    institution of editorial and programme councils in other major media (weeklies,
                    magazines, radio, TV) allows the SZDL to notably influence their policies.”<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn19" n="16">Katarina Spehnjak, “Narodni front
                        Jugoslavije (SSRNJ – razvoj, programsko-teorijske osnove i procesi u
                        društvenoj praksi 1945–1983),” <hi rend="italic">Povijesni prilozi</hi> 3,
                        No. 3 (1984), 67.</note></p>
                <p>The shape of the media landscape in Yugoslavia was therefore also dictated by the
                    political structure. In 1986, Joža Vlahović, the first editor of the Zagreb
                    weekly <hi rend="italic">Danas</hi>, thus stated the following: “For a long
                    time, we have not had a situation where the main newspapers would simultaneously
                    be Party newsletters. That is how it used to be. Everything published today,
                    except newspapers like <hi rend="italic">Komunist</hi>, of course, is a kind of
                    a voice, if not a body, of the Socialist Alliance – from <hi rend="italic"
                        >Borba</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Politika</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
                        >Vjesnik</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Delo</hi>, author’s note) and so on…” The
                    manner of writing was still controlled, though – as it is evident from the
                    example of the <hi rend="italic">Teleks</hi> magazine, where the editors Apih
                    and Anton Rupnik were dismissed due to the negative reviews of the articles on
                    the socialist morality, while the cause for the replacement was the publication
                    of an interview with the controversial Italian publicist Oriana Fallaci.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn20" n="17">Merljak Zdovc, “Slovenska revija
                        Tovariš in njeni revialni ‘tovariši’?,” 537.</note> A similar conclusion can
                    be drawn regarding the popular fortnightly <hi rend="italic">Duga</hi>: in terms
                    of contents, this publication was quite similar to the early <hi rend="italic"
                        >Teleks</hi>, and according to the editor of the <hi rend="italic">Danas
                    </hi>weekly, it had been a victim of political pragmatism before a thorough
                    editorial change in 1985. “Unfortunately, pragmatism is most important for
                    newspapers. Certain weeklies end up in serious conflicts with the ‘daily’
                    pragmatic policy and can easily get a shady reputation, although some of them
                    rightfully so and for a good reason. In terms of their spirit and mission,
                    weeklies should fight for more room for their activities (for the strategic
                    goals of the society) and are not obliged to submit to the dreary and often
                    narrow-minded daily politics…/… I think it was precisely <hi rend="italic"
                        >Duga</hi> that has experienced a lot of this firsthand. If I can put it
                    this way, it was the very magazine that would often get caught in the pitfalls
                    of pragmatism, but with the overtones of politics I could not agree with. Well,
                    now I read about the better assessments by both the Party organisation and the
                    board of your magazine…”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn21" n="18">Tatjana
                        Tagirov, “Ne pucaj na novinara: Joža Vlahović, Borac sa prave strane
                        barikade,” <hi rend="italic">Duga</hi> 332, 15 – 28 November 1986,
                        10–14.</note></p>
                <p>In this context, Joža Vlahović was probably referring to the report from the <hi
                        rend="italic">Duga</hi> publishing board,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn22"
                        n="19">The official founder of the magazine was the Socialist Alliance of
                        Working People of Serbia, but it was published under the auspices of the
                        prominent publishing house BIGZ.</note> which radically altered its
                    orientation in October 1985: “We are firmly decided to create a newspaper with
                    an unequivocally Yugoslav, socialist, and self-management orientation as the
                    best bulwark against nationalism, anti-communism, and dogmatism. During this
                    time, we have gathered thirty journalists from twenty Yugoslav editorships and
                    many scientific, cultural, and socio-political workers from practically all
                    parts of the country. We believe that in this way, we can free ourselves from
                    the stereotypes that have accompanied <hi rend="italic">Duga</hi> for a decade –
                    that it is a kind of a dissident if not even a Greater Serbian newspaper…”<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn23" n="20">Grujica Spasović, “Produžite vašom
                        ulicom: Sednica izdavačkog saveta Duge,” <hi rend="italic">Duga</hi> 331, 1
                        – 14 November 1986, 38.</note> However, even after that, the publication did
                    not manage to avoid controversy: in 1986, it published a lengthy interview with
                    Dimitrij Rupel, whose views managed to inflame the Slovenian-Serbian relations.
                    The editorship therefore faced a long conversation/justification with the
                    Slovenian political leadership.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn24" n="21">Marko
                        Zajc, “Poletni aferi kritičnih misli: Tomaž Mastnak in Dimitrij Rupel,
                        slovenska kritična intelektualca med jugoslovansko in slovensko javnostjo v
                        letu 1986,” <hi rend="italic">Studia Historica Slovenica</hi> 20, No. 3
                        (2020), 921–55.</note> The magazine itself will not be the subject of the
                    analysis of the events surrounding the Eighth Session of the League of
                    Communists of Serbia. However, it is intriguing as an example of a publication
                    that became one of the first to take the side of the Session winners because of
                    the previous actions that had been taken against it due to its orientation and
                    its handling of “hot topics”.</p>
                <p>The role of political weeklies among the media was important, as their way of
                    reporting differed considerably from that of daily newspapers. The period under
                    consideration was their golden age, despite the drops in circulation during the
                    times when the editorships were being disciplined, resulting in less public
                    attention. The more they were perceived as “Party newspapers”, the lesser their
                    influence. This trend can be observed in the examples of <hi rend="italic"
                        >Teleks</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Danas</hi>, as well as <hi rend="italic"
                        >NIN</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Duga</hi>. This made the weekly political
                    newspapers more independent from the day-to-day politics.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn25" n="22">Merljak Zdovc, “Slovenska revija Tovariš in
                        njeni revialni ‘tovariši’,” 530.</note> The editor of <hi rend="italic"
                        >Danas</hi> agreed: “Political weeklies – as well as other similar
                    publications – are, by their very design, a synthesis of all the dailies at the
                    end of the week. Therefore, they do not share the excuse of the daily
                    newspapers, which are often forced to react hastily and superficially. At the
                    same time, as soon as weeklies attempt to conduct deeper analyses, they end up
                    in a delicate situation, as they more often face unpleasantness, clash with
                    certain individuals from politics but also from the economy and culture, and
                    frequently stumble upon the interests of the daily politics and strategic
                    orientations.” During the period we are researching, the main Slovenian daily
                    newspaper <hi rend="italic">Delo</hi> was much more neutral than the writing of
                    the political weeklies <hi rend="italic">Teleks</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
                        >Mladina.</hi> After 1986, the Zagreb-based <hi rend="italic">Danas</hi>
                    paved the way for the positioning of the Croatian politics that was not evident
                    from the writing of the daily owned by the parent media company <hi
                        rend="italic">Vjesnik</hi>. Finally, the Serbian <hi rend="italic">NIN</hi>,
                    published by the newspaper company of the daily <hi rend="italic">Politika
                        –</hi> which became the first proponent of the new political trends in
                    Serbia – still resisted this trend in the first months of 1988. Already in 1983,
                        <hi rend="italic">Danas</hi> and <hi rend="italic">NIN</hi> were recognised
                    as the most important political weeklies in Yugoslavia.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn26" n="23">“Nekatere ocene vsebinske naravnanosti in ekonomskega
                        položaja revije Teleks v letu 1983,” <hi rend="italic">apih.si</hi>, <ref
                            target="http://www.apih.si/nekatere-ocene-vsebinske-neravnanosti-ekonomskega-polozaja-revije-teleks-v-letu-1983/"
                            >http://www.apih.si/nekatere-ocene-vsebinske-neravnanosti-ekonomskega-polozaja-revije-teleks-v-letu-1983/</ref>,
                        accessed on 1 March 2022.</note> In this regard, we should also note that
                    all the weekly newspapers under consideration expressed their Yugoslav
                    orientation, including the Cyrillic <hi rend="italic">NIN</hi>.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn27" n="24">“Ohrabrenja u vremenu iskušenja,” <hi
                            rend="italic">NIN</hi> 1853, 6 July 1986, 16.</note> With ample
                    references to the writing of the other weeklies, by reprinting articles from the
                    Yugoslav press or by commenting on them, the Yugoslav dimension was usually
                    maintained by all the weekly publications.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn28"
                        n="25">For example, in the summer of 1987, the <hi rend="italic">Nin</hi>
                        magazine reprinted extracts from the most controversial texts from the
                        Slovenian media on several pages. ‒ “Slovenačko ogledalo štampe,” <hi
                            rend="italic">NIN</hi> 1963, 23 August 1987, 20–24.</note> However, as
                    it was established in the assessment of the content and orientation of <hi
                        rend="italic">Teleks</hi> in 1983, “a review of these articles revealed that
                    the <hi rend="italic">Teleks</hi> readers could get the impression that
                    everything was wrong in the other provinces and republics, that there was
                    nothing but scandals, affairs, and economic failures, that they were only
                    fighting among themselves, arguing, scheming against each other, and that they
                    were rife with nationalist outbursts. The <hi rend="italic">Teleks</hi> readers
                    only learned the most ‘juicy bits’ of long interviews published in other
                        newspapers.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn29" n="26">“Nekatere ocene
                        vsebinske naravnanosti in ekonomskega položaja revije Teleks v letu 1983,”
                            <hi rend="italic">apih.si</hi>, <ref
                            target="http://www.apih.si/nekatere-ocene-vsebinske-neravnanosti-ekonomskega-polozaja-revije-teleks-v-letu-1983/"
                            >http://www.apih.si/nekatere-ocene-vsebinske-neravnanosti-ekonomskega-polozaja-revije-teleks-v-letu-1983/</ref>,
                        accessed on 1 March 2022.</note> To return to the claim that no common media
                    space existed in Yugoslavia – or rather that the media spaces of the individual
                    republics were prevalent<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn30" n="27">In this
                        context, Bosnia and Herzegovina was a slight exception: there, <hi
                            rend="italic">Danas</hi> and <hi rend="italic">NIN</hi> had a large
                        readership, the main local newspaper company <hi rend="italic"
                            >Oslobođenje</hi> published the weekly newspaper <hi rend="italic"
                            >Nedjelja</hi>, while the youth newspaper <hi rend="italic">Naši
                            Dani</hi> was probably more influential in the period under
                        review.</note> – the actual reach of these publications in Slovenia is also
                    evidenced by the results of the Slovenian Public Opinion survey for the year
                    1988, carried out in June 1988. <hi rend="italic">Teleks</hi> and <hi
                        rend="italic">Mladina</hi> reached between 30 and 50 percent of the
                    population, while the political weeklies from the other republics had a much
                    smaller reach, e.g. 11 % for <hi rend="italic">Danas</hi>, less than 8 % for <hi
                        rend="italic">Duga</hi>, and only 5 % for <hi rend="italic">NIN –</hi> and
                    even in these cases, the readers indicated that they very rarely consulted the
                    press from the other republics. Compared to the daily newspapers, the difference
                    was even greater, with <hi rend="italic">Delo</hi> reaching 65 % of the
                    Slovenian population and Zagreb’s <hi rend="italic">Vjesnik</hi> 11 %, while
                    less than 5 % of respondents had ever got their hands on <hi rend="italic"
                        >Politika</hi>, the most notorious newspaper at the time.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn31" n="28">Niko Toš, “Slovensko javno mnenje 1988 [Podatkovna
                        datoteka],” <hi rend="italic">Arhiv družboslovnih podatkov</hi> (Ljubljana:
                        Univerza v Ljubljani, 2000), <ref
                            target="https://doi.org/10.17898/ADP_SJM88_V1"
                            >https://doi.org/10.17898/ADP_SJM88_V1</ref>, accessed on 1 March
                        2022.</note></p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>The “Eighth Session” and the Beginning of the Collapse of the “Eighth
                    Republic”</head>
                <p>The thesis of the disunity of the Yugoslav media space is almost ubiquitous in
                    the contemporaneous literature and even more so in the media themselves. On the
                    issue of reporting about the Eighth Session of the Central Committee of the
                    League of Communists of Serbia, Svetislav Spasojević wrote the following in the
                        <hi rend="italic">NIN</hi> magazine: “It is not necessary to develop the
                    thesis about the connection between the leaderships of the republics and
                    provinces and their press, but in this connection lies a part of the reason why
                    some of the assessments of the press in Ljubljana and Zagreb about the political
                    situation in Serbia were met with unusually harsh reactions in Belgrade…”. Then
                    Spasojević returned to the metaphor of the eight mirrors held up to the public
                    by the media of the Yugoslav republics and provinces.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn32" n="29">Svetislav Spasojević, “Kako preživeti štampu,” <hi
                            rend="italic">NIN</hi> 1927, 6 December 1987, 12.</note> Was the
                    Yugoslav media space truly as fragmented as the contemporaneous analyses and
                    some historical interpretations suggest? We will attempt to answer this question
                    by analysing the media visibility of the rise and consolidation of Milošević’s
                    domination in Serbia, with the emphasis on the famous Eighth Session of the
                    Central Committee of the League of Communists of Serbia (23 – 24 September
                    1987).</p>
                <p>The authors of the present article are particularly interested in how the
                    Yugoslav magazines (especially the Serbian <hi rend="italic">NIN</hi> and
                    Croatian <hi rend="italic">Danas</hi>) and Slovenian magazines (<hi
                        rend="italic">Teleks</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Mladina</hi>) reacted to
                    Milošević’s consolidation of power in Serbia. The <hi rend="italic">NIN </hi>and
                        <hi rend="italic">Danas </hi>weeklies were both aimed at the Yugoslav
                    public, even though they were also influenced by the political and media
                    circumstances in Serbia or Yugoslavia. Meanwhile, the Slovenian socio-political
                    magazines counted on the Slovenian audience: they were Slovenian in terms of
                    language as well as content, although they were also a part of the broader
                    Yugoslav media space. In the middle of the 1980s, the Yugoslav media space was
                    undergoing a process of democratisation, and the editorships were breaking free
                    from the confines of the political forums, especially in the larger centres
                    (Belgrade, Zagreb, Ljubljana).</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>The Rise of Milošević in Serbia and the Media</head>
                <p>From the very outset, the rise and the establishment of the authoritarian
                    Milošević’s regime were linked to the media landscape in what was then the
                    Socialist Republic of Serbia. According to Miodrag Marović, a researcher of the
                    history of the <hi rend="italic">Politika</hi> newspaper, in the 1980s, <hi
                        rend="italic">Politika</hi> was not only a victim of political manipulations
                    like in the previous decades but also became a public means of retaliating
                    against the editorial offices that refused to accept the new “single-mindedness”
                    in its nationalist manifestation. After Tito’s death, several personalities
                    appeared at the top of the Serbian political forums until Slobodan Milošević
                    assumed control with a Party putsch in October 1987. The rise of the ambitious
                    economist and banker was the result of factional struggles between the two most
                    powerful leaders of the Serbian League of Communists: Dragoljub (Draža)
                    Mihajlović, one of the leaders of the 1972/73 showdown with the Serbian Party
                    liberalism, and Petar Stambolić. In 1984, the Serbian leaders sought a
                    replacement for Dušan Čkrebić, as he moved from the position of the leader of
                    the Serbian League of Communists to the post of the President of the Presidency
                    of the Socialist Republic of Serbia. Petar Stambolić ensured that his cousin
                    Ivan Stambolić, who had previously headed the Belgrade City Committee of the
                    League of Communists, was appointed to the vacant position. Ivan Stambolić’s
                    previous position was filled by Slobodan Milošević. As the leader of the
                    Belgrade Communists, Milošević – in cooperation with his wife Mira Marković, who
                    headed the University Committee of the League of Communists – created a scandal
                    over Marxism as a compulsory subject at the University, which was opposed by
                    prominent Party intellectuals. Already as the head of the Belgrade League of
                    Communists, Milošević started to take issue with the youth press ( <hi
                        rend="italic">Student</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Mladost</hi>, <hi
                        rend="italic">NON</hi>), which opposed his and Mira Marković’s plan to make
                    Marxism a compulsory subject at the faculty. Although this episode revealed that
                    Milošević had broader ambitions, in 1986, Ivan Stambolić, who then took over as
                    the President of the Presidency of the Socialist Republic of Serbia,
                    nevertheless nominated him his successor as the leader of the Serbian
                    Communists. Before the Congress of the League of Communists of Serbia in 1986,
                    Draža Marković – the uncle of Milošević’s wife Mira Marković – publicly opposed
                    Milošević’s selection for the highest Party position in Serbia but was not
                    successful. In May 1986, at the Congress of the League of Communists of Serbia,
                    Milošević was elected as the President of the Central Committee of the League of
                    Communists of Serbia. After his election, Milošević immediately tried to take
                    control of the central Serbian newspaper company <hi rend="italic"
                    >Politika</hi>, and he appointed his confidant Živorad Minović (the former <hi
                        rend="italic">Politika</hi> correspondent from Požarevac) as the president
                    of the Commission for Information of the Central Committee of the League of
                    Communists of Serbia and as the deputy director of <hi rend="italic"
                        >Politika</hi>. When Stambolić’s candidate was chosen as the director of <hi
                        rend="italic">Politika</hi>, Živorad Minović took over this newspaper’s
                        editorship.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn33" n="30">Miodrag Marović, <hi
                            rend="italic">Политика i Politika</hi> (Beograd: Helsinški odbor za
                        ljudska prava u Srbiji, 2002), 215–33. Nebojša Vladisavljević, <hi
                            rend="italic">Antibirokratska revolucija</hi> (Beograd: Arhipelag,
                        2020), 86–106.</note>
               </p>
                <p>In January 1987, <hi rend="italic">Politika</hi> and the Serbian media landscape
                    were shaken by a scandal made possible precisely by this newspaper’s new editor.
                        <hi rend="italic">Politika</hi> published a defamatory article titled “<hi
                        rend="italic">Vojko i Savle</hi>” (Vojko and Savle), in which an unknown
                    writer slandered, beyond any decency, two prominent Serbian academicians: the
                    medical doctor Gojko Nikoliš and the physicist Pavle Savić. The publication of
                    this satire, which was below any level of journalistic standards, caused a
                    cultural and political scandal of Yugoslav proportions. A group of <hi
                        rend="italic">Politika</hi> journalists organised a petition condemning the
                    publication of the article and demanded that the editor be held accountable. The
                    petition was signed by 67 journalists from <hi rend="italic">Politika</hi> and
                    47 of their colleagues from the other publications of the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Politika</hi> newspaper company, which represented a minority of this
                    company’s journalists. The petition demanded that the true author be revealed,
                    but the editor refused. According to Sonja Biserko, the goal of the defamatory
                    article was to intimidate the increasingly vocal and prominent critics of the
                    system, and allegedly, it was also related to the media disclosure of the
                    planned Memorandum of the Serbian Academy of Science and Arts, published by the
                    newspaper <hi rend="italic">Večernje novosti</hi> in September 1986. Meanwhile,
                    Milošević kept actively suppressing the journalists’ attempts at emancipation,
                    meddling in the personnel policy of the Serbian media, and installing his
                    supporters in various positions. By visiting Kosovo polje at the end of April
                    1987, Milošević supported the Kosovo Serbs spectacularly.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn34" n="31">Kosta Nikolić, <hi rend="italic">Niko ne sme da vas
                            bije, Slobodan Milošević u Kosovu Polju 24 – 25 April 1987</hi>
                        (Beograd: ISI, 2006).</note> According to the historian Vladimir Petrović,
                    the visit marked the beginning of a new media strategy. The presentation of the
                    visit on RTV Belgrade enthroned Milošević as the national leader. His statement
                    “ <hi rend="italic">Niko ne sme da vas bije</hi>” (no one is allowed to beat
                    you) became a television attraction in Serbia: it was broadcast endlessly on the
                    Belgrade television, allegedly by the RTV Belgrade Deputy Director Dušan
                    Mitrević, Milošević’s personal friend.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn35" n="32"
                        >Vladimir Petrović, “Uloga medija u učvršćenju vlasti Slobodana Miloševića,”
                            <hi rend="italic">Istorija 20. veka</hi>, 2 (2013), 183–204.</note>
               </p>
                <p>Meanwhile, Milošević’s former mentor Ivan Stambolić was unhappy with the
                    development in the direction of Serbian nationalism: he believed that the
                    radicalisation of the Kosovo question was undermining the Serbian efforts to
                    change the relations between the republic and the autonomous provinces and
                    opening the door for nationalist hysteria. While Stambolić avoided a
                    confrontation with Milošević, the Serbian media kept underlining the conflict
                    between “Ivica and Slobo”. Milošević was supported by <hi rend="italic"
                        >Politika</hi> with Žika Minović at the helm and by the Serbian television.
                    In this tense atmosphere, on 4 September 1987, an incident took place at the
                    military barracks in Paračin, where an Albanian soldier killed four soldiers and
                    wounded several others. The Belgrade press, led by <hi rend="italic"
                        >Politika</hi>, commented on the tragedy in an anti-Albanian manner. In his
                    memoirs, Ivan Stambolić wrote that after the incident, <hi rend="italic"
                        >Politika</hi> started to incite Serbia “as if on command”. The head of the
                    Belgrade City Committee Dragiša Pavlović, a social scientist and university
                    professor, attempted to calm the nationalist hysteria in agreement with
                    Stambolić. At a meeting with newspaper editors on 11 September 1987, Pavlović
                    underlined the dangers of Serbian nationalism regarding Kosovo. Pavlović’s
                    associate Radmilo Kljajić illustrated the described phenomena of Serbian
                    nationalism with examples from the newspapers <hi rend="italic">Politika</hi>,
                        <hi rend="italic">Politika Ekspres</hi>, and <hi rend="italic"
                    >Intervju</hi>. In the following days, <hi rend="italic">Politika ekspres</hi>
                    and <hi rend="italic">Politika</hi> launched a media onslaught against Dragiša
                    Pavlović. As the president of the League of Communists of Serbia, Milošević took
                    advantage of the comments in <hi rend="italic">Politika Express</hi> as a reason
                    to convene a meeting of the Central Committee of the League of Communists of
                    Serbia, where Pavlović’s statements would be discussed. The famous Eighth
                    Session of the Central Committee of the League of Communists of Serbia (23 – 24
                    September 1987), broadcast live on Belgrade television, represented a complete
                    defeat for Dragiša Pavlović and Ivan Stambolić. In his action against them,
                    Milošević used mainly the loyal and previously unestablished cadres from the
                    province. Dragiša Pavlović was dismissed from the leadership of the League of
                    Communists, and at the beginning of 1988, he was even expelled from it.
                    Meanwhile, Stambolić, who held the post of the President of the Presidency of
                    the Socialist Republic of Serbia, was increasingly attacked by the mainstream
                    Serbian media under the influence of Milošević until he resigned under public
                    pressure at the end of 1987. Simultaneously, the purge in the managements and
                    editorships of media companies continued. Party commissions demanded
                    “accountability” at all levels. Apart from the function of the editor of <hi
                        rend="italic">Politika</hi>, Živorad Minović also assumed the post of its
                    director. The <hi rend="italic">NIN</hi> weekly was the publication that managed
                    to resist Milošević’s purges the longest. At the beginning of 1988, Milošević
                    replaced its editor-in-chief, but the journalists rebelled and refused to write
                    in accordance with the new guidelines. The ultimate destruction of the
                    journalistic independence of <hi rend="italic">NIN</hi> took place in June 1988,
                    when the local municipal committee of the League of Communists organised a
                    commission of inquiry, which interrogated the <hi rend="italic">NIN</hi> editors
                    and journalists and imposed harsh Party punishments on them.</p>
                <p>Vladimir Petrović noted, however, that it had not been the media that had brought
                    Slobodan Milošević to power: he had gradually ascended up the Party ladder,
                    assisted by Ivan Stambolić. Nevertheless, on this ambitious path, Milošević
                    recognised the importance of controlling the mass media, which was decisive for
                    his domination over his former mentor. Once at the helm of the Serbian
                    Communists, he attempted to maintain and justify his monopoly with a new
                    political mission: the solution to the Serbian national question. The media
                    sphere became a key tool in consolidating Milošević’s power and developing it
                    into a regime.</p>
                <div>
                    <head><hi rend="italic">Danas</hi></head>
                    <p>The <hi rend="italic">Danas</hi> weekly was founded in 1982 as a project of
                        the newspaper company <hi rend="italic">Vjesnik</hi>. It was planned as
                        Zagreb’s rival to the Belgrade weekly <hi rend="italic">NIN</hi>.<note
                            place="foot" xml:id="ftn36" n="33">
                            Alemka Lisinski, “Novinarstvo i mediji:
                            izazovi osvojenih sloboda,” in: <hi rend="italic">Jugoslavija: Poglavlje
                                1980–1991</hi>, ed. Sonja Biserko (Beograd: Helsinški odbor za
                            ljudska prava u Srbiji, 2022), 528.</note> The magazine <hi
                            rend="italic">Vjesnik u srijedu</hi> (<hi rend="italic">VUS</hi>),
                        launched in 1952, is deemed as its predecessor. In the early 1970s, <hi
                            rend="italic">VUS</hi> was going through a crisis, as several
                        journalists were removed for supporting the “Croatian Spring”. After the
                        purges during this period, the magazine never recovered, despite the
                        attempts at modernisation, and it ceased to exist in 1977.<note place="foot"
                            xml:id="ftn37" n="34">“Vjesnik u srijedu,” <hi rend="italic">Hrvatska
                                enciklopedija, mrežno izdanje</hi> (Zagreb: Leksikografski zavod
                            Miroslav Krleža, 2021), <ref
                                target="http://www.enciklopedija.hr/Natuknica.aspx?ID=64990"
                                >http://www.enciklopedija.hr/Natuknica.aspx?ID=64990</ref>, accessed
                            on 6 March 2022.</note> Already during the first year of its
                        publication, <hi rend="italic">Danas</hi> gained significant influence
                        thanks to its analytical and critical writing, reaching a circulation of
                        120,000 copies. However, due to the political pressure, its first
                        editor-in-chief Joža Vlahović was forced to resign in May 1983, which led to
                        the weekly changing its concept and losing its readership (the circulation
                        dropped to 30,000 copies). After 1986, when Mirko Galić (1986–88) and Dražen
                        Vukov-Colić (1988–90) were the editors-in-chief, it grew into a very
                        influential weekly with a circulation of between 100 and 180 thousand
                        copies. In the second half of the 1980s, the weekly critically addressed the
                        most crucial social issues, encouraged liberal and democratic solutions to
                        the Yugoslav crisis, and cautioned against the rise of Slobodan
                            Milošević.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn38" n="35">“Danas,” <hi
                                rend="italic">Hrvatska enciklopedija, mrežno izdanje</hi> (Zagreb:
                            Leksikografski zavod Miroslav Krleža, 2021), <ref
                                target="http://www.enciklopedija.hr/Natuknica.aspx?ID=69427"
                                >http://www.enciklopedija.hr/Natuknica.aspx?ID=69427</ref>, accessed
                            on 7 March 2022.</note> Marinko Čulić, a journalist of the <hi
                            rend="italic">Danas</hi> weekly during this period, told the <hi
                            rend="italic">Lupiga</hi> website in 2017 that <hi rend="italic"
                            >Danas</hi> had been a Yugoslav magazine sold all over the former
                        country. More than a fifth of the magazine’s copies were sold outside of the
                        Socialist Republic of Croatia. The focus of the magazine was to cover the
                        relevant events throughout Yugoslavia. <hi rend="italic">Danas</hi> reacted
                        harshly to Milošević’s rise, with the journalist Jelena Lovrić being
                        particularly critical of him. According to Čulić, Milošević allegedly threw
                        an issue of <hi rend="italic">Danas</hi> to the floor in a moment of anger
                        and literally stomped on it. The former <hi rend="italic">Danas</hi>
                        reporter Jasna Babić especially highlighted the atmosphere of political
                        freedom and the <hi rend="italic">Danas</hi> editorship’s tolerance of
                        original and provocative topics.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn39" n="36"
                            >Jerko Bakotin, “FELJTON-HRVATSKA ŠTAMPA 80-IH I DANAS: Zlatno doba
                            novinarstva i njegova propast,” <hi rend="italic">Lupiga.Com</hi>, <ref
                                target="https://lupiga.com/vijesti/feljton-hrvatska-stampa-80-ih-i-danas-zlatno-doba-novinarstva-i-njegova-propast"
                                >https://lupiga.com/vijesti/feljton-hrvatska-stampa-80-ih-i-danas-zlatno-doba-novinarstva-i-njegova-propast</ref>,
                            accessed on 6 March 2022.</note></p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head><hi rend="italic">Mladina</hi></head>
                    <p>According to the American historian Patrick Hyder Patterson, it is somewhat
                        surprising that in the 1980s, the official newsletter of the youth
                        organisation in the Socialist Republic of Slovenia transformed into an
                        alternative political newspaper. In the complex system of the late socialist
                        self-management, the Socialist Youth League of Slovenia (ZSMS) was one of
                        the socio-political organisations that operated relatively independently.
                        Although media liberalisation was a phenomenon characteristic of the entire
                        Yugoslavia at the time, the trend was most obvious in Slovenia. The
                        communist authorities in Slovenia tolerated the critical youth press, and
                        only in specific cases would it resort to various means of interfering with
                        the editorial policy.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn40" n="37">Patrick Hyder
                            Patterson, “The East is Read: the End of Communism, Slovenian
                            Exceptionalism and the Independent Journalism of Mladina,” <hi
                                rend="italic">East European Politics and Societies</hi> 14 (2000),
                            411.</note> The actual freedom to write and publish was not limitless:
                        certain topics were still considered taboo. For decades, <hi rend="italic"
                            >Mladina</hi> served as the internal magazine of the ZSMS, informing its
                        members about the past and future activities and providing them with
                        ideological guidance. It was disseminated through the extensive network of
                        the ZSMS organisation. Despite its broad reach and institutional funding,
                            <hi rend="italic">Mladina</hi> had few readers. It was allegedly so
                        boring that even some of the municipal committees of the ZSMS refused to pay
                        the compulsory subscription. The poor handling of the economic crisis after
                        Tito’s death on the part of the authorities resulted in political
                        instability. New trends in popular culture emerged (punk), and new social
                        movements were born, including the pacifist, antimilitarist,
                        environmentalist, feminist, and gay/lesbian movements. At its 12 <hi
                            rend="superscript">th</hi> Congress in 1982, the ZSMS substantially
                        changed its fundamental principles. It dedicated itself to a broad range of
                        topics that concerned the youth, but above all, it adopted a stance that
                        legitimised the criticism of the system. Moreover, it – even if shyly at the
                        beginning – defined itself as the protector of the new social movements that
                        were institutionalised into the system of socialist self-management through
                        the ZSMS. All of this was reflected in the editorial changes of the <hi
                            rend="italic">Mladina</hi> magazine. In addition to a critical attitude
                        towards the social reality, the magazine also started exploring
                        light-hearted or entertaining topics – including graphic depictions of
                        sexuality. As early as in the first half of the 1980s, <hi rend="italic"
                            >Mladina</hi> exposed the influence of the League of Communists and
                        other political forums on the media editorships. The editorship of <hi
                            rend="italic">Mladina</hi> redefined the boundaries of media freedom,
                        using innovative strategies to attract readers. By transforming itself into
                        an alternative medium, the weekly helped educate a critical readership that
                        was becoming increasingly sensitive for critical issues and taboos. The
                        provocative style of writing became a trademark of <hi rend="italic"
                            >Mladina</hi>, which increasingly functioned as a free platform where
                        all social critics could present their views and ideas.<note place="foot"
                            xml:id="ftn41" n="38">Blaž Vurnik, <hi rend="italic">Med Marxom in
                                punkom</hi> (Ljubljana: Modrijan, 2005), 345‒49. Bernard Nežmah, <hi
                                rend="italic">Časopisna zgodovina novinarstva na slovenskem med
                                letoma 1797 in 1989</hi> (Ljubljana: Koda, 2012), 313‒36.</note></p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head><hi rend="italic">Teleks</hi></head>
                    <p>The <hi rend="italic">Teleks</hi> magazine was founded as a modern political
                        weekly based on the tradition of two editions of the <hi rend="italic">ČGP
                            Delo</hi> newspaper company, <hi rend="italic">Tovariš</hi> as a family
                        weekly and <hi rend="italic">Tedenska tribuna</hi>, which were merged into
                        the joint <hi rend="italic">ITD</hi> edition between 1974 and 1977. The
                        altered media consumption that followed the rise of television called for a
                        new concept for the magazine, which was envisioned by Ante Mahkota. Due to
                        the death of the director of the <hi rend="italic">ČGP Delo</hi> newspaper
                        company Mitja Gorjup and the change in management positions, Jure Apih,
                        primarily a marketing expert, became the magazine’s first editor. The
                        editorship’s report shows a design that was much more commercially oriented:
                        “In <hi rend="italic">Teleks – </hi>the <hi rend="italic">Delo</hi>
                        company’s informative weekly – the consistency with the contents of the <hi
                            rend="italic">Delo</hi> daily newspaper is reflected especially in the
                        influences of the everyday Slovenian, Yugoslav, economic, domestic,
                        cultural, and foreign politics on the published materials. The journalistic
                        approach is adapted to the fact that as a weekly, the publication cannot
                        normally be the first to publish the relevant information. However, it can
                        produce more complete, synthesised, commented, precise, and selective
                        information. <hi rend="italic">Teleks</hi> should thus mainly cover the
                        events whose importance, exceptionality, and appeal would otherwise not be
                        sufficiently prominent in the flood of other daily information or which
                        would lose the attention of the readers too quickly. An equally important
                        area of interest for <hi rend="italic">Teleks</hi> is the discovery of those
                        facts and images that are present among us, but at the same time hidden,
                        concealed, and invisible, and which only journalistic research can reveal
                        and draw attention to. The magazine’s aim is therefore not only the
                        transmission but also the creation of information. Last but not least, <hi
                            rend="italic">Teleks</hi> should provide its readers with a package of
                        relaxed, interesting, and entertaining reading. Thus, we have outlined the
                        structure of the newspaper in our basic content document. It was clear to us
                        (and the Co-Council also assessed this issue) that <hi rend="italic"
                            >Teleks</hi> is a publication that cannot be aimed at the broadest
                        readership, which is already covered quite successfully by other newspapers
                            (<hi rend="italic">ND</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Jana</hi>, <hi
                            rend="italic">Stop</hi>, <hi rend="italic">7D</hi>, etc.), but rather at
                        those who are also interested in more demanding information.”<note
                            place="foot" xml:id="ftn42" n="39">“Poročilo uredništva Teleks, december
                            1979,” <hi rend="italic">apih.si</hi>, <ref
                                target="http://www.apih.si/1329-2/"
                            >http://www.apih.si/1329-2/</ref>, accessed on 1 March 2022.</note> The
                        magazine boasted an impressive circulation for the time,<note place="foot"
                            xml:id="ftn43" n="40">70,000 copies in its first year of publication,
                            which is about half the circulation of the similar Croatian weekly <hi
                                rend="italic">Danas</hi> when it started coming out in 1982. ‒
                            “Naklada revije Teleks,” <hi rend="italic">apih.si</hi>, <ref
                                target="http://www.apih.si/naklada-revije-teleks/"
                                >http://www.apih.si/naklada-revije-teleks/</ref>, accessed on 1
                            March 2022, and Tagirov, “Ne pucaj na novinara: Joža Vlahović,”
                            12.</note> but it started to decline sharply in the 1980s – partly due
                        to a change in the editorial policy as a result of the critical assessment
                        on the part of the Slovenian regime.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn44" n="41"
                            >The magazine was discussed by the Commission for Agitation and
                            Propaganda of the Presidency of the Central Committee of the League of
                            Communists of Slovenia.</note> In 1980, in the time leading up to the
                        democratisation process, the different outlooks on the political reality –
                        which were, however, not the result of political dissent but rather of the
                        desire to increase visibility and sales – were the reason for the dismissal
                        of the editorship.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn45" n="42">Nežmah, <hi
                                rend="italic">Časopisna zgodovina novinarstva</hi>, 300.</note>
                        Despite the high profile of the weekly, the decline in its circulation
                        continued throughout the 1980s. <hi rend="italic">Teleks’s</hi> role as a
                        release valve was assumed by the <hi rend="italic">Mladina</hi> magazine as
                        a “political project”, and in 1990, <hi rend="italic">Teleks</hi> stopped
                        coming out for business reasons.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head><hi rend="italic">NIN</hi></head>
                    <p>In Yugoslavia, the Serbian political weekly <hi rend="italic">NIN</hi> (<hi
                            rend="italic">Nedeljne informativne novine</hi>) had both a long
                            tradition<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn46" n="43">A weekly with the same
                            name, published by the circle of the then illegal Communist Party of
                            Yugoslavia, existed for a short time in 1935. ‒ Nikola Šegota,
                            “Zagrebačke čestitke,” <hi rend="italic">NIN</hi> 1775, 6 January 1985,
                            52.</note> and a high circulation, half of which – according to Najdan
                        Pašić, a former journalist and later a prominent politician and social
                        theorist – ended up in the other republics. It started coming out in 1951
                        and became a part of the central publishing house <hi rend="italic"
                            >Politika</hi> in 1958. At the paper’s peak in 1981, its circulation
                        amounted to 180,000 copies.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn47" n="44">“<hi
                                rend="italic">НИН — Википедија,”</hi>
                            <ref target="https://sr.wikipedia.org/sr/%D0%9D%D0%98%D0%9D"
                                >https://sr.wikipedia.org/sr/%D0%9D%D0%98%D0%9D</ref>, accessed on 2
                            March 2022.</note> After a staff purge in the 1970s, resulting from a
                        showdown with the liberal Serbian political leadership, it was taken over by
                        a new generation of journalists in the late 1970s, who elevated it to a high
                        and professional standard. In the spirit of democratisation, they were often
                        a thorn in the side of the power structures.<note place="foot"
                            xml:id="ftn48" n="45">Milan Milošević, “Ministar i NIN,” <hi
                                rend="italic">NIN</hi> 1914, 6 September 1987, 5.</note> During the
                        changes in the leadership of <hi rend="italic">NIN’s</hi> parent company <hi
                            rend="italic">Politika</hi>, which became a tool for the promotion of
                        the new Serbian leadership and for discrediting the Party’s opposition, the
                        weekly remained independent and professional long after the Eighth Session
                        of the Central Committee of the League of Communists of Serbia.<note
                            place="foot" xml:id="ftn49" n="46">At the time of controversies and
                            staff struggles for the leadership of the <hi rend="italic"
                                >Politika</hi> newspaper company, it kept reporting objectively and
                            did not adopt the discourse that had become dominant in the Serbian
                            media landscape, from daily newspapers to television. ‒ Slobodanka Ast,
                            “Smenjivanje direktora Politike,” <hi rend="italic">NIN</hi> 1920, 18
                            October 1987, 16–19.</note> However, it faced severe pressures following
                        the Serbian leadership’s interference with the media landscape and was
                        accused of both nationalism and excessive criticism of nationalism at a time
                        of unfathomable changes in the course of the Serbian politics, as Mirko
                        Đekić, <hi rend="italic">NIN’s</hi> editor at the time, complained in an
                            editorial.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn50" n="47">Mirko Đekić,
                            “Značajne reči,” <hi rend="italic">NIN</hi> 1921, 1 November 1987, 9,
                            10.</note> He was dismissed a week after the editorial, and a loyal
                        replacement from the parent company, Predrag Vuković, was appointed as
                        acting editor.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn51" n="48">“Mirko Đekić razrešen
                            dužnosti glavnog i odgovornog urednika Nin-a in Predrag Vuković imenovan
                            za v. d. glavnog i odgovornog urednika Nin-a,” <hi rend="italic"
                                >NIN</hi> 1923, 8 November 1987, 8.</note> By installing a new,
                        proven editorial board, the political leadership helped him pave the way for
                        a change in <hi rend="italic">NIN’s </hi>editorial policy.<note place="foot"
                            xml:id="ftn52" n="49">“Izdavački svet Nin-a,” <hi rend="italic">NIN</hi>
                            1925, 22 November 1987, 13.</note> However, the disciplining of the
                        staff did not go according to the plan: despite the change at the top, the
                        policy of the weekly was very slow to change and also required staff
                            purges.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn53" n="50">“Violinista na krovu,”
                                <hi rend="italic">NIN</hi> 1930, 27 December 1987, 27.</note> Thus,
                        the consolidation of the new course and the identification with the new
                        political orientation continued well into 1988 and is symbolically marked by
                        the first interview with the Serbian leader Slobodan Milošević, conducted
                        almost sycophantically by the new editorship under the leadership of Đoko
                        Stojičić and published on 3 July 1988.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn54"
                            n="51">Đoko Stojičić, Teodor Anđelić, Dragan Jovanović and Tomislav
                            Peternek, “47 pitanja Slobodanu Miloševiću: Jugoslavija i socijalizam –
                            istorijske tekovine,” <hi rend="italic">NIN</hi> 1957, 3 July 1988,
                            8–15.</note></p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>The Analysis of the Response of the Magazines <hi rend="italic"
                        >Danas</hi>, <hi rend="italic">NIN</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Mladina</hi>, and
                        <hi rend="italic">Teleks</hi> to the Eighth Session
                        of the Central Committee of the League of Communists of Serbia (23 – 24
                        September 1987)</head>
                <p>A common feature of the <hi rend="italic">Danas</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
                        >Teleks</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">Mladina</hi> magazines – regardless of
                    their different profiles – is the almost complete absence of references to the
                    politician Slobodan Milošević before the famous Eighth Session of the Central
                    Committee of the League of Communists of Serbia, although he had been the leader
                    of the Serbian League of Communists since 28 April 1986 and had faced Serbian
                    demonstrators in Kosovo on 24 April 1987. Naturally, the Serbian <hi
                        rend="italic">NIN</hi> did follow the political rise of the Serbian leader
                    and the events in Kosovo. This lack of references is partly due to the
                    journalistic discourse, especially in <hi rend="italic">Danas</hi> and <hi
                        rend="italic">Teleks</hi>, which, although critical, were closer to the
                    mainstream at the time. During that period (1986–87), <hi rend="italic"
                        >Mladina</hi> already cultivated an image of an alternative and provocative
                    medium. In the analyses of the socio-political organisations’ politics and
                    particularly of the League of Communists politics at the Yugoslav level, the
                    actors or protagonists of certain factions are rarely mentioned. The journalists
                    usually describe the clashes between different factions or ideological struggles
                    in an impersonal way. The nuances in the use of the established terms from the
                    self-management communist vocabulary are also important, e.g. bureaucracy,
                    differentiation, democratic centralism, antagonism, etc. This means that
                    commentators could criticise Slobodan Milošević’s politics without mentioning
                    the protagonist. <hi rend="italic">Mladina</hi> would more often mention
                    political actors in a negative context. For example, it mentioned Milošević in
                    an article of 20 March 1987 about the failed organisation of a symposium on new
                    forms of genocide in Belgrade. The symposium was organised by Vladimir Dedijer
                    and hosted by the Serbian Academy of Sciences and Arts. <hi rend="italic"
                        >Mladina</hi> claimed that when the President of the Central Committee of
                    the League of Communists of Serbia Milošević had read the programme of the
                    symposium, he had immediately prevented it.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn55"
                        n="52">D. T., “Politika je presodila, znanosti ne potrebujemo,” <hi
                            rend="italic">Mladina</hi>, 20 March 1987, 6.</note> When <hi
                        rend="italic">Mladina</hi> reported on the Serbian demonstrations in Kosovo
                    on 24 April in its weekly review of events titled <hi rend="italic"
                        >Zlopamtilo</hi>, it did not name Milošević. Furthermore, for the subsequent
                    media and political history, it is certainly not irrelevant that Milošević’s
                    famous motto “ <hi rend="italic">niko ne sme da vas bije</hi>” (“no one is
                    allowed to beat you”), promoted by TV Belgrade at the time, was not mentioned
                    either. The Ljubljana weekly <hi rend="italic">Teleks</hi> did not even register
                    Milošević’s visit and the events in Kosovo, while <hi rend="italic">Teleks</hi>
                    mentioned him only briefly on 14 May 1987 in a commentary on the “ideological
                    plenum” of the Central Committee of the League of Communists of Yugoslavia,
                    which took place in Belgrade after the Kosovo events. In its commentary, <hi
                        rend="italic">Teleks</hi> also referred to the articles published in <hi
                        rend="italic">NIN</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Danas</hi>, but it paid more
                    attention to the standpoints of Slovenian Party leader Milan Kučan. At the Party
                    summit, Kučan warned of the danger of “constant purges” and “differentiation” in
                    the League of Communists, which were preventing the social crisis from being
                        resolved.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn56" n="53">Igo Tratnik, “Opomin časa
                        za poglabljanje idejnih razlik,” <hi rend="italic">Teleks</hi>, 14 May 1987,
                        23.</note> Compared to the two Slovenian magazines, <hi rend="italic"
                        >Danas</hi> devoted much more attention to the events in Kosovo on 24 April
                    and to the ideological plenum of the Central Committee of the League of
                    Communists of Yugoslavia. Regarding the Kosovo events, <hi rend="italic"
                        >Danas</hi> wondered what had actually happened. It cited different sources
                    and listed various interpretations of events. <hi rend="italic">Danas</hi> did
                    not quote Milošević’s famous sentence either, but it did provide a more detailed
                    description of the events. The crowd of people that gathered apparently shouted
                    that they were being beaten by the police and demanded the resignation of Azem
                    Vlasi, the leader of the Kosovo Communists, with whom Milošević had a meeting.
                    Milošević supposedly reacted by demanding that order be maintained without the
                    police. The <hi rend="italic">Danas</hi> journalists clearly demonstrated the
                    difference between the official statement of the Priština police, which strived
                    to justify the moderate use of force, and Milošević’s statement that the police
                    had no reason to intervene. The <hi rend="italic">Danas</hi> commentators did
                    not accuse Milošević of siding with the Serbian nationalist protesters, but they
                    did write the piece in such a manner that this interpretation was also possible.
                    The article concluded by quoting the assessments of various Party officials, who
                    stressed the need to distinguish between the legitimate demands of the Serbs
                    that their problems in Kosovo be solved and their nationalist aspirations.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn57" n="54">Gojko Marinković, Miloš Antić, “Što se
                        zapravo dogodilo,” <hi rend="italic">Danas,</hi> 3 May 1987, 20.</note>
               </p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Danas</hi> paid the most attention to the marathon Eighth
                    Session of the Central Committee of the League of Communists of Serbia (23 – 24
                    September 1987). The magazine’s cover featured a picture of the deposed
                    Pavlović, the commentator Jelena Lovrić analysed the session on five pages, and
                    Pavlović’s biography was published as well. In a dedicated section, the Zagreb
                    weekly also published a transcript of Pavlović’s controversial speech, which,
                    according to the journalist, the members of the Central Committee of the League
                    of Communists of Serbia who were deciding his fate had not received before the
                        meeting.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn58" n="55">Parts of the speech were
                        also published by the then still undisciplined <hi rend="italic">NIN</hi>,
                        but not until three days after the end of the Session. At the time when the
                        issue was being prepared for print, the Session had still been ongoing, and
                        therefore only an official explanation concluding the report from the
                        previous session of the Belgrade City Committee was published in a separate
                        section. ‒ “Šta je Pavlović rekao,” <hi rend="italic">NIN</hi> 1917, 27
                        September 1987, 18–20.</note> The journalist openly asked what Pavlović had
                    done to deserve such a harsh punishment. Would sacrificing Pavlović and his
                    comrades be enough, or was this the beginning of a process that some called
                    differentiation and others ruthless reckoning? The question remained unanswered,
                    although the journalist quoted one of the participants in the debate, who
                    remarked that they had been hunting a rabbit but caught a wolf. The metaphor
                    suggested the links between Pavlović and the President of the Presidency of the
                    Socialist Republic of Serbia Ivan Stambolić, who had written a letter of support
                    for Pavlović after a meeting with newspaper editors on 11 September. According
                    to the commentator, the most plausible theory was that it was all a clash
                    between two leading figures in the Serbian leadership: Ivan Stambolić and
                    Slobodan Milošević. The insiders argued that no major differences existed
                    between these two politicians in terms of what they wanted, but rather merely in
                    how to achieve it. Nevertheless, they were associated with two different
                    orientations in the Serbian League of Communists as well as with two different
                    concepts. These two lines exhibited different attitudes towards Kosovo and the
                    Serbian nationalism as well as towards democracy and the methods of the Party
                    work. One line was convinced that the counter-revolution was to be found in all
                    Yugoslav nationalisms, including Serbian, and that using the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Politika</hi> newspaper to encourage emotional reactions in the Serbian
                    public could be dangerous.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn59" n="56">The same
                        argumentation can be found in <hi rend="italic">NIN</hi>, where Milan
                        Milošević already emphasised this in the heading of the report from the
                        Belgrade City Committee meeting. ‒ Milan Milošević, “Trenutak istine,” <hi
                            rend="italic">NIN</hi> 1917, 27 September 1987, 18–23.</note> Moreover,
                    this faction was also convinced that in the case of Pavlović, the principles of
                    intra-Party democracy had been violated. The other line did not declare its
                    opinions so clearly. Although it adopted the position that all nationalisms were
                    bad in principle, it primarily emphasised the fight against the Albanian
                    nationalism. This faction was openly prone to emotional reactions and spoke out
                    publicly against “cool heads” in politics.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn60"
                        n="57">Jelena Lovrić, “Anatomija slučaja Pavlović,” <hi rend="italic"
                            >Danas</hi>, 29 September 1987, 9.</note>
               </p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Danas</hi> published a harsh critique of the factional
                    struggles in Serbia as a biography of Dragiša Pavlović. The article titled <hi
                        rend="italic">Čovek drugog vremena</hi> (A Man from Another Era) was signed
                    by Ratko Rodić. This was an editorial pseudonym, as no journalists with this
                    name existed, and allegedly, the article was (according to subsequent testimony)
                    written by Aleksandar Tijanić, then a journalist at the Belgrade weekly <hi
                        rend="italic">NIN</hi>.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn61" n="58">“Aleksandar
                        Tijanić – Istinomer,” <hi rend="italic">Istinomer.rs</hi>, <ref
                            target="https://www.istinomer.rs/akter/aleksandar-tijanic/"
                            >https://www.istinomer.rs/akter/aleksandar-tijanic/</ref>, accessed on 1
                        March 2022.</note> The commentator claimed that Pavlović’s biggest problem
                    was that he repelled people with his perfection. Just like Milošević, Pavlović
                    belonged to the group called “ <hi rend="italic">mladoturci</hi>” (Young Turks),
                    which Ivan Stambolić promoted in order to carry out a generational change in the
                    Serbian leadership. Only once he had attained the position of the leader of the
                    Belgrade Communists, Pavlović supposedly realised that lately, the Party
                    positions had been divided according to the principle of “one Stambolić
                    supporter – one Milošević supporter”. Allegedly, each of these two
                    “mini-Parties” controlled its own medium. Stambolić was said to control the <hi
                        rend="italic">NIN </hi>weekly, while Milošević controlled <hi rend="italic"
                        >Politika</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Politika Express</hi>. Pavlović was
                    allegedly the victim of poor timing: he spoke out openly at the moment when the
                    distribution of the political power between several centres in Serbia collapsed
                    and a single power centre emerged. Nations are like people – they prefer to put
                    up with their own diseases rather than a doctor. The principle of “one Serbia –
                    one nation” was being joined by the principle of “one opinion – one leader”, and
                    there was a danger, the journalist argued, that dissenting views might be
                    labelled as anti-Serbian. In such a climate, any attempts at a dialogue turned
                    into an ideological dispute, making any discussion impossible.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn62" n="59">Ratko Rodić, “Čovek drugog vremena,” <hi rend="italic"
                            >Danas</hi>, 29 September 1987, 12, 13.</note> Tanja Torbarina, known
                    for her ironic and critical style of writing, also mentioned the session under
                    consideration in her column about television: “Apparently, things are becoming
                    democratic: the ten-hour debate of the Belgrade Central Committee is being
                    broadcast on TV. Dragiša Pavlović is the subject of a dispute. He was also
                    condemned because he showed no remorse or self-criticism regarding his opinion,
                    which he had arrived at through reflection and observation.”<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn63" n="60">Tanja Torbarina, “Katastrofičari,” <hi rend="italic"
                            >Danas</hi>, 29 September 1987, 34.</note></p>
                <p>In the Slovenian press, <hi rend="italic">Mladina</hi> was the magazine that
                    devoted the most attention to the Eighth Session. On 2 October 1987, it
                    published an editorial on the developments in the Serbian politics, written by
                    the editor of the internal politics section David Tasić. The journalist in
                    question was the most “Yugoslav” member of <hi rend="italic">Mladina’s</hi>
                    editorship at the time. In 1981, he had moved to Ljubljana from Serbia to study,
                    and apart from <hi rend="italic">Mladina</hi>, he also wrote for various
                    Yugoslav newspapers and was well acquainted with both the Yugoslav and Serbian
                    media landscape. In his editorial, Tasić clearly defined the developments in the
                    Serbian leadership. He mentioned Dragiša Pavlović’s warnings about the rise of
                    the Serbian nationalism in <hi rend="italic">Politika</hi>, which marked the
                    beginning of a ruthless political struggle. Also this time, Slobodan Milošević,
                    who had already proved to be a fan of repression in his confrontations with
                    political opponents, resorted to any means at his disposal. He bypassed all of
                    the Party’s statutory rules and got Pavlović dismissed on the pretext of
                    undermining the unity. In Tasić’s view, the unity platform was clearly a
                    platform for open Serbian nationalism. He was clear in his opinion that if this
                    prevailed, it would mean that Serbia would return to the romantic nationalism of
                    the 19 <hi rend="superscript">th</hi> century while Yugoslavia would enter the
                    most serious political crisis of the post-war period.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn64" n="61">David Tasić, “Nacionalistična platforma,” <hi
                            rend="italic">Mladina</hi>, 2 October 1987, 1.</note> In the same issue,
                        <hi rend="italic">Mladina</hi> published an article by the Belgrade-based
                    independent journalist Milovan Brkić on the clashes in the Serbian Party
                    regarding the media and Pavlović, which had apparently been written before the
                    Eighth Session. Brkić informed <hi rend="italic">Mladina’s</hi> readership about
                    the importance of the media landscape for the factional disputes in the Serbian
                    Party. He described Pavlović as a reasonable politician and Milošević as a
                    hardliner who gathered people without authority around him and put relatives and
                    friends in prominent positions. He was particularly critical of Milošević’s wife
                    Mira Marković, whom he renamed Elena (alluding to Elena Ceaușescu, the wife of
                    the Romanian dictator). Brkić claimed that Slobodan Milošević, until recently an
                    anonymous economist, wanted to assert himself at all costs, while Ivan Stambolić
                    kept avoiding controversy with Milošević.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn65"
                        n="62">Milovan Brkić, “Komunisti proti komunistom,” <hi rend="italic"
                            >Mladina</hi>, 2 October 1987, 32, 33.</note></p>
                <p>In the following issue of <hi rend="italic">Mladina</hi>, a comprehensive report
                    on the purges in the Serbian Party was published. The article was signed by a
                    certain Nešo Dragošević – most probably a pseudonym, as the author of this
                    article has not been able to find a journalist by that name anywhere else.
                    “Pavlović was ousted in a typical rigged political process aimed at discrediting
                    him by any means necessary”, the journalist was clear. “Now that the
                    authoritarian spirit backed by a firm hand has prevailed, the question rightly
                    arises as to who in Serbia will now even dare, without fearing for their own
                    head, to speak out about Serbian nationalism or to criticise the undemocratic
                    methods of the senior leadership.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn66" n="63">Nešo
                        Dragošević, “Montiran proces, Kako je odstopil Dragiša Pavlović,” <hi
                            rend="italic">Mladina</hi>, 9 October 1987, 8, 9.</note> Miha Kovač
                    commented on the Belgrade purges in the <hi rend="italic">Čejeni in Šošoni</hi>
                    section. In his commentary, Kovač repeatedly referred to the Zagreb-based <hi
                        rend="italic">Danas</hi>, where he had acquired the most crucial
                    information. Kovač described the reprisal against Pavlović as disgusting: almost
                    all the speakers only accused Pavlović of thinking independently, while they (if
                    the claims made by <hi rend="italic">Danas</hi> were true) had not even read the
                    speech he was accused of making. The fight against one’s own nationalism in the
                    home environment was no longer a fundamental moral virtue of the Yugoslav
                    communists, the commentator established. The old ideology was collapsing and a
                    new one was emerging, with Serbian revanchism aimed at the abolition of Kosovo
                    as an autonomous province. The amendments to the Constitution of the Socialist
                    Federal Republic of Yugoslavia, discussed in all of the Yugoslav political
                    forums, went in the direction of restricting the republics and provinces. The
                    Yugoslav unitarism met the fundamental demand of the Serbian nationalism: the
                    abolition of Kosovo as an autonomous province. It appeared that the Serbian
                    nationalism would be articulated as the Yugoslav unitarism. Kovač did not stop
                    at the Serbian nationalism: instead, he also commented on the “democratic”
                    nationalism of the Slovenian intellectual opposition from the circle of the <hi
                        rend="italic">Nova revija</hi> magazine. During the same period, the
                    Slovenian literary historian and philosopher Taras Kermavner was publishing his
                    texts titled <hi rend="italic">Pisma srbskemu prijatelju</hi> (Letters to a
                    Serbian Friend) in the Slovenian and Serbian press, which attracted considerable
                    media attention.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn67" n="64">Balázs Trencsenyi,
                        Michal Kopeček, Luka Lisjak Gabrijelčič, Maria Falina and Mónika Baár, <hi
                            rend="italic">A History of Modern Political Thought in East Central
                            Europe: Volume II</hi> (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 2018),
                        114.</note> In Kermavner’s opinion, the cornerstone of democratisation was
                    that society recognised itself as divided. Allegedly, the Slovenian society
                    succeeded in doing this, especially by publicly discussing the killings
                    committed by the communists after World War II. According to Kermavner, this
                    discussion undermined the ruling ideology, which allowed for democratisation.
                    According to Kovač, Kermavner formulated an ideology in which universal and
                    anational democratic elements appeared as a part of the national ideology. For
                    several years, democratic freedoms had been promoted by <hi rend="italic"
                        >Mladina</hi> as the newsletter of the ZSMS, which had adopted democracy as
                    its political programme – and all this without any national, Slovenian
                    connotations. Kovač was clear: what the Yugoslav unitarism and Slovenian
                    “democratic nationalism” had in common was that they both functioned as national
                    ideologies. This meant that within Yugoslavia, political definitions were
                    transforming into the characteristic features of the Yugoslav nations
                    (Slovenians were democratic and Serbs unitarist). In Kovač’s opinion, the
                    solution lay in radical democratic reforms throughout Yugoslavia, ensuring that
                    the national identification became merely one in a series of possible democratic
                        identifications.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn68" n="65">Miha Kovač, “Požig
                        Reichstaga II, Čejeni in Šošoni,” <hi rend="italic">Mladina</hi>, 9 October
                        1987, 11, 12.</note></p>
                <p>The same issue of <hi rend="italic">Mladina</hi> reported on the arrest of the
                    Serbian journalist Milovan Brkić, who had published an article on Milošević and
                    Pavlović in this magazine’s previous issue. Apparently, Milošević’s war against
                    the media reached Slovenia as early as in 1987. When the Belgrade magazine <hi
                        rend="italic">Student</hi> was being disciplined and accused of
                        anti-Titoism<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn69" n="66">Marović, <hi
                            rend="italic">Политика i politika</hi>, 228.</note> by the Serbian Party
                    leadership, the editorship of the Maribor student magazine <hi rend="italic"
                        >Katedra</hi> handed over the central part of its publication to its
                    Belgrade colleagues for editing. “The <hi rend="italic">Katedra</hi> magazine,
                    which would be sent by train from Maribor to the south of the country and also
                    sold on the streets of Belgrade, was probably the only voice of the public
                    protest against the purges initiated by the pivotal Eighth Session of the
                    Serbian League of Communists at the time,” Igor Mekina, a member of <hi
                        rend="italic">Katedra’s</hi> editorship, later recalled.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn70" n="67">Igor Mekina, “Natiskane izvode bodo uničili,” <hi
                            rend="italic">Katedra</hi>, June/July 2011, 25, 26.</note> On 30 June
                    1987, <hi rend="italic">Katedra</hi> published an article in which Brkić
                    criticised the purges in the Serbian political leadership. Brkić was accused of
                    “disturbing the public”, even though the issue of <hi rend="italic">Katedra</hi>
                    in question had not even been released. The magazine was also confiscated for
                    other critical articles. The prosecutor’s office in Maribor justified the
                    accusations against Brkić with the explanation that around a hundred copies of
                    the banned magazine had disappeared from the printing house and been illegally
                    distributed around Maribor. According to <hi rend="italic">Mladina</hi>, without
                    any announcement, the Serbian police violently arrested Milovan Brkić on 29
                    September 1987. On the same day, he was tried and sentenced to fifty days in
                    prison. <hi rend="italic">Mladina</hi> was positive that his arrest was not a
                    coincidence. The relentless critic of the political activities of the Milošević
                    – Marković couple was brutally arrested for publishing an article in <hi
                        rend="italic">Katedra</hi> on 30 June 1987 as late as at the end of
                    September, a few days after the “Eighth Session”, where Milošević had
                    consolidated his power.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn71" n="68">Adriano Kiršić,
                        “Stalinizem na pohodu,” <hi rend="italic">Mladina</hi>, 9 October 1987,
                        13.</note> The Slovenian critical public was primarily concerned with the
                    role of the Maribor law enforcement and judiciary in suppressing the freedom of
                    the press. The petition signed by the majority of the Slovenian alternative
                    movements expressed fear that the same logic could be used to imprison Slovenian
                    intellectuals on the proposal of some Serbian police station.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn72" n="69">Mariborsko pismo ob ovadbi Milovana Brkića, <hi
                            rend="italic">Mladina</hi>, 9 October 1987, 14.</note></p>
                <p>The first issue of the <hi rend="italic">Teleks</hi> weekly after the Eighth
                    Session was published on 1 October, giving the journalists ample time for their
                    first reflections on the recent developments. In the <hi rend="italic">Teleksova
                        tribuna</hi> section, the journalist Srečo Zajc commented on the purges in
                    the Serbian Party and underlined the Party’s insistence on maintaining its
                    monolithic nature. Zajc was much more cautious in his criticism than <hi
                        rend="italic">Mladina</hi> and mainly considered the role of the League of
                    Communists. The main reason why Stojanović and Pavlović came into conflict with
                    the decisions of the Central Committee of the League of Communists of Serbia was
                    the fact that they had drawn attention to the Serbian nationalism: was it
                    nationalism or a struggle between two factions, the peaceful and the monolithic?
                    The author wondered whether the same fate would befall Ivan Stambolić. The
                    method chosen by the leadership of the Serbian League of Communists consolidated
                    monolithicity. The League of Communists would lose its character of a voluntary
                    alliance of supporters as well as its historical opportunity to reunite a
                    divided Yugoslavia. In his view, this was only possible with a modern, humane,
                    and pluralist programme, through the separation from the state apparatus and
                    rehabilitation of self-management. Srečo Zajc claimed that the Kingdom of
                    Yugoslavia had been buried by the Serbian nationalism, while the new Yugoslavia
                    was born out of patriotism and the programme of the Yugoslav communists.
                    Meanwhile, a third Yugoslavia was not possible “because we will scatter like a
                    flock of geese”. The League of Communists should put a stop to the “divide and
                    conquer” policy pursued by the national and local leaders in order to cover up
                    their past sins related to the economic policy.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn73"
                        n="70">Srečo Zajc, “Monoliti,” <hi rend="italic">Teleks</hi>, 1 October
                        1987, 5.</note></p>
                <p>The <hi rend="italic">Teleks</hi> journalist Jasna Venturini strove to understand
                    the “Eighth Session” purges from the viewpoint of historical comparisons. She
                    compared the events to the showdown with the Serbian “liberalism and
                    technocratism” in 1972. In October 1972, the Central Committee of the League of
                    Communists of Serbia had held a multi-day session where – at Tito’s initiative –
                    the leaders of the Serbian communists at the time (Marko Nikezić, Latinka
                    Perović) had been dismissed.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn74" n="71">Dušan
                        Bilandžić, <hi rend="italic">Zgodovina Socialistične federativne republike
                            Jugoslavije</hi> (Ljubljana: Partizanska knjiga, 1980), 429.</note> The
                    similarities between the two sessions supposedly included the problems being
                    solved in a series of long meetings and through newspaper companies, as well as
                    “heads rolling at the end”. In both cases, the management of the newspaper <hi
                        rend="italic">Politika</hi> had been involved in the disputes. Although the
                    journalist was clear that a major purge had taken place in the Serbian communist
                    leadership and that such activities would likely continue, she was cautious in
                    her conclusions. She pointed out that the “Eighth Session” had been
                    characterised by honest observations during the discussions, and honesty could
                    help make the League of Communists healthier.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn75"
                        n="72">Jasna Venturini, “Ena izključitev in množica neznank,” <hi
                            rend="italic">Teleks</hi>, 1 October 1987, 9–11.</note> In addition to
                    the article, <hi rend="italic">Teleks</hi> published individual statements by
                    the participants of the discussion and the chronology of Dragiša Pavlović’s
                    expulsion. In the same issue, readers could read a report from a roundtable in
                    Celje, organised by <hi rend="italic">Teleks</hi> in cooperation with the ZSMS.
                    The topic of the roundtable was the freedom of information, and the invited
                    participants included “direct actors of the freedom of public information”:
                    journalists, sociologists, politicians, prosecutors, judges, and lawyers. <hi
                        rend="italic">Teleks</hi> summed up the journalists and editors who had
                    defended the freedom of expression in particular.</p>
                <p>On 22 October 1987, <hi rend="italic">Teleks</hi> published a more critical
                    commentary on the situation in Serbia. Janko Lorenci described the death of the
                    dialogue and the new monolithicity in the largest of the Yugoslav republics.
                    What was the reason for the rapid rise of Milošević’s faction? Lorenci claimed
                    that the essence lay in a combination of several factors: a mix of
                    socio-political demagogy and populism, the indulgence of nationalism and
                    anti-Albanian sentiments, the control of most press, and Yugoslavia’s
                    indifference towards Kosovo and the crisis in Serbia. The journalist argued that
                    a “quick and decisive” solution to the Kosovo issue was not possible, and if
                    Milošević’s hardliners were not aware of this, then they were out of touch with
                    reality. Lorenci agreed with the <hi rend="italic">Danas</hi> commentator Jelena
                    Lovrić, who was worried about the silence of the federal authorities. If Serbia
                    was drifting towards the authoritarian option, then this was very bad for Serbia
                    as well as for Yugoslavia. Yugoslavia could only be strong with a strong Serbia,
                    but only a democratic Serbia could be strong, the author concluded.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn76" n="73">Janko Lorenci, “Umiranje dialoga v
                        Srbiji,” <hi rend="italic">Teleks</hi>, 22 October 1987, 12, 13.</note></p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Teleks</hi> would often write about Serbia, but usually about
                    things that concerned the Slovenian reality as well – for example about the
                    relations between the Serbian and Slovenian leadership or the relations between
                    the Slovenian and Serbian cultural workers – while it paid less attention to
                    Serbia as a topic in itself (Kosovo was the only exception). It seems that after
                    the “Eighth Session”, the editorship of what was then the central Slovenian
                    weekly focused on detailed research of the political and media situation in
                    Serbia. In November 1987, <hi rend="italic">Teleks</hi> published an extensive
                    three-part analysis of “the methods, goals, and consequences of the showdowns in
                    Serbian journalism” by the journalist Jasna Venturini. At the beginning of this
                    series of articles, the author established that many journalists in Serbia had
                    been dismissed in the autumn. According to her, it was clear that the main sin
                    of the media that were under attack was the lack of support for the decisions
                    reached at the Eighth Session of the Central Committee of the League of
                    Communists of Serbia. When she looked for someone to discuss this topic with in
                    the Belgrade newspaper companies, the journalist detected a great deal of
                    mistrust. No one at <hi rend="italic">Politika</hi> wanted to talk. The
                    situation was different at the <hi rend="italic">NIN</hi> magazine, where they
                    pointed to the political pressures from the Serbian communist leadership.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn77" n="74">Jasna Venturini, “Na konici oblasti I,”
                            <hi rend="italic">Teleks</hi>, 5 November 1987, 13.</note> A week later,
                    Jasna Venturini noted that the events of the “great purge” in the Serbian
                    journalism outpaced <hi rend="italic">Teleks’s</hi> writing. Before the second
                    part of her article was even published, Mirko Djekić, the editor-in-chief of the
                        <hi rend="italic">NIN</hi> weekly, had been dismissed. Sava Kržavac, the
                    president of the Information Section of the Serbian SZDL, tried to convince the
                    journalist that the recent developments in Serbian journalism were nothing
                    unusual. He assured her that there was no cause for concern among journalists,
                    nor was it true that a list of unwanted journalists existed. The journalist
                    received a completely different testimony from the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Politika</hi> journalist Radmilo Kljajić, who had been dismissed as the
                    secretary of the City Committee of the League of Communists of Belgrade at the
                    “Eighth Session” as well as expelled from the League of Communists. Kljajić was
                    appalled at the accusations at the “Eighth Session” and by the draconian
                    punishment imposed by the Party leadership. He found no rational reason for this
                    but suspected it was the revenge of the Milošević – Marković family. As it was,
                    Kljajić had recently published a contribution on the revolutionary movement in
                    Belgrade, in which he had mentioned Mira Marković’s mother in a negative
                        context.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn78" n="75">
                        <anchor xml:id="Hlk98949802"/>Jasna Venturini, “Na konici oblasti II,” <hi
                            rend="italic">Teleks</hi>, 12 November 1987, 6–8.</note> In the last
                    part of her article on the Serbian media affairs, Jasna Venturini described the
                    purges at the TV Belgrade news programme. In the run-up to the “Eighth Session”,
                    the editor of <hi rend="italic">TV Dnevnik</hi>, the daily news programme,
                    allowed a comment by the <hi rend="italic">Danas</hi> journalist Jelena Lovrić,
                    who characterised the leadership of the Serbian League of Communists as dogmatic
                    and Stalinist. The editor was punished with a pay cut, while the news programme
                    editor was dismissed, even though the journalists’ collective was against this.
                    Meanwhile, the editor of the <hi rend="italic">Svet</hi> magazine Jelisaveta
                    Jevremović was also under attack for reprinting Radmilo Kljajić’s defence from
                    the federal youth magazine <hi rend="italic">Mladost</hi>. Just like <hi
                        rend="italic">Borba</hi>, the main newspaper of the Yugoslav communists, the
                        <hi rend="italic">Mladost</hi> magazine was beyond the reach of the Serbian
                    authorities. Therefore, it could still afford to be critical of Milošević’s
                    “line”. Jasna Venturini concluded that the “cleaners” of the Serbian
                    journalistic scene had no problems when the founder of the media was the Serbian
                    SZDL, but things got complicated in the case of other founders. “However, with a
                    bit of goodwill, even such minor difficulties can be overcome,” the author
                    concluded cynically.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn79" n="76">Jasna Venturini,
                        “Na konici oblasti III,” <hi rend="italic">Teleks</hi>, 26 November 1987,
                        12, 13.</note>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Epilogue</head>
                <p>How does the brief analysis of the writing of <hi rend="italic">Danas</hi>, <hi
                        rend="italic">NIN</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Teleks</hi>, and <hi rend="italic"
                        >Mladina</hi> about this pivotal event reveal the character of the Yugoslav
                    media space during the crisis of the Yugoslav political system? The “Eighth
                    Session” has a special place in the historiography of the dissolution of
                    Yugoslavia. Researchers rightly refer to it as one of the milestones on the path
                    towards the establishment of the authoritarian Milošević’s regime in Serbia and
                    as one of the turning points in the process of the dissolution of Yugoslavia.
                    For example, the German historian Holm Sundhaussen defined the “Eighth Session”
                    as Milošević’s “putsch”.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn80" n="77">Holm
                        Sundhaussen, <hi rend="italic">Jugoslawien und seine Nachfolgestaaten</hi>
                        (Dunaj: Böhlau Verlag, 2012), 251.</note> From the viewpoint of the
                    political history focusing on the public, however, it is legitimate to ask
                    whether the media commentators of the time perceived the decisive character of
                    the “Eighth Session”. All commentators of the analysed media defined the “Eighth
                    Session” as special and groundbreaking, and in the above-mentioned magazines,
                    all of them evaluated the session as a possibility that the Serbian politics
                    might develop in a dangerous direction, even though no one predicted the
                    disintegration of Yugoslavia at that time.</p>
                <p>The common feature of the magazines under consideration was the profound
                    scepticism towards the nationalistic phenomena in Yugoslavia. We can argue that
                    all three magazines were critical of the “Eighth Session” in the sense of
                    rejecting Slobodan Milošević’s policies, his authoritarianism, and the newfound
                    Serbian nationalism, while <hi rend="italic">NIN</hi> was outwardly less
                    critical of the new policy and sometimes described it with different emphases,
                    but in terms of the balance of forces and this magazine’s position in the
                    Serbian media space, it can nevertheless be seen – until the purges of its
                    editorship – as a voice of the opposition. In terms of terminology, all the
                    magazines were critical of the term “differentiation”, which they interpreted as
                    a euphemism for Party purges, authoritarianism, and suppression of intra-Party
                    democracy. However, the critical attitude was expressed in different ways. All
                    the magazines celebrated the freedom of speech and democracy in the broadest
                    sense. <hi rend="italic">Danas</hi> was the most careful in its texts: criticism
                    was concealed in selected quotations and rhetorical questions but still clearly
                    evident to the educated reader. This Zagreb-based weekly evaluated the events by
                    paying much attention to the “Eighth Session”, especially with the image of
                    Dragiša Pavlović on its front page. <hi rend="italic">Teleks</hi> initially
                    reacted in a principled and cautious manner but later became much more critical.
                    The writing of <hi rend="italic">Mladina</hi> was the most honest and without
                    any convoluted comparisons and rhetorical questions: it tried to be
                    straightforward and used the most critical discourse.</p>
                <p>We cannot fully accept the thesis that the Slovenian media space was relatively
                    closed due to the specificity of the Slovenian language. The Yugoslav public was
                    not merely an extension of the Slovenian media space but rather also an
                    important part of the narrower Slovenian public. This supports the thesis of the
                    complex, even liminal nature of the Yugoslav public, which was thus both the sum
                    of the publics of the individual republics and provinces as well as the single,
                    all-Yugoslav public. The coverage of the “Eighth Session” beautifully
                    illustrates this interplay of levels and the unusual richness of the
                    journalistic (and general communication) networks. The Zagreb-based <hi
                        rend="italic">Danas</hi> collaborated with the Serbian journalists who would
                    publish critical texts regarding the Serbian leadership under pseudonyms
                    (Aleksandar Tijanić). The member of <hi rend="italic">Mladina’s</hi> editorship
                    David Tasić came from Serbia, was a respected youth journalist at the Yugoslav
                    level, and understood the political situation in Serbia very well. <hi
                        rend="italic">Mladina</hi> also collaborated with the critical freelance
                    journalist Milovan Brkić. He, together with other Belgrade journalists,
                    regularly published his articles in the Maribor-based <hi rend="italic"
                        >Katedra</hi>, which at one time became an alternative newsletter of the
                    Belgrade students. The collaboration between <hi rend="italic">Katedra</hi> and
                    the journalists of the <hi rend="italic">Student</hi> magazine indicates that
                    critical journalists were able to use the differences between the media regimes
                    in the different republics to their advantage. The editorship of <hi
                        rend="italic">Teleks</hi> made up for its poor initial knowledge of the
                    Serbian media scene with investigative journalism in Belgrade.</p>
                <p>The Croatian music critic and journalist Ante Perković titled his book on the
                    Yugoslav pop-rock music scene <hi rend="italic">Sedma republika</hi> (The
                    Seventh Republic). In it, he mainly analysed the part of the Yugoslav rock that
                    defined itself nationally and politically and supported exclusive nationalist
                    projects with its activities. However, he also described the fate of the part of
                    popular music that “remained faithful to the supranational and pacifist idea of
                    rock and roll in spite of everything”.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn81" n="78"
                        >Samo Rugelj, ”Sedma republika: Pop kultura in razpad Jugoslavije –
                        recenzija,” <hi rend="italic">Bukla.si</hi>, <ref
                            target="https://www.bukla.si/knjigarna/umetnost/glasba/sedma-republika.html"
                            >https://www.bukla.si/knjigarna/umetnost/glasba/sedma-republika.html</ref>,
                        accessed on 8 March 2021.</note> He called this long-term phenomenon the
                    Seventh Yugoslav Republic.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn82" n="79">Ante
                        Perković, <hi rend="italic">Sedma Republika</hi> (Ljubljana: Zenit,
                        2018).</note> A similar framework could be applied to the Yugoslav public as
                    well. A Yugoslav-wide network of critical but non-nationalist journalists
                    existed who supported the democratisation of the society (mostly in the context
                    of the existing system), pointed out economic failures (e.g. the Agrokomerc
                    affair) and the dangers of both unitarism and particular nationalisms. Could
                    this network be defined as the “Eighth Republic”? The media network branched in
                    all directions, not only between the same categories of the Yugoslav media. The
                    media saw Yugoslavia as their own country, recognising its complexity and
                    calling for tolerance and dialogue. Women journalists played an important role
                    in the all-Yugoslav journalistic network, especially at the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Danas </hi>weekly, to a lesser extent at <hi rend="italic">Teleks</hi>, and
                    even less at <hi rend="italic">Mladina</hi>. There were significant differences
                    between them, also conditioned by the environments of the particular republics,
                    but we can nevertheless identify a common field of values that held this
                    pan-Yugoslav media grouping together.</p>
                <p>The Party purges after the “Eighth Session” were closely linked to the purges in
                    the ranks of the press. With the emergence of media populism associated with
                    authoritarian nationalism, these purges had a devastating effect not only on the
                    Yugoslav Party and the political structure but also on the Yugoslav media
                    network. The transnational Yugoslav Republic of Journalists started to crumble.
                    Media cooperation was overshadowed by the media wars. If, in his work on
                    Yugo-rock, Ante Perković suggested that the “Seventh Republic” survived
                    Yugoslavia, then we can conclude that the “Eighth Republic” of Yugoslav
                    journalism was not so fortunate.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="bibliography">
                <head>Sources and Literature</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Articles and literature</head>
                    <bibl>Archer, Rory. “Assessing Turbofolk Controversies: Popular Music between
                        the Nation and the Balkans.” <hi rend="italic">Southeastern Europe</hi> 36,
                        No. 2 (2012): 178–207.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Ast, Slobodanka. “Smenjivanje direktora Politike.” <hi rend="italic"
                            >NIN</hi> 1920, 18 October 1987, 16–19.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Bijelić, Krste. “Slovenija i Jugoslavija: zašto (1): Sindrom ‘paralelnog
                        toka’.” <hi rend="italic">Duga</hi> 359, 28 November –11 December 1987,
                        67–72.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Bilandžić, Dušan. <hi rend="italic">Zgodovina Socialistične federativne
                            republike Jugoslavije</hi>. Ljubljana: Partizanska knjiga, 1980.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Brkić, Milovan. “Komunisti proti komunistom.” <hi rend="italic"
                            >Mladina</hi>, 2 October 1987, 32, 33.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Dragošević, Nešo. “Montiran proces, Kako je odstopil Dragiša Pavlović.”
                            <hi rend="italic">Mladina</hi>, 9 October 1987, 8, 9.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Đekić, Mirko. “Značajne reči.” <hi rend="italic">NIN</hi> 1921, 1 November
                        1987, 9, 10.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Gorjup, Mitja. “Da bi se bolje razumeli.” <hi rend="italic">Delo</hi>,
                        204, 4 September 1974, 7.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Gorjup, Mitja. “Preveč vase zaprta kultura (Iz razprave na sestanku
                        osnovne organizacije ZKS ‘Delo’ – časopisi, 16. januarja 1974).” In: Mitja
                        Gorjup, <hi rend="italic">Samoupravno novinarstvo</hi>, 95–96. Ljubljana:
                        Delavska enotnost, 1978.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Grizelj, Jug. “Jedinstvo nije u rukama novinara.” <hi rend="italic"
                            >NIN</hi> 1832, 2 February 1986, 19–21.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Kiršić, Adriano. “Stalinizem na pohodu.” <hi rend="italic">Mladina</hi>, 9
                        October 1987, 13.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Kovač, Miha. “Požig Reichstaga II, Čejeni in Šošoni.” <hi rend="italic"
                            >Mladina</hi>, 9 October 1987, 11, 12.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Lisinski, Alemka. “Novinarstvo i mediji: izazovi osvojenih sloboda.” In:
                            <hi rend="italic">Jugoslavija: Poglavlje 1980–1991</hi>. Ed. Sonja
                        Biserko, 525–52. Beograd: Helsinški odbor za ljudska prava u Srbiji,
                        2022.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Lorenci, Janko. “Umiranje dialoga v Srbiji.” <hi rend="italic"
                        >Teleks</hi>, 22 October 1987, 12, 13.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Lovrić, Jelena. “Anatomija slučaja Pavlović.” <hi rend="italic"
                        >Danas</hi>, 29 September 1987, 9.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Marinković, Gojko in Miloš Antić. “Što se zapravo dogodilo.” <hi
                            rend="italic">Danas</hi>, 3 May 1987, 20.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Marović, Miodrag. <hi rend="italic">Политика i Politika.</hi> Beograd:
                        Helsinški odbor za ljudska prava u Srbiji, 2002.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Mekina, Igor. “Natiskane izvode bodo uničili.” <hi rend="italic"
                            >Katedra</hi>, June/July 2011, 25, 26.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Merljak Zdovc, Sonja. “Slovenska revija Tovariš in njeni revialni
                        ‘tovariši’ v drugi polovici dvajsetega stoletja.” In: <hi rend="italic"
                            >Prispevki k zgodovini slovenskih medijev</hi>. Ed. Maruša Pušnik,
                        525–40. Ljubljana: Fakulteta za družbene vede, 2008.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Milošević, Milan. “Ministar i NIN.” <hi rend="italic">NIN</hi> 1914, 6
                        September 1987, 5.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Milošević, Milan. “Trenutak istine.” <hi rend="italic">NIN</hi> 1917, 27
                        September 1987, 18–23.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Nežmah, Bernard. <hi rend="italic">Časopisna zgodovina novinarstva na
                            slovenskem med letoma 1797 in 1989.</hi> Ljubljana: Koda, 2012.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Nikolić, Kosta. <hi rend="italic">Niko ne sme da vas bije, Slobodan
                            Milošević u Kosovu Polju 24–25. april 1987</hi>. Beograd: ISI,
                        2006.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Patterson, Patrick Hyder. “The East is Read: the End of Communism,
                        Slovenian Exceptionalism and the Independent Journalism of Mladina.” <hi
                            rend="italic">East European Politics and Societies</hi> 14, No. 2
                        (2000): 411–59.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Perković, Ante. <hi rend="italic">Sedma Republika</hi>. Ljubljana: Zenit,
                        2018.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Petrović, Vladimir. “Uloga medija u učvršćenju vlasti Slobodana
                        Miloševića.” <hi rend="italic">Istorija 20. veka</hi>, No. 2 (2013):
                        183–204.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Pleše, Mladen. “Pravi pogum je povezan z znanjem.” In: Mitja Gorjup, <hi
                            rend="italic">Samoupravno novinarstvo</hi>, 139–46. Ljubljana: Delavska
                        enotnost, 1978.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Rabrenović, Šćepan. “Čije su devize: predsednik Skupštine SR Slovenije
                        Miran Potrč govori za NIN.” <hi rend="italic">NIN</hi> 1864, 21 September
                        1986, 13–16.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Rabrenović, Šćepan. “Slovenija na jugu.” <hi rend="italic">NIN</hi> 1843,
                        27 April 1986, 9, 10.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Repe, Božo. “<hi rend="italic">Slovenci v osemdesetih letih.</hi>”
                        Ljubljana: Zveza zgodovinskih društev Slovenije, 2001.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Repe, Božo. “Zakaj so Slovenci vstopili v Jugoslavijo in zakaj so iz nje
                        odšli?.” In: <hi rend="italic">Jugoslavija v času: devetdeset let od
                            nastanka prve jugoslovanske države</hi>. Ed. Bojan Balkovec, 21–46.
                        Ljubljana: Znanstvena založba Filozofske fakultete, 2009.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Rodić, Ratko. “Čovek drugog vremena.” <hi rend="italic">Danas</hi>, 29
                        September 1987, 12, 13.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Spasojević, Svetislav. “Kako preživeti štampu.” <hi rend="italic">NIN</hi>
                        1927, 6 December 1987, 12–14.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Spasović, Grujica. “Produžite vašom ulicom: sednica izdavačkog saveta
                        Duge.” <hi rend="italic">Duga</hi> 331, 1 – 14 November 1986, 38–40.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Spehnjak, Katarina. “Narodni front Jugoslavije (SSRNJ – razvoj,
                        programsko-teorijske osnove i procesi u društvenoj praksi 1945–1983).” <hi
                            rend="italic">Povijesni prilozi</hi> 3, No. 3 (1984): 9–82.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Stojičić, Đoko, Teodor Anđelić, Dragan Jovanović and Tomislav Peternek.
                        “47 pitanja Slobodanu Miloševiću: Jugoslavija i socijalizam – istorijske
                        tekovine.” <hi rend="italic">NIN</hi> 1957, 3 July 1988, 8–15.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Sundhaussen, Holm. <hi rend="italic">Jugoslawien und seine
                            Nachfolgestaaten.</hi> Vienna: Böhlau Verlag, 2012.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Šegota, Nikola. “Zagrebačke čestitke.” <hi rend="italic">NIN</hi> 1775, 6
                        January 1985, 52.</bibl>
                    <bibl>T., D. “Politika je presodila, znanosti ne potrebujemo.” <hi rend="italic"
                            >Mladina</hi>, 20 March 1987, 6.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Tadić, Ljubomir. “<hi rend="italic">Javno mnenje u savremenom društvu,
                            javno mnenje o Prednacrtu novog Ustava.</hi>” Beograd: Institut
                        društvenih nauka, 1964.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Tagirov, Tatjana. “Ne pucaj na novinara: Joža Vlahović, borac sa prave
                        strane barikade.” <hi rend="italic">Duga</hi>, 332, 15 – 28 November 1986,
                        10–14.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Tasić, David. “Nacionalistična platforma.” <hi rend="italic">Mladina</hi>,
                        2 October 1987, 1.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Torbarina, Tanja. “Katastrofičari.” <hi rend="italic">Danas</hi>, 29
                        September 1987, 34.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Torov, Ivan. “Sunovrat srpskog novinarstva (delovi iz knjige).” In: <hi
                            rend="italic">“Antibirokratska revolucija”: (1987–1989)</hi>. Ed. Bojana
                        Lekić, Zoran Pavić, Slaviša Lekić and Imre Sabo, 269–72. Beograd: Statusteam
                        in Službeni glasnik, 2009.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Tratnik, Igo. “Opomin časa za poglabljanje idejnih razlik.” <hi
                            rend="italic">Teleks</hi>, 14 May 1987, 23.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Trencsenyi, Balázs, Michal Kopeček, Luka Lisjak Gabrijelčič, Maria Falina
                        and Mónika Baár. “<hi rend="italic">A History of Modern Political Thought in
                            East Central Europe: Volume II</hi>”. Oxford: Oxford University Press,
                        2018.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Venturini, Jasna. “Ena izključitev in množica neznank.” <hi rend="italic"
                            >Teleks</hi>, 1 October 1987, 9–11.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Venturini, Jasna. “Na konici oblasti I.” <hi rend="italic">Teleks</hi>, 5
                        November 1987, 13.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Venturini, Jasna. “Na konici oblasti II.” <hi rend="italic">Teleks</hi>,
                        12 November 1987, 6–8.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Venturini, Jasna. “Na konici oblasti III.” <hi rend="italic">Teleks</hi>,
                        26 November 1987, 12, 13.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Vladisavljević, Nebojša. “<hi rend="italic">Antibirokratska
                            revolucija.</hi>” Beograd: Arhipelag, 2020.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Vurnik, Blaž. “<hi rend="italic">Med Marxom in punkom</hi>.” Ljubljana:
                        Modrijan, 2005.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Zajc, Marko. “Poletni aferi kritičnih misli: Tomaž Mastnak in Dimitrij
                        Rupel, slovenska kritična intelektualca med jugoslovansko in slovensko
                        javnostjo v letu 1986.” <hi rend="italic">Studia Historica Slovenica</hi>
                        20, No. 3 (2020): 921–55.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Zajc, Srečo. “Monoliti.” <hi rend="italic">Teleks</hi>, 1 October 1987,
                        5.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Newspapers</head>
                    <bibl><hi rend="italic">Danas</hi>, 1987.</bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="italic">Delo</hi>, 1974.</bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="italic">Duga</hi>, 1986, 1987.</bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="italic">Mladina</hi>, 1987.</bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="italic">Nin</hi>, 1985–1988.</bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="italic">Teleks</hi>, 1987.</bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="italic">Katedra</hi>, 2011.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Online sources</head>
                    <bibl>“Aleksandar Tijanić – Istinomer.” <hi rend="italic">Istinomer.rs.</hi>
                        Available at: <ref
                            target="https://www.istinomer.rs/akter/aleksandar-tijanic/"
                            >https://www.istinomer.rs/akter/aleksandar-tijanic/</ref>. Accessed on 1
                        March 2022.</bibl>
                    <bibl>“Danas.” <hi rend="italic">Hrvatska enciklopedija, mrežno izdanje</hi>.
                        Leksikografski zavod Miroslav Krleža, 2021. Available at: <ref
                            target="http://www.enciklopedija.hr/Natuknica.aspx?ID=69427"
                            >http://www.enciklopedija.hr/Natuknica.aspx?ID=69427</ref>. Accessed on
                        7 March 2022.</bibl>
                    <bibl>“<hi rend="italic">Naklada revije Teleks.</hi>” <hi rend="italic"
                            >apih.si</hi>. Available at: <ref
                            target="http://www.apih.si/naklada-revije-teleks/"
                            >http://www.apih.si/naklada-revije-teleks/</ref>. Accessed on 1 March
                        2022.</bibl>
                    <bibl>“Nekatere ocene vsebinske naravnanosti in ekonomskega položaja revije
                        Teleks v letu 1983.” <hi rend="italic">apih.si</hi>. Available at: <ref
                            target="http://www.apih.si/nekatere-ocene-vsebinske-neravnanosti-ekonomskega-polozaja-revije-teleks-v-letu-1983/"
                            >http://www.apih.si/nekatere-ocene-vsebinske-neravnanosti-ekonomskega-polozaja-revije-teleks-v-letu-1983/</ref>.
                        Accessed on 1 March 2022.</bibl>
                    <bibl>“Poročilo uredništva Teleks, december 1979.” <hi rend="italic"
                            >apih.si</hi>. Available at: <ref target="http://www.apih.si/1329-2/"
                            >http://www.apih.si/1329-2/</ref>. Accessed on 1 March 2022.</bibl>
                    <bibl>“Vjesnik u srijedu.” <hi rend="italic">Hrvatska enciklopedija, mrežno
                            izdanje</hi>. Leksikografski zavod Miroslav Krleža, 2021. Available at:
                            <ref target="http://www.enciklopedija.hr/Natuknica.aspx?ID=64990"
                            >http://www.enciklopedija.hr/Natuknica.aspx?ID=64990</ref>. Accessed on
                        6 March 2022.</bibl>
                    <bibl>“<hi rend="italic">НИН — Википедија.</hi>” Available at: <ref
                            target="https://sr.wikipedia.org/sr/%D0%9D%D0%98%D0%9D"
                            >https://sr.wikipedia.org/sr/%D0%9D%D0%98%D0%9D</ref>. Accessed on 2
                        March 2022.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Bakotin, Jerko. “FELJTON-HRVATSKA ŠTAMPA 80-IH I DANAS: Zlatno doba
                        novinarstva i njegova propast.” <hi rend="italic">Lupiga.Com</hi>. Available
                        at: <ref
                            target="https://lupiga.com/vijesti/feljton-hrvatska-stampa-80-ih-i-danas-zlatno-doba-novinarstva-i-njegova-propast"
                            >https://lupiga.com/vijesti/feljton-hrvatska-stampa-80-ih-i-danas-zlatno-doba-novinarstva-i-njegova-propast</ref>.
                        Accessed on 6 March 2022.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Hladnik Milharčič, Ervin. “#intervju Jure Apih, časnikar: prej so se
                        časopisi delali za partijo, mi smo ga delali za bralce.” <hi rend="italic"
                            >Dnevnik.si</hi>, 24 October 2020. Available at: <ref
                            target="https://www.dnevnik.si/1042941784"
                            >https://www.dnevnik.si/1042941784</ref>. Accessed on 1 March
                        2022.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Toš, Niko. “Slovensko javno mnenje 1988 [Podatkovna datoteka].” <hi
                            rend="italic">Arhiv družboslovnih podatkov</hi>. Ljubljana: Univerza v
                        Ljubljani, 2000. Available at: <ref
                            target="https://doi.org/10.17898/ADP_SJM88_V1"
                            >https://doi.org/10.17898/ADP_SJM88_V1</ref>. Accessed on 1 March
                        2022.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Rugelj, Samo. “Sedma republika: Pop kultura in razpad Jugoslavije –
                        recenzija.” <hi rend="italic">Bukla.si</hi>. Available at: <ref
                            target="https://www.bukla.si/knjigarna/umetnost/glasba/sedma-republika.html"
                            >https://www.bukla.si/knjigarna/umetnost/glasba/sedma-republika.html</ref>.
                        Accessed on 8 March 2021.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
            <div type="summary" xml:lang="sl">
                <docAuthor>Jurij Hadalin</docAuthor>
                <docAuthor>Marko Zajc</docAuthor>
                <head>»PRIMER TOVARIŠA DRAGIŠE PAVLOVIĆA«</head>
                <head>JUGOSLOVANSKI MEDIJSKI PROSTOR IN NJEGOVO DOJEMANJE NA PRIMERU POROČANJA
                    OSREDNJIH POLITIČNIH TEDNIKOV O OSMEM PLENUMU CENTRALNEGA KOMITEJA ZVEZE
                    KOMUNISTOV SRBIJE</head>
                <head>POVZETEK</head>
                <p>Jugoslovanska medijska krajina je že v času svojega obstoja bila ocenjena kot
                    fragmentirana, informacijski sistemi naj bi delovali predvsem v okviru republik
                    in naj bi odsevali interese republiške oziroma pokrajinske oblasti. Dolgoživa
                    teza, ki je z leti dobivala skorajda dogmatski značaj, je zato v prispevku
                    analizirana in potrjena z množico navedb sodobnikov. Pod drobnogled je nato vzet
                    tudi jugoslovanski medijski sistem in načini njegovega nadzora, predvsem pa je
                    bila v procesu analize medijev prisotna jasna segmentacija tiska, ki jasno
                    opredeli, kateri mediji so bili za razumevanje političnih procesov v Jugoslaviji
                    najpomembnejši in so imeli tudi relativno močno prisotno zavest o potrebi po
                    podrobnejši analizi in kritičnem poročanju o dogajanjih v svojem matičnem okolju
                    in izven njega. To so bili politični tedniki. Vloga političnih tednikov v
                    medijski krajini je bila pomembna, saj so se po svoji obliki poročanja bistveno
                    razlikovali od dnevnega časopisja. Njihova zlata doba je bila ravno v
                    obravnavanem obdobju, kljub padcem naklad v časih discipliniranja uredništev, ki
                    so vodila k manjši javni pozornosti. Bolj ko so jih dojemali kot »partijski
                    časopis«, manjši vpliv so imeli. A analiza tekstov, objavljenih v jugoslovanskih
                    tednikih, je to tezo, ki je bila ob načrtovanju raziskave postavljena kot ena od
                    osrednjih raziskovalnih vprašanj, postavila pod vprašaj.</p>
                <p>Drugi namen prispevka je analiza medijske vidnosti vzpona in konsolidacije
                    Miloševićeve prevlade v Srbiji s poudarkom na znameniti osmi seji CK ZK Srbije
                    (24.–26. september 1987). Avtorja predvsem zanima, kako se je na Miloševićevo
                    utrjevanje oblasti v Srbiji odzval jugoslovanski revialni tisk (predvsem srbski
                        <hi rend="italic">NIN</hi> in hrvaški <hi rend="italic">Danas</hi>) in kako
                    slovenske revije (<hi rend="italic">Teleks</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Mladina</hi>). Tednika <hi rend="italic">NIN</hi> in <hi rend="italic"
                        >Danas</hi> sta bila usmerjena v jugoslovansko javnost, čeprav sta bila tudi
                    pod vplivom političnih in medijskih razmer v Srbiji oziroma Jugoslaviji.
                    Slovenski družbenopolitični magazini so računali na slovensko občinstvo – bili
                    so slovenski tudi po vsebini, ne samo po jeziku – čeprav so bili po drugi strani
                    del širšega jugoslovanskega medijskega prostora. Sredi osemdesetih let je v
                    jugoslovanskem medijskem prostoru, še zlasti v večjih centrih (Beograd, Zagreb,
                    Ljubljana), potekal proces demokratizacije medijskega prostora, uredništva so se
                    izvijala iz oklepa političnih forumov.</p>
                <p>Teze o slovenskem medijskem prostoru, ki naj bi bil zaradi specifičnega
                    slovenskega jezika relativno zaprt, ne moremo povsem sprejeti. Jugoslovanska
                    javnost ni bila samo podaljšek slovenskega medijskega prostora, bila je tudi
                    pomemben del ožje, slovenske javnosti. To govori v prid tezi o kompleksni, celo
                    liminalni naravi jugoslovanske javnosti, ki je bila seštevek posameznih javnosti
                    republik in pokrajin pa tudi ena, vsejugoslovanska javnost. Poročanje o »osmi
                    seji« lepo kaže na ta preplet ravni in nenavadno bogastvo novinarskih (in
                    splošno komunikacijskih) mrež. Zagrebški <hi rend="italic">Danas</hi> je
                    sodeloval s srbskimi novinarji, ki so pod psevdonimom objavljali kritična
                    besedila o srbskem vodstvu (Aleksandar Tijanić). Član uredništva <hi
                        rend="italic">Mladine</hi> David Tasić je prihajal iz Srbije, bil je
                    spoštovan mladinski novinar na jugoslovanski ravni in je dobro razumel politične
                    razmere v Srbiji. <hi rend="italic">Mladina</hi> je sodelovala s kritičnim
                    samostojnim novinarjem Milovanom Brkičem. Brkić je skupaj z ostalimi
                    beograjskimi novinarji redno objavljal v mariborski <hi rend="italic"
                        >Katedri</hi>, ki je v nekem obdobju postala alternativno glasilo
                    beograjskih študentov. Sodelovanje <hi rend="italic">Katedre</hi> in novinarjev
                        <hi rend="italic">Studenta</hi> kaže na to, da so kritični novinarji znali
                    uporabljati razlike med medijskimi režimi v različnih republikah v svojo korist.
                    Uredništvo <hi rend="italic">Teleksa</hi> je začetno slabo poznavanje srbske
                    medijske scene nadoknadilo z raziskovalnim novinarskim delom v Beogradu.</p>
                <p>Hrvaški glasbeni kritik in novinar Ante Perković je svojo knjigo o jugoslovanski
                    pop-rock glasbeni sceni naslovil <hi rend="italic">Sedma republika</hi>. Čeprav
                    je v tej knjigi analiziral predvsem tisti del jugoslovanskega rocka, ki se je
                    nacionalno in politično opredelil in je s svojim delovanjem podpiral ekskluzivne
                    nacionalistične projekte, je prikazal tudi usodo tistega dela popularne glasbe,
                    »ki je vsemu navkljub ostal zvest nadnacionalni ter pacifistični ideji
                    rokenrola«. Ta fenomen dolgega trajanja je poimenoval sedma jugoslovanska
                    republika. Podoben okvir razmišljanja bi lahko uporabili tudi za jugoslovansko
                    javnost. Obstajala je vsejugoslovanska mreža kritičnih, a ne nacionalistično
                    usmerjenih novinark in novinarjev, ki so podpirali demokratizacijo družbe
                    (večinoma znotraj sistema), opozarjali na gospodarske napake (na primer afera
                    Agrokomerc) ter na nevarnost unitarizma in partikularnih nacionalizmov. Medijska
                    mreža se je spletala v vse smeri, ne samo med istimi kategorijami jugoslovanskih
                    medijev. Na Jugoslavijo so gledali kot na svojo državo, priznavali so njeno
                    kompleksnost in pozivali k strpnosti in dialogu. Med njimi so bile velike
                    razlike, pogojene tudi s posameznim republiškim okoljem, kljub temu pa lahko
                    identificiramo skupno polje vrednot, ki so to vsejugoslovansko medijsko združbo
                    držale skupaj.</p>
                <p>Partijske čistke po »osmi seji« so bile tesno povezane s čistkami v novinarskih
                    vrstah. Te pa so s pojavom medijskega populizma, navezanega na avtoritarni
                    nacionalizem, delovale uničujoče ne samo na jugoslovansko partijo in politično
                    strukturo, ampak tudi na jugoslovansko medijsko mrežo. Transnacionalna
                    jugoslovanska novinarska republika je začela razpadati. Medijsko sodelovanje so
                    zasenčile medijske vojne.</p>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
