<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Normative Role Orientations of Yugoslav Journalists: A Study of Journalism
                    Ethics Codes in the SFRY<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn1" n="*">This work was
                        financially supported by the Slovenian Research Agency, contract number
                        J5-1793.</note></title>
                <author>
                    <forename>Melita</forename>
                    <surname>Poler</surname>
                    <surname>Kovačič</surname>
                    <roleName>Professor</roleName>
                    <affiliation>Faculty of Social Sciences, University of Ljubljana</affiliation>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Kardeljeva ploščad 5</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>SI-1000 Ljubljana</addrLine>
                    </address>
                    <email>melita.poler-kovacic@fdv.uni-lj.si</email>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>2022-04-21</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>
                    <orgName xml:lang="sl">Inštitut za novejšo zgodovino</orgName>
                    <orgName xml:lang="en">Institute of Contemporary History</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Privoz 11</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>SI-1000 Ljubljana</addrLine>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>http://ojs.inz.si/pnz/article/view/3977</pubPlace>
                <date>2022</date>
                <availability status="free">
                    <licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title xml:lang="sl">Prispevki za novejšo zgodovino</title>
                <title xml:lang="en">Contributions to Contemporary History</title>
                <biblScope unit="volume">62</biblScope>
                <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
                <idno type="ISSN">2463-7807</idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source, born digital.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc xml:lang="en">
                <p>Contributions to Contemporary History is one of the central Slovenian scientific
                    historiographic journals, dedicated to publishing articles from the field of
                    contemporary history (the 19th and 20th century).</p>
                <p>The journal is published three times per year in Slovenian and in the following
                    foreign languages: English, German, Serbian, Croatian, Bosnian, Italian, Slovak
                    and Czech. The articles are all published with abstracts in English and
                    Slovenian as well as summaries in English.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <projectDesc xml:lang="sl">
                <p>Prispevki za novejšo zgodovino je ena osrednjih slovenskih znanstvenih
                    zgodovinopisnih revij, ki objavlja teme s področja novejše zgodovine (19. in 20.
                    stoletje).</p>
                <p>Revija izide trikrat letno v slovenskem jeziku in v naslednjih tujih jezikih:
                    angleščina, nemščina, srbščina, hrvaščina, bosanščina, italijanščina, slovaščina
                    in češčina. Članki izhajajo z izvlečki v angleščini in slovenščini ter povzetki
                    v angleščini.</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="sl"/>
                <language ident="en"/>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords xml:lang="en">
                    <term>journalism</term>
                    <term>ethics codes</term>
                    <term>normative roles</term>
                    <term>socialism</term>
                    <term>Yugoslavia</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords xml:lang="sl">
                    <term>novinarstvo</term>
                    <term>etični kodeksi</term>
                    <term>normativne vloge</term>
                    <term>socializem</term>
                    <term>Jugoslavija </term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change><date>2022-04-28T08:11:01Z</date>
                    <name>Mihael Ojsteršek</name>
                    <desc>Pretvorba iz DOCX v TEI, dodatno kodiranje</desc>
                </change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <docAuthor>Melita Poler Kovačič<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn2" n="**"><hi rend="bold"
                        >Professor, Faculty of Social Sciences, University of Ljubljana, Kardeljeva
                        ploščad 5, SI-1000 Ljubljana; </hi><ref
                        target="mailto:melita.poler-kovacic@fdv.uni-lj.si"><hi rend="bold"
                            >melita.poler-kovacic@fdv.uni-lj.si</hi></ref>
                </note></docAuthor>
            <docImprint>
                <idno type="cobissType">Cobiss tip: 1.01</idno>
                <idno type="DOI">doi: https://doi.org/10.51663/pnz.62.1.3</idno>
            </docImprint>
            <div type="abstract" xml:lang="sl">
                <head>IZVLEČEK</head>
                <head><hi rend="italic">NORMATIVNE USMERITVE VLOG JUGOSLOVANSKIH NOVINARJEV: ŠTUDIJA
                        NOVINARSKIH ETIČNIH KODEKSOV V SFRJ</hi></head>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Cilj te študije je raziskati normativne orientacije vlog
                        novinarjev v SFRJ, kot so zapisane v petih jugoslovanskih novinarskih
                        etičnih kodeksih ali razvidne iz njih. Z analizo dokumentov in primerjalno
                        zgodovinsko metodo smo raziskali razloge za sprejem prvega kodeksa,
                        analizirali pojmovanja svobode in odgovornosti ter odnos med njima v
                        kodeksih in ugotovili, kako kodeksi naslavljajo resnicoljubnost in
                        profesionalne norme. Normativni temelji novinarstva, kot se kažejo v etičnih
                        kodeksih, so se spreminjali skozi čas ter ob spremembah v družbenem,
                        političnem, pravnem in ekonomskem okolju. Medijska/novinarska svoboda je
                        bila dovoljena le v okviru socialistične usmeritve ter prispevka h graditvi
                        in razvoju samoupravne družbe, vsaj do leta 1988, ko so bile izpuščene
                        vrednoti marksizma in leninizma ter opredelitev novinarja kot
                        družbenopolitičnega delavca. Novinar je bil obvezan delovati po svoji
                        socialistični zavesti in je bil odgovoren do delovnih ljudi, do
                        socialistične javnosti, kodeksa v osemdesetih letih pa sta poudarjala
                        njegovo odgovornost do javnosti. Ob več značilnostih sovjetske totalitarne
                        teorije tiska imajo normativni temelji tudi določeno podobnost s teorijo
                        družbene odgovornosti. Profesionalne norme, povezane z resnicoljubnostjo,
                        profesionalno integriteto ter spoštovanjem človekove osebnosti in
                        dostojanstva, so se sčasoma razvijale ter pridobivale več prostora,
                        razdelanosti in poudarka. Dejstvo, da je novinarska skupnost nekatere
                        profesionalne norme prepoznala kot dovolj pomembne za kodifikacijo,
                        nakazuje, da so bili temelji profesionalizacije slovenskega novinarstva
                        položeni že v socialistični Jugoslaviji.</hi></p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Ključne besede: novinarstvo, etični kodeksi, normativne vloge,
                        socializem, Jugoslavija </hi></p>
            </div>
            <div type="abstract">
                <head>ABSTRACT</head>
                <p><hi rend="italic">The goal of this study was to investigate the normative role
                        orientations of journalists in the SFRY, as stated or implied in five
                        Yugoslav journalism ethics codes. Application of the method of document
                        analysis and the comparative historical method identified the reasons for
                        adopting the first code and assisted in the analysis of how the codes
                        conceptualised (the relationship between) freedom and responsibility, and
                        how they addressed truthfulness and professional norms. The normative
                        foundations of journalism outlined in these ethics codes were transforming
                        over time and in response to changes in the socio-politico-legal-economic
                        environment. Media/journalistic freedom was only permitted within the limits
                        of the socialist orientation and if contributing to the building and
                        development of the self-managed society, at least up until 1988 when the
                        Marxist and Leninist values defining a journalist as a socio-political
                        worker were removed. A journalist was obliged to follow their socialist
                        conscience and be responsible to the working people – the socialist public,
                        yet in the 1980s the codes stressed their responsibility to the public.
                        While displaying several characteristics of the Soviet-totalitarian theory
                        of the press, the normative foundations also somewhat resemble the social
                        responsibility theory. Professional norms associated with truthfulness,
                        professional integrity, and respect for human personality and dignity have
                        been evolving over time, gaining more space, elaboration and emphasis. The
                        fact that some professional norms were seen by the journalistic community as
                        sufficiently important to be codified shows that the foundations of the
                        professionalization of Slovenian journalism were laid in the socialist
                        Yugoslavia already.</hi></p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Keywords: journalism; ethics codes; normative roles; socialism;
                        Yugoslavia</hi></p>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div>
                <head>Introduction</head>
                <p>The study of journalistic roles is central to understanding journalism’s identity
                    and place in a given society. <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn3" n="1">Thomas
                        Hanitzsch, “Roles of Journalists,” in: <hi rend="italic">Journalism</hi>,
                        ed. Tim P. Vos (Berlin, Boston: De Gruyter Mouton, 2018), 43.</note> Through
                    journalistic roles, journalists “articulate journalism’s identity and position
                    vis-à-vis society and broader public expectations”<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn4" n="2">Thomas Hanitzsch et al., “Journalistic Culture in a
                        Global Context: A Conceptual Roadmap,” in: <hi rend="italic">Worlds of
                            Journalism: Journalistic Cultures Around the Globe</hi>, eds. Thomas
                        Hanitzsch et al. (New York: Columbia University Press, 2019), 37.</note> on
                    analytically distinct levels.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn5" n="3">Hanitzsch,
                        “Roles of Journalists,” 43.</note> In this study,<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn6" n="4">This research was supported by ARRS – the Slovenian
                        Research Agency (grant No. J5-1793).</note> we focus on normative
                    journalistic roles, dealing with what journalists think they ought to do.
                    Normative roles are found on the level of role orientations, namely, the level
                    of “discursive constructions of the institutional values, attitudes, and beliefs
                    with regards to the position of journalism in society”. <note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn7" n="5">Thomas Hanitzsch and Tim P. Vos, “Journalistic Roles and
                        the Struggle Over Institutional Identity: The Discursive Constitution of
                        Journalism,” <hi rend="italic">Communication Theory</hi> 27 (2017):
                        123.</note> By referring to the ways journalism should serve society,<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn8" n="6">Thomas Hanitzsch et al., “Role
                        Orientations: Journalists’ Views on Their Place in Society,” in: <hi
                            rend="italic">Worlds of Journalism: Journalistic Cultures Around the
                            Globe</hi>, eds. Thomas Hanitzsch et al. (New York: Columbia University
                        Press, 2019), 164.</note> normative journalistic roles constitute “a
                    framework of desirable practice”.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn9" n="7">Ibidem,
                        168.</note></p>
                <p>To better understand journalism in a system distinct from democracy also due to
                    the limitations it placed on civil liberties, including freedom of
                        expression,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn10" n="8">Peruško et al., <hi
                            rend="italic">Comparing Post-Socialist Media Systems</hi>, 26.</note> we
                    investigate Yugoslav journalists’ normative role orientations. General
                    descriptions of journalism in the Socialist Federal Republic of Yugoslavia
                    (SFRY) are often associated with the image of journalists as socio-political
                    workers, serving as lackeys of the political authorities, being short on
                    professional freedom by having to be primarily responsible to the Communist
                    Party. However, the impression of Yugoslav journalism as merely “an agitation
                    power of politics”, <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn11" n="9">Dragoslav Rančić,
                        “Zakaj pripravljamo nov kodeks?,” <hi rend="italic">Teorija in praksa</hi>
                        25, No. 5 (1988): 646.</note> practised in a system where a text could only
                    be published if based on the political philosophy and thought of
                        self-management,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn12" n="10">Mitja Gorjup, <hi
                            rend="italic">Samoupravno novinarstvo</hi> (Ljubljana: Delavska
                        enotnost, 1978), 89. </note> while deviant opinions were suppressed by
                    preventive censorship and repressive penal legislation,<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn13" n="11">Marjan Horvat, “Prepovedi razširjanja tiskane besede v
                        Sloveniji 1945–1990” (Bachelor Thesis, University of Ljubljana,
                        1995).</note> does not reflect the true variety of realities in different
                    media and social environments within the federal state over the period of more
                    than 40 years. Only a few authors have discussed the characteristics of <hi
                        rend="italic">socialist journalism in the SFRY</hi> in any greater depth,
                    revealing differences from the Soviet communist concept of media
                        communications<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn14" n="12">E.g., Gertrude Joch
                        Robinson, <hi rend="italic">Tito's Maverick Media: The Politics of Mass
                            Communications in Yugoslavia</hi> (Urbana, Chicago, London: University
                        of Illinois Press, 1977).</note> and highlighting the complexity of
                    journalistic roles as they change over time<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn15"
                        n="13">E.g., Zrinjka Peruško et al., <hi rend="italic">Comparing
                            Post-Socialist Media Systems: The Case of Southeast Europe</hi> (London,
                        New York: Routledge, 2021).</note> on the levels of media practices and
                    their normative foundations. </p>
                <p>Starting from the premise that ethics codes provide the normative foundations of
                    journalism by both defining and reflecting values and norms on the professional
                    and wider societal levels, our aim is to determine the reasons for adopting the
                    first journalism ethics code in the SFRY, how the codes conceptualised (the
                    relationship between) the values of freedom and responsibility, and how they
                    addressed professional norms, especially those related to truthfulness <hi
                        rend="italic">.</hi></p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>(Normative) Transformations of Journalism in the SFRY</head>
                <p>Research on journalism with respect to its normative transformations is
                    particularly useful for understanding both journalism and society in a given
                    historical period because, as an institution constituted by shared beliefs,
                    norms, rules and routines, journalism denotes a distinct area of social
                    authority and signals institutional autonomy, yet it is also “inherently social
                    and thus inextricably interconnected with other institutions”. <note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn16" n="14">Tim P. Vos, “Journalism as Institution,”
                        2019, <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1093/acrefore/9780190228613.013.825">https://doi.org/10.1093/acrefore/9780190228613.013.825</ref>.</note> The discursive articulation and enactment of journalism’s
                    identity as a social institution may be referred to as <hi rend="italic"
                        >journalistic roles,</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn17" n="15">Hanitzsch
                        and Vos, “Journalistic Roles and the Struggle Over Institutional Identity,”
                        120.</note> which are discursively constituted and “subject to discursive
                    (re)creation, (re)interpretation, appropriation, and contestation”.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn18" n="16">Olivier Standaert et al., “In Their Own
                        Words: A Normative-Empirical Approach to Journalistic Roles Around the
                        World,” <hi rend="italic">Journalism</hi> 22, No. 4 (2021): 921. </note>
                    Journalists and other actors, including those outside of journalism, compete to
                    construct, reiterate and challenge the boundaries of acceptable journalistic
                        practices.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn19" n="17">Matt Carlson,
                        “Metajournalistic Discourse and the Meanings of Journalism: Definitional
                        Control, Boundary Work, and Legitimation,” <hi rend="italic">Communication
                            Theory</hi> 26 (2016): 349.</note> The discourse of journalistic roles
                    has thus become “a central arena where the legitimacy and identity of journalism
                    is reproduced, contested, and negotiated”.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn20"
                        n="18">Standaert et al., “In Their Own Words,” 920.</note> As a result of
                    this contest, dominant positions “crystallize as institutional norms and
                        practices”.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn21" n="19">Hanitzsch Thomas and Tim
                        P. Vos, “Journalism Beyond Democracy,” <hi rend="italic">Journalism</hi> 19,
                        No. 2 (2018): 151.</note> Normative journalistic roles, which pertain to
                    professional aspirations concerning how journalists are supposed to contribute
                    to society,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn22" n="20">Standaert et al., “In Their
                        Own Words,” 919.</note> have emerged through interchanges occurring among
                    both internal and external actors. <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn23" n="21"
                        >Hanitzsch and Vos, “Journalistic Roles and the Struggle Over Institutional
                        Identity,” 121.</note> Hence, investigations into these roles provide
                    insights into journalism’s identity and place in society as well as into other
                    social institutions given that journalists “articulate normative roles with
                    social interlocutors either explicitly or implicitly in mind”.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn24" n="22">Ibid., 124.</note></p>
                <p>The normative position of news media as well as media practices in Yugoslavia
                    were changing over time, alongside changes in the political and economic fields.
                        <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn25" n="23">Peruško et al., <hi rend="italic"
                            >Comparing Post-Socialist Media Systems</hi>, 99.</note> The limits of
                    free expression were shifted in both legislation and journalism practice. The
                    Federal Press Act of 1960 brought, on top of the rights of correction and reply,
                    the right to express and publish opinions, which in 1963 became a constitutional
                    right. <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn26" n="24">Slavko Splichal and France Vreg,
                            <hi rend="italic">Množično komuniciranje in razvoj demokracije</hi>
                        (Ljubljana: Komunist, 1986), 171.</note> Yugoslavia was the only socialist
                    country to forbid any advance censorship in the 1960s, violations of the press
                    laws could only be prosecuted following the appearance of a publication, and
                    even this occurred quite rarely, according to Calic.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn27" n="25">Marie-Janine Calic, <hi rend="italic">A History of
                            Yugoslavia</hi> (West Lafayette, Indiana: Purdue University Press,
                        2019), 198.</note> For example, in the 1960s already some journalists from
                        <hi rend="italic">Tovariš</hi>, a weekly magazine from Ljubljana, used
                    novelistic techniques to reveal the injustices of the system.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn28" n="26">Sonja Merljak Zdovc, “The Use of Novelistic Techniques
                        in Slovene Journalism: The Case of Magazine Tovariš,” <hi rend="italic"
                            >Journalism Studies</hi> 8, No. 2 (2007): 253, 254.</note> The
                    relationship between the media and the state fluctuated between liberalisation
                    and control,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn29" n="27">Peruško et al., <hi
                            rend="italic">Comparing Post-Socialist Media Systems</hi>, 125.</note>
                    and even though media contents on politically sensitive issues may have been
                    limited, “it seems inapt to speak of an ideologically monolithic media”.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn30" n="28">Sergej Flere and Rudi Klanjšek, <hi
                            rend="italic">The Rise and Fall of Socialist Yugoslavia: Elite
                            Nationalism and the Collapse of a Federation</hi> (Lanham, Boulder, New
                        York, London: Lexington Books, 2019), 104.</note></p>
                <p>Transformations of journalism were not limited to the era of the major social
                    changes in the 1980s, albeit they certainly were then the most radical and
                    evident. In this period, when public debate on media freedom was intensifying
                    and negotiating the boundaries of freedom had become a prevalent practice,<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn31" n="29">Ljubica Spaskovska, <hi rend="italic">The
                            Last Yugoslav Generation: The Rethinking of Youth Politics and Cultures
                            in Late Socialism</hi> (Manchester: Manchester University Press, 2017),
                        68.</note> the media was democratising the society and also being
                    democratised by it. The role of a journalist as a socio-political worker started
                    to diminish as the media became more commercialised and the increasingly
                    critical positions of the press, especially in political weeklies, were more
                    tolerated. <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn32" n="30">Peruško et al., <hi
                            rend="italic">Comparing Post-Socialist Media Systems</hi>, 102.</note>
                    At the end of the decade, some media were openly critical of the state,<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn33" n="31">Smilja Amon, “Obdobja razvoja slovenskega
                        novinarstva,” in: <hi rend="italic">Poti slovenskega novinarstva: danes in
                            jutri</hi>, eds. Melita Poler Kovačič and Monika Kalin Golob (Ljubljana:
                        FDV, 2004), 66.</note> such as the investigative journalists at the
                    Slovenian weekly magazine <hi rend="italic">Mladina</hi> who uncovered several
                    scandals of high-level representatives of authorities, such as the building of a
                    villa for the Federal Secretary of the People’s Army of Yugoslavia. <note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn34" n="32">Matjaž Šuen, <hi rend="italic"
                            >Preiskovalno novinarstvo</hi> (Ljubljana: FDV, 1994).</note> The media
                    also played an important role in the series of conflicts that led to the
                    break-up of the SFRY, being both an indicator of and contributor to the
                        crisis.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn35" n="33">Tarik Jusić, “Media
                        Discourse and the Politics of Ethnic Conflict: The Case of Yugoslavia,” in:
                            <hi rend="italic">Media Discourse and the Yugoslav Conflicts:
                            Representations of Self and Other</hi>, ed. Pål Kolstø (London:
                        Routledge, 2009), 21.</note>
                </p>
                <p>Several types of journalists’ normative roles in the SFRY are described in the
                    literature, <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn36" n="34">See: Robinson, <hi
                            rend="italic">Tito's Maverick Media</hi>, 120. Peruško et al., <hi
                            rend="italic">Comparing Post-Socialist Media Systems</hi>, 101.</note>
                    yet despite their variety the role of a journalist as a socio-political worker
                    seemed to be the most prominent over the years, with journalism seen not as a
                    job, but “first of all a political commitment”.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn37"
                        n="35">Gorjup, <hi rend="italic">Samoupravno novinarstvo</hi>, 82.</note>
                    Still, there was also the role of a journalist as a neutral observer of events
                    as well as some other ‘Western’ journalistic roles, such as supporting the
                    public sphere, the gatekeeper role, and being responsive to the interests of the
                        audience.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn38" n="36">Peruško et al., <hi
                            rend="italic">Comparing Post-Socialist Media Systems</hi>, 101.</note>
                    Bogdan Osolnik<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn39" n="37">Robinson, <hi
                            rend="italic">Tito's Maverick Media</hi>, 119.</note> referred to the
                    media’s three vital functions in the self-management society: 1. to supply the
                    citizens and self-managed units with objective and comprehensive social
                    information from a variety of sources; 2. to act as public forums and to
                    criticise negative phenomena and trends in society; and 3. to serve as a means
                    for social education by spreading elementary knowledge for understanding the
                    socio-economic process. According to Robinson, media communications in the SFRY
                    did not follow the Leninist communication theory: Instead of identifying with
                    Leninism, which attaches the media to the party apparatus and makes the
                    journalist a mere transmission belt for the party line, Yugoslav self-managed
                    democracy defines him as a socially responsible yet independent recorder of
                    events who should provide independent and nonpartisan sources of comment and
                    criticism in contemporary Yugoslavia.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn40" n="38"
                        >Ibid., 120.</note> However, the dominant view that journalists were
                    responsible for the social situation rather than being free commentators
                    reporting on this situation was not changed until the congress of Yugoslav
                    journalists held in 1988.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn41" n="39">Bogdan
                        Osolnik, “The intention was to democratise the sphere of communication,” <hi
                            rend="italic">TripleC</hi> 15, No. 1 (2017): 248.</note>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Research Questions and the Methodology</head>
                <p>Ethics codes may be considered key documents while researching the normative role
                    orientations of journalism since they are concerned with normative ethics. Codes
                    define and clarify the values of practitioners <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn42"
                        n="40">Chris Roberts, “Identifying and Defining Values in Media Ethics
                        Codes,” <hi rend="italic">Journal of Mass Media Ethics</hi> 27 (2012):
                        116.</note> and are recognised as “invaluable as an instrument of
                        self-reflection”.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn43" n="41">Clifford
                        Christians and Kaarle Nordenstreng, “Social Responsibility Worldwide,” <hi
                            rend="italic">Journal of Mass Media Ethics</hi> 19, No. 1 (2004):
                        19.</note> Yet, the rationales underlying a decision to adopt a code can
                    vary from journalists genuinely aspiring to recognise the fundamental values and
                    principles for which they stand<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn44" n="42">Louis A.
                        Day, <hi rend="italic">Ethics in Media Communications: Cases and
                            Controversies</hi> (Belmont: Wadsworth Publishing Company, 2000),
                        45.</note> and thus “to understand the reasons behind their actions”,<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn45" n="43">Roberts, “Identifying and Defining Values
                        in Media Ethics Codes,” 116.</note> to ambitions of political authorities to
                    exercise control over the media through a journalism ethics code as “a system of
                    work discipline”.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn46" n="44">Slavko Splichal and
                        Colin Sparks, <hi rend="italic">Journalists for the 21</hi><hi
                            rend="italic superscript">st</hi><hi rend="italic">Century: Tendencies
                            of Professionalization Among First-Year Students in 22 Countries</hi>
                        (Norwood: Ablex Publishing Corporation, 1994), 49.</note> Our first research
                    question is: <hi rend="italic">What were the reasons for adopting the first
                        journalism ethics code in the SFRY?</hi></p>
                <p>Normative role orientations are “an essential element of journalism’s contract
                    with the public: Society grants journalism the authority to deliver us the
                    world; in return, journalists are expected to cater to the communicative needs
                    of their audiences”.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn47" n="45">Hanitzsch and Vos,
                        “Journalistic Roles and the Struggle over Institutional Identity,”
                        124.</note> By adopting a code, journalists undertake to provide public
                    service in exchange for some degree of press freedom.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn48" n="46">Tim P. Vos, “Journalism,” in: <hi rend="italic"
                            >Journalism</hi>, ed. Tim P. Vos (Berlin, Boston: De Gruyter Mouton,
                        2018), 4.</note> Normative conceptualisations of freedom<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn49" n="47">In our study, the term “freedom” is used mostly in the
                        sense of press/media freedom, which concerns the relationship between the
                        media and the government, and less in the sense of journalistic freedom,
                        which individualises media freedom. For more, see: John C. Merrill, <hi
                            rend="italic">The Dialectic in Journalism: Toward A Responsible Use of
                            Press Freedom</hi> (Baton Rouge, London: Louisiana State University
                        Press, 1989), 34, 35.</note> and responsibility are particularly important
                    because journalists’ adherence to autonomous professional work within a free
                    media and their commitment to responsible practice suggest their endorsement of
                    the informal “social contract” with the public whereby society provides
                    journalism with guarantees of freedom and, in return, society expects journalism
                    to act responsibly and deliver a range of public benefits.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn50" n="48">Stephen J. A. Ward, <hi rend="italic">The Invention of
                            Journalism Ethics: The Path to Objectivity and Beyond</hi> (Montreal,
                        Kingston, London, Chicago: McGill-Queen’s University Press, 2004),
                        326.</note> Our second research question is: <hi rend="italic">How did the
                        journalism ethics codes in the SFRY address, explicitly or implicitly, the
                        values of freedom and responsibility, which social and/or political values
                        underpinned the codes’ statements concerning freedom and responsibility, and
                        how was the relationship between the values of freedom and responsibility
                        conceptualised?</hi></p>
                <p>Values, as agents of journalists’ thinking, acting and choosing,<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn51" n="49">Jay Black and Chris Roberts, <hi
                            rend="italic">Doing Ethics in Media: Theories and Practical
                            Applications</hi> (New York, London: Routledge, 2011), 178.</note>
                    underlie particular journalistic norms found in ethics codes. A norm may be
                    defined as a rule or standard which involves a collective evaluation of
                    behaviour in terms of what it ought to be and a collective expectation as to
                    what behaviour will be. <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn52" n="50">Jack P. Gibbs,
                        “Norms: The Problem of Definition and Classification,” <hi rend="italic"
                            >American Journal of Sociology</hi> 70, No. 5 (1965): 589.</note>
                    Written norms are specific guidelines, principles of required or prohibited
                    conduct, grounded in journalists’ conceptualisations of values of freedom and
                    responsibility. Our third research question is: <hi rend="italic">How did the
                        journalism ethics codes in the SFRY address professional norms, especially
                        those related to truthfulness?</hi></p>
                <p>We apply the method of document analysis, that is, “a systematic procedure for
                    reviewing or evaluating documents”.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn53" n="51">
                        Glenn A. Bowen, “Document Analysis as a Qualitative Research Method,” <hi
                            rend="italic">Qualitative Research Journal</hi> 9, No. 2 (2009): 27.
                    </note> Documents bearing witness to past events give “background information as
                    well as historical insight”,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn54" n="52">Ibid.,
                        29.</note> “provide a means of tracking change and development”<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn55" n="53">Ibid., 30.</note> and thereby enable
                    change to be identified. We analyse all Yugoslav journalism ethics codes
                    (adopted in 1965, 1969, 1973, 1982, 1988) as well as a selection of documented
                    discussions within the journalistic professional community related to adopting a
                    code. These codes are relevant because, as Slavković wrote about the 1982 code,
                    they define and explain “in detail the role, function and position of
                    journalists”. <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn56" n="54">Dušan Slavković, “Novinar
                        i novinarstvo,” in: <hi rend="italic">Novinarstvo danas: Priručnik za
                            polaznike novinarske škole Jugoslovenskog instituta za novinarstvo</hi>,
                        ed. Zdravko Leković (Beograd: Jugoslovenski institut za novinarstvo, 1983),
                        100.</note> Other documented discussions like papers, reports and other
                    written sources of the Yugoslav Journalists’ Association (YJA) serve as
                    background material for inferring about the reasons for adopting the first
                    ethics code in 1965. </p>
                <p>The research process combines elements of content analysis (information organised
                    into categories related to the research questions) and thematic analysis
                    (recognition of patterns in the data). <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn57" n="55"
                        >Bowen, “Document Analysis as a Qualitative Research Method,” 32.</note> The
                    comparative historical method makes it possible to identify and compare common
                    or different characteristics and to discover essential manifestations of studied
                    phenomena at a certain stage and trace their dynamics.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn58" n="56">Aleksei Yuryevich Bykov et al., “Codes of Journalism
                        Ethics in Russia and the United States: Traditions and the Current Practice
                        of Application,” <hi rend="italic">International Review of Management and
                            Marketing</hi> 5, Special Issue (2015): 57.</note> The diachronic
                    perspective of this method permits us to determine transformations in normative
                    role orientations of Yugoslav journalism over time. </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Adopting the First Journalism Ethics Code in the SFRY</head>
                <p>Before adopting the first ethics code in 1965, the moral obligations of
                    journalists were addressed in various sources of the YJA. For example,
                    journalistic ethical norms were discussed at the Fifth Assembly (Third Congress)
                    of the YJA in 1953, when its president Dušan Blagojević<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn59" n="57">Dušan Blagojević, “Uloga novinara kao javnih i
                        političkih radnika u našem društvu,” in: <hi rend="italic">Srebrni jubilej
                            SNJ 1945–1970: Knjiga 1</hi>, ed. Miodrag Avramović (Beograd: SNJ,
                        1971), 271.</note> stressed the importance of trust: “To preserve this
                    trust, the entire set of moral norms of journalists’ behaviour while performing
                    their duty has been developed in practice. For journalism as a whole and for
                    journalists as individuals, these norms must be a code which is not to be
                    breached. Each individual violation of these norms harms journalism as a
                    profession”. At the plenary of the League of Communists of Yugoslavia (LCY) in
                    1954, a document entitled <hi rend="italic">Moral obligations of
                        journalists</hi> was adopted, with its first sentence demanding that a
                    journalist “serve the truth” and “act according to their conscience and with a
                    deep sense of responsibility”. <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn60" n="58">SNJ,
                        “Moralne obaveze novinara,” in: <hi rend="italic">Srebrni jubilej SNJ
                            1945–1970: Knjiga 1</hi>, ed. Miodrag Avramović (Beograd: SNJ, 1971),
                        314.</note> However, a journalist would only be able to fulfil their
                    obligations “if they are aware of their relationship and duties to the social
                    community, and if they are always guided by the socialist conscience which they
                    are strengthening through their constant political building”. <note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn61" n="59">Ibid.</note> A report on the activities of the YJA for
                    1953–1957 notes that “experiences showed that these moral obligations of ours
                    were only of declarative nature, and hence there is a need to make the
                    principles and sanctions which are to be used more concrete”.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn62" n="60">UO SNJ, “Izveštaj,” in: <hi rend="italic">Srebrni
                            jubilej SNJ 1945–1970: Knjiga 1</hi>, ed. Miodrag Avramović (Beograd:
                        SNJ, 1971), 369.</note></p>
                <p>The adoption of a code of ethics was initiated by the 1963 inter-congressional
                    conference of YJA.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn63" n="61">Miodrag Avramović,
                        “Izvještaj komisije za kodeks,” in: <hi rend="italic">Srebrni jubilej SNJ
                            1945–1970: Knjiga 1</hi>, ed. Miodrag Avramović (Beograd: SNJ, 1971),
                        540.</note> At the <hi rend="italic">Information and Journalism</hi>
                    symposium held in 1964, the general secretary of the YJA Miodrag Avramović<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn64" n="62">Miodrag Avramović, “Društvena odgovornost
                        i profesionalna etika novinara,” in: <hi rend="italic">Simpozijum
                            Informacija i novinarstvo</hi>, eds. Milo Popović and Milka Lasić-Šeat
                        (Beograd: Sedma sila, 1965), 117.</note> said that the “Association believes
                    that it is necessary to adopt a Code of Yugoslav journalism”. According to
                        Avramović,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn65" n="63">Ibid., 121.</note> the
                    issue of the function and position of journalists could not be defined by a
                    state legal instrument as it is very complex and thus subject to nuanced changes
                    in the socio-political development; including journalists’ social and moral
                    obligations in a normative state document would not correspond to the spirit of
                    the system of direct socialist democracy. This explains why there was only one
                    article in the <hi rend="italic">Press Act</hi> dedicated to professional
                    ethics, stating that journalists were obliged to follow the principles of
                    professional ethics and social responsibility and to act in the spirit of
                    respecting the truth, human rights, and the development of peaceful cooperation
                    among nations.</p>
                <p>For years, honorary courts of arbitration in journalist associations in
                    individual republics as well as the Honorary Court of Arbitration of the YJA
                    took care of exercising professional ethics based on their experience, customs
                    and criteria. <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn66" n="64">Ibid., 129.</note>
                    Professional ethics were thus dealt with superficially, unsystematically and
                    inconsistently due to the different criteria; further tolerance of such a
                    practice would harm the efficiency of the system of direct socialist democracy
                    and journalism’s integration into this system, which is why professional ethics
                    should be codified. <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn67" n="65">Ibid., 126,
                        127.</note> The need for a code arose from the need to appropriately define
                    “an objectively new function and new position of journalists and journalism in
                    new circumstances of the developed direct socialist democracy after adopting the
                    Constitution of the Socialist Federal Republic of Yugoslavia; to define social
                    and moral obligations of journalists”.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn68" n="66"
                        >Ibid.</note></p>
                <p>The code was adopted at the Sixth Congress of the YJA in 1965, with Bobić<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn69" n="67">Drago Bobić, “Nakon donošenja Kodeksa
                        jugoslovenskog novinarstva: suočenje sa praksom,” <hi rend="italic"
                            >Novinarstvo</hi> I, No. 2 (1965): 30.</note> stating that it
                    “reinforces the autonomous position of journalists, making them independent in
                    their acting as socio-political workers”. The Congress concluded that the code
                    is “an efficient means to protect journalists from all those who ruin the
                    principle of publicity and exert pressure on a journalist or interfere with the
                    exercise of their function”.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn70" n="68">SNJ,
                        “Zaključci Šestog kongresa Saveza novinara Jugoslavije,” <hi rend="italic"
                            >Novinarstvo</hi> I, No. 2 (1965).</note></p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Addressing Freedom and Responsibility</head>
                <p>In the 1965 code, the normative conceptualisation of (the relationship between)
                    freedom and responsibility is shown by the explicit labelling of a journalist as
                    “a socio-political worker” who takes part in the building and development of the
                    socialist society; strives for full implementation of the self-management rights
                    of working people and for civilised relations among people; contributes to the
                    development of a socialist conscience and the formation of socialist public
                    opinion. A journalist’s professional work consists of researching social
                    processes, phenomena and contradictions; forming their own opinions and views
                    through objective findings; informing the public about them; promoting the
                    broader social exchange of opinions; and contributing to activities that solve
                    societal issues. The code’s general provisions require a journalist to inform
                    the public “by acting according to their socialist conscience and by being aware
                    of their societal obligations and responsibilities to the socialist public”.
                    Thus, the media holds primary responsibility to the working people of the
                    self-managed socialist society, with their freedom strongly attached to the role
                    of journalists as socio-political workers and allowed only within the framework
                    of the social and political values they are bound to follow, such as socialism,
                    self-management, equality, civilised relations among people, freedom and
                    dignity. The same goes for the more personal level of journalistic freedom and
                    responsibility, with the code stating: “While forming their own views, a
                    journalist relies on the basic generally accepted socialist principles and
                    norms.” </p>
                <p>The 1969 code continues to define a journalist as a “committed socio-political
                    worker” who transmits, promotes and introduces a broader social exchange of
                    opinions, and contributes to the activity of socialist forces based on socialist
                    self-management, with their commitments being grounded in the same social and
                    political values as 4 years before. In the general provisions, struggling
                    against nationalistic and anti-self-management tendencies and all the phenomena
                    that hinder the development of the socialist democracy is added to the list,
                    including the fight for the full respect of the freedom, dignity and equality of
                    all Yugoslav nations and nationalities. The character of the media as open
                    tribunes, acknowledged in the previous code, is given greater attention by
                    defining them as “open socialist tribunes” accessible to all working people in
                    Yugoslavia. According to the code, it is a journalist’s societal and
                    professional obligation to inform the working people comprehensively and
                    objectively about social phenomena, needs and relations for them to be able to
                    more effectively perform their self-management role.</p>
                <p>The 1973 code incorporates new values like Marxism, Leninism, the politics of
                    Non-Alignment, the unity of Yugoslavia, peace, independence and equality in
                    international relations. A journalist is still seen as a socio-political worker
                    with their “conscious commitment to the ideas of Marxism and Leninism” being
                    emphasised. The subchapter on journalists’ role, functioning and status is
                    extended; the list of what a journalist fights for now includes additional
                    goals, such as: deepening the equality and self-management autonomy of nations
                    and nationalities in Yugoslavia; developing Yugoslav socialist patriotism;
                    strengthening the country’s defence ability; the unity and integrity of
                    Yugoslavia; commitment to consistent Non-Aligned politics, peace, independence
                    and equality in international relations. A journalist always firmly stands
                    against arbitrary behaviour of the bureaucracy, technocratic usurpation, various
                    kinds of nationalistic chauvinism, separatism, hegemony, the penetration of
                    liberal-anarchistic concepts, opportunistic comfort, monopolistic closing and
                    all phenomena that block, jeopardise and undermine the progress and
                    consolidation of the socialist democracy. A journalist is therefore expected to
                    be very active, engaged, and not merely a passive observer of society: in
                    disputes with contrary opinions, they respect the right to free expression, yet
                    “openly and strongly identify and condemn phenomena and tendencies which are
                    hostile to self-managed humane socialism as well as the agents of such phenomena
                    and tendencies”. Media freedom derives from “the self-management socialist
                    orientation of social development” and a journalist’s freedom grows “in
                    proportion to their Marxist, general and specialist knowledge and journalistic
                    professional skill”. Freedom is thus recognised, yet within the limits of
                    affirming the socialism based on self-management. A journalist is still obliged
                    to act according to their socialist conscience while carrying out their
                    responsibility to the socialist public. </p>
                <p>The 1982 code maintains the idea of a journalist as a socio-political worker who
                    participates in the building and development of the socialist self-managed
                    society. Apart from the values previously included, other values appear in the
                    general provisions like prohibition on ideologies of hostility, national and
                    racial intolerance and discrimination, and the fight for fairer
                    societal-economic relations in the world. Media freedom continues to be
                    connected to the self-management socialist orientation of social development,
                    while a journalist’s “autonomy in their work grows in proportion to their own
                    political and professional training”. Responsibility to the socialist public is
                    replaced by responsibility to comprehensively inform the public.</p>
                <p>The 1988 code brings a major normative change by no longer defining a journalist
                    as a socio-political worker and omitting the values of Marxism and Leninism.
                    Yet, a journalist is still expected to strive for the development of socialist
                    self-management, for unity and the federal system of Yugoslavia, for the
                    principle of equality of its nations and nationalities, for civilised socialist
                    relations among people and for the principles of non-alignment and peaceful
                    coexistence in the Yugoslav foreign policy. In line with some newly added
                    values, a journalist is obliged to advocate respect for the freedom, dignity and
                    human rights of citizens, the rule of law, and equality before the law. The code
                    explicitly states that news media are “free, autonomous and researching”, and a
                    journalist should take part in the formation of public opinion by communicating
                    autonomous and critical views when searching for the truth. The struggle for the
                    free flow of information across the whole Yugoslav area is defined as a
                    journalist’s right and duty. The code also declares that a journalist is held
                    accountable by society, laws and the professional organisation, stressing their
                    responsibility to the public. </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Norms on Truthfulness and Professionalism</head>
                <p>Already in its general provisions, the 1965 code articulates some professional
                    norms, such as the correction of errors and declares that a journalist “prevents
                    misinforming of the public, struggles against all that is fake, fabricated and
                    unverified to be brought to and kept in the public’s attention”. A Yugoslav
                    journalist is committed to truthfulness since they “truthfully informs and
                    correctly as well as comprehensively explains events and phenomena”. The chapter
                    on the moral/political professional obligations of journalists outlines several
                    norms in two subchapters: 1. <hi rend="italic">Professional integrity</hi>
                    (norms like source confidentiality and non-plagiarism) and 2. <hi rend="italic"
                        >Respecting human personality and dignity</hi>. The chapter initially
                    requires that “[o]n all occasions a journalist must seek to offer an accurate
                    and objective information to the public”, noting that a journalist “would rather
                    give up information than publish information which is wrong or insufficiently
                    verified”. </p>
                <p>The subchapter on respecting human personality and dignity is set out in more
                    detail in the 1969 code, introducing norms related to respecting privacy and the
                    considerate treatment of sensitive topics like accidents, illness or rape. The
                    code also states that a journalist should not point out a person’s race,
                    nationality, profession or religion, particularly not of those who have been
                    arrested, charged or convicted, if this information is not of great importance
                    for the story a journalist is reporting on. </p>
                <p>In the 1973 code, several socio-political and professional norms are still
                    intertwined in the subchapters dedicated to professional integrity and
                    respecting human personality and dignity. The latter is elaborated on more, with
                    some norms added and others explained in greater detail. For example, the facile
                    moral and political disqualification of people is considered to be among the
                    most serious ethical offences. The importance of truthfulness is further
                    underlined by demanding that a journalist “must always think about the truth”.
                    Commitment to truthfulness is already pointed out in the general provisions,
                    stating that the “basic social categories of journalistic work – truth, freedom,
                    responsibility – are at the same time also primarily professionally ethical
                    requirements”. A journalist is bound to inform accurately, to explain events and
                    phenomena faithfully and comprehensively. All that impedes and distorts the
                    correct, true, objective, comprehensive and timely information is a danger to
                    society and a moral offence: not only a deliberate lie, but also all other ways
                    of changing, hiding or distorting the truth. </p>
                <p>In the 1982 code, the chapter’s title <hi rend="italic">Moral-political and
                        professional obligations of journalists</hi> is removed, yet the content
                    mostly remains the same, with the previous values and norms (objectivity,
                    respect for human personality and dignity, error correction, respecting privacy
                    and non-plagiarism etc.) retaining their place in the code. Everything that
                    interferes with and deforms accurate, comprehensive and timely information is to
                    be seen as a danger to society: “Objective informing is an important integral
                    part of a self-management relationship /…/ and a professionally-ethical
                    requirement of the journalist profession”.</p>
                <p>The 1988 code has a new structure: it begins with general provisions followed by
                    the main chapter entitled <hi rend="italic">Rights and duties</hi>, with a few
                    concluding provisions at the end. Journalists’ rights and duties contain several
                    norms related to truthfulness, respect for a person’s dignity and integrity, and
                    protection of human personality and intimacy. The search for truth is declared
                    to be a basic principle of journalists’ work: “By communicating an autonomous
                    and critical view while searching for the truth, which is a basic principle of
                    professional work, a journalist actively participates in the formation of public
                    opinion …”. Further, “It is a journalist’s obligation to communicate the truth,
                    a comprehensive and verified information to the public”. </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Discussion with a Conclusion</head>
                <p>The normative foundations of journalism, as outlined in the Yugoslav journalism
                    ethics codes, were transforming over time and in response to changes occurring
                    in the socio-politico-legal-economic environment: at each reference point (the
                    year of a code’s adoption or revision), modifications can be associated with the
                    socio-political and economic circumstances in society, thereby supporting
                    Hanitzsch’s conclusion that normative role orientations are socially negotiated,
                    sensitive to context, and in a constant state of flux. <note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn71" n="69">Hanitzsch, “Roles of Journalists,” 45.</note></p>
                <p>The Yugoslav constitution of 1963 emphasised that Yugoslavia was a socialist
                    democratic community and revealed a tendency for the Marxist ideal of the state
                    withering away, while self-management was declared inviolable. <note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn72" n="70">Jovan R. Bazić, “The Socio-Political
                        System of Yugoslavia as the Systemic Cause of Its Collapse,” <hi
                            rend="italic">Sociološki pregled</hi> 52, No. 4 (2018): 1162.</note> The
                    new constitution introduced the citizens’ <hi rend="italic">right to be
                        informed</hi> and <hi rend="italic">freedom of the press and other media of
                        information</hi>, and “drastically changed the role of the Yugoslav
                        journalist”:<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn73" n="71">Robinson, <hi
                            rend="italic">Tito's Maverick Media</hi>, 42.</note> instead of being a
                    mere recorder of events, they were expected to function as an interpreter and
                    critic. Two years later, the first ethics code was adopted. The second half of
                    the 1960s was marked decreasing economic growth, increasing regional disparities
                    and higher unemployment; nationalist rhetoric resurfaced, accompanied by
                    problems pushed to the surface by the economic downturn. <note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn74" n="72">Calic, <hi rend="italic">A History of Yugoslavia</hi>,
                        223.</note> The emerging crisis raised questions concerning ethnic
                    coexistence and the distribution of political power and prosperity; social and
                    economic interests were being discussed more and more in categories of ethnic
                        differences.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn75" n="73">Ibid., 226.</note>
                    Towards the end of the 1960s, the nationalisms in Yugoslavia had increased.
                        <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn76" n="74">Dušan Bilandžić, <hi rend="italic"
                            >Zgodovina SFRJ: Glavni procesi</hi> (Ljubljana: Partizanska knjiga,
                        1980), 346.</note> The code of 1969 extended the list of negative phenomena
                    that a journalist should fight against by adding the struggle against
                    nationalistic and anti-self-management tendencies and everything that hinders
                    the development of the socialist democracy. The fight for the full respect of
                    the freedom, dignity and equality of all Yugoslav nations and nationalities was
                    included, while the media, previously described as <hi rend="italic">open
                        tribunes</hi>, were now defined as <hi rend="italic">open socialist
                        tribunes</hi>. </p>
                <p>In the 1970s, Yugoslavia went into economic recession, yet at the beginning of
                    the decade its international status had been stronger than ever before.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn77" n="75">Calic, <hi rend="italic">A History of
                            Yugoslavia</hi>, 240–42.</note> Still, the economic problems and growing
                    development disparities among the regions led to political dissatisfaction and
                    inter-republic disputes. <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn78" n="76">Flere and
                        Klanjšek, <hi rend="italic">The Rise and Fall of Socialist Yugoslavia</hi>,
                        116. </note> In the 1973 code, new values appeared, such as Marxism,
                    Leninism, the politics of Non-Alignment, the unity of Yugoslavia, socialist
                    patriotism, peace, independence and equality in international relations. After
                    Tito’s death in 1980, secessionist processes in Yugoslavia accelerated, as
                    greatly contributed to by the socio-economic crisis. <note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn79" n="77">Bazić, “The Socio-Political System of Yugoslavia as
                        the Systemic Cause of Its Collapse,” 1165.</note> The devastating economic
                    crisis was accompanied by other factors leading to the decay of Yugoslavia like
                    the 1981 conflict in Kosovo and the demands of the Albanian population for a
                        change,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn80" n="78">Josip Glaurdić, <hi
                            rend="italic">The Hour of Europe: Western Powers and the Breakup of
                            Yugoslavia</hi> (New Haven, London: Yale University Press, 2011),
                        15.</note> and the resurgence of radical nationalist policies in
                        Serbia.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn81" n="79">Peruško et al., <hi
                            rend="italic">Comparing Post-Socialist Media Systems</hi>, 87.</note>
                    The 1982 code introduced additional values such as the prohibition on ideologies
                    of hostility, national and racial intolerance and discrimination, and the fight
                    for fairer societal-economic relations in the world. In the 1988 code, the
                    Marxist and Leninist values were replaced by the human rights of citizens, the
                    rule of law, and equality before the law – values which are key to any
                    democracy. </p>
                <p>The normative conceptualisations of the relationship between freedom and
                    responsibility in the Yugoslav journalism ethics codes add support for
                    Robinson’s <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn82" n="80">Robinson, <hi rend="italic"
                            >Tito's Maverick Media</hi>, 119.</note> observation that Yugoslav
                    journalism cannot be identified with the Soviet media philosophy, as one might
                    expect when considering that Yugoslavia was a socialist country. While
                    displaying several characteristics of the Soviet-totalitarian theory of the
                    press, the normative foundations also somewhat resemble the social
                    responsibility theory from the first code onward, peaking in the period of the
                    major socio-political changes in the late 1980s. </p>
                <p>Under the Soviet theory, the mass media is used almost exclusively as instruments
                    of the propaganda and agitation of the state and the Communist Party,<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn83" n="81">Fred S. Siebert et al., <hi rend="italic"
                            >Four Theories of the Press: The Authoritarian, Libertarian, Social
                            Responsibility, and Soviet Communist Concepts of What the Press Should
                            Be and Do</hi> (Urbana: University of Illinois Press, 1956), 121.</note>
                    while the media’s functions in the social responsibility theory include
                    servicing the political system by providing information, discussion and debate
                    of public affairs as well as enlightening the public to make it capable of
                        self-management.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn84" n="82">Ibid., 74.</note>
                    Already in the 1965 code , Yugoslav journalists were expected to research social
                    processes, phenomena and contradictions; to form their own opinions and views
                    through objective findings; to inform the public about it; to promote a broader
                    social exchange of opinions; and to contribute to activities that solve societal
                    issues. Indications of the function of a watchdog against government came later,
                    not until the 1988 code, when journalists had given up the role of
                    socio-political workers and instead chosen to take part in the formation of
                    public opinion by communicating autonomous and critical views while searching
                    for the truth. </p>
                <p>Under the Soviet theory, the media is to look at events from a
                    Marxist-Leninist-Stalinist standpoint,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn85" n="83"
                        >Ibid., 124.</note> while journalists are free to express themselves within
                    the bounds and limits of the allegedly beneficent state that protects citizens
                    in doing what is good for them.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn86" n="84">Ibid.,
                        127.</note> The media is required to do certain things, such as increase the
                    political awareness of the masses, to rally the population in support of the
                    leaders and their programme, to raise the level of worker efficiency etc.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn87" n="85">Ibid., 141.</note> In the Yugoslav codes,
                    the idea of media and journalist freedom was conceived in a similar way –
                    permitted within the limits of the socialist orientation and if contributing to
                    the building and development of the self-managed society, at least up until the
                    1988 code when the Marxist/Leninist values and the definition of a journalist as
                    a socio-political worker were removed. The social responsibility theory sees
                    freedom of expression as a moral right grounded in an individual’s duty to their
                    own conscience, while the Soviet theory stresses the duty to the proletariat.
                        <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn88" n="86">Ibid., 96–98.</note> In the codes
                    of 1965, 1969 and 1973, a Yugoslav journalist was explicitly obliged to act in
                    line with their socialist conscience and be responsible to the socialist working
                    people – the socialist public, thereby bringing the concept of responsibility
                    closer to the Soviet idea. The codes of 1982 and 1988 emphasised a journalist’s
                    responsibility to the public, now no longer labelled as a socialist one. The
                    concept of responsibility to the public, based on a journalist’s autonomy and
                    critical stance, assumed a journalist’s duty to their conscience in the sense of
                    the social responsibility theory since conscience was no longer defined by the
                    adjective “socialist”. </p>
                <p>Professional norms related to truthfulness, professional integrity, and respect
                    for human personality and dignity, some of which were already introduced in the
                    1965 code, were evolving over time, gaining more space, elaboration and
                    emphasis. However, they must be considered in the context of how the
                    relationship between media/journalistic freedom and responsibility was
                    conceptualised, which relativises some of the stronger commitments, such as
                    “always thinking about the truth”, on the normative level already, let alone the
                    level of media practices. Nevertheless, the fact that some professional norms
                    that always featured in journalism ethics codes in developed democracies were
                    recognised by the journalistic community as sufficiently important to be
                    codified shows that the foundations of the professionalisation of Slovenian
                    journalism were already laid in socialist Yugoslavia. </p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="bibliography">
                <head>Sources and Literature</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Literature</head>
                    <bibl>Amon, Smilja. “Obdobja razvoja slovenskega novinarstva.” In: <hi
                            rend="italic">Poti slovenskega novinarstva: danes in jutri</hi>. Eds.
                        Melita Poler Kovačič and Monika Kalin Golob, 53–68. Ljubljana: FDV,
                        2004.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Bazić, Jovan R. “The Socio-Political System of Yugoslavia as the Systemic
                        Cause of Its Collapse.” <hi rend="italic">Sociološki pregled</hi> 52, No. 4
                        (2018): 1158–70.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Bilandžić, Dušan. <hi rend="italic">Zgodovina SFRJ: Glavni procesi</hi>.
                        Ljubljana: Partizanska knjiga, 1980.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Black, Jay and Chris Roberts. <hi rend="italic">Doing Ethics in Media:
                            Theories and Practical Applications</hi>. New York, London: Routledge,
                        2011.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Bowen, Glenn A. “Document Analysis as a Qualitative Research Method.” <hi
                            rend="italic">Qualitative Research Journal</hi> 9, No. 2 (2009): 27–40. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Calic, Marie-Janine. <hi rend="italic">A History of Yugoslavia</hi>. West
                        Lafayette, Indiana: Purdue University Press, 2019.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Carlson, Matt. “Metajournalistic Discourse and the Meanings of Journalism:
                        Definitional Control, Boundary Work, and Legitimation.” <hi rend="italic"
                            >Communication Theory</hi> 26 (2016): 349–68.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Christians, Clifford and Kaarle Nordenstreng. “Social Responsibility
                        Worldwide.” <hi rend="italic">Journal of Mass Media Ethics</hi> 19, No. 1
                        (2004): 3–28.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Day, Louis A. <hi rend="italic">Ethics in Media Communications: Cases and
                            Controversies</hi>. Belmont: Wadsworth Publishing Company, 2000.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Flere, Sergej and Rudi Klanjšek. <hi rend="italic">The Rise and Fall of
                            Socialist Yugoslavia: Elite Nationalism and the Collapse of a
                            Federation</hi>. Lanham, Boulder, New York, London: Lexington Books,
                        2019.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Gibbs, Jack P. “Norms: The Problem of Definition and Classification.” <hi
                            rend="italic">American Journal of Sociology</hi> 70, No. 5 (1965):
                        586–94.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Glaurdić, Josip. <hi rend="italic">The Hour of Europe: Western Powers and
                            the Breakup of Yugoslavia</hi>. New Haven, London: Yale University
                        Press, 2011.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Gorjup, Mitja. <hi rend="italic">Samoupravno novinarstvo</hi>. Ljubljana:
                        Delavska enotnost, 1978.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Hanitzsch, Thomas and Tim P. Vos. “Journalistic Roles and the Struggle
                        Over Institutional Identity: The Discursive Constitution of Journalism.” <hi
                            rend="italic">Communication Theory</hi> 27 (2017): 115–35.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Hanitzsch Thomas and Tim P. Vos. “Journalism Beyond Democracy.” <hi
                            rend="italic">Journalism</hi> 19, No. 2 (2018): 146–64.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Hanitzsch, Thomas, Laura Ahva, Martin Oller Alonso, Jesus Arroyave,
                        Liesbeth Hermans, Jan Fredrik Hovden, Sallie Hughes, Beate Josephi, Jyotika
                        Ramaprasad, Ivor Shapiro and Tim P. Vos. “Journalistic Culture in a Global
                        Context: A Conceptual Roadmap.” In: <hi rend="italic">Worlds of Journalism:
                            Journalistic Cultures Around the Globe</hi>, eds. Thomas
                        Hanitzsch, Folker Hanusch, Jyotika Ramaprasad and Arnold de Beer, 23–45. New
                        York: Columbia University Press, 2019. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Hanitzsch, Thomas, Tim P. Vos, Olivier Standaert, Folker Hanusch, Jan
                        Fredrik Hovden, Liesbeth Hermans and Jyotika Ramaprasad. “Role Orientations:
                        Journalists’ Views on Their Place in Society.” In: <hi rend="italic">Worlds
                            of Journalism: Journalistic Cultures Around the Globe</hi>, eds. Thomas
                        Hanitzsch, Folker Hanusch, Jyotika Ramaprasad and Arnold de Beer, 161–97.
                        New York: Columbia University Press, 2019.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Hanitzsch, Thomas. “Roles of Journalists.” In: <hi rend="italic"
                            >Journalism</hi>. Ed. Tim P. Vos, 43–61. Berlin, Boston: De Gruyter
                        Mouton, 2018.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Horvat, Marjan. “Prepovedi razširjanja tiskane besede v Sloveniji
                        1945–1990.” Bachelor Thesis, University of Ljubljana, 1995.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Jusić, Tarik. “Media Discourse and the Politics of Ethnic Conflict: The
                        Case of Yugoslavia.” In: <hi rend="italic">Media Discourse and the Yugoslav
                            Conflicts: Representations of Self and Other</hi>, ed. Pål Kolstø,
                        21–38. London: Routledge, 2009. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Merljak Zdovc, Sonja. “The Use of Novelistic Techniques in Slovene
                        Journalism: The Case of Magazine Tovariš.” <hi rend="italic">Journalism
                            Studies</hi> 8, No. 2 (2007): 248–63.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Merrill, John C. <hi rend="italic">The Dialectic in Journalism: Toward A
                            Responsible Use of Press Freedom</hi>. Baton Rouge, London: Louisiana
                        State University Press, 1989.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Peruško, Zrinjka, Dina Vozab and Antonija Čuvalo. <hi rend="italic"
                            >Comparing Post-Socialist Media Systems: The Case of Southeast
                            Europe</hi>. London, New York: Routledge, 2021.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Roberts, Chris. “Identifying and Defining Values in Media Ethics Codes.”
                            <hi rend="italic">Journal of Mass Media Ethics</hi> 27 (2012):
                        115–29.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Robinson, Gertrude Joch. <hi rend="italic">Tito's Maverick Media: The
                            Politics of Mass Communications in Yugoslavia</hi>. Urbana, Chicago,
                        London: University of Illinois Press, 1977.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Siebert, Fred S., Theodore Peterson and Wilbur Schramm. <hi rend="italic"
                            >Four Theories of the Press: The Authoritarian, Libertarian, Social
                            Responsibility, and Soviet Communist Concepts of What the Press Should
                            Be and Do</hi>. Urbana: University of Illinois Press, 1956.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Slavković, Dušan. “Novinar i novinarstvo.” In: <hi rend="italic"
                            >Novinarstvo danas: Priručnik za polaznike novinarske škole
                            Jugoslovenskog instituta za novinarstvo</hi>. Ed. Zdravko Leković,
                        95–101. Beograd: Jugoslovenski institut za novinarstvo, 1983.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Spaskovska, Ljubica. <hi rend="italic">The Last Yugoslav Generation: The
                            Rethinking of Youth Politics and Cultures in Late Socialism</hi>.
                        Manchester: Manchester University Press, 2017.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Splichal, Slavko and Colin Sparks. <hi rend="italic">Journalists for the
                            21</hi><hi rend="italic superscript">st</hi><hi rend="italic"> Century:
                            Tendencies of Professionalization Among First-Year Students in 22
                            Countries</hi>. Norwood: Ablex Publishing Corporation, 1994.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Splichal, Slavko and France Vreg. <hi rend="italic">Množično komuniciranje
                            in razvoj demokracije</hi>. Ljubljana: Komunist, 1986.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Standaert, Olivier, Thomas Hanitzsch and Jonathan Dedonder. “In Their Own
                        Words: A Normative-Empirical Approach to Journalistic Roles Around the
                        World.” <hi rend="italic">Journalism</hi> 22, No. 4 (2021): 919–36. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Šuen, Matjaž. <hi rend="italic">Preiskovalno novinarstvo</hi>. Ljubljana:
                        FDV, 1994.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Vos, Tim P. “Journalism.” In: <hi rend="italic">Journalism</hi>, ed. Tim
                        P. Vos, 1–17. Berlin, Boston: De Gruyter Mouton, 2018.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Vos, Tim. P. “Journalism as Institution.” Available at: <ref
                            target="https://doi.org/10.1093/acrefore/9780190228613.013.825"
                            >https://doi.org/10.1093/acrefore/9780190228613.013.825</ref>. Published
                        online: 25. 2. 2019. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Ward, Stephen J. A. <hi rend="italic">The Invention of Journalism Ethics:
                            The Path to Objectivity and Beyond. Montreal, Kingston, London, Chicago:
                            McGill-Queen’s University Press,</hi> 2004.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Yuryevich Bykov, Aleksei, Elena Savova Georgieva, Yuliya Sokratovna
                        Danilova and Anna Vitalyevna Baychik. “Codes of Journalism Ethics in Russia
                        and the United States: Traditions and the Current Practice of Application.”
                            <hi rend="italic">International Review of Management and Marketing</hi>
                        5, Special Issue (2015): 55–61.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Sources</head>
                    <bibl>Avramović, Miodrag. “Društvena odgovornost i profesionalna etika
                        novinara.” In: <hi rend="italic">Simpozijum Informacija i novinarstvo</hi>.
                        Eds. Milo Popović and Milka Lasić-Šeat, 117–30. Beograd: Sedma sila,
                        1965.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Avramović, Miodrag. “Izvještaj komisije za kodeks.” In: <hi rend="italic"
                            >Srebrni jubilej SNJ 1945–1970: Knjiga 1</hi>. Ed. Miodrag Avramović,
                        540–46. Beograd: SNJ, 1971.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Blagojević, Dušan. “Uloga novinara kao javnih i političkih radnika u našem
                        društvu.” In: <hi rend="italic">Srebrni jubilej SNJ 1945–1970: Knjiga
                        1</hi>. Ed. Miodrag Avramović, 266–72. Beograd: SNJ, 1971.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Bobić, Drago. “Nakon donošenja Kodeksa jugoslovenskog novinarstva:
                        suočenje sa praksom.” <hi rend="italic">Novinarstvo</hi> I, No. 2 (1965):
                        28–35.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Osolnik, Bogdan. “The intention was to democratise the sphere of
                        communication.” Interview. <hi rend="italic">TripleC</hi> 15, No. 1 (2017):
                        231–50.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Rančić, Dragoslav. “Zakaj pripravljamo nov kodeks?” <hi rend="italic"
                            >Teorija in praksa</hi> 25, No. 5 (1988): 645–49.</bibl>
                    <bibl>SNJ. “Kodeks jugoslovenskog novinarstva.” <hi rend="italic"
                            >Novinarstvo</hi> I, No. 2 (1965): 204,205.</bibl>
                    <bibl>SNJ. “Kodeks jugoslovenskog novinarstva.” <hi rend="italic"
                            >Novinarstvo</hi> V, No. 3–4 (1969): 180–85.</bibl>
                    <bibl>SNJ. “Kodeks novinara Jugoslavije.” <hi rend="italic">Novinarstvo</hi> IX,
                        No. 1–2 (1973): 98–102.</bibl>
                    <bibl>SNJ. “Kodeks novinara Jugoslavije.” <hi rend="italic">Novinarstvo</hi>
                        XVIII, No. 3–4 (1982): 136–40.</bibl>
                    <bibl>SNJ. “Kodeks novinara Jugoslavije.” <hi rend="italic">Novinarstvo</hi>
                        XXIV, No. 3–4 (1988): 82, 83.</bibl>
                    <bibl>SNJ. “Moralne obaveze novinara.” In: <hi rend="italic">Srebrni jubilej SNJ
                            1945–1970: Knjiga 1</hi>. Ed. Miodrag Avramović, 314, 315. Beograd: SNJ,
                        1971.</bibl>
                    <bibl>SNJ. “Zaključci Šestog kongresa Saveza novinara Jugoslavije.” <hi
                            rend="italic">Novinarstvo</hi> I, No. 2 (1965): 197–99.</bibl>
                    <bibl>UO SNJ. “Izveštaj.” In: <hi rend="italic">Srebrni jubilej SNJ 1945–1970:
                            Knjiga 1</hi>. Ed. Miodrag Avramović, 360–78. Beograd: SNJ, 1971.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
            <div type="summary" xml:lang="sl">
                <docAuthor>Melita Poler Kovačič</docAuthor>
                <head>NORMATIVNE USMERITVE VLOG JUGOSLOVANSKIH NOVINARJEV: ŠTUDIJA NOVINARSKIH
                    ETIČNIH KODEKSOV V SFRJ</head>
                <head>POVZETEK</head>
                <p>Cilj te študije je raziskati normativne orientacije vlog novinarjev v SFRJ, kot
                    so zapisane ali razvidne v petih jugoslovanskih novinarskih etičnih kodeksih
                    (sprejetih v letih 1965, 1969, 1973, 1982 in 1988). Z analizo dokumentov in
                    primerjalno zgodovinsko metodo smo raziskali razloge za sprejem prvega kodeksa,
                    analizirali pojmovanja svobode in odgovornosti ter odnos med njima v kodeksih in
                    ugotovili, kako kodeksi naslavljajo resnicoljubnost in profesionalne norme.</p>
                <p>Normativni temelji novinarstva, kot se kažejo v etičnih kodeksih, so se
                    spreminjali skozi čas ter ob spremembah v družbenem, političnem, pravnem in
                    ekonomskem okolju, denimo ob sprejetju ustave leta 1963, ekonomski krizi in
                    porastu nacionalizmov proti koncu šestdesetih let in v sedemdesetih letih ter
                    družbeno-ekonomski krizi, secesionističnih procesih in kosovski krizi v
                    osemdesetih letih. Novinarji so v etične kodekse zapisovali z družbenimi
                    dogajanji povezane vrednote in cilje, denimo boj proti nacionalističnim težnjam
                    in za spoštovanje enakosti vseh jugoslovanskih narodov in narodnosti v kodeks
                    leta 1969; vrednote marksizma, leninizma, enotnosti Jugoslavije, socialističnega
                    patriotizma idr. v kodeks leta 1973; prepoved ideologij sovražnosti ter
                    nacionalne in rasne nestrpnosti ter diskriminacije v kodeks leta 1982; človekove
                    pravice, vladavino prava ter enakost pred zakonom v kodeks leta 1988.</p>
                <p>Ob več značilnostih sovjetske totalitarne teorije tiska imajo normativni temelji
                    tudi določeno podobnost s teorijo družbene odgovornosti. Že v prvem etičnem
                    kodeksu iz leta 1965 se je od novinarja pričakovalo, da raziskuje družbene
                    procese, pojave in nasprotja, oblikuje svoja lastna mnenja in poglede na podlagi
                    objektivnih spoznanj; o tem obvešča javnost; spodbuja širšo družbeno izmenjavo
                    mnenj; in prispeva k aktivnostim za reševanje družbenih problemov. Vendar sta
                    bili medijska in novinarska svoboda dovoljeni le v okviru socialistične
                    usmeritve ter prispevka h graditvi in razvoju samoupravne družbe, vsaj do leta
                    1988, ko so bile iz kodeksa izpuščene vrednoti marksizma in leninizma ter
                    opredelitev novinarja kot družbenopolitičnega delavca. Zadnji jugoslovanski
                    novinarski etični kodeks je kot osnovno načelo poklicnega dela opredelil
                    sporočanje samostojnih in kritičnih stališč pri iskanju resnice. Jugoslovanski
                    novinar je bil normativno obvezan delovati po svoji socialistični zavesti in je
                    bil odgovoren do delovnih ljudi oziroma socialistične javnosti, kar je bliže
                    sovjetski ideji odgovornosti, kodeksa v osemdesetih letih pa sta poudarila
                    njegovo odgovornost do javnosti.</p>
                <p>Profesionalne norme, povezane z resnicoljubnostjo, profesionalno integriteto ter
                    spoštovanjem človekove osebnosti in dostojanstva, so se sčasoma razvijale ter
                    pridobivale več prostora, razdelanosti in poudarka. Vendar jih je treba razumeti
                    v kontekstu pojmovanj odnosa med medijsko/novinarsko svobodo in odgovornostjo,
                    ki relativizira nekatere močne zaveze, kot je »vedno misliti na resnico«, že na
                    normativni ravni, kaj šele na ravni medijskih praks. Toda dejstvo, da je
                    novinarska skupnost nekatere profesionalne norme prepoznala kot dovolj pomembne
                    za kodifikacijo, nakazuje, da so bili temelji profesionalizacije slovenskega
                    novinarstva položeni že v socialistični Jugoslaviji.</p>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
