<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Student Movement 1968/1971 in Ljubljana in Wider Context</title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename>Zdenko</forename>
                        <surname>Čepič</surname>
                        <roleName>Research Counsellor</roleName>
                        <roleName>PhD</roleName>
                        <affiliation>Institute of Contemporary History</affiliation>
                        <address>
                            <addrLine>Kongresni trg 1</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>SI-1000 Ljubljana</addrLine>
                        </address>
                        <email>zdenko.cepic@inz.si</email>
                    </name>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>2017-11-23</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>
                    <orgName xml:lang="sl">Inštitut za novejšo zgodovino</orgName>
                    <orgName xml:lang="en">Institute of Contemporary History</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Kongresni trg 1</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>SI-1000 Ljubljana</addrLine>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>http://ojs.inz.si/pnz/article/view/311</pubPlace>
                <date>2018</date>
                <availability status="free">
                    <licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title xml:lang="sl">Prispevki za novejšo zgodovino</title>
                <title xml:lang="en">Contributions to Contemporary History</title>
                <biblScope unit="volume">58</biblScope>
                <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
                <idno type="ISSN">2463-7807</idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source, born digital.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc xml:lang="en">
                <p>Contributions to Contemporary History is one of the central Slovenian scientific
                    historiographic journals, dedicated to publishing articles from the field of
                    contemporary history (the 19th and 20th century).</p>
                <p>The journal is published three times per year in Slovenian and in the following
                    foreign languages: English, German, Serbian, Croatian, Bosnian, Italian, Slovak
                    and Czech. The articles are all published with abstracts in English and
                    Slovenian as well as summaries in English.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <projectDesc xml:lang="sl">
                <p>Prispevki za novejšo zgodovino je ena osrednjih slovenskih znanstvenih
                    zgodovinopisnih revij, ki objavlja teme s področja novejše zgodovine (19. in 20.
                    stoletje).</p>
                <p>Revija izide trikrat letno v slovenskem jeziku in v naslednjih tujih jezikih:
                    angleščina, nemščina, srbščina, hrvaščina, bosanščina, italijanščina, slovaščina
                    in češčina. Članki izhajajo z izvlečki v angleščini in slovenščini ter povzetki
                    v angleščini.</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="sl"/>
                <language ident="en"/>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords xml:lang="en">
                    <term>student movements</term>
                    <term>students protests</term>
                    <term>Yugoslavia</term>
                    <term>politics</term>
                    <term>Slovenia</term>
                    <term>University of Ljubljana</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords xml:lang="sl">
                    <term>študentsko gibanje</term>
                    <term>študentski protesti</term>
                    <term>politika</term>
                    <term>Jugoslavija</term>
                    <term>Slovenija</term>
                    <term>Univerza v Ljubljani</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change>
                    <date>2017-12-14</date>
                    <name>Neja Blaj Hribar</name>
                    <desc>Pretvorba iz DOCX v TEI, dodatno kodiranje</desc>
                </change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <docAuthor>Zdenko Čepič<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn1" n="*">
                <hi rend="bold" xml:space="preserve">Research Counsellor, PhD, Institute of Contemporary History,
                            Kongresni trg 1, SI-1000 Ljubljana, Slovenia,</hi>
                        <ref target="mailto:zdenko.cepic@inz.si">zdenko.cepic@inz.si</ref></note></docAuthor>
            <docImprint>
                <idno type="cobissType">Cobiss type: 1.01</idno>
                <idno type="UDC">UDC: 378.18:329.78(497.4)"1968/1972"</idno>
            </docImprint>
            <div type="stanza"><l style="text-align:right;"><hi rend="italic">Ev'rywhere I hear the sound of marching,
                charging feet, boy</hi></l>
                <l style="text-align:right;"><hi rend="italic">'Cause summer's here and the time is right for fighting in
                    the street, boy</hi></l>
                <l style="text-align:right;"><hi rend="italic">Well then what can a poor boy do</hi></l>
                <l style="text-align:right;"><hi rend="italic">Except to sing for a rock 'n' roll band</hi></l>
                <l style="text-align:right;"><hi rend="italic">'Cause in sleepy London town</hi></l>
                <l style="text-align:right;"><hi rend="italic">There's just no place for a street fighting man</hi></l>
                <l style="text-align:right;"><hi rend="italic">No!</hi></l>
                <p style="text-align:right;"><hi rend="italic">(Street Fighting Man, The Rolling Stones
                    (M. Jagger, K. Richards), 1968</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn2" n="1">
                        The song was created under the impression of
                        student protests in Paris. The words of the song Mick Jagger wrote in
                        spring of 1968 and published in the review The Black Dwarf, political
                        and cultural newspaper (published between May 1968 and 1972) by a
                        collective of socialists in United Kingdom (editor was Tariq Ali,
                        British Pakistan writer, journalist, historian, filmmaker, political
                        activist). Jagger wrote the song after he attended a 1968 anti-war rally
                        at London's US embassy. He also found inspiration in the rising violence
                        among student rioters in Paris. The author of the song Mick Jagger
                        remembered: “It was very strange time in France. But not only in France
                        but also in America, because of the Vietnam War and the endless
                        disruptions … I wrote a lot of the melody and all the words.” Recording
                        from April until May 1968.This song originally titled and recorded as
                        “
                        <hi rend="italic">Did Everyone Pay Their Dues?”</hi>
                        containing the same music but very different
                        lyrics. The song became well known in August 1968 (single); in December
                        1968 it recorder in album
                        <hi rend="italic">Beggar's Banquet</hi>. “
                        <hi rend="italic">Street Fighting Man</hi>” is the band's most political song. The song was
                        released within a week of the violent confrontations between the police
                        and anti-Vietnam War protesters at the
                        <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/1968_Democratic_National_Convention">1968 Democratic National Convention
                        </ref>
                        in Chicago. Worried about the possibility of the
                        song inciting further violence, Chicago radio stations refused to play
                        the song.
                    </note>!</p></div>
            <div type="abstract" xml:lang="sl">
                <head>IZVLEČEK</head>
                <head>ŠTUDENTSKO GIBANJE V LJUBLJANI 1968 IN 1971 V ŠIRŠEM KONTEKSTU</head>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">V letu 1968 so bili med političnimi dogodki
                        tega leta (»Praška pomlad« in njen konec, predsedniške volitve v ZDA, protesti
                        proti vojni v Vietnamu, …) pomembni študentski protesti. Bili so po vsej Evropi,
                        najbolj intenzivni v Parizu. Bili so tudi v Jugoslaviji, v Beogradu (začetek
                        junija). V Ljubljani so bili študenti v svojih protestih bolj socialno usmerjeni
                        kot pa politično. Več političnega je bilo v protestih študentov v Ljubljani
                        aprila in maja 1971, ko so iz protesta zasedli Filozofsko fakulteto. Avtor na
                        osnovi dokumentov slovenskega študentskega gibanja prestavlja delovanje
                        študentov v Ljubljani leta 1968 in 1971.</hi></p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Ključne besede: študentsko gibanje,
                        študentski protesti, politika, Jugoslavija, Slovenija, Univerza v
                        Ljubljani</hi></p>
            </div>
            <div type="abstract" xml:lang="en">
                <head>ABSTRACT</head>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">In 1968, during the political events of
                        this year ("Prague Spring" and its end, US presidential elections, protests
                        against the war in Vietnam, ...) significant student protests. They were all
                        over Europe, the most intense in Paris. They were also in Yugoslavia, in
                        Belgrade (early June). In Ljubljana, students in their protests were more
                        socially oriented than political. More political occurred in students' protests
                        in Ljubljana were in April and May 1971, when the Faculty of Arts students took
                        over for eight days. The author presents the work of students in Ljubljana in
                        1968 and 1971 on the basis of the documents of the Slovenian student
                        movement.</hi></p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Keywords: student movements, students
                        protests, politics, Yugoslavia, Slovenia, University of Ljubljana</hi></p>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <p> The student movement is “a specific phenomenon of a relatively mass protest on the
                world scale, related to the tradition of proletarian movement for citizen’s rights
                and to the tradition of war and post-war intellectual movements”.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn3" n="2"> Darko Štrajn, “Nekoč je bilo
                        študentsko gibanje?,” in: <hi rend="italic">Pričevanja, December 1985:
                            študentske pomladi,</hi> eds. Iztok Ilich et al. (Ljubljana: Partizanska
                        knjiga, 1986), 183, 184.</note> One can speak of the student movement as a
                historical phenomenon in particular in the late 1960s, when it was an organised
                political activity of students aimed at achieving certain political goals. Mass
                student movements were a characteristic of the late 1960s throughout the world.
                Although student protests started even before 1968 – at some universities in the
                USA, first at Berkeley where students protested against the war in Vietnam – the
                worldwide student unrest actually culminated in 1968. It, however, continued also
                after that year. In Slovenia it climaxed three years later.</p>
            <p> The active and mass student movement of the late 1960s was on the one side marked by
                its world dimension stemming from similar social and economic issues, and on the
                other side movements in individual countries had certain specific features. They
                were reflected in diverse forms of protests as well as in the very causes for
                opposition and the goals which they wanted to achieve. The political demands of
                students varied across the countries. In the USA, they called for the end of war in
                Vietnam, in France they fought against the authoritarian De Gaulle regime, in the
                “real socialism” countries they aspired for greater democratisation against the
                state bureaucracy, whilst in Yugoslavia they demanded greater consistency of the
                socialist self-management system. </p>
            <p> The student movement – given the lack of any formal connectedness (organisational or
                substantive) between the students’ activities in various countries – were largely
                political. The causes were in the first place social and the movements were a
                response of students to the current social conflicts. They emerged as a critical
                “conscience” of economic and social relations and the contradictions in the society.
                They had ideological roots in Marxism and had a character of a “new leftist”
                movement. This was the case in western as well as eastern student movements. In
                Yugoslavia, students advocated socialism, but they wanted to make it better, more
                humane. What was common to all student movements was their anti-war, pacifist
                orientation enshrined in a slogan “Make love, not war”. Their political goals were
                aimed at changing the society towards greater democratisation and humanisation.
                Students wanted to save the world and change the social conditions. They were
                agitated by the social relations that were established by developing capitalism and
                contributed to increasing social disparities. Capital and consumerism brought the
                working classes to apathy, and the students considered themselves the chosen ones to
                draw attention to social problems. They wanted not only to explain the world, but to
                change it. Their intention was to “revolutionise the every day life”. Above all, the
                student movements were aimed at establishing students as a political subject of a
                society. </p>
            <p> The student movement marked a certain historical period and was aimed at solving not
                only the problems of that period and but also more long-term ones. All student
                actions had a common purpose – social “purification”. As a consequence of the
                increasing social disparities in the capitalist world, and also in Yugoslavia, the
                students in the developed countries of the West expressed their demands for greater
                social justice. In the Eastern European countries of the Soviet political reality,
                however, the demands for political changes or at least political “loosening” were in
                the forefront. </p>
            <p> Common to all students’ political activities in the late 1960s was the question
                against whom and against what their activities were oriented, what were their
                motives and reasons for action. They also shared their eruptive character, dynamism,
                radical views and goals. Each movement emerged from its own environment, from the
                critical attitude towards it, from the criticism of university system and the
                demands for reforms of the study process. At this stage, they wanted to become a
                subject or better, a partner in the reform of the university and study. This
                “mobilisation” phase was followed by a phase that went beyond the university and
                student problems, questioning wider social issues. The student movement turned into
                a political movement, and students wanted to become an important social subject
                capable of changing the world. They saw themselves as the essence of social change,
                as a substitute for the former revolutionary workers’ movement. </p>
            <p> There were similarities and also great differences between student movements in the
                world, in Europe and even in Yugoslavia, where it evolved differently in various
                university centres. It was the same and very different at the same time. Students
                were solving global problems on a local scale, as the movements in individual
                countries, including Yugoslavia, stemmed from diverse political, economic and social
                conditions. The methods of showing disapproval with the situation at universities
                and in the society were more or less the same everywhere, but the demands and goals
                varied. The student movement in Yugoslavia and Slovenia differed from that in the
                Western and Eastern Europe, as it did not reject the existing political system. It
                supported and approved it, but demanded greater consistency in its implementing. It
                supported the self-management socialism and considered it the best possible
                political system. </p>
            <p> The student movement in Yugoslavia and Slovenia arouse from the social and political
                reality of the 1960s. The outbreak in 1968 coincided with political, economic and
                social conditions emerging from the crisis of economic reform. The problems typical
                for a consumer society, to which Yugoslavia was entering at that time, came out,
                such as increasing social disparities, increasing wealth of selected individuals,
                difficulties in finding employment, looking for work abroad. In the political arena,
                this was a period of conflict between those in favour of greater centralisation and
                those in favour of de-centralisation and greater role of national entities –
                republics, and liberalisation of political and economic relations. The reform in the
                mid-1960s was meant to provide the economy a great momentum, but had many social
                consequences, i.e. consumerism, individuals gaining wealth usually in suspicious
                ways, social differentiation; all of these affected also students. In their public
                appearances in 1968, they clearly condemned these deviations and required
                “corrections”. They wanted to establish an ideal system.</p>
            <ab type="milestone" style="text-align:center">* * *</ab>
            <p> The student movement in Europe is closely connected with the year 1968. Not only in
                European but also in the Yugoslav history, this year has a special significance. It
                was a turning point in many aspects. There were a number of events which shook the
                Yugoslav political reality, in particular the Yugoslav political leaders, who had to
                start searching for different solutions to the pressing problems. The student
                demonstrations in Belgrade in early June 1968 caused the first serious political
                uproar. “The Prague Spring” – an attempt of the new leadership to bring more
                democracy to the social system was also felt in Yugoslavia. The Yugoslav political
                leaders approved of the events in the Czechoslovakia and during his visit to Moscow
                in April 1968, Tito tried to dissuade his counterpart Brežnjev from interfering in
                the Czechoslovak internal affairs. When Brežnjev decided for an armed “defence” of
                socialism and sent the armed forces of five Warsaw Pact countries to Czechoslovakia
                on 21 August 1968, the Yugoslav party leadership condemned the intervention and
                believed it was in fact a demonstration of power to Yugoslavia.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn4" n="3"> Jože Pirjevec, <hi rend="italic">Jugoslavija 1918-1992: nastanek, razvoj ter razpad Karadjordjevićeve in
                            Titove Jugoslavije</hi> (Koper: Lipa, 1995), 276.</note>
            </p>
            <p> In 1968, Slovenia and Yugoslavia entered the phase of “core liberalism”.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn5" n="4"> Božo Repe, <hi rend="italic">“Liberalizem” v Sloveniji</hi> (Ljubljana: RO ZZB NOV
                        Slovenije, 1992), 67.</note> The “party liberalism”, which was supposed
                to change the manner of operation within the party and also within the state and its
                    system,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn6" n="5"> The
                        “liberals” wanted to change the manner of governing, but not the political
                        system: socialism and self-management. They advocated the “correction” of
                        the Yugoslav socialism, in particular in the economy; as for the political
                        relations, they emphasised the need for rearranging the relations in the
                        federative state, notably between the “centre” and the republics.</note>
                marked the politics in the following years, up to its ending in 1972. The emergence
                and the end of the student movement and the “party liberalism” thus roughly
                coincided. Like “liberalism”, also student movement was swept away by the storm of
                “pseudo-revolution”, which after 1972 spread all over the Yugoslav society and was
                manifested in the overall “proletarization”. </p>
            <p rend="header"> It is difficult to decide where to place the student movement in the
                political struggle between the “liberal” and the “conservative” political poles.
                Their demands for greater efficiency of the socialist self -management political
                system were close to the “conservative” beliefs. “Conservatives” controlled the
                leadership of the party (the Union of Communists of Slovenia), whereas the party
                “liberals” were concentrated in the government. Although students chose the state
                authority as their main “adversary”, they were also very critical to the rigid party
                leadership. They were aware that it was the party that was behind the government and
                that it was not ready to change. Students supported the socialist self-management
                system, but they required the changes that would make it more efficient, democratic
                and humane.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn7" n="6"> See
                        “programme” of May 1970, <hi rend="italic">Tribuna</hi>, Nov. 1970.
                    “Revolucioniranje družbe in univerze,” in: Ciril Baškovič et al., <hi rend="italic">Študentsko
                            gibanje: 1968-72</hi>, (Ljubljana:
                        Republiška konferenca ZSMS, Univerzitetna konferenca ZSMS, 1982),
                    77-80.</note>
            </p>
            <p rend="header">The student movement in Ljubljana was thus on the one side an
                expression of anti-capitalist views, and on the other side a criticism of communist
                power in Yugoslavia. Students in fact fought for communism against “communism”.</p>
            <p rend="header" style="text-align:center;">* * *</p>
            <p> Most student protests in the world sparked off in 1968. Everywhere they happened
                suddenly and spontaneously. The reasons behind them varied. Although usually the
                eventual reason for a student revolt was rather banal, marginal, the real causes
                became clearer later. The problems which at first seemed marginal turned to be
                crucial. Although it all started in Germany at the beginning of the year, Paris soon
                became the epicentre of the student unrest in Europe, witnessing heavy student
                protests. Barricades were erected. Students were supported by workers' general
                strike, which caused a chaos in France and put at risk the authority of General De
                Gaulle. Student protests started also in the Eastern European countries and in
                Yugoslavia. They were not mere imitations of protests in the capitalist countries,
                because they had different reasons and demands. In Prague, student protests were
                sparked off by poor living conditions, but soon also demands for democratisation
                were expressed, thus supporting the views of the “Prague Spring”. In Poland, the
                authorities set the workers against the students. </p>
            <p> In Belgrade, the student unrests started in early June 1968. The reason was truly
                banal: they could not agree who would occupy more sits to watch some show, students
                or brigadiers. After the fight broke out, the police intervened with force. This led
                to a student uprising. Students were exasperated at the brutality and relentlessness
                of the police, who prevented them to march from the campus to the city centre. At
                first, students had no programme or specific goals. These were only formulated after
                the fight with the police, as police represented the authorities. They formulated
                their political and social demands and addressed them to the authorities. They
                protested against the inconsistencies of the Yugoslav society, but mostly from the
                perspective of the situation in Serbia and Belgrade. They called for more
                consistency in functioning of the socialist self-management system, for less social
                inequalities, in short, they demanded a better socialism. A few days after the
                protests, the president of the state and the party Tito commented it on the TV.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn8" n="7"> Baškovič et al.
                            <hi rend="italic">Študentsko gibanje 68-72</hi> (Ljubljana: Republiška
                        konferenca ZSMS, Univerzitetna konferenca ZSMS, 1982), 36. It is a
                        collection of 227 documents, notably articles published in the student
                        magazine Tribuna in the period 1968-1972.</note> In
                principle, he supported the students and this was the sole example in the world that
                the president of the state and the governing party supported the demands of the
                students. He also said that if he was not capable of solving the problems expressed
                by the students, he could no longer stay on his present position. On the other hand,
                he was also a little insulted, as given the scope of these protests Yugoslavia lost
                the status of being a non-conflict state. <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn9" n="8"> SI AS 1589, Stenografske beleške sa IX. zajedničke
                        sednice Predsedništva in Izvršnog komitete CK SKJ, održane 9. VI. 1968, 77.
                    </note>
            </p>
            <p> Also in Slovenia (in Ljubljana, at that time the only Slovene university) the
                student movement as a political subject emerged for the first time in 1968. On 6
                June 1968 students organised a protest meeting in the student campus, because the
                management of the campus decided to let student rooms to tourists during the summer,
                which is why students had to vacate them. At the same time, the management also
                announced to raise the prices of rents. This led to the beginning of organised
                students’ movement at the Ljubljana University. Although these reasons seem banal,
                there were in fact deeper motives behind them, with a social connotation. The
                students expressed social demands, such as “Also students from poor families should
                study, not only those from wealthy families”. They demanded greater role of students
                in managing the university, and they also reacted to the pressing social issues,
                such as gaining of wealth in dishonest ways, experts leaving the country to work
                    abroad.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn10" n="9">
                        Students largely opposed to the experts leaving the country to work abroad –
                        the “gastarbajterstvo”, which was very common in Yugoslavia after the
                        economic reform in 1965. State employment services arranged the work abroad.
                        In the period 1964–1969, 62,347 persons went to work to the Western-European
                        countries through the state employment offices. </note> One of the
                positions of the students was: “We want to use our knowledge at home”.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn11" n="10">
                    Baškovič et. al., <hi rend="italic">Študentsko gibanje 68-72</hi>, 18, 19.</note> Around
                3000 students participated in the protests, and even representatives of Slovene
                government. The government expressed its readiness to listen to the students. It
                obviously feared the protests to get out of control. Despite the concurrence of the
                protests in Ljubljana and Belgrade, there was no connection between the two. The
                demands were nevertheless similar, e.g. unfair gaining of wealth. Student in
                Ljubljana only found out about the protests in Belgrade through private channels,
                i.e. letters from their friends in Belgrade. </p>
            <p> Also the student movement in Slovenia went through different phases, from the “trade
                unionist” demands stemming from worsening of students’ material conditions to
                political demands. The political demands of students did, however, not go beyond the
                critical attitude to social discrimination and requests for social justice. In the
                following years however, the movement at the Ljubljana University became more
                radical and also political. It turned into a true student movement in terms of their
                demands and methods of work. This could largely be attributed to the students of
                social sciences, who by then took over the initiative of the student movement. </p>
            <p> In 1969 and 1970, the student movement in Ljubljana focused their criticism to the
                foreign policy area and since 1970, they decisively intervened also in political
                questions, in particular those with the international dimension. </p>
            <p> The foreign policy situation revived the students’ activities in Ljubljana. It was
                one of the main reasons for activation and radicalisation of student movement in
                Ljubljana. It all started on 14 May 1970, when a mass protest was organised against
                the USA military interventions in Cambodia.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn12" n="11"> Ibid., 83-88.</note> The protest took place in
                the student campus, but the students also marched through the city centre burning
                American and Soviet flags, which hung out all around the town because of the world
                basketball championship. They called out slogans such as “Let’s exterminate
                Pentagon”, “To Vietnam with Coca-Cola”, “Vietnam – Czechoslovakia”, “Yankee go
                home”, “Peace-Freedom”, etc.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn13" n="12"> Ibid., 86.</note> They protested against the visit
                of the American President Nixon to Yugoslavia and against Yugoslavia’s too friendly
                relationship with the Greek military regime.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn14" n="13"> Ibid., 83, 84.</note> They were in general very
                critical to the Yugoslav foreign policy, to individual countries and leaders. In
                their letters to the Foreign Ministry, they demanded the Yugoslav government to
                break the contacts with non-democratic regimes in the world. Students reacted
                against all forms of fascism in the world by criticising the attitude of the
                Yugoslav authorities towards these phenomena. The Ljubljana student movement was in
                general – like other movements worldwide – a pacifist one. </p>
            <p> Students in Ljubljana paid particular attention to the problems of Slovene minority
                in Austria and Italy.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn15" n="14"> Ibid., 111-20.</note> As a result of the fascist
                actions in Trieste and the Italian Foreign Minister Aldo Moro claiming Italy’s
                rights to the former zone B, they organised a protest on 12 December 1970,
                assembling 8000 people, among whom also the inhabitants of Ljubljana. They called it
                a national and not a political protest meeting, a “spontaneous political move aiming
                at the plebiscite unity of Slovene students, youth and other citizens.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn16" n="15"> Ibid.,
                    116, 117.</note> In their letters to Tito, Foreign Ministry, and Yugoslav
                Assembly, they addressed their demands for a different Yugoslav policy towards
                Slovenes in the neighbouring countries. </p>
            <p> In the autumn 1970, the “international« issues were replaced by domestic ones. The
                student movement in Ljubljana became engaged also in the internal policy. They
                organised a literary marathon and a “teach inn” at the Faculty of Arts. Arresting
                and convicting one of the student leaders at the Belgrade University was the motive
                for their political engagement. The intellectual “elite” from the Faculty of Arts
                took over the leadership of the student movement. </p>
            <p>The Ljubljana student movement obtained a political dimension and became massive in
                the spring 1971. </p>
            <p> In April 1971, the students in Ljubljana moved from the “forum” work to the streets.
                Students went public and their demands to the authorities went beyond the merely
                student questions. Student activists understood this as a form of “direct
                democracy”. Student movement became a part of the town, a part of the urban
                environment as the student protests moved to the very centre of Ljubljana. </p>
            <p> It started with the protest meeting on 14 April 1971, when students assembled on the
                road which passed along the Faculty of Arts, some other faculties and a high school.
                With this meeting, around 2000 students wanted to draw the attention of the
                government and the public to unbearable study conditions. The reason was in fact
                “ecological”. The road passing the faculties was in fact the main transit line for
                heavy trucks travelling from the West to the East of Europe. Because of the
                impossible conditions for study (noise and trembling of the houses), students
                demanded the heavy traffic to be moved out of the city centre. However, at the
                initiative of more radical student functionaries, this peaceful one-hour meeting
                turned into a spontaneous march to the city centre, where it was stopped by a cordon
                of helmeted police. The demonstrations ended quietly after three hours, although
                some calls were heard for a combat with the police. A poet Milan Jesih was even
                charged before court for “agitating for revolt and physical violence”, when he –
                under the influence of alcohol – metaphorically called for a more radical student
                action saying: “Too bad we didn’t make the barricades, put our snipers behind them
                and let them shoot the police straight between their eyes”. This was the first court
                proceeding of the authorities against students. It was followed by two more, which
                resulted in the radicalisation of the student movement. It became a fight against
                the repression of the state for expressing political opinion and demanding a more
                efficient state, which the authorities understood as criticism and opposition. </p>
            <p> In late April, there was another hustling between the students and the police, when
                a group of fifty students protested against the visit of the president of the French
                Government Chaban-Delmas to Ljubljana; they were expressing support to the French
                left-wing movement by shouting “Vive le mai 68”, “Vive l'idée du mai 68”, “Long live
                the Paris Commune” (it was the 100 anniversary of the Paris Commune), “Down with
                bourgeoisie” and similar<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn17" n="16"> Ibid., 145.</note> and they sang the
                Internationale. These demonstrations were stopped by the police. </p>
            <p> The interventions of the police and the National Security Service and the court
                proceedings that followed provoked a conflict between the students and the state
                authorities. The repressive measures against the students led to the climax of
                student movement in Ljubljana, when students occupied for eight days the premises of
                the Faculty of Arts. The authorities’ assessment was that the student movement could
                eventually become so radical that it would turn to violence. They understood the
                paroles that hung out on the walls of the Faculty of Arts saying: “Students, it is
                time for a guerrilla, let us resist authoritarianism, and the rise of capitalism!”
                as a call for action against the authorities as well as an insult to the political
                system. What the author of the text had in mind was students’ unconventional action;
                he expressed an opposition to the inflow of foreign capital to the Yugoslav economy
                in a “leftist” manner, because it was supposed to deny socialism and the
                self-management system. The police confiscated the poster and initiated criminal
                proceedings against the author; it also prohibited the public tribune where students
                wanted to raise the questions of noise, pollution and destruction of the nature as a
                sign of “hypocritical politics of the society ruled by alienation”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn18" n="17"> Iztok Ilich, “Naša pomlad 1971,”
                        in: <hi rend="italic">Pričevanja, december 1985: študentske pomladi,</hi> 88.</note>; as a consequence, also the student leadership reacted. They
                demanded that the police dismissed all criminal charges against the students. When
                receiving no answer from the court with regard to the criminal proceedings against
                the three students charged with attempts of a violent overturn of the social and
                state system, physical revolt and hostile propaganda, they decided for the
                occupation of the Faculty of Arts. On May 1971, students occupied the faculty and
                turned it into the “working colony”. They organised debates, lectures, roundtables.
                Every morning they raised a red flag on the faculty roof singing the International.
                Professors and the faculty leadership supported them, as did the students from other
                faculties. Also the university organisation of the Union of Communists agreed with
                them, finding out that it was “the best school of self-management democracy and of
                self-raising the revolutionary awareness” and that “the development of the student
                movement was basically a very positive process, which is a constituent part of the
                democratisation of the society”, because “the essential characteristic of the
                ideological and political thinking of the students was their desire to achieve a
                better, more humane socialism very quickly, over the night.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn19" n="18">
                    Baškovič et. al., <hi rend="italic">Študentsko gibanje 68-72</hi>, 210, 303.</note></p>
            <p> Apart from the demands which provoked the occupation of the faculty, students also
                called for an improvement of the situation in the society, for general
                democratisation, for more clarity in economic and political decisions, etc.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn20" n="19"> Ibid.,
                    170.</note> Therefore, the student movement understood the occupation of the
                faculty as a protest against the authorities’ reaction to “certain forms of student
                movement”, which in their opinion betrayed the basic “self-management principles of
                our society”.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn21" n="20">
                        Ibid., 201.</note> In the opinion of students, the reasons for such a
                reaction lied in the social relations, inefficient economic policy, social
                disparities (students warned against the “red bourgeoisie”), poor social position of
                the university and intellectuals in the society, as well as in “insufficient
                activity of the Union of Communists”.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn22" n="21"> Ibid., 206. (5.5.5)</note> They saw the occupation
                as a means of amending the political and economic system and not as a means of
                change. “The society is free only if it dares to face the truth,” was the position
                of the student movement. In the occupation, they saw “a protest against everything
                that enslaves and takes away freedom, against alienation; it is a manifestation of
                our freedom and serious distress”. They wrote in the Manifest of the occupied
                Faculty of Arts: “By fighting for freedom of thought and freedom of science, we do
                not fight for power”. They called for more radical self-management, for its
                realisation, as this was the goal of all reforms. The student movement supported
                socialism, but required better relations in the society. It was enshrined in the
                slogan “for communism against ‘communism’”, and in “Our movement is a fight for
                    socialism.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn23" n="22">
                        Ibid, 167, 204. </note> They justified their action by the fact that
                “nobody and nothing except our own conscious action could assure us socialism”. They
                believed that the party – the Union of Communists – should “become the conscience of
                the society” and has to “preserve its guerrilla character in its relation to
                institutions”. It was in fact an appeal for the “party” to withdraw from the state
                authority, from “the Stalinist concept of the party”.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn24" n="23"> Ibid, 202, 203.</note></p>
            <p> The occupation ended after eight days. There was no special reaction to it from the
                authority. Media did not report much about it, which disturbed the students. The
                main newspaper “Delo” even tried to discredit them with an article about student
                demonstrations on the occasion of the visit of Chaban-Delmas, by saying that
                students called him a fascist. They believed the article caused them political
                damage and required a corrigendum. In the protests against the manipulations of the
                media, there are some similarities with the events in Berlin in 1968, when students
                fought against the Springer press. </p>
            <p> The student movement in Ljubljana as a critical political factor thus culminated
                with the occupation of the Faculty of Arts. After this act, the mass activity of the
                movement waned. By many supporters leaving, it eventually broke up. Only the
                hard-line activist leaders with the most radical views remained active. They
                expressed their views in the magazine Tribuna, which was often confiscated. A group
                of students which also took part in the occupation of the Faculty of Arts tried to
                organise a left-wing “student party”, which was to preserve ‘the revolutionary air’
                of the spring 1971. But still, the student movement was on the decline. </p>
            <p> In the memories of student leaders, their activities of 1971 got mythical
                dimensions. They were convinced that their mission was to open the eyes of the
                people and the authorities. They aspired for being the representatives of the
                society who wanted a change. But criticism was also heard that “despite their
                pretentious words, they were just at the beginning, their actions were improvised,
                insufficient and superficial, only a little or even nothing was in fact achieved and
                their declarative equalisation with proletariat was in fact only a “masturbating”
                pretentiousness”.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn25" n="24"> Ibid, 222. Mladen Dolar, “Prove yourself alive,” <hi rend="italic">Tribuna</hi>, No. 1, 10. 10. 1971, 4.</note> One of
                the more radical student leaders said soon after the climax of the student movement:
                “My first impression is that we exaggerated. We exaggerated about the significance
                of our actions. We thought we were so important, but we were only nagging students
                whom only a few listened and almost none took seriously”.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn26" n="25"> Iztok Ilich: “Naša pomlad 1971.”
                        In: <hi rend="italic">Pričevanja, December 1985: študentske pomladi</hi>, 179, (Jaša
                        Zlobec).</note></p>
            <ab type="milestone" style="text-align:center">* * *</ab>
            <p> The public opinion poll conducted in 1969 revealed how the public saw the student
                movements. It was made only a year after the student demonstrations stirred Europe
                and Yugoslavia in 1968. According to the poll, people considered social issues to be
                the main reasons for student protests in Slovenia, i.e. poor employment
                opportunities, low value of the work of experts and their leaving for work abroad,
                poor material conditions of students and limited opportunities for study: the
                problem of scholarships. More than a half of the surveyed people were favourably
                inclined to student protests. Only a small proportion (from 4 to 10%) considered
                student protests an expression of political problems; they believed students
                protested against the inconsistency of politics, discrepancy between the promises,
                declarations and practice, little opportunities for self-management at the
                university and inability of students to have any say within the university system,
                as well as a protest against bureaucracy and non-democratic actions of the
                authorities. A part of the public considered student protests only a replication of
                protests abroad, thus denying the students being a political subject. There was also
                a “hostile” position to students, saying that they were doing too well, that they
                did not know what they wanted, that the society and authorities were too generous to
                them and that they exploited democracy. Some said that it was not a student movement
                at all but only an activity of some eccentric individuals. The Slovene public
                considered protests more as a unique student action than an activity which was
                thought to awake also other layers of the population. The public opinion did not
                acknowledge student movement the role of a critical voice against the basic
                contradictions in the society.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn27" n="26"> Peter Klinar, “Vzroki študentskih nemirov in
                        protestov,” <hi rend="italic">Teorija in praksa: revija za družbena
                            vprašanja</hi> 8, No. 3 (1971): 386, 395.</note> In 1971, when
                students wanted to “revolutionise” the society, the public opinion was not explored,
                but it most likely remained basically the same: reserved and “conservative”.</p>
            <p> The student movement in Ljubljana and elsewhere in the late 1960s and early 1970s
                could be described as diverse and interesting. If judged by the mark it left on the
                history, it could also be described as being “much ado about nothing”. It is above
                all a nice memory of its creators on their youth and ideals of that time.</p>
            
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="bibliography">
                <head>Sources and Literature</head>
            <list type="unordered">
                <head><hi style="font-size:10pt">Sources:</hi></head>
                <item>SI AS, Arhiv Republike Slovenije: <list>
                    <item>AS 1589, Stenografske beleške sa IX.
                    zajedničke sednice Predsedništva in Izvršnog komitete CK SKJ, održane 9. VI.
                    1968, 77. </item></list></item>
            </list>
            <listBibl>
                <head>Literature:</head>
                <bibl>“Revolucioniranje družbe in universe.” In: <hi rend="italic">Študentsko
                    gibanje: 1968-72</hi>. Ljubljana: Republiška konferenca ZSMS, Univerzitetna
                    konferenca ZSMS, 1982.</bibl>
                <bibl>Ilich, Iztok. “Naša pomlad 1971.” In: <hi rend="italic">Pričevanja, december
                    1985: študentske pomladi</hi>, edited by Iztok Ilich, Darko Štrajn, and Jaša
                    L. Zlobec. Ljubljana: Partizanska knjiga, 1986.</bibl>
                <bibl>Klinar, Peter. “Vzroki študentskih nemirov in protestov.” <hi rend="italic">Teorija in praksa: revija za družbena vprašanja</hi>, 8, No. 3 (1971):
                    381-96.</bibl>
                <bibl>Pirjevec, Jože.
                    <hi rend="italic">Jugoslavija 1918-1992: nastanek, razvoj
                        ter razpad Karadjordjevićeve in Titove Jugoslavije.</hi>
                    Koper: Lipa, 1995.</bibl>
                <bibl>Repe, Božo.
                    <hi rend="italic">“Liberalizem” v Sloveniji</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt">. Ljubljana: RO ZZB NOV Slovenije, 1992.</hi>
                </bibl>
                <bibl><hi style="font-size:10pt">Štrajn, Darko. “Nekoč je bilo študentsko gibanje?.”
                    In:</hi>
                    <hi rend="italic">Pričevanja, december 1985: študentske
                        pomladi</hi>, edited by Iztok Ilich, Darko Štrajn, Jaša L. Zlobec. Ljubljana: Partizanska knjiga, 1986.
                </bibl>
                <bibl><hi rend="italic">Tribuna.</hi> “Prove yourself alive.” October 10,
                    1971.</bibl>
            </listBibl>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Printed Sources:</head>
                    <bibl>Baškovič, Ciril, Pavle Gantar, Marjan Pungartnik, and Pavle Zgaga. <hi rend="italic">Študentsko gibanje 1968/72</hi>. Ljubljana Republiška
                        konferenca ZSMS, Univerzitetna konferenca ZSMS, 1982.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
            <div type="summary">
                <docAuthor>Zdenko Čepič</docAuthor>
                <head><hi rend="allcaps">The student
                movement 1968/1971 in Ljubljana in wider context</hi></head>
            <head><hi rend="allcaps">Summary</hi></head>
            <p>
                Mass student movements were a characteristic of the late
                    1960s throughout the world. In Yugoslavia and in Slovenia, too. The student
                    movement in Europe is closely connected with the year 1968. Not only in European
                    but also in the Yugoslav history, this year has a special significance. The
                    student movement is »a specific phenomenon of a relatively mass protest on the
                    world scale. We can speak of the student movement as a historical phenomenon in
                    particular in the late 1960s, when it was an organised political activity of
                    students aimed at achieving certain political goals. The student movements –
                    given the lack of any formal connectedness (organisational or substantive)
                    between the students’ activities in various countries – were largely political.
                    They emerged as a critical “conscience” of economic and social relations and the
                    contradictions in the society. They had ideological roots in Marxism and had a
                    character of a “new leftist” movement. Common to all students’ political
                    activities in the late 1960s was the question against whom and against what
                    their activities were oriented, what were their motives and reasons for action.
                    There were similarities and also great differences between student movements in
                    the world, in Europe and even in Yugoslavia, where it evolved differently in
                    various university centres. It was the same and very different at the same time.
                    The student movement in Yugoslavia and Slovenia arouse from the social and
                    political reality of the 1960s. In Yugoslavia, students advocated socialism, but
                    they wanted to make it better, more humane. Students supported the socialist
                    self-management system, but they required the changes that would make it more
                    efficient, democratic and humane.
            </p>
            <p>
                The student demonstrations in Belgrade in early June 1968
                    caused the first serious political uproar. The reason was truly banal: they
                    could not agree who would occupy more sits to watch some show, students or
                    brigadiers. After the fight broke out, the police intervened with force. This
                    led to a student uprising. At first, students had no programme or specific
                    goals. These were only formulated after the fight with the police. Also in
                    Slovenia, in Ljubljana (at that time the only Slovene university) the student
                    movement as a political subject emerged for the first time in 1968. On 6 June
                    1968 students organised a protest meeting in the student campus, because the
                    management of the campus decided to let student rooms to tourists during the
                    summer, which is why students had to vacate them. At the same time, the
                    management also announced to raise the prices of rents. This led to the
                    beginning of organised students’ movement at the Ljubljana University. Although
                    these reasons seem banal, there were in fact deeper motives behind them, with a
                    social connotation. Also the student movement in Slovenia went through different
                    phases, from the “trade unionist” demands stemming from worsening of students’
                    material conditions to political demands. In the following years however, the
                    movement at the Ljubljana University became more radical and also political. It
                    turned into a true student movement in terms of their demands and methods of
                    work. In 1969 and 1970, the student movement in Ljubljana focused their
                    criticism to the foreign policy area and since 1970, they decisively intervened
                    also in political questions, in particular those with the international
                    dimension (Vietnam War, Cambodia, Greek military regime, problems of Slovene
                    minority in Austria and Italy). In the autumn 1970, the »international« issues
                    were replaced by domestic ones. The student movement in Ljubljana became engaged
                    also in the internal policy. The Ljubljana student movement obtained a political
                    dimension and became massive in the spring 1971. The student movement in
                    Ljubljana was thus on the one side an expression of anti-capitalist views, and
                    on the other side a criticism of communist power in Yugoslavia. Students in fact
                    fought for communism against “communism”. In April 1971, the students in
                    Ljubljana moved from the “forum” work to the streets. It started with the
                    protest meeting on 14 April 1971, when students assembled on the road which
                    passed along the Faculty of Arts; around 2000 students wanted to draw the
                    attention of the government and the public to unbearable study conditions. The
                    reason was in fact “ecological”. Road passing the faculties was in fact the main
                    transit line for heavy trucks travelling from the West to the East of Europe.
                    This peaceful one-hour meeting turned into a spontaneous march to the city
                    centre, where it was stopped by a cordon of helmeted police. The demonstrations
                    ended quietly after three hours. The repressive measures against the students
                    led to the climax of student movement in Ljubljana, when students occupied for
                    eight days the premises of the Faculty of Arts. The authorities’ assessment was
                    that the student movement could eventually become so radical that it would turn
                    to violence. On May 1971, students occupied the faculty and turned it into the
                    “working colony”. They organised debates, lectures, roundtables. Every morning
                    they raised a red flag on the faculty roof singing the International. Professors
                    and the faculty leadership supported them, as did the students from other
                    faculties. Apart from the demands which provoked the occupation of the faculty,
                    students also called for an improvement of the situation in the society, for
                    general democratisation, for more clarity in economic and political decisions,
                    etc. The student movement supported socialism, but required better relations in
                    the society. The occupation ended after eight days. There was no special
                    reaction to it from the authority. The student movement in Ljubljana as a
                    critical political factor thus culminated with the occupation of the Faculty of
                    Arts. After this act, the mass activity of the movement waned.
            </p></div>
            <div type="summary" xml:lang="sl">
                <docAuthor>Zdenko Čepič</docAuthor>
            <head><hi rend="allcaps">Študentsko
                gibanje v Ljubljani 1968/1971 v širšem kontekstu</hi></head>
            <head>POVZETEK</head>
            <p>
                Študentsko gibanje je specifični fenomen svetovnega
                    značaja. O študentskem gibanju kot zgodovinskem pojavu je moč govoriti zlasti ob
                    koncu šestdesetih let 20. stoletja, ko je šlo za organizirano politično
                    dejavnost študentov po vsem svetu, ki so želeli doseči določene politične
                    cilje. Študentsko gibanje je bilo predvsem politično usmerjeno, čeprav ni imelo
                    neke formalne organizacijske niti vsebinske povezave med študenti in njihovo
                    dejavnostjo v posameznih državah. Nastalo je kot kritična »vest« ekonomskih in
                    iz njih izhajajočih socialnih razmerij in protislovij takratne družbe v
                    različnih državah. Ideološko se je naslanjalo na marksizem in je imelo značaj t.
                    i. novolevičarstva. V Jugoslaviji so poudarjeno zagovarjali socializem in ga
                    želeli napraviti boljšega, bolj človeškega. Skupna točka politične dejavnosti
                    študentov ob koncu šestdesetih let je bilo vprašanje proti komu in proti čemu je
                    bila usmerjena ta dejavnost, kakšni so bili vzroki in kakšni povodi. Med
                    študentskim gibanjem po svetu, v Evropi in v Jugoslaviji, kjer se je po
                    različnih univerzitetnih središčih razvijalo različno, so obstajale nekatere
                    podobnosti, pa tudi velike razlike. Bilo je enako in hkrati zelo različno.
                    Študentsko gibanje v Jugoslaviji in v Sloveniji je izhajalo iz družbenih in
                    političnih razmer, ki so opredeljevale jugoslovansko državo v šestdesetih
                    letih.
            </p>
            <p>
                Študentsko gibanje v Evropi je ozko povezano z letom
                    1968. To leto ima v evropski in tudi v jugoslovanski zgodovini posebno mesto in
                    pomen. Bilo je v mnogočem prelomno leto. Študentske demonstracije v Beogradu v
                    začetku junija so povzročile v Jugoslaviji v letu 1968 prvi resni politični
                    pretres. Študenti so bili sicer za politični sistem socialističnega
                    samoupravljanja, vendar so zahtevali spremembe, ki bi le-tega napravil bolj
                    učinkovitega, bolj demokratičnega in bolj humanega. Delovanje študentskega
                    gibanja v Ljubljani je bilo na eni strani izraz protikapitalističnega pogleda
                    študentov, na drugi pa kritika komunističnih oblasti v Jugoslaviji. Borili so se
                    za komunizem proti »komunizmu«.
            </p>
            <p>
                Po svetu (večinoma v Evropi) so študentski protesti
                    večinoma izbruhnili v letu 1968. V Beogradu v začetku junija 1968. Tam so
                    izbruhnili zaradi resnično banalnega povoda: kdo bo zasedel več mest v
                    dvorani na neki zabavni prireditvi, ali študenti ali brigadirji. Po prerivanju
                    in pretepu med njimi je s silo nastopila policija. Njen nastop je povzročil
                    študentske nemire. V Sloveniji (na ljubljanski, tedaj še edini slovenski
                    univerzi) je študentsko gibanje kot politični subjekt tudi nastopilo v letu
                    1968. V študentskem naselju so študenti 6. junija 1968 pripravili zborovanje,
                    ker je vodstvo študentskih domov sklenilo čez poletje oddati študentske sobe
                    turistom, zato naj bi jih študentje izpraznili. Hkrati pa so napovedali
                    podražitev najemnin za posteljo v študentskem naselju. To oboje je sprožilo
                    začetek organiziranega študentskega gibanja na ljubljanski univerzi. Povod zanj
                    je bil na videz banalen, vzroki pa so bili globlji in so bili socialno
                    obarvani.
            </p>
            <p>
                Za študentsko gibanje v Sloveniji so tako tudi značilne
                    stopnje razvoja, od »sindikalističnih« zahtev (imenovane tudi »menzaške«
                    zahteve), ki so izhajale iz slabšanja materialnih pogojev študentov, do
                    politizacije. V naslednjih letih se je študentsko gibanje na ljubljanski
                    univerzi radikaliziralo in je postalo bolj politično. Postalo je pravo
                    študentsko gibanje, ki se je kazalo kot tako po vsebini in načinih delovanja.
                    Študentsko gibanje v Ljubljani se je v letu 1969 in 1970 kritično usmerilo v
                    zunanjepolitično dogajanje. Od spomladi 1970, so študentje bolj odločno posegli
                    v politična dogajanja, zlasti tista povezana z mednarodnim dogajanjem (vojna v
                    Vietnamu, vojna v Kambodži, proti grški vojaški hunti, problemi slovenske
                    manjšine v Avstriji in v Italiji). Jeseni 1970 je »internacionalno« problematiko
                    začela zamenjavati domača. Študentsko gibanje v Ljubljani se je začelo
                    ukvarjati tudi z notranjo politiko. Zares pa je politično vsebino in množičnost
                    dobilo ljubljansko študentsko gibanje spomladi 1971, ko je doseglo vrhunec
                    svojega poslanstva. Aprila 1971 je študentsko gibanje v Ljubljani prešlo iz
                    »forumskega« dela na ulico. Začelo se je s protestnim shodom 14. aprila 1971 na
                    cesti, ob kateri je Filozofska fakulteta in še nekaj drugih fakultet ter srednja
                    šola. S tem protestnim shodom, ki se ga je udeležilo nad 2000 študentov so
                    želeli opozoriti oblasti in javnost na slabe študijske pogoje. Vzrok je bil
                    »ekološki«. Po tej cesti, ki je dejansko v centru mesta, je potekal
               tranzitni promet težkih tovornjakov iz Zahoda na Vzhod
                    Evrope. Študenti so zaradi nemogočih razmer za študij (hrup in tresenje hiš)
                    zahtevali preusmeritev prometa ven iz mestnega središča. Sicer miren enourni
                    protestni shod se je na poziv bolj ‘radikalnih’ študentskih funkcionarjev
                    spremenil v spontan pohod proti mestnemu centru, kjer jih je pričakal kordon
                    policije v čeladah. Zborovanje je preraslo v demonstracijo, ki se je po treh
                    urah mirno končala, čeprav je bilo slišati tudi pozive k spopadu s policijo.
                    Konflikt med študentskim gibanjem in državnimi oblastmi pa so sprožili posegi
                    policije oziroma Službe državne varnosti in sodni postopki proti študentom, ki
                    so izražali svoje mnenje. Oblasti so namreč ocenile, da želi študentsko gibanje
                    svoje delovanje radikalizirati do te mere, da bo začelo nastopati s silo. Povod
                    za vrhunec dejavnosti študentskega gibanja v Ljubljani, ko so študenti za osem
                    dni zasedli Filozofsko fakulteto, so bili represivni ukrepi proti študentom. 26.
                    maja 1971 so študentje zasedli fakulteto in jo spremenili v »delovni kolonijo«.
                    Organizirali so pogovore, predavanja, okrogle mize. Vsako jutro so ob petju
                    Internacionale na strehi fakultete dvignili rdečo zastavo. Podprli so jih
                    profesorji, vodstvo univerze, z njimi so solidarizirali tudi študentje drugih
                    fakultet. Študentske zahteve, poleg tistih, ki so bile povod za zasedbo
                    fakultete, so zadevale urejanje razmer v državi in družbi (obča
                    demokratizacija), več jasnosti pri gospodarskih in političnih odločitvah ipd.
                    Študentsko gibanje je bilo namreč socialistično naravnano, želeli pa so bolj
                    urejene odnose v družbi. Zasedba se je končala po osmih dneh. Neke posebne
                    reakcije proti študentom s strani oblasti ni bilo. Z zasedbo Filozofske
                    fakultete je študentsko gibanje v Ljubljani kot kritični politični dejavnik
                    doseglo svojo najvišjo točko. Po koncu zasedbe Filozofske fakultete pa se je
                    množična aktivnost študentskega gibanja, ki je bilo ob manifestacijah,
                    demonstracijah in drugih množičnih prireditvah množično, nehala. Doživelo je
                    hiter osip in razpad.</p></div>
            </back>
    </text>
</TEI>