<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Filling the Gap in Historical Statistics: Macroeconomic Indicators of the
                    Debt Burden of the Kingdom of Yugoslavia during the Great Depression<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn1" n="*"> Paper presented at the 11<hi
                            rend="superscript">th</hi> SEEMHN Conference, 28 October 2016, National
                        Bank of Romania, Bucharest, Romania "Gaps and Economic Crisis in South-East
                        Europe: Present and Past".</note></title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename>Dragana</forename>
                        <surname>Gnjatović</surname>
                    </name>
                    <roleName>Full Professor</roleName>
                    <roleName>dr</roleName>
                    <affiliation>University of Kragujevac, Faculty for Hotel Management and
                        Tourism</affiliation>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Vojvođanska bb</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>36210 Vrnjačka Banja</addrLine>
                    </address>
                    <email>dragana.gnjatovic@kg.ac.rs</email>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>2017-02-21</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>
                    <orgName xml:lang="sl">Inštitut za novejšo zgodovino</orgName>
                    <orgName xml:lang="en">Institute of Contemporary History</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Kongresni trg 1</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>SI-1000 Ljubljana</addrLine>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>http://ojs.inz.si/pnz/article/view/204</pubPlace>
                <date>2016</date>
                <availability status="free">
                    <licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title xml:lang="sl">Prispevki za novejšo zgodovino</title>
                <title xml:lang="en">Contributions to Contemporary History</title>
                <biblScope unit="volume">57</biblScope>
                <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
                <idno type="ISSN">2463-7807</idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source, born digital.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc xml:lang="en">
                <p>Contributions to Contemporary History is one of the central Slovenian scientific
                    historiographic journals, dedicated to publishing articles from the field of
                    contemporary history (the 19th and 20th century).</p>
                <p>The journal is published three times per year in Slovenian and in the following
                    foreign languages: English, German, Serbian, Croatian, Bosnian, Italian, Slovak
                    and Czech. The articles are all published with abstracts in English and
                    Slovenian as well as summaries in English.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <projectDesc xml:lang="sl">
                <p>Prispevki za novejšo zgodovino je ena osrednjih slovenskih znanstvenih
                    zgodovinopisnih revij, ki objavlja teme s področja novejše zgodovine (19. in 20.
                    stoletje).</p>
                <p>Revija izide trikrat letno v slovenskem jeziku in v naslednjih tujih jezikih:
                    angleščina, nemščina, srbščina, hrvaščina, bosanščina, italijanščina, slovaščina
                    in češčina. Članki izhajajo z izvlečki v angleščini in slovenščini ter povzetki
                    v angleščini.</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="sl"/>
                <language ident="en"/>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords xml:lang="en">
                    <term>public debt</term>
                    <term>Great War</term>
                    <term>Great Depression</term>
                    <term>sovereign debt default</term>
                    <term>Kingdom of Yugoslavia</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords xml:lang="sl">
                    <term>ideološki boj</term>
                    <term>Kranjska</term>
                    <term>socialni program</term>
                    <term>časopisi</term>
                    <term>politika</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change>
                    <date>2017-04-25</date>
                    <name>Neja Blaj Hribar</name>
                    <desc>Pretvorba iz DOCX v TEI, dodatno kodiranje</desc>
                </change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <docAuthor>Dragana Gnjatović<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn2" n="**">
                    <hi rend="bold">Full Professor, University of Kragujevac, Faculty for Hotel
                        Management and Tourism, Vojvođanska bb, 36210 Vrnjačka Banja, <ref
                            target="mailto:dragana.gnjatovic@kg.ac.rs"
                            >dragana.gnjatovic@kg.ac.rs</ref></hi></note></docAuthor>
            <docImprint>
                <idno type="cobissType">Cobiss tip: 1.01</idno>
                <idno type="UDC">UDK: </idno>
            </docImprint>
            <div type="abstract">
                <head>ABSTRACT</head>
                <p><hi rend="italic">The following paper focuses on the specific causes of the
                        sovereign debt default of the Kingdom of Yugoslavia in 1932. In the first
                        part of the paper, the time series of the public debt with the subcategories
                        of domestic and foreign public debt for the period from 1929 to 1939 were
                        constructed on the basis of data from the Statistical Yearbooks of the
                        Kingdom of Yugoslavia and the League of Nations. In the second part of the
                        paper, the sustainability of the Kingdom of Yugoslavia's public debt has
                        been measured with help of relevant macroeconomic indicators: public
                        debt-to-GDP ratio and debt service-to-public revenue ratio. In the third
                        part of the paper, the decomposition of public debt data has been carried
                        out in accordance with the methodology used in the Statistical Yearbook of
                        the Kingdom of Yugoslavia. This decomposition has shown that public debt
                        accumulation had to do little if anything with the Great Depression, and was
                        to a large extent caused by the political, economic and financial
                        consequences of the Great War. </hi></p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Keywords: public debt, Great War, Great Depression, sovereign
                        debt default, Kingdom of Yugoslavia</hi></p>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>

            <div>
                <head>Introduction</head>
                <p>Sovereign debt defaults are not rare historical economic phenomena. In
                    particular, they remain widespread in the periods of global political and
                    economic crises.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn3" n="1"> Kim Oosterlinck,
                        "Sovereign Debt Defaults: Insights from History," <hi rend="italic">Oxford
                            Review of Economic Policy, </hi>29 (4) (2013): 691–714.</note> Among the
                    European countries during the Great Depression (1929–1933), the following states
                    were forced to temporarily suspend regular repayments of foreign debts: Hungary
                    (1931), Austria (1932), Bulgaria (1932), Greece (1932), Germany (1932),
                    Yugoslavia (1932) and Romania (1933).<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn4" n="2">
                        Federico Sturzenegger and Jeromin Zettelmeyer, <hi rend="italic">Debt
                            Defaults and Lessons from a Decade of Crises</hi> (MIT Press, 2007), 7.
                        George Chouliarakis and Sophia Lazaretou, "Déjâ vu? The Greek Crisis
                        Experience, the 2010s <hi rend="italic">versus </hi>the 1930s. Lessons from
                        History," <hi rend="italic">Bank of Greece Working Paper, </hi>No. 176
                        (2014): 23.</note></p>
                <p>In the less developed agrarian countries in Europe, which also included the
                    Kingdom of Yugoslavia, the shortage of foreign currency was the outcome of a
                    drastic decline in the value of agricultural product exports and remittances
                    from emigrants. Furthermore, these countries were obliged to transition to the
                    clearing method of payments in trade with their major trading partners.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn5" n="3"> Barry Eichengreen and Richard Portes,
                        "Debt and Default in the 1930s, Causes and Consequences," <hi rend="italic"
                            >European Economic Review </hi>30 (1986): 599–640.</note></p>
                <p>The value of foreign trade of the Kingdom of Yugoslavia was hit hard by the
                    crisis. From 1929 to 1932, the foreign exchange inflow on current account of the
                    balance of payments decreased from 11.6 billion dinars to 3.9 billion dinars.
                    Revenues from the exports of goods dropped from 7.9 billion to 3.0 billion
                    dinars, exports of services from 2.1 billion dinars to 612 million dinars, and
                    the remittances of emigrants from 888 million dinars to 206 million dinars.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn6" n="4"> Dragana Gnjatović, "Foreign Exchange
                        Policy in the Kingdom of Yugoslavia during and after Great Depression," <hi
                            rend="italic">The Experience of Exchange Rate Regimes in South eastern
                            Europe in a Historical and Comparative Perspective, </hi>OENB Workshops
                        No. 13, (2008): 330–48. </note> In addition, the central government budget
                    for the fiscal year of 1931/32 was left without a regular foreign exchange
                    inflow equivalent to 406 million dinars based on the reparations from
                        Germany.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn7" n="5"> Privilegovana narodna banka
                        Kraljevine Jugoslavije, <hi rend="italic">Godišnji izveštaj 1932
                        </hi>(Belgrade, 1933), XVII.</note> Bilateral clearing agreements had to be
                    concluded with Austria, Czechoslovakia, Belgium and Luxembourg, Italy, France,
                    Switzerland and Germany. They facilitated foreign trade of the country, but
                    further contributed to the shortages of foreign exchange. However, the decline
                    in foreign exchange earnings was only one of the reasons why the Kingdom of
                    Yugoslavia faced the crisis of public debt and was forced to ask the creditors
                    for debt restructuring. Another reason was the continued growth of both foreign
                    and domestic public debt, mainly due to the successive increases in liabilities
                    of the state that have been imposed by the Great War and its territorial,
                    political and financial consequences.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Data sources</head>
                <p>The time series of public debt with the subcategories of domestic and foreign
                    public debt for the period from 1929 to 1939 were constructed on the basis of
                    data from the <hi rend="italic">Statistical Yearbooks</hi> of the Kingdom of
                    Yugoslavia and the League of Nations.</p>
                <p>For 1929, 1930, 1931, and 1932, the public debt was calculated by summing up
                    disaggregated data on debt stock generated from each government domestic and
                    foreign loan, published in the <hi rend="italic">Statistical Yearbook of the
                        Kingdom of Yugoslavia</hi>.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn8" n="6"> In 1932,
                        the Kingdom of Yugoslavia started publishing the <hi rend="italic"
                            >Statistical Yearbook </hi>in Serbian and French, whereas the first
                        volume contained the data for 1929. That is the reason why the time series
                        for public debt start from 1929. – Opšta državna statistika Kraljevine
                        Jugoslavije, <hi rend="italic">Statistički godišnjak Kraljevine Jugoslavije
                            1929</hi> (Belgrade, 1932), 498, 499. Opšta državna statistika
                        Kraljevine Jugoslavije, <hi rend="italic">Statistički godišnjak Kraljevine
                            Jugoslavije 1930</hi> (Belgrade, 1933), 468, 469. Opšta državna
                        statistika Kraljevine Jugoslavije, <hi rend="italic">Statistički godišnjak
                            Kraljevine Jugoslavije 1931</hi> (Belgrade, 1934), 466, 467, 480,
                        481.</note> Given that for 1929, 1930, and 1931 the debt after each foreign
                    loan was expressed in a currency of that particular loan, for aggregate data on
                    the size of external debt for each of these years it was necessary to convert
                    all of the individual data to dinars. For each respective year, the conversion
                    was calculated using the average exchange rates of the French franc, Pound
                    sterling, US dollar and the German mark at the Belgrade Stock Exchange.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn9" n="7">
                        <hi rend="italic">South-Eastern European Monetary and Economic Statistics
                            from the Nineteenth Century to the World War Two </hi>(Athens, Sofia,
                        Bucharest and Vienna: Bank of Greece, Bulgarian National Bank, National Bank
                        of Romania and Oesetreichische Nationalbank, 2014), 350.</note> For the year
                    1932, the data on the public debt for individual loans was presented in the <hi
                        rend="italic">Statistical Yearbook of the Kingdom of Yugoslavia </hi>both in
                    the currency of the loan and in dinars.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn10" n="8">
                        Opšta državna statistika, <hi rend="italic">Statistički godišnjak Kraljevine
                            Jugoslavije 1932 </hi>(Belgrade, 1934), 480.</note></p>
                <p>For the period between 1933 and 1939, the data on the public debt of the Kingdom
                    of Yugoslavia could be found in the<hi rend="italic"> Statistical Yearbook of
                        the League of Nations</hi>.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn11" n="9"> League
                        of Nations,<hi rend="italic"> Statistical Year-Book of the League of Nations
                            1936/37 </hi>(Geneva, 1937), 285. League of Nations (1941):<hi
                            rend="italic"> Statistical Year-Book of the League of Nations
                            1940/41</hi> (Geneva), 288.</note> In fact, starting from 1933, the
                    General Government Statistics of the Kingdom of Yugoslavia ceased to publish the
                    disaggregated data on government debt in its <hi rend="italic">Statistical
                        Yearbook</hi>. Since then, the Yugoslav royal government provided the
                    statistical service of the League of Nations with aggregated data on public
                    debt, with the subcategories of domestic and foreign debt, for all years from
                    1933 to 1939. Since this information was expressed in dinars, the data could be
                    downloaded directly from the <hi rend="italic">Statistical Yearbook of the
                        League of Nations</hi> in order to construct the time series of the public
                    debt for the observed period.</p>
                <p>The data on the nominal national income 1929–1939, calculated on the principle of
                    material production, is from the study of Stevan Stajić: <hi rend="italic"
                        >National Income in Constant and Current Prices 1923</hi>–<hi rend="italic"
                        >1939 </hi>(in Serbian).<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn12" n="10"> Stevan
                        Stajić, <hi rend="italic">Nacionalni dohodak Jugoslavije 1923</hi>–<hi
                            rend="italic">1939 u stalnim i tekućim cenama</hi> (Belgrade: Ekonomski
                        institut, 1959). </note> This study has been accepted internationally as a
                    relevant source of statistical data on the national accounts of the Kingdom of
                        Yugoslavia.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn13" n="11">
                        <hi rend="italic">South-Eastern European Monetary and Economic
                            Statistics</hi>, 335.</note></p>
                <p>The data on public revenue and debt service (principal and interest) is from the
                    statistical publication <hi rend="italic">South-Eastern European Monetary and
                        Economic Statistics from the Nineteenth Century to the World War
                        Two.</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn14" n="12"> Ibid., 351.</note></p>
                <p>The data on foreign debt service for the individual loans in the period from 1923
                    to 1928 was taken from the <hi rend="italic">Annual Reports</hi> of the
                    Privileged National Bank of the Kingdom of SCS.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn15"
                        n="13"> Privilegovana narodna banka Kraljevine SHS, <hi rend="italic"
                            >Godišnji izveštaj 1923 </hi>(Belgrade, 1924), XIV. Privilegovana
                        narodna banka Kraljevine SHS, <hi rend="italic">Godišnji izveštaj 1924
                        </hi>(Belgrade, 1925), XIV. Privilegovana narodna banka Kraljevine SHS, <hi
                            rend="italic">Godišnji izveštaj 1925</hi> (Belgrade, 1926), XIII.
                        Privilegovana narodna banka Kraljevine SHS, <hi rend="italic">Godišnji
                            izveštaj 1926 </hi>(Belgrade, 1927), XV. Privilegovana narodna banka
                        Kraljevine SHS, <hi rend="italic">Godišnji izveštaj 1927 </hi>(Belgrade,
                        1928), XV. Privilegovana narodna banka Kraljevine SHS, <hi rend="italic"
                            >Godišnji izveštaj 1928 </hi>(Belgrade, 1929), XVII. </note></p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Measuring the sustainability of public debt of the Kingdom of
                    Yugoslavia</head>
                <p>The generally accepted indicator of solvency of the state public finances is the
                    state's public debt-to-GDP ratio. In the today's international economic and
                    financial organisations no consensus exists regarding the benchmark for the
                    sustainability of this relationship. During the preparation for the introduction
                    of a single currency, in 1992 the European Union proclaimed that the public debt
                    of a Member State must not exceed 60 % of its GDP if it wants to maintain
                    macroeconomic stability, but the practice has brought this standard into
                        question.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn16" n="14"> Most countries of the
                        Euro Zone are not capable of meeting this criterion. – Dragana Gnjatović,
                        "Fiscal Integration in the European Union," <hi rend="italic">Bankarstvo,
                        </hi>42 (5) (2013): 14–29.</note> In a 2002 study by the International
                    Monetary Fund, however, it was concluded that the external debt-to-GDP ratio
                    higher than 40 % is a sign of a high probability of debt crisis, but "at the
                    same time, it bears emphasizing that a debt ratio above 40 percent of GDP by no
                    means necessarily implies a crisis."<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn17" n="15">
                        International Monetary Fund, <hi rend="italic">Assessing Sustainability</hi>
                        (Washington D.C., 2002), 25. </note> Therefore, the limit for public debt
                    sustainability is not viewed as a statically-defined benchmark. Rather, the
                    public debt-to-national income dynamics is analysed on the basis of the theory
                    of E. Domar, according to which the public debt of a given country could be
                    considered sustainable as long as its national income recorded growth.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn18" n="16"> Evsey D. Domar, "The ‘Burden of the
                        Debt’ and the National Income," <hi rend="italic">American Economic
                            Review</hi> 34 (4), (1944): 798–827.</note> The growth of national
                    income contributes to the growth of fiscal revenues from which the state can
                    regularly service its financial obligations, even when they are increasing due
                    to the growth of public debt. However, any long-term growth of public debt,
                    swifter than that of the national income, brings the debtor country into an
                    unsustainable position. </p>
                <p>Table 1: The public debt of the Kingdom of Yugoslavia 1929-1939, millions of
                    dinars</p>
                <p>Source: Opšta državna statistika Kraljevine Jugoslavije, <hi
                        rend="italic">Statistički godišnjak Kraljevine Jugoslavije 1929</hi>
                    (Belgrade, 1932), 498, 499. Opšta državna statistika Kraljevine Jugoslavije, <hi
                        rend="italic">Statistički godišnjak Kraljevine Jugoslavije 1930</hi>
                    (Belgrade, 1933), 468, 469. Opšta državna statistika Kraljevine Jugoslavije, <hi
                        rend="italic">Statistički godišnjak Kraljevine Jugoslavije 1931
                    </hi>(Belgrade, 1934), 466, 467. League of Nations,<hi rend="italic">
                        Statistical Year-Book of the League of Nations 1936/37</hi> (Geneva, 1937),
                    285. League of Nations (1941):<hi rend="italic"> Statistical Year-Book of the
                        League of Nations 1940/41</hi> (Geneva), 288.</p>
                <p>Chart 1: The public debt of the Kingdom of Yugoslavia
                    1929–1939, millions of dinars</p>
                <p>During the Great Depression, from 1929 to 1932, the decrease of the national
                    income was itself a generator of the public debt crisis. Moreover, at the same
                    time when the country faced a decreasing national income, decline in foreign
                    exchange earnings on the current account, and a drop in budget revenues, the
                    public debt of the Kingdom of Yugoslavia increased from 34.7 billion dinars to
                    38.8 billion dinars and thus the debt burden became untenable. The public debt
                    accumulation in this period was the outcome of growth in both domestic and
                    foreign public debt, resulting in their relatively stable share in the total
                    public debt of 15 % and 85 % respectively. After 1932, however, the total public
                    debt has, on several occasions, decreased due to the reduction of the foreign
                    public debt. Conversely, the domestic public debt kept growing constantly: in
                    1939 the total public debt amounted to 24.6 billion dinars, of which the
                    domestic debt accounted for as much as 12.6 billion dinars or 51.2 % and the
                    foreign debt accounted for 12 billion dinars or </p>
                <p>48.8 % (Table 1).</p>
                <p>Table 2: Indebtedness of the Kingdom of Yugoslavia: public debt-to-national
                    income ratio</p>
                <p>1929–1939</p>
                <p>Source: For national income Stevan Stajić, <hi rend="italic"
                        >Nacionalni dohodak Jugoslavije 1923</hi>–<hi rend="italic">1939 u stalnim i
                        tekućim cenama</hi> (Belgrade: Ekonomski institut, 1959); for public debt:
                    same as for Table 1 </p>
                <p>Chart 2: Indebtedness of the Kingdom of Yugoslavia: public
                    debt-to-national income ratio </p>
                <p>1929–1939</p>
                <p>The indebtedness of the Kingdom of Yugoslavia, as measured by the public
                    debt-to-national income ratio, was constantly worsening. From 1929 to 1932, this
                    ratio increased from 57.8 % to 106.3 %. The domestic public debt-to-national
                    income ratio increased from 8.7 % to 16.5 %, and the foreign public
                    debt-to-national income ratio from 49.1 % to 89.8 % (Table 2). The worsening
                    level of indebtedness was the result of the dwindling national income and the
                    growth of public debt, both domestic and foreign. Only as late as in 1938 was
                    indebtedness reduced to the level comparable with the time before the Great
                    Depression, thanks to the recovery of national income but also due to a drastic
                    cut of foreign public debt.</p>
                <p>Table 3: Public debt service (principal and interest) capacity of the Kingdom of
                    Yugoslavia: Debt service-to-public revenue ratio 1929–1939</p>
                <p>*In the Kingdom of SCS (Yugoslavia), the fiscal year started
                    on 1 April every year and ended on 31 March of the following year.</p>
                <p>Source: <hi rend="italic">South-Eastern European Monetary
                        and Economic Statistics from the Nineteenth Century to the World War
                        Two</hi> (Vienna: Bank of Greece, Bulgarian National Bank, National Bank of
                    Romania, Oesetreichische Nationalbank, Athens, Sofia, Bucharest, 2014), 335.</p>
                <p>The continuously increasing public debt of the Kingdom of Yugoslavia from 1929 to
                    1932 was accompanied by the growth of financial liabilities for debt service.
                    From the 1929/30 to 1932/33 fiscal year, the obligations to service the
                    principal and interest on the public debt increased from 873 million dinars to
                    1.010 billion dinars. At the same time, budget revenues have decreased from 15.9
                    billion dinars to 9.7 billion dinars. Consequently, it was necessary to allocate
                    5.5 % of public revenue towards public debt service in 1929, while in 1932 as
                    much as 10.4 % of public revenue was needed for public debt service (Table
                    3).</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Decomposition of public debt</hi></p>
                <p>In the Kingdom of Yugoslavia, the common denominator of the circumstances giving
                    rise to the public debt accumulation during the Great Depression was the Great
                    War. Debts originated in the time before, during and after the Great War. They
                    were directly or indirectly related to political, territorial, social and
                    economic changes, brought about or caused by World War I. The only loan that was
                    partly intended for the construction of new infrastructure facilities,
                    contracted in 1922 on the American financial market, was only partially realised
                    because the issue of war debts of the Kingdom of Serbia to the United States had
                    to be resolved first.</p>
                <p>The Great War was the main criterion for the classification of public debt in
                    different categories. The General Government Statistics of the Kingdom of
                    Yugoslavia classified public debt into five categories: debt on government bonds
                    issued on local financial market after the Great War (Post-war domestic public
                    debt); debt accumulated in the Kingdoms of Serbia and Montenegro (Direct pre-war
                    debt); war debt to allies of the Kingdom of Serbia (War debt); debt inherited
                    from the Austro-Hungarian Monarchy (Indirect pre-war debt); and debt on foreign
                    loans concluded in the Kingdom of SCS (Yugoslavia) after the Great War (Post-war
                    foreign public debt).</p>
                <p>Table 4: Decomposition of public debt of the Kingdom of Yugoslavia 1929–1932</p>
                <p>*The Kingdom of Yugoslavia did not keep repaying war debt after 1931. The
                    difference in war debt stock between 1931 and 1932 appeared because of the
                    devaluation of Pound sterling after Great Britain had abolished the gold
                    standard.</p>
                <p>Source: Opšta državna statistika Kraljevine Jugoslavije, <hi
                        rend="italic">Statistički godišnjak Kraljevine Jugoslavije 1929</hi>
                    (Belgrade, 1932), 498, 499. Opšta državna statistika Kraljevine Jugoslavije, <hi
                        rend="italic">Statistički godišnjak Kraljevine Jugoslavije 1930</hi>
                    (Belgrade, 1933), 468, 469. Opšta državna statistika Kraljevine Jugoslavije, <hi
                        rend="italic">Statistički godišnjak Kraljevine Jugoslavije 1931</hi>
                    (Belgrade, 1934), 466, 467.</p>
                <p>The analysis of each of these categories of public debt reveals the specific
                    circumstances which made it impossible to avoid public debt accumulation during
                    the Great Depression.</p>
                <div>
                    <head>Post-war domestic public debt</head>
                    <p>Post-war domestic public loans, issued both before and during the Great
                        Depression, were intended to mitigate the consequences of the Great War and
                        the financial liquidation of feudal relations on the agrarian lands in the
                        provinces of the former Ottoman Empire and Austro-Hungarian Monarchy.</p>
                    <p>Before the Great Depression, the Kingdom of SCS issued three domestic loans.
                        The first loan was the so-called Investment Loan, issued in 1921 and
                        amounting to 500 million dinars, with a 7 % interest rate and a repayment
                        period of 50 years. It was aimed at rebuilding the roads demolished during
                        the Great War. This loan was contracted with a syndicate of 108 banks from
                        all over the country. The second loan was the so-called Agrarian Loan, also
                        issued in 1921 and amounting to 130 million dinars, with a 4 % interest rate
                        and a repayment period of 30 years. This was the first tranche of a loan
                        intended for the financial compensation to earlier feudal land owners in
                        Bosnia and Herzegovina, whose land was seized due to the agrarian reform.
                        The third loan was the so-called War Damage Loan, intended for the
                        compensation for war damages suffered by the citizens of Serbia and
                        Montenegro during the Great War. Government bonds for the compensation for
                        war damages were issued between 1923 and 1925, in the nominal amount of 4.9
                        billion dinars, with a 2.5 % interest rate and a repayment period of 50
                            years.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn19" n="17"> Dragana Gnjatović,
                            "Stari državni dugovi, Prilog ekonomskoj i političkoj istoriji Srbije i
                            Jugoslavije 1962-1941," <hi rend="italic">Jugoslovenski pregled</hi>
                            (1991): 133–6.</note></p>
                    <p>At the beginning of the Great Depression in 1929, the domestic public debt of
                        the Kingdom of Yugoslavia amounted to 5.2 billion dinars (Table 5). By 1932,
                        this debt had increased to over 6 billion dinars, as new loans for the
                        financial liquidation of the agrarian reform were issued during the crisis. </p>
                    <p>Table 5: Domestic public debt of the Kingdom of Yugoslavia 1929–1932</p>
                    <p>Source: Opšta državna statistika Kraljevine Jugoslavije,
                            <hi rend="italic">Statistički godišnjak Kraljevine Jugoslavije 1929</hi>
                        (Belgrade, 1932), 498, 499. Opšta državna statistika Kraljevine Jugoslavije,
                            <hi rend="italic">Statistički godišnjak Kraljevine Jugoslavije 1930</hi>
                        (Belgrade, 1933), 468, 469. Opšta državna statistika Kraljevine Jugoslavije,
                            <hi rend="italic">Statistički godišnjak Kraljevine Jugoslavije 1931</hi>
                        (Belgrade, 1934), 466, 467.</p>
                    <p>In the Kingdom of SCS (Yugoslavia), the resistance against the implementation
                        of the agrarian reform was considerable.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn20"
                            n="18"> Ratko Ljubojević, <hi rend="italic">Agrarna politika Kraljevine
                                Jugoslavije za vreme šestojnuarske diktature</hi> (Belgrade<hi
                                rend="italic">: </hi>Naučno društvo agrarnih ekonomista Balkana,
                            2015), 91–6.</note> Therefore a decade had passed before new loans for
                        the financial compensation to the former land owners were issued. During the
                        Great Depression their issuance decreased. In 1930, the first tranche of the
                        new, so-called Beylik Loan intended for the financial compensation of the
                        former feudal land owners in Bosnia and Herzegovina was issued, amounting to
                        150 million dinars, with a 6 % interest rate and a repayment period of 43
                        years. In the following year, 1931, the second tranche of the Beylik Loan
                        was issued under the same conditions, amounting to 200 million dinars.
                        Furthermore, in 1931 the so-called Dalmatian Loan intended for the financial
                        compensation of the former landlords in Dalmatia was issued, amounting to
                        400 million dinars, with a 4% interest rate and a repayment period of 30
                            years.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn21" n="19"> Gnjatović, "Stari
                            državni dugovi," 133–6. </note></p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Direct pre-war debt</head>
                    <p>During the Great Depression, direct pre-war debts of the Kingdom of Serbia
                        tripled as a result of the revaluation of the debts to France.</p>
                    <p>Table 6: Direct pre-war debt stock on the loans revalued by the Convention of
                        5 April 1930, </p>
                    <p>before and after their revaluation to gold francs </p>
                    <p>Source: Opšta državna statistika,<hi rend="italic"
                            >Statistički godišnjak Kraljevine Jugoslavije 1931 </hi>(Belgrade,
                        1934), 466, 467. Opšta državna statistika, <hi rend="italic">Statistički
                            godišnjak Kraljevine Jugoslavije 1932</hi> (Belgrade, 1934), 480,
                        481.</p>
                    <p>After the Great War, the Kingdom of SCS made a commitment to continue to
                        repay 10 foreign loans of the Kingdom of Serbia in the amount of 815.3
                        million dinars in gold: the Lottery Loan (1881), the Loan for repurchase of
                        tobacco monopoly (1888), the Conversion Loan (1895), the Monopoly Loan
                        (1902), the Loan for railroad construction and army modernization I (1906),
                        the Loan for railroad construction and army modernization II (1909), the
                        Loan for Balkan Wars (1913), the Loan of the state mortgage bank <hi
                            rend="italic">Uprava fondova</hi> (1910), the Communal loan of <hi
                            rend="italic">Uprava fondova</hi> (1911), and the Loan of Serbian Red
                        Cross Society (1907). Also, the Kingdom of SCS continued to repay two
                        foreign loans of the Kingdom of Montenegro from 1909 and 1913, in the amount
                        of 17 million dinars in gold.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn22" n="20"> For
                            more information on the loans of the Kingdom of Serbia see: Dragana
                            Gnjatović, "Foreign Long Term Government Loans of Serbia 1862-1914," in:
                                <hi rend="italic">Economic and Financial Stability in SE Europe in a
                                Historical and Comparative Perspective, </hi>ed. Branko Hinić
                            (Belgrade: National Bank of Serbia, Belgrade, 2009), 33–55.</note> The
                        annuities of the first seven loans of the Kingdom of Serbia and both loans
                        of the Kingdom of Montenegro have fallen at the expense of the central
                        government budget, while the annuities of the two <hi rend="italic">Uprava
                            fondova</hi> loans and the loan of the Serbian Red Cross Society
                        continued to be repaid by these public institutions. Loans were repaid in
                        the currencies in which they were contracted, while the loans contracted in
                        France were repaid in the French paper franc that was worth a fifth of the
                        gold franc.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn23" n="21"> League of Nations, <hi
                                rend="italic">International Statistical Year-Book 1927 </hi>(Geneva,
                            1928), 13.</note></p>
                    <p>However, on the basis of the judgment of the Permanent Court of International
                        Justice, on 5 April 1930 the Government of the Kingdom of Yugoslavia signed
                        a Convention with French porters, according to which the remaining debts on
                        the aforementioned French tranches of loans were revalued. According to the
                        letter of the Convention, starting from the 1931/32 fiscal year, not only
                        the aforementioned revalued loans from the Kingdoms of Serbia and
                        Montenegro, but also the two revalued <hi rend="italic">Uprava fondova</hi>
                        loans and the loan of the Serbian Red Cross Society were to be repaid from
                        central government budget. Due to this revaluation, between 1931 and 1932
                        the foreign public debt on loans included in the Convention with French
                        porters increased from 1.4 billion dinars to 5.5 billion dinars (Table
                        6).</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>War debt</head>
                    <p>The Kingdom of SCS regulated the repayment of the war debt to the United
                        States and the United Kingdom before the Great Depression, while the
                        regulation of the war debt to France and surpluses received from Germany on
                        the basis of the Dawes Plan took place precisely in the times of the
                        crisis.</p>
                    <p>After the Great War, the issue of inter-ally debts was resolved, at the
                        request of the United States, by bilateral agreements between the states
                        concerned. The United States signed agreements with Britain in 1923, with
                        Belgium, Italy and Romania in 1925, France and the Kingdom of SCS in 1926,
                        and Greece in 1928. In addition, the agreements with Great Britain and
                        France contained a clause according to which these two countries would repay
                        their war debt to the United States only if they received reparation
                        payments from Germany, under the condition that they regulate their own
                        claims towards other war allies in the same manner.<note place="foot"
                            xml:id="ftn24" n="22"> Veroljub Dugalić, "Ratne reparacije u prošlosti:
                            Obračun i naplata," <hi rend="italic">Finansije, </hi>59 (1-6) (2004),
                            124.</note> In this way, the possibility of the repayment of inter-ally
                        war debts depended directly on the payments of reparations by Germany.<note
                            place="foot" xml:id="ftn25" n="23"> Ivan M. Becić, "Ratni dugovi
                            Kraljevine Jugoslavije u svetlu politike." <hi rend="italic">Istorija
                                20. veka, </hi>28 (3) (2010): 45–56.</note> Immediately after the
                        conclusion of the Peace Treaty of Versailles, it was clear that the
                        reparations imposed on Germany were far beyond its fiscal capacity.<note
                            place="foot" xml:id="ftn26" n="24"> John Maynard Keynes, <hi
                                rend="italic">The Economic Consequences of the Peace </hi>(New York:
                            Harcourt, Brace and Howe, Inc. Pub., 1919), 80–98.</note> In the period
                        between 1 November 1924 and 31 August 1929, Germany repaid war reparations
                        in accordance with the Dawes Plan, according to which the German reparation
                        debt was reduced from 126.3 billion gold marks to 42 billion gold
                            marks.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn27" n="25">
                            From 1924 to 1930, in the name of the reparations from Germany, based on the Dawes Plan, the Kingdom of SCS (Yugoslavia) received 275 million gold marks in money and in kind. –
                            Dugalić, "Ratne reparacije u prošlosti," 118.</note> However, according
                        to the Young Plan of 1929, the German reparation debt was reduced to 33
                        billion gold marks and converted to paper German marks.<note place="foot"
                            xml:id="ftn28" n="26"> Ibid. Ministarstvo finansija Kraljevine
                            Jugoslavije, <hi rend="italic">Ministarstvo finansija 1918</hi>–<hi
                                rend="italic">1938 </hi>(Belgrade, 1938), 205.</note> Finally, at
                        the conference in Lausanne in 1932, a moratorium on the German reparations
                        payments was declared, and afterwards these payments were suspended.</p>
                    <p>Based on the Agreement signed in Washington D.C. on 3 May 1926, the war debt
                        of the Kingdom of Serbia to the United States was determined at the amount
                        of 62.85 million U.S. dollars and a repayment period of 62 years. The war
                        debt to the United Kingdom was regulated by the agreement of 9 August 1927,
                        according to which the Kingdom of SCS agreed to repay the sum of 25,591,428
                        pounds sterling within 62 years, as well as the sum of 3,103,848 pounds
                        sterling within 15 years, in the name of assistance in kind.<note
                            place="foot" xml:id="ftn29" n="27"> Dugalić, "Ratne reparacije u
                            prošlosti."</note></p>
                    <p>The war debt to France was settled as late as in 1930. During the
                        negotiations that began in May 1928, a dispute took place regarding the
                        total amount of debt and how the debt should be repaid. The Kingdom of SCS
                        (Yugoslavia) was of the opinion that the debt should be denominated in paper
                        French francs, while France argued that the debt should be denominated in
                        gold francs.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn30" n="28"> Ministarstvo finansija
                            Kraljevine Jugoslavije, <hi rend="italic">Ministarstvo finansija
                                1918</hi>–<hi rend="italic">1938</hi>, 205</note> The dispute was
                        resolved on 20 January 1930 in favour of the Kingdom of Yugoslavia, and the
                        total sum of this war debt was determined in the amount of 1,024,812,476
                        French francs and a repayment period of 37 years.<note place="foot"
                            xml:id="ftn31" n="29"> Dugalić, "Ratne reparacije u prošlosti,"
                            125.</note> Furthermore, the Yugoslav government agreed to pay to France
                        the sum of 157.3 million German paper marks on behalf of the surpluses
                        received in the last five months of the fifth annuity of the Dawes
                            Plan.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn32" n="30"> Ibid.</note></p>
                    <p>Table 7: War debt repayments of the Kingdom of SHS (Yugoslavia) 1926-1931</p>
                    <p>Source: The same as for Table 4</p>
                    <p>The Kingdom of SCS (Yugoslavia) regularly serviced its war debt until 1931. A
                        total of 569.8 million dinars were repaid, of which 68 million dinars (1.2
                        million U.S. dollars) went to the United States; 450 million dinars (1.66
                        million pounds sterling) went to the United Kingdom; 41.6 million dinars
                        (18.9 million French francs) for the war debt and 10.2 million dinars
                        (758.807 German paper marks) went to France for the surpluses received on
                        behalf of the Dawes Plan (Table 7). After the declaration of the moratorium
                        on German reparation payments at the Lausanne Conference in1932, the Kingdom
                        of Yugoslavia suspended its repayments of war debt. The last instalment of
                        war debt was paid on June 15, 1931, and according to the budget for the
                        1931/32 fiscal year, the following instalment was intended for payment on 15
                        June 1932. However, due to the moratorium on German reparation payments,
                        this financial obligation on the side of the public expenditure was not met.
                        Beginning from the 1933/34 fiscal year, war debt repayments were no longer
                        planned on the side of public expenditure.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn33"
                            n="31"> Privilegovana narodna banka Kraljevine Jugoslavije, <hi
                                rend="italic">Godišnji izveštaj 1932</hi>, XVI.</note></p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Indirect pre-war debt</head>
                    <p>The indirect pre-war (inherited) public debt consisted of state and
                        provincial pre-war Austro-Hungarian debt. At the time of the Great
                        Depression, the repayment of the Austro-Hungarian state debt was suspended
                        for reasons that were not related to the crisis and that the Yugoslav
                        government could not influence. Also, the repayment of the provincial debt
                        started as late as in 1932.</p>
                    <p>The Kingdom of SCS (Yugoslavia) inherited 2.034 % of the Austrian public debt
                        and 14.116 % of the Hungarian public debt from the period before the Great
                        War. The Austrian and Hungarian pre-war public debts emerged from the loans
                        that had been contracted in gold or in multiple currencies and repaid as
                        perpetual annuities. On the basis of the Innsbruck Protocol of 29 June 1923,
                        the Common Treasury was established in Paris (<hi rend="italic">Caisse des
                            porteurs commune des étrangers dettes publiques et autrichienne
                            hongroise émises avant la Guerre</hi>). Its purpose was to service the
                        Austro-Hungarian government bonds in the hands of the French, Belgian,
                        Dutch, Swiss, English, German and Italian porters. The Common Treasury
                        started operating in 1926. In the same year, the Kingdom of SCS began with
                        the regular servicing of the pre-war Austro-Hungarian debts on behalf of
                        five Austro-Hungarian government loans.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn34"
                            n="32"> The state debts, inherited from the Austro-Hungarian Monarchy,
                            included the following: 4 % Austrian gold rent, 4 % Austrian treasury
                            certificates from 1914, 4 % Hungarian gold rent, 4 % Hungarian rent in
                            four currencies from 1913 and 4 % Hungarian rent in four currencies from
                            1914. – Gnjatović, "Stari državni dugovi," 122.</note> From 1926 to
                        1929, the government of SCS paid 244.3 million dinars on behalf of the
                        Austro-Hungarian government loans.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn35" n="33">
                            Privilegovana narodna banka Kraljevine SHS, <hi rend="italic">Godišnji
                                izveštaj 1926, </hi>XV. Privilegovana narodna banka Kraljevine SHS,
                                <hi rend="italic">Godišnji izveštaj 1927,</hi> XV. Privilegovana
                            narodna banka Kraljevine SHS, <hi rend="italic">Godišnji izveštaj
                                1928,</hi> XVII.</note> Between 1930 and 1932, however, their
                        repayments were temporarily suspended. As it was, the creditors were not
                        satisfied with the amount of money they could collect, and they initiated
                        the negotiations for changing the conditions of the repayment of these
                        debts. However, the new agreement did not enter into force and the
                        repayments were to continue in 1933 in line with the original contractual
                            terms.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn36" n="34">
                            Article 9 of the Innsbruck Protocol stipulated
                                that the loans contracted as perpetual annuities should be repayable
                                on a reduced basis of 32 %, while those contracted in multiple
                                currencies should be repayable on a reduced basis of 27 %. In this
                                regard, the Kingdom of SCS was committed to repaying 4,141,735 gold
                                francs on behalf of five Austro-Hungarian government loans. However,
                                on the basis of the Paris Agreement of 31 October 1930, there has
                                been a revision of this article of the Innsbruck Protocol, on the
                                basis of which the Kingdom of Yugoslavia accepted that perpetual
                                annuities should be transformed into loans with fixed maturities,
                                and the debt to Common Treasury in the amount of 273,951,000 gold
                                francs should be repaid within 50 years. This debt was included in
                                the total sum of the public debt, but its servicing was postponed
                                until all State Parties ratified the Paris Agreement. Thus identical
                                amounts owed to Common Treasury in Paris could be found in the lists
                                of public debt stock for the period from 1930 to 1932. As the Paris
                                Agreement had not entered into force because it was not ratified by
                                Hungary, Yugoslavia reverted to the previous legal regime of the
                                repayment of debt, inherited from the Austro-Hungarian Monarchy,
                                which had been defined by the Innsbruck Protocol. –
                            Ministarstvo finansija Kraljevine Jugoslavije, <hi rend="italic"
                                >Ministarstvo finansija 1918</hi>–<hi rend="italic">1938</hi>,
                            204.</note></p>
                    <p>In addition to the obligation of servicing a share of Austro-Hungarian state
                        debt, the Kingdom of SHS assumed the obligation to pay 336 million gold
                        crowns on behalf of the remaining autonomous debts of those provinces that
                        had been parts of the Austro-Hungarian Monarchy before the Great War: Bosnia
                        and Herzegovina, Slavonia and Croatia, Slovenia and Dalmatia.<note
                            place="foot" xml:id="ftn37" n="35"> Gnjatović, "Stari državni dugovi,"
                            126. </note> The terms of servicing these debts had been agreed with the
                        creditors successively, and the agreed sum of each concrete provincial debt
                        would be added to the stock of public debt only upon its regulation.<note
                            place="foot" xml:id="ftn38" n="36">
                            An item of the provincial debt was shown for
                                the first time in a list of the public debt stock of the Kingdom of
                                Yugoslavia in 1932 only: the debt to the Czech Savings Bank in the
                                amount of 1.8 million dinars for servicing Slovenian provincial
                                debts (Table 8).</note></p>
                    <p>Table 8: Indirect pre-war debt 1929-1932, million dinars</p>
                    <p>Source: Opšta državna statistika Kraljevine Jugoslavije,
                            <hi rend="italic">Statistički godišnjak Kraljevine Jugoslavije 1929</hi>
                        (Belgrade, 1932, 498, 499. Opšta državna statistika Kraljevine Jugoslavije,
                            <hi rend="italic">Statistički godišnjak Kraljevine Jugoslavije 1930</hi>
                        (Belgrade, 1933), 468, 469. Opšta državna statistika Kraljevine Jugoslavije,
                            <hi rend="italic">Statistički godišnjak Kraljevine Jugoslavije 1931</hi>
                        (Belgrade, 1934), 466, 467.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Post-war foreign public debt</head>
                    <p>The post-war foreign loans of the Kingdom of SCS, made before the Great
                        Depression, were intended for the construction of a new railway line, the
                        financing of current government expenditure, and the financial compensation
                        of foreign joint stock companies for the nationalised railways. On 1 July
                        1929, the post-war foreign public debt amounted to 7.0 billion dinars and
                        accounted for a fifth of the total public debt. During the Great Depression,
                        the post-war foreign public debt continued to grow for reasons unrelated to
                        the crisis. Only in 1931 did the Yugoslav government manage to make a loan
                        in France for financing the legal stabilisation of the dinar, as it had
                        previously had to agree to the revaluation of debts of the Kingdom of
                        Serbia, and to regulate the war debt to France. Therefore, on 1 July 1932,
                        the post-war foreign public debt of the Kingdom of Yugoslavia amounted to
                        9.1 billion dinars and accounted for one third of the total public debt of
                        the country.</p>
                    <p>From the first foreign loan (Blair's Loan), which the Kingdom of SCS
                        concluded in 1922 on the US financial market, 70 % was to be used for the
                        construction of a new railway line from Belgrade to the Adriatic Sea and 30
                        % for the current government expenditures. However, the railway was not
                        built because only 46.25 million US dollars from the originally agreed 100
                        million US dollars in gold had been realised.<note place="foot"
                            xml:id="ftn39" n="37"> Gnjatović, "Stari državni dugovi," 141.</note>
                        The first tranche amounting to 15.25 million U.S. dollars in gold, with an 8
                        % interest rate and maturity of 40 years, was realised after the conclusion
                        of the loan. The second tranche amounting to 30 million U.S. dollars in
                        gold, with a 7 % interest rate and maturity of 35 years, was realised in
                        1927, only after the Kingdom of SCS had resolved the issue of the repayment
                        of its war debt to the United States.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn40"
                            n="38"> Becić, "Ratni dugovi Kraljevine Jugoslavije."</note> As
                        Yugoslavia ceased to repay the war debt already in 1932, the possibilities
                        to continue the realisation of Blair's Loan were exhausted.</p>
                    <p>The other two foreign loans were intended to cover the current public
                        expenditure. The second foreign loan was used for government procurement in
                        France. It was contracted in 1924, amounted to 300 million French francs
                        with a 5 % interest rate, and had a maturity of 17 years. The third foreign
                        loan was used to cover the expenses of the Autonomous Monopoly
                        Administration. It was contracted in 1928, with a Swedish trust (Swedish
                        Loan), and amounted to 22 million US dollars with a 6.25 % interest rate and
                        maturity of 30 years.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn41" n="39"> Financial
                            resources for the debt service of the Swedish Loan accumulated in a
                            separate amortisation fund established in the Autonomous Monopoly Administration. The loan was repurchased in
                                1937 for one seventh of its nominal value. – Opšta državna
                            statistika, <hi rend="italic">Statistički godišnjak 1932,</hi>
                            481.</note></p>
                    <p>Table 9: Post-was foreign public debt, 1929-1932, in
                        millions of dinars</p>
                    <p>Source: Opšta državna statistika Kraljevine Jugoslavije,
                            <hi rend="italic">Statistički godišnjak Kraljevine Jugoslavije 1929</hi>
                        (Belgrade, 1932), 498, 499. Opšta državna statistika Kraljevine Jugoslavije,
                            <hi rend="italic">Statistički godišnjak Kraljevine Jugoslavije 1930</hi>
                        (Belgrade, 1933), 468, 469. Opšta državna statistika Kraljevine Jugoslavije,
                            <hi rend="italic">Statistički godišnjak Kraljevine Jugoslavije 1931</hi>
                        (Belgrade, 1934), 466, 467.</p>
                    <p>In the process of the nationalisation of the railways throughout the country,
                        the Kingdom of SCS (Yugoslavia) <hi rend="alt-edited1">assumed the
                            obligation to repurchase</hi> the railways from a variety of foreign
                        joint stock companies.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn42" n="40"> Gojko
                            Malović, <hi rend="italic">Saobraćaj i veze u Kraljevini Jugoslaviji
                                1918</hi>–<hi rend="italic">1941 </hi>(Belgrade: Arhiv Jugoslavije,
                            2013), 10.</note> Based on the Agreement from Rome of 29 March 1923, the
                        Kingdom of SCS made a commitment to the Southern Railway Company to pay 261
                        million gold francs, in equal instalments of 5.8 million gold francs within
                        45 years, for the repurchase of 530.6 km of the Southern Railways.<note
                            place="foot" xml:id="ftn43" n="41">
                            Railroads: Rijeka-Ljubljana and Maribor-Zidani Most-Zagreb-Sisak –
                            Gnjatović, "Stari državni dugovi," 142–4.</note> Furthermore, in that
                        same year the Kingdom of SCS made a commitment to the Oriental Railway and
                        Ottoman Railway Company from France to pay 149.9 million French francs with
                        a 7.5% interest rate for the repurchase of the Oriental Railways.<note
                            place="foot" xml:id="ftn44" n="42">
                            Railroads: Gevgelija-Kosovska Mitrovica,
                                Skopje-Zibevče, Gevgelija-Thessaloniki, Thessaloniki-Bitola –
                            Ibid.</note> The debts for the repurchase of Southern and Oriental
                        Railways were regularly repaid, including the years of the Great
                            Depression.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn45" n="43"> Privilegovana
                            narodna banka Kraljevine SHS, <hi rend="italic">Godišnji izveštaj
                                1926,</hi> XV. Privilegovana narodna banka Kraljevine SHS, <hi
                                rend="italic">Godišnji izveštaj 1927,</hi> XV. Privilegovana narodna
                            banka Kraljevine SHS, <hi rend="italic">Godišnji izveštaj 1928,</hi>
                            XVII. Opšta državna statistika Kraljevine Jugoslavije, <hi rend="italic"
                                >Statistički godišnjak Kraljevine Jugoslavije 1931</hi>, 467.
                        </note> Also, during the process of the nationalisation of the railways
                        throughout the country, the Kingdom of Yugoslavia assumed the obligation to
                        repurchase the vicinal (local) railways in the territories formerly
                        belonging to the Austro-Hungarian Monarchy, which were owned by different
                        foreign joint stock companies. The agreement with the owners of the vicinal
                        railways was achieved only on 1 May 1931. Based on this agreement, in the
                        list of public debt stock for the year 1932, the financial obligation for
                        the repurchase of the vicinal railways in the amount of 220.7 million dinars
                            appeared.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn46" n="44"> Opšta državna
                            statistika, <hi rend="italic">Statistički godišnjak Kraljevine
                                Jugoslavije 1932,</hi> 480, 481.</note></p>
                    <p>Although the post-war foreign public debt was regularly
                        serviced, also in the years of the Great Depression, it was precisely at
                        that time that its swift increase was recorded. As it happened, on 8 May
                        1931 the Yugoslav government took a Stabilisation Loan in gold in the amount
                        of 1.025 billion French francs, with a 7 % interest rate and maturity of 40
                        years from the <hi rend="italic">Banque de l’Union Parisienne</hi> bank
                        which served to strengthen the gold reserves of the National Bank. Then, on
                        11 May 1931, the gold exchange standard was introduced on the basis of the
                        new Law on Money of the Kingdom of Yugoslavia.<note place="foot"
                            xml:id="ftn47" n="45"> Gnjatović, "Foreign Exchange Policy in the
                            Kingdom of Yugoslavia," 340.</note></p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Sovereign Debt Default and Its Financial
                            Consequences</hi></p>
                    <p>In late July 1932, when it was not possible to provide
                        enough foreign exchange for the repayment of the enlarged foreign debt to
                        France, an attempt was made to reach an agreement with the French government
                        to postpone the outstanding liabilities for a year.<note place="foot"
                            xml:id="ftn48" n="46"> Privilegovana narodna banka Kraljevine
                            Jugoslavije, <hi rend="italic">Godišnji izveštaj 1932,</hi> XVII.</note>
                        This measure did not produce the desired results, and this led to the
                        temporary suspension of all payments of public debt in foreign
                            currency.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn49" n="47"> Ministarstvo
                            finansija Kraljevine Jugoslavije, <hi rend="italic">Ministarstvo
                                finansija 1918</hi>–<hi rend="italic">1938, </hi>211.</note>
                        Following the example of Bulgaria and Romania, in December 1932 negotiations
                        with the representatives of foreign porters of the bonds of the Yugoslav
                        government loans were initiated in order to "facilitate the service on these
                        bonds, as long as there are difficulties in providing foreign
                            exchange".<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn50" n="48"> Privilegovana
                            narodna banka Kraljevine Jugoslavije, <hi rend="italic">Ministarstvo
                                finansija 1918</hi>–<hi rend="italic">1938.</hi></note></p>
                    <p>The negotiations were finalised on 26 July 1933, with
                        the signing of the Convention on the regulation of repayments of foreign
                        government loans for the three-year period, from 14 October 1932 to 15
                        October 1935. On the basis of this Convention, the Kingdom of Yugoslavia has
                        concluded a series of international agreements on the so-called funding
                        loans for the refinancing of almost all external government debt.<note
                            place="foot" xml:id="ftn51" n="49">
                            The Convention also encompassed three loans of the State Mortgage Bank, intended for the post-war reconstruction of municipal and residential buildings in cities. Two loans were taken in 1924 and 1927 in Switzerland, amounting to 15 million Swiss francs and 12 million Swiss francs respectively, with an interest rate of 7 % and a repayment period of 12 years. The third post-war loan of the State Mortgage Bank was taken in 1927 from the New York banking house Seligman Brothers, amounting to 12 million US dollars with an interest rate of 7 % and a repayment period of 30 years. –
                            Gnjatović, "Stari državni dugovi," 172–4.</note> Funding loans were
                        concluded with an interest rate of 5 % and a repayment period of 25 years.
                        They were used to refinance 90 % of the commitments which became due in the
                        indicated period of three years, while the Kingdom of Yugoslavia continued
                        to repay the remaining 10 % of those liabilities in foreign currency.<note
                            place="foot" xml:id="ftn52" n="50"> Ibid.</note> However, even after the
                        expiry of the three-year moratorium, the Yugoslav state was unable to
                        continue repaying the foreign debt in accordance with the originally-agreed
                        terms, and on 25 April 25 1936 a new Convention was signed concerning the
                        two-year period from 16 October 1935 to 15 October 1937. The Kingdom of
                        Yugoslavia took a new funding loan to refinance 45 % of liabilities due
                        within that specified period, while 15 % of those liabilities were still to
                        be repaid in foreign currency. The remaining 40 % of liabilities due within
                        that specified period were written off. Even after this two-year moratorium,
                        the Yugoslav state was not able to continue to repay foreign debt in
                        accordance with the originally agreed terms. Therefore, on 27 March 1938 the
                        third Convention, concerning the two-year period from 16 October 1937 to 15
                        October 1939, was signed. This Convention stipulated that 45 % of the bond
                        face value should be repaid to foreign porters of the Yugoslav government
                        loans, while the remaining 55 % were written off.<note place="foot"
                            xml:id="ftn53" n="51"> Ibid.</note></p>
                    <p>Since its sovereign debt default in October 1932 until
                        World War II, the foreign financial markets were closed to the Kingdom of
                        Yugoslavia. The changes in the size of the public debt in the period between
                        1933 and 1939 were primarily the result of the repudiation of war debt
                        payments and Conventions on the regulation of the repayments of foreign
                        government loans. Between 1932 and 1933, the foreign public debt decreased
                        by 14.4 billion dinars, from 32.8 billion dinars to 18.4 billion dinars,
                        because the Yugoslav government, unable to continue to collect reparations
                        from Germany, stopped to service the war debt and no longer registered it in
                        the public debt stock.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn54" n="52"> League of
                                Nations,<hi rend="italic"> Statistical Year-Book of the League of
                                Nations 1936/37, </hi>285. Opšta državna statistika Kraljevine
                            Jugoslavije, <hi rend="italic">Statistički godišnjak Kraljevine
                                Jugoslavije 1931</hi>, 466. </note> In the following three-year
                        period, the foreign public debt was accumulating again due to the funding of
                        loans taken for the refinancing of outstanding debt, and thus it increased
                        to 21.4 billion dinars in 1936. According to the League of Nations data,
                        thanks to the successive write-offs, the foreign public debt of the Kingdom
                        of Yugoslavia was once again reduced to 12 billion dinars in 1939.<note
                            place="foot" xml:id="ftn55" n="53"> League of Nations,<hi rend="italic">
                                Statistical Year-Book of the League of Nations 1940/41,</hi>
                            288.</note></p>
                    <p>Unable to borrow abroad, the Yugoslav government relied
                        on the domestic financial market to help the economy overcome the crisis.
                        The extent of the expansive policy of public expenditure is revealed in the
                        data from the League of Nations, according to which the domestic public debt
                        stood at 12.6 billion dinars in 1939, meaning that it was doubled in
                        comparison with 1932.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn56" n="54"> Ibid.</note>
                        Domestic public loans were repaid regularly, and thus their investors did
                        not perceive buying government bonds as a risky operation even at times of
                        the already open crisis of foreign debt. In the period from 1935 to 1938,
                        the government bonds of the new tranches of loans for the financial
                        liquidation of the agrarian reform, the loan for major public works, as well
                        as the loan for the liquidation of farmers' debts were issued.<note
                            place="foot" xml:id="ftn57" n="55"> Ministarstvo finansija Kraljevine
                            Jugoslavije, <hi rend="italic">Ministarstvo finansija 1918</hi>–<hi
                                rend="italic">1938,</hi> 206.</note> In addition to these long-term
                        domestic loans, with the Decree of 2 January 1936 the Yugoslav state began
                        issuing treasury bills, "with the purpose to revive the national economy by
                        meeting earlier payments obligation of the state and to strengthen the
                        liquidity of the Treasury".<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn58" n="56"> Ibid.,
                            208.</note></p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Conclusion</head>
                <p>The Great War left behind a burden of financial obligations that far exceeded the
                    fiscal capacity of the Kingdom of SCS (Yugoslavia). The continued growth of
                    public debt was, in large part, the result of the successive acceptance of these
                    commitments on the external and internal level. At the time of the Great
                    Depression, with the declining national income the growth of public debt turned
                    into a crisis of public debt. With the rate of indebtedness of 106 %, measured
                    by the ratio of public debt to national income, in 1932 the Kingdom of
                    Yugoslavia ranked among the most indebted European countries. In fact, more than
                    a half of its public debt was related to the international obligations after the
                    war debts as well as direct and indirect pre-war debt.</p>
            </div>

        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="bibliography">
                <head>Sources and Literature</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Books and Journal Articles:</head>
                    <bibl>Becić, Ivan M. "Ratni dugovi Kraljevine Jugoslavije u svetlu politike."
                            <hi rend="italic">Istorija 20. veka, </hi>28 (3) (2010): 45–56.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Chouliarakis, George and Sophia Lazaretou. "Déjâ vu? The Greek Crisis
                        Experience, the 2010s <hi rend="italic">versus </hi>the 1930s. Lessons from
                        History." <hi rend="italic">Bank of Greece Working Paper,</hi> No. 176
                        (2014). </bibl>
                    <bibl>Domar, Evsey. D. "The ‘Burden of the Debt’ and the National Income." <hi
                            rend="italic">American Economic Review</hi> 34 (4), (1944):
                        798–827.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Dugalić, Veroljub. "Ratne reparacije u prošlosti: Obračun i naplata." <hi
                            rend="italic">Finansije, </hi>59 (1-6) (2004): 113–38.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Eichengreen, Barry and Richard Portes. "Debt and Default in the 1930s,
                        Causes and Consequences." <hi rend="italic">European Economic Review </hi>30
                        (1986): 599–640.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Gnjatović, Dragana. "Stari državni dugovi, Prilog ekonomskoj i političkoj
                        istoriji Srbije i Jugoslavije 1962–1941." <hi rend="italic">Jugoslovenski
                            pregled</hi> (1991): 133–6.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Gnjatović, Dragana. "Foreign Exchange Policy in the Kingdom of Yugoslavia
                        during and after Great Depression." <hi rend="italic">The Experience of
                            Exchange Rate Regimes in South eastern Europe in a Historical and
                            Comparative Perspective, </hi>OENB Workshops No. 13 (2008):
                        330–48.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Gnjatović, Dragana. "Foreign Long Term Government Loans of Serbia
                        1862–1914." In: <hi rend="italic">Economic and Financial Stability in SE
                            Europe in a Historical and Comparative Perspective,</hi> ed. Branko
                        Hinić, 33–55. Belgrade: National Bank of Serbia, Belgrade, 2009.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Gnjatović, Dragana. "Fiscal Integration in the European Union." <hi
                            rend="italic">Bankarstvo, </hi>42 (5) (2013): 14–29.</bibl>
                    <bibl>International Monetary Fund, <hi rend="italic">Assessing
                            Sustainability</hi>. Washington D.C., 2002. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Keynes, John Maynard. <hi rend="italic">The Economic Consequences of the
                            Peace.</hi> New York: Harcourt, Brace and Howe, Inc. Pub., 1919. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Ljubojević, Ratko. <hi rend="italic">Agrarna politika Kraljevine
                            Jugoslavije za vreme šestojnuarske diktature.</hi> Belgrade<hi
                            rend="italic">: </hi>Naučno društvo agrarnih ekonomista Balkana,
                        2015.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Malović, Gojko. <hi rend="italic">Saobraćaj i veze u Kraljevini
                            Jugoslaviji 1918</hi>–<hi rend="italic">1941.</hi> Belgrade: Arhiv
                        Jugoslavije, 2013.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Ministarstvo finansija Kraljevine Jugoslavije, <hi rend="italic"
                            >Ministarstvo finansija 1918</hi>–<hi rend="italic">1938, </hi>Belgrade:
                        1938. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Oosterlinck, Kim. "Sovereign Debt Defaults: Insights from History." <hi
                            rend="italic">Oxford Review of Economic Policy, </hi>29 (4) (2013):
                        691–714.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Stajić, Stevan. <hi rend="italic">Nacionalni dohodak Jugoslavije
                            1923</hi>–<hi rend="italic">1939 u stalnim i tekućim cenama,
                        </hi>Belgrade: Ekonomski institut, 1959. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Sturzenegger, Federico and Jeromin Zettelmeyer. <hi rend="italic">Debt
                            Defaults and Lessons from a Decade of Crises</hi>. MIT Press:
                        2007.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Statistical Publications:</head>
                    <bibl>League of Nations, <hi rend="italic">International Statistical Year-Book
                            1927. </hi>Geneva, 1928. </bibl>
                    <bibl>League of Nations,<hi rend="italic"> Statistical Year-Book of the League
                            of Nations 1936/37. </hi>Geneva, 1937.</bibl>
                    <bibl>League of Nations,<hi rend="italic"> Statistical Year-Book of the League
                            of Nations 1940/41. </hi>Geneva, 1941. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Opšta državna statistika Kraljevine Jugoslavije, <hi rend="italic"
                            >Statistički godišnjak Kraljevine Jugoslavije 1929</hi>. Belgrade,
                        1932.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Opšta državna statistika Kraljevine Jugoslavije, <hi rend="italic"
                            >Statistički godišnjak Kraljevine Jugoslavije 1930</hi>. Belgrade,
                        1933.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Opšta državna statistika Kraljevine Jugoslavije, <hi rend="italic"
                            >Statistički godišnjak Kraljevine Jugoslavije 1931</hi>. Belgrade, 1934. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Opšta državna statistika, <hi rend="italic">Statistički godišnjak
                            Kraljevine Jugoslavije 1932. </hi>Belgrade, 1934.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Opšta državna statistika, <hi rend="italic">Statistički godišnjak
                            Kraljevine Jugoslavije 1933. </hi>Belgrade, 1934. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Privilegovana narodna banka Kraljevine SHS, <hi rend="italic">Godišnji
                            izveštaj 1923. </hi>Belgrade, 1924.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Privilegovana narodna banka Kraljevine SHS, <hi rend="italic">Godišnji
                            izveštaj 1924. </hi>Belgrade, 1925. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Privilegovana narodna banka Kraljevine SHS, <hi rend="italic">Godišnji
                            izveštaj 1925. </hi>Belgrade, 1926. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Privilegovana narodna banka Kraljevine SHS, <hi rend="italic">Godišnji
                            izveštaj 1926. </hi>Belgrade, 1927. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Privilegovana narodna banka Kraljevine SHS, <hi rend="italic">Godišnji
                            izveštaj 1927. </hi>Belgrade, 1928. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Privilegovana narodna banka Kraljevine SHS, <hi rend="italic">Godišnji
                            izveštaj 1928. </hi>Belgrade, 1929. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Privilegovana narodna banka Kraljevine Jugoslavije, <hi rend="italic"
                            >Godišnji izveštaj 1932. </hi>Belgrade, 1933.</bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="italic">South-Eastern European Monetary and Economic Statistics
                            from the Nineteenth Century to the World War Two. </hi>Athens, Sofia,
                        Bucharest and Vienna: Bank of Greece, Bulgarian National Bank, National Bank
                        of Romania and Oesetreichische Nationalbank, 2014. </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
            <div type="summary">
                <docAuthor>Dragana Gnjatović</docAuthor>
                <head>ZAPOLNITEV VRZELI V ZGODOVINSKI STATISTIKI – MAKROEKONOMSKI
                    KAZALCI KREDITNEGA DOLGA KRALJEVINE JUGOSLAVIJE V ČASU VELIKE SVETOVNE
                    GOSPODARSKE KRIZE</head>
                <head>POVZETEK</head>
                <p>V času velike svetovne gospodarske krize se je Kraljevina Jugoslavija soočala s
                    krizo javnega dolga. Od leta 1929 do 1932 se je raven zadolženosti, merjena z
                    razmerjem med javnim dolgom in nacionalnim dohodkom, povečala s 57,8 odstotka na
                    106,3 odstotka; v okviru domačega javnega dolga od 8,7 odstotka do 16,5
                    odstotka, v okviru zunanjega javnega dolga pa z 49,1 odstotka na 89,8 odstotka.
                    Dolžniška kriza je povzročila hkratno zmanjšanje deviznih prihodkov in rast
                    javnega dolga. Upad deviznih prihodkov je bil neposredna posledica velike
                    svetovne gospodarske krize, medtem ko je bila rast javnih prihodkov posledica
                    političnih, ozemeljskih, socialnih in gospodarskih sprememb, ki jih je s seboj
                    prinesla oziroma za seboj pustila velika vojna. Dejstvo je, da je bila
                    Kraljevina Jugoslavija prav v času nenadnega zmanjševanja deviznih prihodkov od
                    izvoza in izseljenskih nakazil prisiljena sprejeti številne nove mednarodne
                    obveznosti, ki so izzvale močno povečanje javnih izdatkov.</p>
                <p>Da bi se našli konkretni vzroki, zaradi katerih se je javni dolg Kraljevine
                    Jugoslavije v obdobju od leta 1929 do 1932 povečal s 34,7 milijarde dinarjev na
                    38,8 milijarde dinarjev, je bila izvedena dekompozicija javnega dolga. Pri tem
                    je bila uporabljena metodologija Obče državne statistike Kraljevine Jugoslavije,
                    po kateri je obstajalo pet kategorij javnega dolga: dolg Kraljevine Srbije in
                    Kraljevine Črne gore, ki ga je v odplačevanje prevzela Kraljevina SHS (Predvojni
                    oziroma direktni predvojni dolg); dolg zaveznikom Kraljevine Srbije iz Vélike
                    vojne (Vojni dolg); dolg, ki ga je Kraljevina SHS nasledila od avstro-ogrske
                    monarhije in Osmanskega imperija (Nasledstveni oziroma indirektni predvojni
                    dolg), dolg zaradi tujih posojil Kraljevini SHS oziroma Kraljevini Jugoslaviji
                    po veliki vojni (Povojni dolg) in dolg zaradi notranjih posojil po veliki vojni
                    (Notranji dolg). Dekompozicija javnega dolga je pokazala, da vzroki njegove
                    hitre rasti v času velike svetovne gospodarske krize niso bili v nobeni
                    neposredni zvezi s krizo.</p>
                <p>Prav v času Velike svetovne gospodarske krize se je zaradi revalorizacije
                    francoskih posojil dolg Kraljevine Srbije potrojil. Šele po privolitvi
                    Kraljevine Jugoslavije, da bo revalorizirala posojila Kraljevini Srbiji, je
                    njena vlada skupaj s francosko regulirala vojni dolg in sklenila novo posojilo,
                    s katero bi zakonsko stabilizirala dinar. Istočasno pa se neposredni predvojni
                    dolg ni zmanjševal, saj je bilo začasno ustavljeno odplačevanje nasledstvenega
                    avstro-ogrskega državnega dolga zaradi vzrokov, ki niso bili povezani s krizo in
                    na katere jugoslovanska vlada ni mogla vplivati. Upniki namreč niso bili
                    zadovoljni z vsoto, ki jo je zmogla odplačevati, zato so tekla pogajanja o
                    spremembi pogojev teh dolgov. Ne nazadnje niti notranja javna posojila iz časa
                    velike svetovne gospodarske krize s krizo sámo niso imela nobene zveze;
                    namenjena so bila saniranju posledic prve svetovne vojne in finančni likvidaciji
                    nasledstvenih fevdalnih odnosov pri izvajanju agrarne reforme. </p>
                <p>Za Kraljevino Jugoslavijo je breme zunanjega dolga leta 1932 postalo pretežko.
                    Temu je sledil državni stečaj in niz zaporednih sporazumov z upniki o
                    refinanciranju in odpisu dela dolga. Notranji javni dolg je bil istočasno redno
                    servisiran.</p>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
