<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>»What does it have to do with us?« – Rethinking the Russian
                        Revolution in Germany</title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename>Andreas</forename>
                        <surname>Schulz</surname>
                    </name>
                    <roleName>Professor</roleName>
                    <roleName>PhD</roleName>
                    <affiliation>Kommission für Geschichte des
                        Parlamentarismus und der politischen Parteien,</affiliation>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Schiffbauerdamm 40</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>D-10117 Berlin</addrLine>
                    </address>
                    <email>schulz@kgparl.de</email>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>2018-02-20</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>
                    <orgName xml:lang="sl">Inštitut za novejšo zgodovino</orgName>
                    <orgName xml:lang="en">Institute of Contemporary History</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Kongresni trg 1</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>SI-1000 Ljubljana</addrLine>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>http://ojs.inz.si/pnz/article/view/256</pubPlace>
                <date>2018</date>
                <availability status="free">
                    <licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title xml:lang="sl">Prispevki za novejšo zgodovino</title>
                <title xml:lang="en">Contributions to Contemporary History</title>
                <biblScope unit="volume">58</biblScope>
                <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
                <idno type="ISSN">2463-7807</idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source, born digital.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc xml:lang="en">
                <p>Contributions to Contemporary History is one of the central Slovenian scientific
                    historiographic journals, dedicated to publishing articles from the field of
                    contemporary history (the 19th and 20th century).</p>
                <p>The journal is published three times per year in Slovenian and in the following
                    foreign languages: English, German, Serbian, Croatian, Bosnian, Italian, Slovak
                    and Czech. The articles are all published with abstracts in English and
                    Slovenian as well as summaries in English.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <projectDesc xml:lang="sl">
                <p>Prispevki za novejšo zgodovino je ena osrednjih slovenskih znanstvenih
                    zgodovinopisnih revij, ki objavlja teme s področja novejše zgodovine (19. in 20.
                    stoletje).</p>
                <p>Revija izide trikrat letno v slovenskem jeziku in v naslednjih tujih jezikih:
                    angleščina, nemščina, srbščina, hrvaščina, bosanščina, italijanščina, slovaščina
                    in češčina. Članki izhajajo z izvlečki v angleščini in slovenščini ter povzetki
                    v angleščini.</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="sl"/>
                <language ident="en"/>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords xml:lang="en">
                    <term>Commemorating the »World Revolution«, , </term>
                    <term>Global effects of 1917</term>
                    <term>Impacts of the Red October on Germany</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords xml:lang="sl">
                    <term>čaščenje spomina na "svetovno revolucijo"</term>
                    <term>globalne posledice leta 1917</term>
                    <term>vplivi Rdečega oktobra na Nemčijo</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change>
                    <date>2018-02-23</date>
                    <name>Neja Blaj Hribar</name>
                    <desc>Pretvorba iz DOCX v TEI, dodatno kodiranje</desc>
                </change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <docAuthor>Andreas Schulz<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn1" n="*">
                <hi rend="bold">Professor, PhD, Kommission für Geschichte des
                    Parlamentarismus und der politischen Parteien,<lb/>Schiffbauerdamm 40,
                    D-10117 Berlin, </hi><ref target="mailto:schulz@kgparl.de"><hi rend="bold">schulz@kgparl.de</hi></ref></note></docAuthor>
            <docImprint>
                <idno type="cobissType">Cobiss type: 1.01</idno>
                <idno type="UDC">UDC: 323.272(47)"1917":930(430)”1918/2018”</idno>
            </docImprint>
            <div type="abstract" xml:lang="sl">
                <head>IZVLEČEK</head>
                <head>»KAJ IMA ZA OPRAVITI Z NAMI?« – PONOVNO VREDNOTENJE RUSKE REVOLUCIJE V NEMČIJI</head>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Avtor predstavlja pregled razstav in novejših publikacij v Nemčiji,
                    posvečenih stoti obletnici oktobrske revolucije leta 1917. Po stoletju
                    raziskovanja sta veličastnost in herojstvo iz časov rojstva "velike
                    socialistične oktobrske revolucije" že povsem zbledela. Z demistifikacijo se je
                    tako imenovana "svetovna revolucija" premaknila v okvir ruske zgodovine. Vendar
                    ta nacionalizacija revolucije marginalizira globalne posledice Rdečega oktobra,
                    zlasti kadar se boljševiški prevzem oblasti razlaga preprosto kot uspešno
                    prizadevanje za preoblikovanje anarhije v organizirani režim terorja, ki ga je
                    izvajala odločna in požrtvovalna avantgarda. Medtem ko totalitarni pristop
                    zanemarja socialne korenine revolucije, novejše kulturne študije poudarjajo
                    naključne dejavnike in degradirajo revolucionarno vstajo kot eskalacijo
                    državljanske vojne na kontaminiranih "območjih nasilja". Avtor v drugem delu
                    tega prispevka pusti za sabo vse takšne celovite razlage in velike načrte ter
                    opozori na dolgotrajne strukturne spremembe, ki jih je ruska revolucija
                    povzročila v povojni Evropi. Svoje argumente osredotoči na tri ravni – najprej
                    na politične institucije, nato na gospodarski in družbeni red, nazadnje pa na
                    demografske spremembe.</hi></p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Ključne besede: čaščenje spomina na "svetovno revolucijo", globalne
                    posledice leta 1917, vplivi Rdečega oktobra na Nemčijo</hi></p></div>
            <div type="abstract"><head>ABSTRACT</head>
                <p><hi rend="italic">The author reviews exhibitions and recent publications in Germany
                    which commemorate the centennial of the October Revolution 1917. After a full
                    century of research there is little left of glory and heroism that had been
                    present at the dawn of the »Great Socialist October Revolution«. A
                    de-mystification has taken place which relocates the proclaimed »World
                    Revolution« into the frame of Russian history. But this nationalization of the
                    revolution tends to marginalize the global effects of the Red October,
                    especially when the Bolshevik seizure of power is simply explained as a
                    successful effort to transform anarchy into an organised regime of terror
                    practised by a determined and self-sacrificing Avantgarde. While the
                    totalitarian approach neglects the social origins of the Revolution, recent
                    cultural studies emphasise contingent factors downrating revolutionary uprisings
                    as an escalation of civil war in contaminated »landscapes of violence«. Leaving
                    behind such entire explanations and grand designs, the second part of this paper
                    wants to draw attention to the enduring structural changes which the Russian
                    Revolution caused in post-war Europe. The author concentrates his arguments on
                    three levels, beginning with the political institutions, secondly, the economic
                    and social order, and thirdly, the demographic change.</hi></p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Keywords: Commemorating the »World Revolution«, Global effects of
                    1917, Impacts of the Red October on Germany</hi></p></div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div><p>In the calendar of centennial commemorations of the October Revolution in Germany,
                the exhibition »<hi rend="italic">1917 Revolution – Russland und die Folgen«</hi> in
                the <hi rend="italic">Deutsche Historische Museum</hi> in Berlin had a prominent
                place. »What does the revolution have to do with us? « – is a rhetorical question,
                which the curators did not specifically answer because they were more interested in
                the celebrations of the revolutionary heritage in post-soviet Russia.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn2" n="1"> Kristiane Janeke,
                        "Einführung," in:
                        <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">1917. Revolution: Russland und die Folgen </hi>(Berlin:
                        Sandstein Verlag, 2017), 10–13.</note> But indeed, looking back from
                2017, it is evident that nothing is left of the hopes and fears that contemporaries
                all over the world shared when the Bolsheviks announced the dawn of a new age of
                mankind under the name of the »Great Socialist October Revolution«.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn3" n="2"> Eric J. Hobsbawm, <hi rend="italic">Das Zeitalter der Extreme: Weltgeschichte des 20.
                            Jahrhunderts 1914–1991</hi> (München: Hanser, 1995), 91–93.</note>
                With the end of the Cold War, it seemed as if the global revolutionary challenge and
                the utopian promises, which the Soviet Union held up as the legitimate heir of
                Leninism, completely disappeared.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn4" n="3"> Jan Claas Behrends et. al., "100 Jahre Roter Oktober.
                        Versuche zur Historisierung der Russischen Revolution," in: <hi rend="italic">100 Jahre Roter Oktober. Zur Weltgeschichte der Russian
                            Revolution</hi> (Berlin: Christoph Links, 2017), 9. Jan C. Behrends,
                        "Was bleibt vom Kommunismus? Eine historische Betrachtung zum 100. Jahrestag
                        der Russischen Revolution," in: <hi rend="italic">1917. 100 Jahre
                            Oktoberrevolution und ihre Fernwirkungen auf Deutschland</hi>
                        (Baden-Baden: Nomos, 2017), 23‒37.</note> A brief look at the bestseller
                book list shows that the year 1917 has become a rather forgotten time in history.
                While the commemoration of the »Great War« from 1914 to 1918 produced a rich harvest
                of detailed studies<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn5" n="4">
                        Books on First World War are bestsellers, see for example: Jörn Leonhard,
                            <hi rend="italic">Die Büchse der Pandora. Geschichte des Ersten
                            Weltkriegs</hi> (München: C.H.Beck, <hi rend="superscript">5</hi>2014).
                        Herfried Münkler, <hi rend="italic">Der große Krieg. Die Welt 1914‒1918</hi>
                        (Berlin: Rowohlt, <hi rend="superscript">4</hi>2014).</note>, which
                claim to deliver new insights, recent publications about the Russian Revolution of
                1917 remain in the shadow of latest historiographical research. Nonetheless, it is
                worth considering its significant importance once again after a hundred years,
                despite the fact that the »World Revolution«, which Lenin and the Bolsheviks
                proclaimed, never happened.</p></div>
            <div><head>A Final Farewell to the World
                Revolution?</head>
            <div><p>A full century of research has de-mystified the Russian Revolution, leaving little of
                the glory and heroism which had always surrounded memories and historiography.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn6" n="5"> Gerd Koenen, "Der
                        »Rote Oktober« als Mythos und Utopicum," in: <hi rend="italic">Russland und
                            die Folgen</hi>, 141‒57.</note> Some historians wonder if the
                revolution really mattered enough to call it a break of continuity in contemporary
                world history at all. There is a growing tendency to locate the years 1917‒1920 in
                the frame of <hi rend="italic">Russian</hi> history, so that we may speak of a
                »de-globalisation« and »nationalisation« of the October Revolution. How this
                rearrangement has changed our general perception of the Russian Revolution will be
                discussed in the first part of this paper. It is evident that with the end of the
                Cold War, ideological debates ceased and grand narratives fell silent. However,
                there is reason enough to consider the immediate impacts and long-term structural
                changes that the revolution caused. This will be explored in the second part of this
                paper.</p></div>
            <div><head>Relocating the Russian Revolution</head>
            <p>It has long been common knowledge that the Russian Revolution was a turning point in
                world history because it laid the foundations for a global bi-polar division between
                liberal-capitalist »Western« democracies and the socialist hemisphere, dominated by
                a Soviet system and based on social collectivism and state economy. Historians in
                the GDR periodically celebrated the Bolshevik Revolution as the beginning of an age
                of emancipation which liberated mankind from expropriation and imperialistic wars.
                Their »bourgeois« counterparts in West Germany agreed with them insofar as they
                recognised the global historical dimension of the revolution. In the aftermath of
                the dissolution of the Soviet Union, this perception entirely changed. Only a
                marginalised group of convinced Marxist-Leninists remains engaged in periodical
                commemorations of the »Great Socialist October Revolution«, thus preserving the
                canonical interpretation of the Bolsheviks’ historical mission.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn7" n="6"> See for example the contributions
                        to the 10th conference of Historical Research organised by the »Marxistische
                        Arbeitskreis zur Geschichte der deutschen Arbeiterbewegung bei der
                        Historischen Kommission der Partei des Demokratischen Sozialismus (PDS)« in
                        1997: Lothar Berthold, "»Sie war und bleibt die Große Sozialistische
                        Oktoberrevolution!«," in: <hi rend="italic">Die Oktoberrevolution 1917 und
                            ihr Platz in der Geschichte</hi> (Bonn: Pahl-Rugenstein, 1997), 71–81.
                        Stefan Doernberg, "Oktoberrevolution ‒ Epochenwechsel oder Weg in die
                        Sackgasse?," in: <hi rend="italic">Die Oktoberrevolution 1917 und ihr Platz
                            in der Geschichte,</hi> 9–26. Martin Sabrow, "Der »Rote Oktober« und
                        sein Nachhall im geteilten Deutschland," in: <hi rend="italic">Russland und
                            die Folgen</hi>, 125‒39.</note> With the vanishing aurora of the
                »Red October«<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn8" n="7">
                        François Furet, <hi rend="italic">Das Ende der Illusion. Der Kommunismus im
                            20. Jahrhundert</hi> (München and Zürich: Piper, <hi rend="superscript">2</hi>1996) 87–137, 549–97. Behrends et. al., <hi rend="italic">Historisierung</hi>, 26.</note>, the main stream of research is
                re-directing its orientation, substituting the outlook on the global impacts of the
                revolution with a retrospection on its national origins. Historians are turning
                their attention to the late Empire, explaining the Russian Revolutions in view of
                the economic crises and social uprisings which accelerated the breakdown of the
                    Empire.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn9" n="8"> Manfred
                        Hildermeyer, <hi rend="italic">Geschichte Russlands vom Mittelalter bis zur
                            Oktoberrevolution</hi> (München: C.H.Beck, 2013). Manfred Hildermeyer,
                            <hi rend="italic">Die Sowjetunion 1917‒1991</hi> (Berlin: De Gruyter,
                            <hi rend="superscript">3</hi>2016). Helmut Altrichter, <hi rend="italic">Russland 1917. Ein Land auf der Suche nach sich selbst</hi> (Paderborn:
                        Ferdinand Schöningh, <hi rend="superscript">2</hi>2017).</note> The
                great narratives published in Germany during the last few years tell us about <hi rend="italic">Russian</hi> history, thereby emphasising the singularity of
                the<hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve"> Russian</hi> revolutions from February to
                October 1917. However, nationalising the October Revolution does not necessarily
                imply neglecting or denying its considerable impacts on other countries, which will
                be demonstrated later in the paper. It is not a complete revision but rather a
                de-mystification of the glorious »Great Socialist Revolution« that has taken place,
                returning Red October back into Russian history. </p></div>
            <div><head><hi rend="italic">Revolutionary Leviathan</hi></head>
            <p>Marxist historiography has failed to validate its »scientific« dogma of the
                inevitability of a socialist world revolution terminating the age of capitalism.
                Treating history as a continuous progression of mankind towards perfection, made the
                October Revolution appear inevitable. Quite a corresponding teleology is offered by
                Western theories of modernisation, which presume a final destination of modern civil
                societies. According to each country’s current level of participation,
                industrialisation and pluralism, standards of »advanced democracies« are developed,
                dividing the world into areas of progression and regression. In reference to this
                paradigm of progress, the Russian Revolutions were qualified as »crises«, resulting
                from the disability of an autocratic state to adjust its traditional society and
                local economy to global modernisation. </p>
            <p>Anticipations concerning the irreversibility of the emancipation of mankind, the
                progress of democracy and economic globalisation did affect historiographic research
                on the Russian Revolution for quite some time. Obviously, the progressive approach
                to history tended to emphasise the structural deficiencies of the autocratic system
                in the late Empire. Unlike the dynasty’s violent physical elimination, the Empire of
                the Romanovs suffered a silent breakdown rather than being swept away by
                revolutionary force. The »failed« Empire did not simply drown in anarchy and civil
                war, contrary to what the liberal opponents of the Russian revolutionaries have
                always maintained. Against all expectations, the Bolshevik Revolution finally
                succeeded in establishing a centralised bureaucratic party-rule. It continued to
                submit civil society to the restructured state authority. Converting the former
                imperial military and police forces to loyal instruments, the Bolshevik Leviathan
                practised (red) terror in similar ways to how the autocratic monarchy had exerted
                    power.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn10" n="9"> See
                        chapter II »Ein Staat in der Krise,« in: Altrichter, <hi rend="italic">Russland 1917</hi>, 192–259. Resuming latest research: Hildermeyer, <hi rend="italic">Sowjetunion</hi>. For a differentiating and critical
                        Marxist interpretation see: Helmut Bock, "Die Russische Revolution 1917‒1921
                        ‒ Sieg oder Tragödie?," <hi rend="italic">Pankower Vorträge,</hi> No. 71
                        (2005).</note></p>
            <p>Recent historiography evidently adopts a renewed totalitarianism-paradigm, explaining
                that the seizure of power and the regime of total control, that the Bolshevik
                intelligentsia established, was for their own sake. After the victorious
                pacification of the Civil War, the mission of authoritarian rule and state
                monopolism was accomplished.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn11" n="10"> Martin Malia, <hi rend="italic">Vollstreckter Wahn.
                            Russland 1917–1991</hi> (Stuttgart: Klett-Cotta, 1994). Hildermeyer, <hi rend="italic">Sowjetunion</hi>, 117–22.</note> Its centralised state
                power and modernism was pushed forward by a determined elite, who acted with
                revolutionary energy. The analogy of this narrative to Tocqueville’s »Ancien Régime
                and the Revolution« and the liberal interpretation of the French Revolution is
                    obvious.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn12" n="11"> Arno
                        J. Mayer, <hi rend="italic">The Furies. Violence and Terror in the French
                            and the Russian Revolution</hi> (Princeton/NJ: Princeton University
                        Press, 2000).</note> Aside from this »statist« view, there is a growing
                inclination to avoid such all-embracing »entire« explanations. Recent research has
                taken into account the peculiarities, singularities and contingencies of Russian
                history which might not be derived from general assumptions about authoritarian
                pre-dispositions of a centralised state. The outstanding personality of Lenin, the
                self-sacrificing ideological determination of the revolutionary »Avantgarde«, and
                the massive agrarian discontent might be mentioned as crucial elements of an
                exceptional case of revolutionary pre-conditions.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn13" n="12"> Bock, <hi rend="italic">Russische
                            Revolution</hi>, 29–46.</note></p></div>
            <div><head>Extinguishing Revolutionary Time ‒ The Continuous Experience of War
                    and Violence.</head>
            <p>Not surprisingly, the cultural turn produced some essential revisions in
                historiography which might be considered as a marginalisation of the October
                Revolution. Historians representing the current main-stream of »culturalism« have
                dismissed the breaking-point of 1917 in the continuum of a history of violence
                linking Imperial Russia, the October Revolution and the Civil War.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn14" n="13"> Jörg Baberowski and Gabriele
                        Metzler, eds. <hi rend="italic">Gewalträume ‒ soziale Ordnungen im
                            Ausnahmezustand</hi> (Frankfurt am Main: Campus Verlag, 2012). Jörg
                        Baberowski, <hi rend="italic">Räume der Gewalt</hi> (Frankfurt am Main: S.
                        Fischer, <hi rend="superscript">2</hi>2015). Dietrich Beyrau, <hi rend="italic">Krieg und Revolution. Russische Erfahrungen</hi>
                        (Paderborn: Ferdinand Schöningh, 2017), 200<hi rend="italic">‒</hi>26. Felix
                        Schnell, <hi rend="italic">Räume des Schreckens. Gewalträume und
                            Gruppenmilitanz in der Ukraine 1905‒1933</hi> (Hamburg: Hamburger
                        Edition, 2012). Peter Holquist, <hi rend="italic">Making War, Forging
                            Revolution. Russia’s Continuum of Crisis, 1914‒1921</hi>
                        (Cambridge/Mass.: Harvard University Press, 2002). Anna Greifman, <hi rend="italic">Thou shalt kill. Revolutionary Terrorism in Russia,
                            1894‒1917</hi> (Princeton/NJ: Princeton University Press,
                    1993).</note> A landscape of »killing fields« and »areas of violence«
                (»Gewalträume«) is constructed, where everyone is exposed to an overwhelming
                experience of destruction, lawlessness and murder. Deprived of the ability to
                establish civil order, people submit to the iron circle of violence and
                counter-violence, thereby losing control of themselves and becoming active
                participants of crime. Criminals and victims merge in a »timeless« slaughter, in an
                »orgy of destruction«<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn15" n="14"> Jörg Baberowski, "Die Russische Revolution und die
                        Neuordnung der Welt," in: <hi rend="italic">1917 Revolution ‒ Russland und
                            die Folgen</hi>, 21.</note> where terror and revenge, banditry and
                looting, hooliganism and alcoholism, ethnic fighting, pogroms and deportations
                eliminate social order until state authority finally collapses. Amidst this
                apocalyptic battlefield, the Bolsheviks advance to the stage, presenting themselves
                as the only players who are determined to re-establish order by force of
                    violence.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn16" n="15">
                        Beyrau, <hi rend="italic">Krieg und Revolution</hi>, 207.</note></p>
            <p>In this perspective, the Russian Revolution and Civil War merely appear as an
                escalation of violence, and the Bolshevik seizure of power as a successful effort to
                transform anarchy into an organised regime of »Red Terror«. Did Leninism
                conceptualise party rule and social control as self-serving, creating nothing else
                but a revolutionary culture of force and order? Recent cultural studies pay
                attention to the popular claim for terminating war and pacifying civil conflicts
                which the Bolshevik’s political agenda supported. Nevertheless, a historiographic
                creation of »landscapes of violence« obviously neglects social incentives for
                popular uprisings in Russia. Grand designs of revolution and war history tend to
                disconnect the time and place of the Revolution of 1917, illustrating Red October as
                either a collective effort to terminate fighting or as a revolutionary coup d’état
                which established an organised terror regime in a contaminated area where violence
                and killing is an elementary »timeless« experience.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn17" n="16"> Jörg Baberowski, "Verwüstetes Land: Macht und
                        Gewalt in der frühen Sowjetunion," in: <hi rend="italic">Gewalträume</hi>,
                        169–89. A more differentiated study is: Stefan Plaggenborg, <hi rend="italic">Revolutionskultur. Menschenbilder und kulturelle Praxis in
                            Sowjetrussland zwischen Oktoberrevolution und Stalinismus</hi> (Köln et
                        al.: Böhlau, 1996). Stefan Plaggenborg, <hi rend="italic">Ordnungen der
                            Gewalt: Sozialismus, Kemalismus, Faschismus</hi> (München: Oldenbourg
                        Wissenschaftsverlag, 2012).</note></p>
            <p>The de-mystification and nationalisation of Red October has drawn attention away from
                the reverberations that the Russian Revolution released far beyond its borders,
                especially in the belligerent countries of the First World War. The immediate
                impacts of the revolution and the enduring structural changes it caused in post-war
                Europe will be discussed in the second part of this paper. </p></div></div>
            <div><head>Impacts of the Russian Revolution in Europe: the German and the
                    British Case</head>
            <p>Immediate reactions all throughout Europe occurred when the news of the February
                Revolution spread. In war-sick Germany, hopes of reaching a separate peace agreement
                with Russia grew, and the massive intervention of the Entente powers during the
                Civil War provoked solidarity with the Bolsheviks, especially among workers. The
                British suffragist Emmeline Pankhurst, who had travelled on a 4-month journey to
                Revolutionary Russia to urge the Provisional Government to carry on the war against
                the <hi rend="italic">Mittelmächte</hi> on the Eastern front, had initially welcomed
                the February Revolution as a step towards parliamentary democracy. When she returned
                home in October 1917, she warned that a political seizure of power by the Bolsheviks
                was near. They would take Russia out of the war and then conclude a separate peace
                with Germany.</p>
            <p>While Pankhurst was performing her patriotic mission in Petrograd, the German
                secretary of the International League of Women, Clara Zetkin, had concluded her
                break from the Social Democratic party which had been her home from the beginning of
                her political life. The revolutions in Russia turned Zetkin’s misery into excited
                expectations of a decisive turnover of world history. Recovering from a period of
                depression and loneliness caused by her disillusion about the failure of workers
                internationalism against imperialistic war, Zetkin was literally reborn as a
                communist activist, preparing herself for the prospective venue of the forthcoming
                World Revolution. In a message to the <hi rend="italic">Komintern</hi> (Communist
                International), she declared her devotion to »socialist Soviet Russia«, celebrating
                the October Revolution as » the mighty sun, rising in crimson splendor out of the
                darkness and horror of the World War«.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn18" n="17"> »[ …] die große gewaltige Sonne, die in purpurner
                        Pracht aus dem Dunkel und Grauen des Weltkriegs emporsteigt«; quoted in:
                        Tânia Puschnerat, <hi rend="italic">Clara Zetkin ‒ Bürgerlichkeit und
                            Marxismus. Eine Biografie</hi> (Essen: Klartext Verlag, 2003), 222
                        f.</note> One of the signatures on an international address of
                solidarity, which she directed to the Bolsheviks in November 1919, was written by
                Sylvia Pankhurst who had openly diverted from the political course of her mother,
                Emmeline.</p>
            <p>The reflections on the revolutions in Russia from two outstanding political women
                could not have been more conflicting. Whereas Emmeline Pankhurst had turned away
                from her radical origins, Zetkin embraced the Red Revolution as the dawn of a
                liberated mankind. Apart from their personal involvement, their reactions also
                reflect the different impacts that the revolutions in Russia had on the belligerent
                nations in the First World War. While the victorious Entente countries soon returned
                to parliamentary government, the monarchies of the Central powers were swept away by
                revolutionary uprisings. However, all efforts to light a revolutionary fire failed,
                and the slogan “Proletarier aller Länder, vereinigt euch!” (Proletarians of all
                countries, unite!), which was first addressed to German workers, was met with weak
                support among the Spartacus League and the Internationalists. </p>
            <p>Although expectations of a coming World Revolution were soon disappointed, people
                would not lose hope for a better future in post-war Europe. Some parts of the
                political Left observed the Russian experience following the October Revolution.
                Promises that the Bolsheviks made concerning social reform, land re-distribution,
                popular education and women’s emancipation supported the European workers movement’s
                essential claims. Russia and the Soviet-Union remained a point of reference for
                labour force, and an incentive and challenge for European democracies. While recent
                German historiography commemorates the Revolution in Russia, after 100 years, there
                is reason enough to re-consider the long-term effects it might have had on the
                Weimar Republic’s liberal democracy.</p>
            <p>The year 1917 was a turning point for the constitutional monarchies in Germany and
                Austria. When the Social Democratic Party refused to give further approval to war
                loans, this signalled the end of the national war consensus which the Emperor had
                proclaimed in August 1914. An informal political coalition of the »Parliamentary
                Left«, which included the catholic <hi rend="italic">Zentrumspartei</hi>, Left
                Liberals and Social Democrats, agreed on a resolution in the <hi rend="italic">Reichstag</hi>, announcing to the world that Germany should declare its will to
                conclude a peace without annexations and reparations. The famous Reichstag Peace
                Resolution of July 1917 openly referred to the Petrograd Soviet which had proclaimed
                a fundamental rupture with the conventional logic of fighting and waging war earlier
                in the year. When the German Supreme Command ignored the parliamentarian majority’s
                initiative by submitting Russia to a dictatorial Peace Treaty and intensified its
                useless war efforts, the Germany public lost faith in the military and political
                leadership of the monarchy. News about the Revolution in Russia aggravated the
                growing discontent in Germany, but it can hardly be claimed that the constant loss
                of popular loyalty was due to the propaganda war that the Bolsheviks staged against
                imperialism. It was not the suspected »stab-in-the-back« (<hi rend="italic">Dolchstoss</hi>) led by revolutionary elements of a treacherous »Homefront«,
                but rather the failed <hi rend="italic">Siegfrieden</hi>-strategy which caused the
                collapse of the monarchies. Therefore, if we want to reflect the impacts of the
                Russian Revolution, we have to go beyond the political turnover of the German
                November Revolution in 1918 and consider the long-term effects. My paper
                concentrates on three levels, beginning with political institutions, secondly, the
                economic and social order, and thirdly, the demographic change.</p>
            <list type="ordered">
                <item><p>The complete failure of the military and political leadership’s war strategy
                    made constitutional reforms, including the enfranchisement of the bulk of the
                    working population, indispensable. However, the sudden turn over of the 1918
                    October cabinet to a republican order came too late. Mutinies in the army, as
                    well as in major factories, had already broken out, leading directly to the
                    German November Revolution. Spontaneous, grass-roots councils of soldiers and
                    workers were spreading all over the country. They directly referred to the
                    Russian soviets, such as the Workers and Soldiers Council of the Free City of
                    Hamburg which proclaimed that »Soviet Russia and the Soviets of Hamburg are
                    inseparably connected«.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn19" n="18"> »[…] das revolutionäre Hamburg hat durch die Tat
                            bewiesen, dass das Russland der Räteregierung und die Räteregierung
                            Hamburgs eine Einheit sind, die nichts trennen kann«, in: <hi rend="italic smallcaps">Hamburger Echo</hi>, 7. 11. 1918, quoted in:
                            Volker Stalmann and Jutta Stehling, <hi rend="italic">Der Hamburger
                                Arbeiter- und Soldatenrat 1918/19</hi> (Düsseldorf: Droste, 2013),
                            43.</note> Even in England, where labour movement and trade unions
                    had ceased their strike activities in 1914, a Council of Workmen of more than a
                    thousand representatives gathered in the Coliseum of the industrial city of
                    Leeds, which was known as <hi rend="italic">The Leeds Soviet</hi>. It warmly
                    hailed the Russian Revolution and called upon the establishment of »Councils of
                    Workmen and Soldiers« in every town, urban and rural district. They regarded the
                    Russian Soviets as a historical achievement of the working class which would one
                    day become the nucleus of a new social order in Britain. Similar conventions in
                    Newcastle and Manchester were soon suppressed by police force under the
                    provisions of the Defense of the Realm Act.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn20" n="19">
                            <hi rend="italic">Northern Voices: The Leeds Soviet – 1917!</hi>, 15
                            February 2018,
                            http://northernvoicesmag.blogspot.de/2017/01/the-leeds-soviet-1917.html.
                            Ian Bullock, <hi rend="italic">Romancing the revolution: the myth of
                                Soviet democracy and the British Left</hi> (Edmonton: Athabasca
                            University Press, 2011), 41‒88.</note> Although their hope of
                    launching a British network of extra-parliamentarian Soviets with sovereign
                    powers failed, workers felt encouraged by their Russian comrades to enforce
                    their bargaining power. They were politicised by watching the Russian
                    revolutionary experience. </p>
            
            <p>But whereas the British version of Soviets remained a marginal
                phenomenon that did not cause much attention in historiography, there was a lengthy
                debate in Germany during the 1970s about the reform potential of the <hi rend="italic">Rätebewegung</hi> (Council Movement). Evidence proved that most of
                the revolutionary delegates themselves did not claim to represent a political
                alternative to parliamentary democracy, but rather a means of political control to
                secure the transfer of power to the parties of the working class. Apart from this,
                people did not believe that the Russian experience would survive much longer, and
                even the radical Left rejected »bolshevist terror«.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn21" n="20"> Heinrich Laufenberg (1872‒1937) former member of
                        the Social Democrats (SPD), 1919 member of the Communist Party (KPD), first
                        President of the Hamburg Workers and Soldiers Council until 21/1/1919,
                        quoted in: <anchor xml:id="Hlk505333623"/>Stalmann and Stehling, <hi rend="italic">Der Hamburger Arbeiter- und Soldatenrat
                    1918/19</hi>.</note> However, one should not underestimate the <hi rend="italic">Rätebewegung’s</hi> commitment and solidarity with the Russian
                soviets which they perceived as a strong symbol of the Revolution, showing that the
                working class was prepared to seize power and establish a participatory model of
                workers democracy.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn22" n="21">
                        David Priestland, "The Left and the Revolutions," in: <hi rend="italic">The
                            Oxford Handbook of European History, 1914‒1945</hi> (Oxford: Oxford
                        University Press, 2016), 88‒91.</note> Indeed, the independent <hi rend="italic">Rätebewegung</hi> practised a transfer of revolutionary experience
                from Russia to Germany, and when the elected representatives of German workers
                referred to the Russian Soviets, they were demonstrating their solidarity with them.
                Yet, revolutionary internationalism soon faded away when the soviets were
                subordinated to the »iron discipline« of the centralised Bolshevik party-rule.
                Whereas the soviets became virtually powerless, the <hi rend="italic">Betriebsräte</hi> (Work Council) in Germany survived as an instrument of
                participatory democracy in industrial working relations. The so-called »Paritätische
                Mitbestimmung« (Equal Participation) remains, to this day, a basic institutional
                pillar of the Social Market Economy of the Federal Republic.</p></item>
               <item><p>Although the origins of the national welfare state go back to the last quarter
                    of the 19<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> century, there can be no doubt about the
                    importance of social legislation following the First World War. Total war meant
                    heavy casualties, broken lives and financial losses for most families at home.
                    War victims had to be compensated for enduring sacrifices. The obligation to
                    care for the masses of war veterans, disabled people, widows and orphans,
                    refugees and displaced persons led to a vast extension of state allowances,
                    pensions and other sources of material relief. Social Security was thus,
                    essentially, a material compensation for the war commitment of European
                    populations. Nevertheless, the strong demand for social improvements has to be
                    interpreted in close relation to the rising force of working class movements all
                    across Europe. Strike activities returned in 1917 after the patriotic war
                    consensus in the belligerent nations ended, also affecting neutral countries
                    such as Spain. The Bolshevik government in Russia indicated the power of the
                    labour force, increasing trade unionism and industrial unrest, even in remote
                    England, where some leading members of the Labour Party »felt disquiet about
                    “the potential for a revolutionary situation”«.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn23" n="22"> June Purvis, <hi rend="italic">Emmeline
                                Pankhurst ‒ a Biography</hi> (London: Routledge, 2002),
                        303.</note> Obviously, British parliamentary government was discredited
                    since it couldn’t solve the Irish Question, nor conclude peace with its enemies
                    of war. Political polarisation divided the country and split the women’s
                    liberation movement from which Sylvia Pankhurst and her radical comrades turned
                    away in order to join the Communist International in 1919. She called for a
                    peace settlement and dreamed of a »Socialist Commonwealth«, whereas her mother
                    Emmeline patriotically continued to support the war efforts of the British
                    Government.</p> 
            <p>It is evident that when industrial strikes targeted the
                capitalist economy, their agenda was at least partly influenced by the Russian
                Revolution. The Soviet State proclaimed a fundamental reverse of labour relations,
                setting free peasants and industrial workers as a political force.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn24" n="23"> See Altrichter, <hi rend="italic">Russland 1917</hi>, 259–307, 330–67.</note> Factory workers’
                self-governing committees, the centralisation of distribution and the promise of a
                socialist producers’ community that would replace market relations offered an
                alternative model of a non-capitalist political economy. The Russian experience thus
                remained a source of permanent incentives and challenges for Western capitalism,
                which forced post-war governments to improve social relations at home. Corporatism
                and organised capitalism in England or Weimar Germany could therefore be seen as a
                reaction to Soviet »State Capitalism«, bringing forth preventive Social Welfare
                legislation, destined to discipline and integrate the labour force.</p></item>
            <item><p>War and revolution caused an unprecedented population transfer, especially in
                    Eastern and South-Eastern Europe. The decomposition of the Habsburg, Ottoman and
                    Romanov Empires led to a massive demographic drain of expatriates, creating new
                    ethnic urban quarters in those countries which took them in. Ethnic cleansing
                    had its origins in the war when national minorities were suspected as enemies
                    who posed a threat to the national political community. The Civil War in Russia
                    motivated the beleaguered Soviet government to dislocate greater parts of its
                    native population which it suspected as being politically unreliable. Political
                    pressure exerted on minorities released a second wave of mass migration which
                    followed the millions of people fleeing from war and violence inside the
                    territory of Imperial Russia – <hi rend="italic">a whole empire walking</hi>, to
                    use the famous phrase from Peter Gatrell.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn25" n="24"> Peter A. Gatrell, <hi rend="italic">A Whole
                                Empire Walking. Refugees in Russia During World War I</hi>
                            (Bloomington/Indiana: Indiana University Press, 1999).</note> The
                    bulk of refugees were expropriated and expatriated individuals and families, now
                    »stateless«, former residents of aristocratic or bourgeois origin and also
                    ethnic minorities that were forced to seek shelter elsewhere. When these groups
                    targeted European capitals such as Constantinople, Paris, Prague, Belgrade or
                    Berlin, they experienced new hardships laid upon them by authorities who
                    perceived them as strangers or even hostile groups who threatened the social
                    homogeneity of the indigenous community.</p>
           
            <p>The Russian Revolution challenged the world with the »first
                modern refugee-crisis«.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn26" n="25"> Behrends et. al., <hi rend="italic">Historisierung</hi>, 14. Catherine Gousseff, <hi rend="italic">L’exile
                            russe. La fabrique du réfugié apatride (1920–1939)</hi> (Paris: CNRS
                        Éditions, 2008).</note> Stateless <hi rend="italic">émigrés</hi> from
                Russia either had to rely on the acceptance of the Nansen-passport by foreign
                countries, or address single refugee relief organisations supported by the League of
                Nations. Immigrants arriving in Weimar-Germany were treated in different ways
                according to administrative categories referring to their supposed ethnic origins or
                social status, such as the Jewish refugees from Russia, Latvia or Poland who were
                merged into a single ethnic category labelled »<hi rend="italic">Ostjuden</hi>«.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn27" n="26"> Heiko Haumann, <hi rend="italic">Geschichte der Ostjuden</hi> (München:
                        DTV, <hi rend="superscript">6</hi>2008 [1990]), 77–89, 190–196. Frank M.
                        Schuster, <hi rend="italic">Zwischen allen Fronten. Osteuropäische Juden
                            während des Ersten Weltkrieges (1914‒1919)</hi> (Köln et al.: Böhlau,
                        2004).</note> This East-Jewish minority population remained an object of
                popular disdain, whereas the Russian community in Weimar-Germany, which numbered
                about half a million people at its peak at the beginning of the 1920s, succeeded to
                establish enduring cultural and social structures. Although Russian refugees were
                dispersed soon after living conditions deteriorated in late Weimar Germany and moved
                on westwards, they left the memory of <hi rend="italic">Russki Berlin</hi> behind
                them which remains, even today, an essential part of the history of Berlin, for
                example »<hi rend="italic">Charlottengrad«</hi> amongst other places.</p> </item>
            </list>
            <p><hi rend="italic">What does the Russian Revolution have to do with us</hi>? Reviewing
                the present state of research, it might seem as if the revolution was closely linked
                to war and the crisis of Imperial Russia. The vast literature on the World War has
                emphasised the contingent factors of military events and, at the same time,
                neglected social forces and political power structures in the belligerent societies.
                Finally, Red October appears merely as a secondary act in the grand drama of the
                European theatre of war.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn28" n="27"> Münkler, <hi rend="italic">Der Große Krieg</hi>,
                        546‒58, 617‒18, 653‒56, is rating the decay of the Imperial Army and the
                        violent military suppression of social uprisings in Petrograd much higher
                        than the social origins of the Revolution. </note> Much has been written
                about »blood lands« and »killing fields« in certain contaminated areas, where
                violence has been a constant experience of everyday life since the beginning of the
                20th century. Culturalist liberal historians tend to pay more attention to mental
                and cultural dispositions, which they consider to be relevant, to explain popular
                uprisings. However, a globalising approach which lacks to investigate specific
                constellations which caused revolutions in Russia, Germany, Hungary, or elsewhere
                risks downrating them as secondary phenomena to the Great War or as just another
                stage in an ongoing rage of civil war which turned the heart of Europe into a united
                slaughterhouse. What we tried to do here instead was to consider the different
                settings of political and social conditions that separated European countries during
                the war and which made them more or less susceptible to the challenges of the
                Russian Revolutions. Differentiations and comparisons are necessary to help us
                understand why the »Great Socialist October Revolution« is still relevant after 100
                years.</p></div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="bibliography">
                <head>Sources and Literature</head>
            <listBibl>
                <bibl>Altrichter, Helmut. <hi rend="italic">Russland 1917. Ein Land auf der Suche
                    nach sich selbst</hi>. Paderborn: Ferdinand Schöningh, <hi rend="superscript">2</hi>2017 (1997).</bibl>
                <bibl>Baberowski, Jörg and Gabriele Metzler, eds. <hi rend="italic">Gewalträume ‒
                    soziale Ordnungen im Ausnahmezustand</hi>. Frankfurt am Main: Campus Verlag,
                    2012.</bibl>
                <bibl>Baberowski, Jörg. "Die Russische Revolution und die Neuordnung der Welt." In:
                    <hi rend="italic">1917. Revolution: Russland und die Folgen</hi>, eds.
                    Deutsches Historisches Museum and Schweizer Nationalmuseum, 15–26. Berlin:
                    Sandstein Verlag, 2017.</bibl>
                <bibl>Baberowski, Jörg. <hi rend="italic">Räume der Gewalt</hi>. Frankfurt am Main:
                    S. Fischer, <hi rend="superscript">2</hi>2015. </bibl>
                <bibl>Baberowski, Jörg. "Verwüstetes Land: Macht und Gewalt in der frühen
                    Sowjetunion." In: <hi rend="italic">Gewalträume</hi>, eds. Jörg Baberowski and
                    Gabriele Metzler, 169‒89. Frankfurt am Main: Campus Verlag, 2012.</bibl>
                <bibl>Behrends, Jan C., Nikolaus Katzer and Thomas Lindenberger. "100 Jahre Roter
                    Oktober. Versuche zur Historisierung der Russischen Revolution." In: <hi rend="italic">100 Jahre Roter Oktober. Zur Weltgeschichte der Russian
                        Revolution</hi>, eds. Jan C. Behrends, Nikolaus Katzer and Thomas
                    Lindenberger, 9. Berlin: Christoph Links, 2017.</bibl>
                <bibl>Behrends, Jan C. "Was bleibt vom Kommunismus? Eine historische Betrachtung zum
                    100. Jahrestag der Russischen Revolution." In: <hi rend="italic">1917. 100 Jahre
                        Oktoberrevolution und ihre Fernwirkungen auf Deutschland</hi>, eds. Tilman
                    Mayer and Julia Reuschenbach, 23‒37. Baden-Baden: Nomos, 2017.</bibl>
                <bibl>Berthold, Lothar. "»Sie war und bleibt die Große Sozialistische
                    Oktoberrevolution!«." In: <hi rend="italic">Die Oktoberrevolution 1917 und ihr
                        Platz in der Geschichte</hi>, ed. Marx-Engels-Stiftung, 71‒81. Bonn:
                    Pahl-Rugenstein, 1997.</bibl>
                <bibl>Beyrau, Dietrich. <hi rend="italic">Krieg und Revolution. Russische
                    Erfahrungen</hi>. Paderborn: Ferdinand Schöningh, 2017.</bibl>
                <bibl>Bock, Helmut. "Die Russische Revolution 1917‒1921 ‒ Sieg oder Tragödie?." <hi rend="italic">Pankower Vorträge</hi>, No. 71 (2005).</bibl>
                <bibl>Bullock, Ian. <hi rend="italic">Romancing the revolution: the myth of Soviet
                    democracy and the British Left</hi>. Edmonton: Athabasca University Press,
                    2011.</bibl>
                <bibl>Doernberg, Stefan. "Oktoberrevolution ‒ Epochenwechsel oder Weg in die
                    Sackgasse?." In: <hi rend="italic">Die Oktoberrevolution 1917 und ihr Platz in
                        der Geschichte</hi>, ed. Marx-Engels-Stiftung, 9‒26. Bonn: Pahl-Rugenstein,
                    1997.</bibl>
                <bibl>Furet, François. <hi rend="italic">Das Ende der Illusion. Der Kommunismus im
                    20. Jahrhundert</hi>. München and Zürich: Piper, <hi rend="superscript">2</hi>1996 [<hi rend="italic">Le passé d’une illusion. Essai sur l’idée
                        communiste au XXe siècle</hi>, Paris: R. Laffont/Calmann-Léyy, 1995].</bibl>
                <bibl>Gatrell, Peter A. <hi rend="italic">A Whole Empire Walking. Refugees in Russia
                    During World War I</hi>. Bloomington/Indiana: Indiana University Press,
                    1999.</bibl>
                <bibl>Gousseff, Catherine. <hi rend="italic">L’exile russe. La fabrique du réfugié
                    apatride (1920–1939)</hi>. Paris: CNRS Éditions, 2008.</bibl>
                <bibl>Greifman, Anna. <hi rend="italic">Thou shalt kill. Revolutionary Terrorism in
                    Russia, 1894‒1917</hi>. Princeton/NJ: Princeton University Press
                    1993.</bibl>
                <bibl>Haumann, Heiko. <hi rend="italic">Geschichte der Ostjuden</hi>. München: DTV,
                    <hi rend="superscript">6</hi>2008 (1990).</bibl>
                <bibl>Hildermeyer, Manfred. <hi rend="italic">Die Sowjetunion 1917‒1991</hi>.
                    Berlin: De Gruyter, <hi rend="superscript">3</hi>2016.</bibl>
                <bibl>Hildermeyer, Manfred. <hi rend="italic">Geschichte Russlands vom Mittelalter
                    bis zur Oktoberrevolution</hi>. München: C.H.Beck, 2013.</bibl>
                <bibl>Hobsbawm, Eric J. <hi rend="italic">Das Zeitalter der Extreme: Weltgeschichte
                    des 20. Jahrhunderts 1914–1991</hi>. München: Hanser, 1995 [<hi rend="italic">The Age of Extremes: A History of the World, 1914-1991</hi>.
                    New York: Vintage Books, 1996].</bibl>
                <bibl>Holquist, Peter. <hi rend="italic">Making War, Forging Revolution. Russia’s
                    Continuum of Crisis, 1914‒1921</hi>. Cambridge/Mass.: Harvard University
                    Press, 2002.</bibl>
                <bibl>Janeke, Kristiane. "Einführung." In: <hi rend="italic">1917. Revolution:
                    Russland und die Folgen</hi>, eds. Deutsches Historisches Museum and
                    Schweizer Nationalmuseum, 10‒13. Berlin: Sandstein Verlag 2017.</bibl>
                <bibl>Koenen, Gerd. "Der »Rote Oktober« als Mythos und Utopicum." In: <hi rend="italic">1917. Revolution: Russland und die Folgen</hi>, eds. Deutsches
                    Historisches Museum and Schweizer Nationalmuseum, 141‒57. Berlin: Sandstein
                    Verlag, 2017.</bibl>
                <bibl>Leonhard, Jörn. <hi rend="italic">Die Büchse der Pandora. Geschichte des
                    Ersten Weltkriegs</hi>. München: C.H.Beck, <hi rend="superscript">5</hi>2014.</bibl>
                <bibl>Malia, Martin. <hi rend="italic">Vollstreckter Wahn. Russland 1917‒1991</hi>.
                    Stuttgart: Klett-Cotta, 1994.</bibl>
                <bibl>Mayer, Arno J. <hi rend="italic">The Furies. Violence and Terror in the French
                    and the Russian Revolution</hi>, Princeton/NJ: Princeton University Press,
                    2000.</bibl>
                <bibl>Münkler, Herfried. <hi rend="italic">Der Große Krieg. Die Welt 1914‒1918</hi>.
                    Berlin: Rowohlt, <hi rend="superscript">7</hi>2014.</bibl>
                <bibl><hi rend="italic">Northern Voices: The Leeds Soviet – 1917!</hi>. 15 February
                    2018. http://northernvoicesmag.blogspot.de/2017/01/the-leeds-soviet-1917.html.</bibl>
             <bibl>Plaggenborg, Stefan. <hi rend="italic">Ordnungen der Gewalt: Sozialismus,
                    Kemalismus, Faschismus</hi>. München: Oldenbourg Wissenschaftsverlag,
                    2012.</bibl>
                <bibl>Plaggenborg, Stefan. <hi rend="italic">Revolutionskultur. Menschenbilder und
                    kulturelle Praxis in Sowjetrussland zwischen Oktoberrevolution und
                    Stalinismus</hi>. Köln et al.: Böhlau, 1996.</bibl>
                <bibl>Priestland, David. "The Left and the Revolutions." In: <hi rend="italic">The
                    Oxford Handbook of European History</hi>, ed. Nicholas Doumanis, 88‒91.
                    Oxford: Oxford University Press, 2016.</bibl>
                <bibl>Purvis, June. <hi rend="italic">Emmeline Pankhurst ‒ a Biography</hi>. London:
                    Routledge, 2002.</bibl>
                <bibl>Puschnerat, Tânia. <hi rend="italic">Clara Zetkin ‒ Bürgerlichkeit und
                    Marxismus. Eine Biografie</hi>. Essen: Klartext Verlag, 2003.</bibl>
                <bibl>Sabrow, Martin. "Der »Rote Oktober« und sein Nachhall im geteilten
                    Deutschland." In: <hi rend="italic">1917. Revolution: Russland und die
                        Folgen</hi>, eds. Deutsches Historisches Museum and Schweizer
                    Nationalmuseum, 125‒39. Berlin: Sandstein Verlag, 2017.</bibl>
                <bibl>Schnell, Felix. <hi rend="italic">Räume des Schreckens. Gewalträume und
                    Gruppenmilitanz in der Ukraine 1905‒1933</hi>. Hamburg: Hamburger Edition,
                    2012.</bibl>
                <bibl>Schuster, Frank M. <hi rend="italic">Zwischen allen Fronten. Osteuropäische
                    Juden während des Ersten Weltkrieges (1914‒1919)</hi>. Köln et al.: Böhlau,
                    2004.</bibl>
                <bibl>Stalmann, Volker and Jutta Stehling. <hi rend="italic">Der Hamburger Arbeiter-
                    und Soldatenrat 1918/19</hi>. Düsseldorf: Droste, 2013.</bibl>
            </listBibl></div>
            <div type="summary" xml:lang="sl"><docAuthor>Andreas Schulz</docAuthor>
                <head>»KAJ IMA ZA OPRAVITI Z NAMI?«– PONOVNO VREDNOTENJE RUSKE REVOLUCIJE V NEMČIJI</head>
            <head>POVZETEK</head>
            <p>"Kaj ima za opraviti z nami?"– Ponovno vrednotenje ruske revolucije
                v Nemčiji Če pogledamo trenutno stanje na področju raziskav, bi lahko
                dobili vtis, da je bila revolucija tesno povezana z vojno in krizo carske Rusije. V
                obsežni literaturi o svetovni vojni so poudarjeni naključni dejavniki vojaških
                dogodkov, hkrati pa se zanemarjajo nekatere družbene sile in strukture politične
                moči v vojskujočih se družbah. Rdeči oktober se pojavi zgolj kot dejanje drugotnega
                pomena v veliki drami evropskega bojišča. Veliko je bilo napisanega o "krvavi
                zemlji" in "poljih smrti" na nekaterih kontaminiranih območjih, kjer je bilo nasilje
                od začetka 20. stoletja nenehno del vsakdanjega življenja. Kulturalistični liberalni
                zgodovinarji se pri razlaganju ljudskih vstaj navadno bolj osredotočajo na miselne
                in kulturne dispozicije, ki se jim zdijo pomembne. Vendar pa pri globalističnem
                pristopu, v okviru katerega se ne preučujejo specifična razmerja, ki so povzročila
                revolucije v Rusiji, Nemčiji, na Madžarskem in drugod, obstaja tveganje, da se te
                revolucije degradirajo v pojave drugotnega pomena glede na veliko vojno ali zgolj v
                eno od faz razbesnele državljanske vojne, ki je srce Evrope spremenila v skupinsko
                klavnico. Avtor namesto tega obravnava različne politične in družbene pogoje, ki so
                ločevali evropske države med vojno in zaradi katerih so bile te bolj ali manj
                dovzetne za izzive ruskih revolucij. Razlikovanja in primerjave so potrebne, da bi
                lahko razumeli, zakaj je "velika socialistična oktobrska revolucija" po 100 letih še
                vedno pomembna.</p></div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>