<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Sixty years of the contemporary history magazine that has itself become a part of contemporary history</title>
                <author>
                    <forename>Jure</forename>
                    <surname>Gašparič</surname>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2020-09</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>
                    <orgName xml:lang="sl">Inštitut za novejšo zgodovino</orgName>
                    <orgName xml:lang="en">Institute of Contemporary History</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Privoz 11</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>SI-1000 Ljubljana</addrLine>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>http://ojs.inz.si/pnz/article/view/1209</pubPlace>
                <date>2020</date>
                <availability status="free">
                    <licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title xml:lang="sl">Prispevki za novejšo zgodovino</title>
                <title xml:lang="en">Contributions to Contemporary History</title>
                <biblScope unit="volume">60</biblScope>
                <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
                <idno type="ISSN">2463-7807</idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source, born digital.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc xml:lang="en">
                <p>Contributions to Contemporary History is one of the central Slovenian scientific
                    historiographic journals, dedicated to publishing articles from the field of
                    contemporary history (the 19th and 20th century).</p>
                <p>The journal is published three times per year in Slovenian and in the following
                    foreign languages: English, German, Serbian, Croatian, Bosnian, Italian, Slovak
                    and Czech. The articles are all published with abstracts in English and
                    Slovenian as well as summaries in English.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <projectDesc xml:lang="sl">
                <p>Prispevki za novejšo zgodovino je ena osrednjih slovenskih znanstvenih
                    zgodovinopisnih revij, ki objavlja teme s področja novejše zgodovine (19. in 20.
                    stoletje).</p>
                <p>Revija izide trikrat letno v slovenskem jeziku in v naslednjih tujih jezikih:
                    angleščina, nemščina, srbščina, hrvaščina, bosanščina, italijanščina, slovaščina
                    in češčina. Članki izhajajo z izvlečki v angleščini in slovenščini ter povzetki
                    v angleščini.</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change>
                    <date>2020-09</date>
                    <name>Mihael Ojsteršek</name>
                    <desc>Pretvorba iz DOCX v TEI, dodatno kodiranje</desc>
                </change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <docAuthor>Jure Gašparič</docAuthor>
        </front>
        <body>
           <quote>
                <hi rend="italic">“...let us build, one stone at a time, the structure of the
                    contemporary history of the main social forces and transformations...”</hi>
            </quote>
            <p>The editorship prepared the first issue of the magazine in June 1969, soon after the
                establishment of the Institute for the History of the Workers’ Movement, the
                forerunner of the today’s Institute of Contemporary History. The editorship that
                consisted of seven members under the leadership of France Klopčič submitted 388
                pages for printing (including the final <hi rend="italic">errata</hi> page, which
                was customary at that time). A modest and tasteful cover was designed by Plečnik’s
                student Vlasto Kopač, who also designed the Liberation Front’s newsletters.
                Stereotypes were made by the stereotype casting room ČZP Ljudska pravica, while the
                Tone Tomšič printing house took care of the printing. The first issue of the
                Contributions to the History of the Workers’ Movement, a new scientific publication
                in Slovenia, finally hit the bookshelves in an astonishing print run of 3000 copies.
                In a short introduction, the members of the editorship wrote that the publication
                continued the tradition of the two issues of the yearbook, published, until then, by
                the Museum of National Liberation of the People’s Republic of Slovenia. They added
                that it would strive to “explore, in the Marxist tradition, the emergence,
                development, and social role of the working class in Slovenia as the proponent of
                socialist and communist ideas, the driving force of social transformations, and the
                leader and liberator of the working people from the old system of exploitation,
                oppression, and wars”. </p>
            <p>Finally, the editorship ambitiously emphasised that Contributions hoped to become “a
                new, additional factor in the Slovenian historiography with no intentions to
                restrict or replace any existing historical institutions or their functions. On the
                contrary, the scope and depth of historiography will thus only expand and open new
                possibilities for Slovenian historians to create freely.” </p>
            <p>Sixty years have passed since then and the publication that initially focused on the
                aforementioned issues of the most recent history, which were naturally relevant at
                that time, has transformed, redirected, and expanded the spatial, topical, and
                temporal foci of its interests in accordance with the development of contemporary
                historiography. One of the main scientific media of contemporary history researchers
                has eventually become a part of contemporary history itself. The only things that
                have not changed – if I may add somewhat mischievously – are the commitment to
                scientific methodology and the occasional short introductions. </p>
            <p>In the opinion of Franc Rozman, one of the publication’s later editors, Contributions
                specifically reflected the Institute’s work, development, shortcomings, and
                successes during the first decade. “More than any other Slovenian historical
                magazine, it is closely connected to the development and concepts of its publishing
                institution, thus representing an overview of a considerable part of the Institute’s
                scientific, research, and archival activities.” Despite all the changes, this
                statement mostly still holds true today. All the junior researchers at the Institute
                begin by publishing in Contributions, and all the associates keep publishing there
                more or less regularly until or even after they retire. The publication is a
                wonderful reflection of the progress, achieved by the Institute’s explorers of the
                most recent past, but in no way exclusively by them – the door of the editorial
                office is wide open to everyone. </p>
            <p>The initial concept of the programme lasted only for a decade, as the magazine, along
                with the Institute, swiftly outgrew its initial framework. The workers’ movement and
                World War II remained at the forefront for a while, yet they were certainly not the
                only subjects of discussion. The scope kept widening – from the Party to other
                political camps, from workers to broader socio-economic analyses, history of
                everyday life, environmental history, history of culture, etc. The temporal
                framework kept expanding as well: in the beginning, it was based on the period from
                1941 to 1945 and the Kingdom of Yugoslavia. Until today, however, its scope has
                extended well into the 19 th and the 21st century. Similarly, we can also follow
                methodological transformation and growth, as well as changes in the approaches to
                narration, structuring, and presentation of subjects. </p>
            <p>Today, Contributions are thus a reflection of our times. We believe that the magazine
                still represents a decent mirror to historiography, committed to the contemporary
                trends in the publishing of scientific periodicals. The editorship insists on
                linguistic perfection and encourages publishing in the Slovenian language.
                Nevertheless, each article is also accompanied by a comprehensive summary in a
                foreign language. We also publish topical issues in the English language, thus
                increasing the visibility of the published research findings. </p>
            <p>The main question that we face, has, however, remained the same throughout these
                sixty years: who do we write for, and why? Nowadays, scientific historiographical
                publications are no match for the competition, represented by television and other
                electronic as well as standard newspaper media. The print run is now six times
                smaller than sixty years ago. Eric Hobsbawm has already established that “modern
                media society has given the past unprecedented prominence and marketing potential”.
                However, this primarily means that it is profitable to “sell” the past in all kinds
                of ways – and, if need be, also to simplify, transfigure, and adapt it (not
                necessarily, though!). The modern trends foresee further “marginalisation” of the
                classic scientific magazine. The editorship is nonetheless convinced that scientific
                magazines should not and cannot search for ways to compete with the media that
                appeal to readers in a more efficient and seducing manner. Instead, scientific
                publications should endeavour (along with books) to keep forming the very
                foundations of the scientific historiography for the foreseeable future. This,
                however, does not mean that they should not strive to approach the readers who are
                not necessarily experts in specific fields. A modern scientific magazine should be
                as appealing and accessible as possible in all formats (printed, digital, etc.). </p>
            <p>All these years, the magazine has been edited by editorships consisting
                mainly of the Institute members. The chief and (or) managing editors have always
                come from the ranks of the Institute. The first editor was France Klopčič, a
                critical explorer of the Slovenian contemporary historical development. He was
                succeeded by the World War II historians Franček Saje and France Škerl. After Škerl,
                the magazine was edited by Jože Šorn, a specialist in economic history; and later by
                Franc Rozman, an expert in the 19 th century, who is even nowadays renowned for
                reading everything written by Slovenian historians with a particularly critical eye.
                Between two Rozman’s editorships, the publication was in the care of Stane Granda,
                an economic historian; after which it was, for a long time, in the hands of Zdenko
                Čepič, one of the first researchers of the period after World War II. He and Damijan
                Guštin ensured that the magazine survived the tumultuous times of the transition.
                Finally, the editorship was taken over by the author of this introduction. </p>
            <p>Each editor and every editorship did their best to steer the magazine’s
                development. However, it was undoubtedly most profoundly influenced by the authors –
                writers with their foci, their manners of communicating the topics, and their
                understanding of contemporary history. They are the most deserving that the
                publication is celebrating such an important anniversary. Therefore, this issue
                should be dedicated precisely to them: the authors of contributions about
                contemporary Slovenian history. I wish many more outstanding texts to all of them! </p>            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
