<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Editorial</title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename>Jurij</forename>
                        <surname>Gašparič</surname>
                    </name>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>2018-10-15</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>
                    <orgName xml:lang="sl">Inštitut za novejšo zgodovino</orgName>
                    <orgName xml:lang="en">Institute of Contemporary History</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Kongresni trg 1</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>SI-1000 Ljubljana</addrLine>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>http://ojs.inz.si/pnz/article/view/346</pubPlace>
                <date>2019</date>
                <availability status="free">
                    <licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title xml:lang="sl">Prispevki za novejšo zgodovino</title>
                <title xml:lang="en">Contributions to Contemporary History</title>
                <biblScope unit="volume">59</biblScope>
                <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
                <idno type="ISSN">2463-7807</idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source, born digital.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc xml:lang="en">
                <p>Contributions to Contemporary History is one of the central Slovenian scientific
                    historiographic journals, dedicated to publishing articles from the field of
                    contemporary history (the 19th and 20th century).</p>
                <p>The journal is published three times per year in Slovenian and in the following
                    foreign languages: English, German, Serbian, Croatian, Bosnian, Italian, Slovak
                    and Czech. The articles are all published with abstracts in English and
                    Slovenian as well as summaries in English.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <projectDesc xml:lang="sl">
                <p>Prispevki za novejšo zgodovino je ena osrednjih slovenskih znanstvenih
                    zgodovinopisnih revij, ki objavlja teme s področja novejše zgodovine (19. in 20.
                    stoletje).</p>
                <p>Revija izide trikrat letno v slovenskem jeziku in v naslednjih tujih jezikih:
                    angleščina, nemščina, srbščina, hrvaščina, bosanščina, italijanščina, slovaščina
                    in češčina. Članki izhajajo z izvlečki v angleščini in slovenščini ter povzetki
                    v angleščini.</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change>
                    <date>2019-05-31</date>
                    <name>Neja Blaj Hribar</name>
                    <desc>Pretvorba iz DOCX v TEI, dodatno kodiranje</desc>
                </change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <docAuthor>
                <name>
                    <forename>Darja Fišer, Andrej Pančur and Tomaž Erjavec</forename>
                    <surname>Gašparič</surname>
                </name>
            </docAuthor>
            
        </front>
        <body>
            <p style="text-align:center;"><hi rend="bold">Editorial</hi></p>
            <p> The current special issue of the journal <hi rend="italic">Contributions to
                    contemporary history</hi> brings papers which seem to break with the established
                editorial tradition. The journal has been issued regularly by the Institute of
                contemporary history since 1960 which was called <hi rend="italic">Institute for the
                    History of the Labour Movement</hi> until 1986. The journal was renamed at the
                same time as the institute, and it has since become one of the major Slovenian
                scientific journals in the field of history that publishes papers on the
                contemporary history (19th and 20th century) of Central and Southeastern Europe.
                With the establishment of an infrastructure programme Research infrastructure of
                Slovenian Historiography the Institute has entered the field of digital history and
                has contributed to the establishment of the European <hi rend="italic">Digital
                    Research Infrastructure for Arts and Humanities</hi> (DARIAH) since 2008. With
                this, the Institute of contemporary history has started to develop into one of the
                major digital humanities hubs in Slovenia. The current special issue is one of the
                results of this new research direction of its publisher and reflects a distinct
                interdisciplinary and heterogeneous profile of digital humanities.</p>
            <p> With this special issue we are celebrating the 20th anniversary of the first <hi
                    rend="italic">Language technologies conference</hi> which took place in 1998 in
                Cankarjev dom, Ljubljana and was organized by Tomaž Erjavec, Vojko Gorjanc, Jerneja
                Žganec Gros and Anica Rant. The topics of the first conference were the development
                and application of language technologies for Slovene and directions for the future.
                The conference has since been held biennially and has recently expanded its focus to
                digital humanities. As the intersection of digital technologies and the humanities,
                digital humanities is a very active research field where digital technologies are
                used in the study of language, society and culture, but humanities research also
                paves the way for the development of new digital technologies. Digital humanities is
                a highly interdisciplinary and collaborative field which transforms traditional
                practices in the humanities and acts as a catalyst of new analytical techniques and
                methods as well as promotes discussion between the different stakeholders in the
                field. This initiative aims to promote integration of the disciplines and at the
                same act as an important hub for fellow researchers in the region. </p>
            <p> We invited authors of 11 best-reviewed regular papers and the best student paper
                that were presented a the <hi rend="italic">Language technologies and digital
                    humanities conference</hi> which took place on 20–21 September 2018 in
                Ljubljana, organized by the <hi rend="italic">Slovenian language technologies
                    society, Centre for language resources and technologies at the University of
                    Ljubljana, Faculty of Electrical Engineering of the University of Ljubljana</hi>
                and the research infrastructures <hi rend="italic">CLARIN.SI</hi> and <hi
                    rend="italic">DARIAH-SI</hi>. Authors of 10 regular papers and the student paper
                from the fields of language technologies, digital linguistics and digital humanities
                accepted the invitation and prepared extended papers relevant for an international
                audience which then underwent another reviewing procedure by international
                reviewers.</p>
            <p> The editors of the special issue would like to thank the authors and the reviewers
                for their dedicated work as well as for believing in the challenge and being willing
                to engage in an interdisciplinary dialogue which requires all the parties involved
                to step out of their comfort zone but also brings knowledge transfer and rewarding
                results. </p>
            <p></p>
            <p>Ljubljana, May 16<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>, 2019</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
