<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Titoism, Dissidents and Culture of Dissent</title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename>Albert</forename>
                        <surname>Bing</surname>
                        <roleName>Senior Research Fellow</roleName>
                        <roleName>PhD</roleName>
                        <affiliation>Croatian Institute of History</affiliation>
                        <address>
                            <addrLine>Opatička 10</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>10000–Zagreb, Croatia</addrLine>
                        </address>
                        <email>albert1.bing@gmail.com</email>
                    </name>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>2017-10-18</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>
                    <orgName xml:lang="sl">Inštitut za novejšo zgodovino</orgName>
                    <orgName xml:lang="en">Institute of Contemporary History</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Kongresni trg 1</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>SI-1000 Ljubljana</addrLine>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>http://ojs.inz.si/pnz/article/view/305</pubPlace>
                <date>2018</date>
                <availability status="free">
                    <licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title xml:lang="sl">Prispevki za novejšo zgodovino</title>
                <title xml:lang="en">Contributions to Contemporary History</title>
                <biblScope unit="volume">58</biblScope>
                <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
                <idno type="ISSN">2463-7807</idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source, born digital.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc xml:lang="en">
                <p>Contributions to Contemporary History is one of the central Slovenian scientific
                    historiographic journals, dedicated to publishing articles from the field of
                    contemporary history (the 19th and 20th century).</p>
                <p>The journal is published three times per year in Slovenian and in the following
                    foreign languages: English, German, Serbian, Croatian, Bosnian, Italian, Slovak
                    and Czech. The articles are all published with abstracts in English and
                    Slovenian as well as summaries in English.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <projectDesc xml:lang="sl">
                <p>Prispevki za novejšo zgodovino je ena osrednjih slovenskih znanstvenih
                    zgodovinopisnih revij, ki objavlja teme s področja novejše zgodovine (19. in 20.
                    stoletje).</p>
                <p>Revija izide trikrat letno v slovenskem jeziku in v naslednjih tujih jezikih:
                    angleščina, nemščina, srbščina, hrvaščina, bosanščina, italijanščina, slovaščina
                    in češčina. Članki izhajajo z izvlečki v angleščini in slovenščini ter povzetki
                    v angleščini.</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="sl"/>
                <language ident="en"/>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords xml:lang="en">
                    <term>Dissidents</term>
                    <term>Josip Broz Tito</term>
                    <term>Yugoslavia</term>
                    <term>Titoism</term>
                    <term>Communism</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords xml:lang="sl">
                    <term>Disidenti</term>
                    <term>Josip Broz Tito</term>
                    <term>titoizem</term>
                    <term>Jugoslavija</term>
                    <term>komunizem</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change>
                    <date>2017-12-18</date>
                    <name>Neja Blaj Hribar</name>
                    <desc>Pretvorba iz DOCX v TEI, dodatno kodiranje</desc>
                </change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <docAuthor>Albert Bing<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn1" n="*">
                <hi rend="bold" xml:space="preserve">Senior Research Fellow, PhD, Croatian Institute of History,
                            Opatička 10, 10000–Zagreb, Croatia,</hi>
                        <ref target="mailto:albert1.bing@gmail.com"><hi rend="bold">albert1.bing@gmail.com</hi></ref><hi rend="bold">.</hi></note></docAuthor>
            <docImprint>
                <idno type="cobissType">Cobiss type: 1.01</idno>
                <idno type="UDC">UDC: 329.052:323.281 (497.1)"1945/1990"</idno>
            </docImprint>
            <div type="abstract" xml:lang="sl">
                <head>IZVLEČEK</head>
                <head>TITOIZEM, DISIDENTI IN KULTURA NASPROTOVANJA</head>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Prispevek obravnava vprašanje jugoslovanskih disidentov v zvezi s
                        sistemom komunističnega upravljanja in delovanja države pod vodstvom Josipa
                        Broza Tita. V širšem kontekstu je analizirana vloga kritične inteligence, tj.
                        kulture disidentstva, v značilnih jugoslovanskih okvirjih. Prispevek vsebuje
                        krajši pregled posebnosti jugoslovanskih disidentov, predvsem razlik v njihovem
                        dojemanju, vrst kritik in medsebojnih odnosov, ki so jih imeli kot nasprotniki
                        režima, pa tudi različnih usod posameznikov. Poseben poudarek je bil na stališču
                        Zahoda do jugoslovanskih disidentov, ki se je precej razlikoval v primerjavi s
                        stališčem do disidentov iz Sovjetske zveze in drugih držav
                        realsocializma.</hi></p>
                <p><hi rend="italic"> Ključne besede: Disidenti, Josip Broz Tito, titoizem, Jugoslavija, komunizem</hi></p>
            </div>
            <div type="abstract">
                <head><hi rend="italic allcaps">Abstract</hi></head>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">The paper deals with the issue of the Yugoslav dissidents with
                        regard to the system of communist governance and the functioning of the state
                        led by Josip Broz Tito. In the wider context the role of critical intelligentsia
                        – a culture of dissent – is analyzed within distinctive Yugoslav frameworks. The
                        paper includes a shorter overview of the particularity of the Yugoslav
                        dissidents, above all the differences in their perceptions, type of criticism,
                        their mutual relations – as the opponents to the regime, and different destinies
                        of individuals. Special emphasis was put on the West’s position of Yugoslav
                        dissidents which differed considerably in comparison with dissidents from the
                        Soviet Union and other states of real socialism.</hi></p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Keywords: Dissidents, Josip Broz Tito, Titoism, Yugoslavia,
                        Communism</hi></p>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div><head>Titoism and Culture of Dissent</head>
            <p> The nature of the post–war Yugoslav version of a dissident is closely related to the
                system of governance and values of the Yugoslav socialist society (Titoism),
                embodied by Josip Broz Tito. According to many indicators, the Yugoslav sovereign
                was an autocrat. But what was the nature of his dictatorship? How did he govern and
                what was the state he ruled? Josip Broz Tito, the first name of Yugoslav communism,
                the guerrilla leader who has gained fame and respect even with his ideological
                opponents during and after the Second World War, ruled the post–war Yugoslav
                communist state “with an iron hand in a velvet glove.” Historian Ivo Banac reveals
                in Broz’s individuality the persistent historical paradigm for the South Slav zone:
                “ill fate of the Balkans” which exhibits “the need for order in a mobile encampment,
                faith in an imperial idea as the sole guarantor against chaos.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn2" n="1"> Ivo Banac, <hi rend="italic">Acta
                            Turcarum</hi> (Zagreb: Durieux), 2006, 32.</note> In this sense,
                British historian A. J. P. Taylor notes that “Marshal Tito was the last
                    Habsburg.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn3" n="2"> A.J.P.
                        Taylor, <hi rend="italic">Habsburška monarhija 1809 – 1918</hi> (Zagreb:
                        Znanje, 1990), 323–24.</note> According to the writer Stanko Lasić, Tito
                was a hypocritical pragmatist, an extremely determined and skilled politician and a
                statesman who knew how to use his strength and turn defeats into a victory.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn4" n="3"> Stanko Lasić<hi rend="italic">, Mladi Krleža i njegovi kritičari 1914. –
                        1924</hi><hi rend="short_text" xml:space="preserve"> (</hi>Zagreb: Globus,
                        1987), 590–91.</note> For political emigrants, he was a Machiavellian,
                cruel communist dictator.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn5" n="4"> Jure Petričević, “Hrvatski nacionalni problem,” in:
                            <hi rend="italic">Hrvatska revija</hi>, Vol. 2–3 (1964):
                200.</note></p>
            <p> As observed by Aleksa Đilas Yugoslavia was “a country that was difficult to explain
                and understand, perhaps even harder for those who lived in it and were not
                indifferent to it, but to those who do not carry that experience. It was a land full
                of paradoxes.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn6" n="5"> Dejan
                        Jović, <hi rend="italic">Jugoslavija koja je odumrla</hi> (Zagreb: Prometej,
                        2003), 495.</note> Anecdotally, Tito’s Yugoslavia was described as a
                country with “six republics, five people, four languages, three religions, two
                letters, and one Tito.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn7" n="6"> Martti Ahtisaari, <hi rend="italic">Beogradska zadaća
                            – Kako je slaman Mil</hi>ošević (Zagreb: Naklada Szabo A3 data, 2002),
                        23.</note> In the short resume on Tito’s Yugoslavia, Tvrtko Jakovina
                concludes: “Yugoslavia was a one–party dictatorship in which elections were not
                democratic, in which one could be prosecuted for singing an inappropriate song, the
                society in which the advancement of the service sought membership in the Communist
                Party, the state in which it was not free to believe and pray. Yugoslavia was not a
                free country, but it was the most liberal communist state in Europe.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn8" n="7"> Tvrtko Jakovina,
                        “J.B.T. Historiografija vs. Mitologija. Komunist kojega je Zapad podržavao,”
                            <hi rend="italic">Večernji list</hi>, April 30, 2005.</note> What
                were repressive and liberal aspects in Tito’s Yugoslavia? How did they manifest
                themselves and how they were connected? What was the nature of dissent in
                Yugoslavia? What was the position of those who – in any way – questioned the
                political authorities? Who were the Yugoslav dissidents?</p>
            <p> The questioning of freedom in the societies ruled by the undisputed authorities
                implies the emergence of critical thinking, resistance, and dissent. The
                relationship between authoritarian power and opponents to the regime had specific
                historical significance in communist societies. In the words of Vaclav Havel: “You
                do not become a ‘dissident’ just because you decide one day to take up this most
                unusual career. You are thrown into it by your personal sense of responsibility,
                combined with a complex set of external circumstances. You are cast out of the
                existing structures and placed in a position of conflict with them.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn9" n="8"> “Václav Havel: From a
                        political dissident to a dissident politician,” accessed August 13, 2018,
                            <ref target="http://www.pehe.cz/Members/redaktor/vaclav-havel-from-a-political-dissident-to-a">http://www.pehe.cz/Members/redaktor/vaclav–havel–from–a–political–dissident–to–a</ref>.
                    </note> As well as other communist states Yugoslavia cherished a cult
                leader, carried out censorship and ideological manipulations and repressed those who
                opposed to the authority of Tito and Communist Party. The periodical clash with
                those disobedient in their own ranks was combined with the constant struggle with
                political emigration (which was considered as people enemies). </p>
            <p>However, the system of political and social control characteristic to totalitarian
                regimes in the states of real communism significantly differed in the Yugoslav case.
                Unlike the other communist states Yugoslavia was under the strong influence of the
                West – especially in culture (from the early 1950s) and it was relatively open
                country. The Yugoslav cultural politics was one of the most significant indicators
                to Yugoslav distinctiveness; it was also relevant to the emergence of the specific
                Yugoslav culture of dissent as a result of a constant struggle of liberal–minded
                intellectuals and authoritarian rule. The Yugoslav ambiguities, and afterward the
                fact that the very state ceased to exist, are probably the reasons why it is not
                easy to deal with the complex Yugoslav past. A rational and critical approach to the
                phenomenon of Titoism and Tito’s Yugoslav state still present a challenge to
                historical analysis. </p>
            <p>One of the problems of historical analysis can be identified in the deficit of
                historiographic synthesis of wider social scopes in the postwar period. Tito’s
                Yugoslavia broke up, and even while it lasted there were weak attempts of more
                significant historical synthesis to its past. Serbian historian Andrej Mitrović
                notes: “Concerning the past of Yugoslavia it is very important to stress that it has
                been not historically sufficiently explored. It doesn’t mean that there had not been
                valuable research, but in that context, two external indicators can be considered as
                well. How many histories of the Yugoslav state did we produce? Two, three, mostly in
                the eighties at the end of the decay of the state. In world history, every country
                has dozens of its history, ‘small’ and ‘big’, booklets and multi–editions ...”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn10" n="9"> Andrej Mitrović,
                        “Javna, tajna i porodična istorija,” interviewed by Aleksandar Ćirić,
                        <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Vreme, </hi>No. 429, Januar 9,
                        1999.</note> Many would argue that the “lack of history” was the problem
                of Yugoslav successor states and its people, but it certainly does not contribute to
                a better understanding of the complexity of the Yugoslav past. Considering many
                “unsolved” historical issues one can observe that past places a burden on
                contemporaries as an eternal presence.</p>
            <p>The phenomenon of culture of dissent in the Yugoslav society, including the that of
                dissidents, had its cyclic changes – variations that largely depended on the vague
                ambivalences of Titoism: “he ‘cold’ and ‘hot’ periods interchanged; after the period
                of release and relative liberalization the period of ‘clash’ would follow, and it
                was skillfully maintained as a balance between different ideological currents in
                party leadership and confrontation between republics.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn11" n="10"> Ivica Župan,
                        <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Pragmatičari, dogmati, sanjari – hrvatska umjetnost i društvo 1950.–ih godina </hi>(Zagreb:
                        Ina industrija nafte d.d. and Meridijani, 2007), 19.</note> Like the
                other communist states Yugoslavia had a capillary system of social control based on
                censorship and ideological commissions and a privileged position of “socio–political
                workers” was maintained as the power lever. Following the cyclic changes of Yugoslav
                society the social power and control of one–party system slightly faded away, but
                almost until the very end of the Yugoslav state the Communist Party apparatus was a
                decisive factor in almost all aspects of public life. However, under Tito’s
                “scepter” some of the liberties in Yugoslavia have been developed that were
                unimaginable in other states powered by the communists. Strangely enough, in
                Yugoslav socialist society the ideological indoctrination conducted by the party
                apparatus “coexisted” with various forms of intelligentsia criticism; the compelling
                repertoire of the Communist “Reveille” and hymn – dedicated to the cult of Tito’s
                personality – was pervaded by jazz and rock’n’roll and the admiration of American
                film actors. According to Czech film director Jiří Menzel socialist Yugoslavia, as a
                country open to Western influences, has been perceived in communist bloc countries
                as “America of the East.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn12" n="11"> Jiří Menzel, <hi rend="italic">Moja Hrvatska</hi>,
                        HTV, Documentary, August 18, 2011.</note> Such a cultural climate would
                not be possible without a certain social cohesion and the main integrating factor
                was the Yugoslav sovereign.</p>
            <p> An important instrumentality of authority was the cultural policy. Like in other
                aspects of the public sphere Tito had the most important role as supreme arbitrator.
                All other institutional mechanisms simply followed. Promoting the workers
                self–management at the beginning of 1950s the National Assembly “predicted that its
                success will depend on how rapidly the cultural development will advance.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn13" n="12"> Predrag Matvejević,
                            <hi rend="italic">Jugoslavensvo danas–Pitanja kulture</hi> (Zagreb:
                        Globus, 1982), 128.</note> With the “ups and downs” and parallel to the
                party propaganda a distinct “space of freedom” will be developed due to a relatively
                liberal cultural policy. And it wasn’t deprived of controversy. One of the central
                figures of the Croatian and Yugoslav culture and close associate to Tito – Miroslav
                Krleža, was often portrayed as the rebellious free spirit. As a writer, he
                frequently emphasized the destiny of an artist as someone who is doomed to dissent:
                “In order to practice his craftsmanship properly a writer must have the ability to
                be a dissident or even a defector in some ways, from the institutions, the nation,
                and the authorities. He is a prodigal son who returns to his father’s hearth just to
                be able to leave him again. Negation is his familiar form of acceptance of the
                world. The only one who radically understands and accepts this truth can really help
                the writer or the artist.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn14" n="13"> Predrag Matvejević, “Mjera naše zrelosti,” <hi rend="italic">Školske novine</hi>, January 7, 1982.</note>
                In 1952, at the Third Congress of the Yugoslav
                        Writers’ Union in Ljubljana Krleža opposed socialist realism and announced the liberation of literature from ideological bonds. Broad cultural activity developed and, within it, various cultures of dissent.</p>
            <p> Culture went through non–linear metamorphosis just as did the Yugoslav socialist
                society as a whole; from the Stalinist phase of showdown with “national enemies” –
                when there was strict censorship and rigid party control over all aspects of life
                including culture, until the end of the eighties when communist officials publicly
                stated that they were no longer able to control the social processes that ultimately
                led to the emergence of political pluralism. The film director Đorđe Kadijević (<hi rend="italic">Praznik, Pohod</hi>) who was a representative of socially engaged
                Yugoslav film – so–called <hi rend="italic">Blake Wave</hi> – described the paradox
                of Titoism: “My films, albeit forbidden, went to world festivals and had great
                success.” On Tito’s role in cultural policy Kadijević states the following: “As we
                know, Tito was the predominant personality in every aspect of our country. He was
                not an intellectual, he had no great education, no particular culture, but he had a
                genuine interest in art and he supported the artists. In Tito’s time culture was a
                constituent part of state politics and systems” (...) Although an
                        adversary of modern art
                    – in 1962 Tito spoke explicitly against abstract art – at the same time his ‘soft
                        Stalinism’ enabled the Museum of Contemporary Art to be built
                    quite unhindered. A similar paradox is the fact that
                        the writer Borislav Pekić was
                        imprisoned but afterward received prestigious literary awards such as <hi rend="italic">Nin’s and October’s</hi>.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn15" n="14"> “Đorđe Kadijević o
                        Titu: Nije imao obrazovanje ali je znao da uzdigne kulturu,” accessed June
                        18, 2018, <ref target="http://www.kurir.rs/zabava/pop-kultura/dorde-kadijevic-o-titu-nije-imao-obrazovanje-ali-je-znao-da-uzdigne-kulturu-clanak-1889209">http://www.kurir.rs/zabava/pop–kultura/dorde–kadijevic–o–titu–nije–imao–obrazovanje–ali–je–znao–da–uzdigne–kulturu–clanak–1889209</ref>.</note></p>
            <p> An important component of the development of dissent related to the culture of young
                people who have been under the strong influence of the West since the 1950s and
                especially in the 1960s. This influence, despite the “changes”, will continue until
                the fall of the Yugoslav state. The influence of literature, film, and music –
                ranging from pop culture to avant–garde streams, were among the younger generations
                manifested by action that was not devoid of political connotations. Thus the
                conceptual artist Vladimir Dodig Trokut states that members of his 68<hi rend="supscript">th</hi> generation
                were considered a group of “humanists, nihilists, anarchists, anarcho–liberal,
                anarcho–humanist, dialectics, disbelievers, rebels and party defectors.” Members of
                the “rebel” youth had already formed attitudes in relation to the social situation
                and the cultural reality (dialectics of liberation and theology of freedom). As
                Trokut states, everything was happening under the watchful eye of the authorities,
                who made sure that the behavior of the “rebels” did not escape control; there were
                even occasional sanctions. On the other hand, some Communist leaders and
                intellectuals, such as Vicko Krstulović, Koča Popović, and Jure Kaštelan, guarded
                and supported the alternative path of the younger generation.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn16" n="15">
                        Dodig Trokut, Vladimir, interview by Albert Bing
                            for COURAGE–project, December 22, 2016.</note> Vicko Krstulović
                was known by the idea of establishing Dalmatia as a federal unit. Koča Popović
                performed high functions in the Communist nomenclature, but also acted as a
                surrealist (in his young days) and an independent intellectual who even opposed Tito
                himself. The academic and poet Jure Kaštelan – who in 1948 acted as a “cultural
                worker” in Agitprop of CC CPC – in 1968 published a new edition of the <hi rend="italic">Bible</hi> that was sold in more than 200,000 copies.</p>
            <p> Despite the rigid single–party communist system and the persecution of the
                disobedient, due to an ambiguity of Titoism various forms of a critical thought
                emerged. Some of the actors who criticized Yugoslav ideology and politics become
                dissidents.</p></div>
           <div> <head>Who Were the Yugoslav Dissidents?</head>
            <p> The phenomenon of a dissident in Tito’s Yugoslavia can be considered from very
                different perspectives. However, so far no particular typology of the Yugoslav
                dissident has been formed in humanities and social sciences. There is no
                considerable attempt to synthesize the historical circumstances and motifs of
                dissidents; their dissociative “critical potential”, the effector or forms of
                repression that the government has carried out against the “disinformation”, as
                there is no complete phenomenological analysis of Titoism. The notion of dissident
                occurs in very different contexts; it is manifested and evaluated differently in
                certain phases of Yugoslav history as well as in different parts of Tito’s
                Yugoslavia.</p>
            <p> In general Yugoslav dissidents have been apostrophized as defectors of the Communist
                Party. They are also referred as the opponents of the regime; individuals who at
                some point emerged in public from “unacceptable positions” and were “excluded” from
                public life (although sometimes they were formally not members of the party or of
                party structures). In the wider context, they also appear as critics – free
                thinkers; their public criticism or “improper” thinking that questioned the
                socialist reality – very different manifestations of the culture of dissent – often
                led to conflicts with the authorities, including persecution and internment or
                isolation. Even in the last decade of the Yugoslav socialist state, when the demands
                for democratic reforms increasingly emerged and when it became clear that the party
                system is unsustainable – the practice of social control will continue despite the
                formal absence of censorship; according to Stipe Šuvar’s report at the Central
                Comity CPY’s 7th Session in April 1987, between 1981 and 1985, there were 36
                prohibitions of publications: ten newspapers, sixteen books, three journals, two
                calendars, two tourist brochures, one geographical map, one bulletin, and poster.
                Between 1982 and 1987, claims for “political delinquency” were raised against 2,443
                persons (1,748 for verbal delict); the highest in Kosovo (1,020), followed by
                Croatia (473), Serbia without the province (306) and Bosnia and Herzegovina (291).
                In Slovenia, there were 90, in Montenegro 71, in Macedonia 51 and in Vojvodina 37
                persons who were indicted (in court) for political crimes.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn17" n="16"> Jović, <hi rend="italic">Jugoslavija</hi>, 331.</note> However, the forms of “resistance”
                and “punishment” were very different, especially in comparison with the relationship
                between authorities and dissidents in other states where communists were in power.
                In short, attempts to further define the phenomenon of Yugoslav dissident face many
                problems. The arguments for this thesis are numerous.</p>
            <p> Already at the level of perception of dissident one can observe very different
                opinions. Literate and publicist Miljenko Jergović thinks that Ivan Supek – one of
                the most prominent Croatian intellectuals of the post–war period, physicist and
                philosopher as well as the rector of the Zagreb
                    University during the turbulent 1971 Croatian Spring – was not a dissident.
                Supek was first of all “a convinced leftist and a Democrat” (despite the fact that
                he was a member of the Communist Party before the Second World War; he left the
                Party in 1940, among other things, because of disagreement with the party’s
                interpretation of Albert Einstein’s thesis that was dismissed as inadmissible in
                    Moscow).<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn18" n="17">
                        Miljenko Jergović, “Sumnjivo lice – Kako su izumrli građani u Hrvatskoj,”
                            <hi rend="italic">Jutarnji list</hi>, April 7, 2015.</note> On the
                other side one of the most prominent intellectuals in Croatian emigration, Bogdan
                Radica considered Ivan Supek to be a dissident, as did a student leader from the
                period of the Croatian Spring, Dražen Budiša. Introducing Supek’s book <hi rend="italic">Heretic on the left</hi> Budiša noted: “To preserve internal
                freedom, autonomous political thinking, and scientific activity, to be on the side
                of his people and belong to the left, it was possible only if one was a dissident.
                This has been shown in Supek’s book.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn19" n="18"> Dražen Budiša, na koricama knjige Ivan Supek, <hi rend="italic">Krivovjerac na ljevici</hi>.</note> The controversy in
                the understanding of dissidence is related to some of the key moments of Tito’s
                Yugoslavia, such as the break with Stalin in 1948. In the ranks of Yugoslav
                dissidents can be included the communist “deportees” who, following the resolution
                of Informbiro, agreed with Stalin (as well as a number of innocent persons who were
                guilty of being accused as “Stalinists”). At the same time while the purge against
                the Yugoslav Stalinists – dissidents from Tito’s CPY – went on (by using the
                Stalinist matrix) Josip Broz was recognized in the West as the most important
                communist dissident after Lev Trotsky.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn20" n="19"> Albert Bing, “Disidenti/’divergenti’, ljudska prava i
                        osamostaljivanje Hrvatske,” in: <hi rend="italic">Disidentstvo u suvremenoj
                            povijesti</hi><hi rend="short_text" xml:space="preserve">, eds. </hi>Kisić
                        Kolanović, et al. (Zagreb: Hrvatski institut za povijest, 2010),
                    408.</note> Moreover, Yugoslavia itself got the label of dissident; in the
                words of François Furet: “... disconnected from the Stalin order, Tito introduces a
                new genre in the history of communism: the rejection of national communism.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn21" n="20"> François Furet,
                        <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Prošlost jedne iluzije – Ogled o komunističkoj ideji u XX. Stoljeću </hi>(Zagreb:
                        Politička kultura, 1997), 395–96.</note></p>
            <p> Various interpretations of the character of “Yugoslav dissident” are related to real
                and apparent controversies. In this context, it is interesting to note how political
                emigrant Bogdan Radica – who was never a member of the Communist Party (he was a
                sympathizer of the Croatian Peasant Party) – is regarded as a dissident in today’s
                post–communist perspective. On the Croatian historical portal Radica is
                apostrophized as “formally (...) the first Yugoslav dissident, even eight years
                before “Milovan Đilas”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn22" n="21"> “Bogdan Radica – hrvatska veza sa svijetom,” <hi rend="italic">Hrvatski povijesni portal</hi>, accessed June 18, 2018,
                            <ref target="http://povijest.net/bogdan-radica-hrvatska-veza-sa-svijetom/">http://povijest.net/bogdan–radica–hrvatska–veza–sa–svijetom/</ref>.
                    </note>. The reason for this was Radica’s leaving Yugoslavia in 1945 for
                failing to accept the single–party system, although he actively supported the
                struggle of Tito’s partisans in America during the WWII but disagreed with the
                one–party system and repression committed by communist authorities: “In accepting an
                ordinary dictatorship or semi–dictatorial regime man can compromise with himself as
                well as the society in which he lives. Who did not do it? But in the matter of
                accepting fascism or communism, that is, a system that demands the full submission
                of a lie–dogma, it is necessary for one to clarify it to himself and to his
                conscience and the society in which he lives, for which he has done all this and for
                what he has aspired.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn23" n="22"> Bogdan Radica, <hi rend="italic">Hrvatska 1945</hi>
                        (Zagreb: Grafički zavod Hrvatske, 1992), 240.</note></p>
            <p> The fact of Radica’s active support to Tito’s Partisans during World War II did not
                bother the Yugoslav regime’s publicists to disqualify him not only as a “dissident”
                but as an “Ustasha” as well (since he belonged to Croatian political emigration).
                When Radica met with Milovan Đilas in the late sixties in Princeton and New York (he
                wrote about meeting Đilas in the <hi rend="italic">Croatian Review</hi> magazine),
                Zagreb daily <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Večernji list </hi>published the
                following information: “In America, Đilas met with some Ustasha leaders including
                the cutthroat ideologist Bogdan Radica.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn24" n="23"> Branko Vlahović, “Đilasov san o vlasti,” <hi rend="italic">Večernji list</hi>, June 11, 1984.</note> Much more
                interesting were the impressions of Radica after an encounter with Đilas “in an
                unforgettable conversation.” For Radica, Đilas was “one of the disappointed
                idealists who has lost faith in ‘his’ God” and “the rebellious angel of the official
                communist galaxy.” However, he was also a consistent follower of the “divine”
                emanation a dared to “face God” (Tito) for his “faith”, pointing to his “sin”: “To
                dream about at the perfect state, then to realize it and then to feel that it is a
                fake and weaker than any common and even bourgeois dictatorship, and to stand
                against it to such an extent that the faults are exposed by their own being, it is
                not a small and insignificant feat. This is certainly a strong and decisive step,
                which requires a lot of inner courage, which can only impose the search for truth in
                man (...) the clashes in the position of the heretics from the Communist theocratic
                society are not easy or simple, especially when society has all the means of modern
                government which was never achieved by any other authority, even by the Pharaoh or
                the Inquisition.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn25" n="24">
                        Bogdan Radica, “Metapolitika Milovana Đilasa,” in: <hi rend="italic">Hrvatska revija</hi>, Vol. 3 (1969): 255–56.</note></p>
            <p> The fate of many dissidents was intertwined in a variety of ways (among the other
                relationship between Tito as a dissident and his victims who have become
                dissidents). In the immediate post–war period, innumerable intellectuals in a short
                time were struck by a new power that left the policy of the National Front and
                imposed a communist political monopoly. Among them were writers of various political
                affinities such as Edvard Kocbek and Borislav Pekić. Despite the labeling by the
                authorities – Pekić was imprisoned, and Kocbek under supervision – both writers
                managed to publish remarkable and award–winning works. Politician and professor
                Dragoljub Jovanović who sympathized with the social ideas of the CP in the prewar
                Kingdom of Yugoslavia and came into conflict with the then authorities will become
                the victim of the communist regime.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn26" n="25"> Srđan Cvetković, <hi rend="italic">Portreti
                            disidenata</hi> (Beograd: Institut za savremenu istoriju, 2007),
                        228.</note> “Always in opposition and a dissident” Jovanovic
                consistently fought for “multi–party system and freedom of speech.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn27" n="26"> Ibid.</note> As
                a people’s deputy at the National Assembly of the FNRJ in 1947 Jovanović was
                prosecuted by the chief of Agitprop of CC CPY Milovan Đilas. When arguing the
                one–party system and promoting a form of pluralism in 1953/1954 Đilas himself –
                after confronting Tito – became a political victim and the most famous Yugoslav
                dissident. For a couple of times, he was sentenced to prison and then released (at
                the end of
                <hi rend="color(222222)" xml:space="preserve">1966 Đilas was finally granted amnesty after nine years spent in jail). He even traveled abroad and gave a series of interviews for the foreign press. However, he was constantly </hi>under
                the watchful eye of authorities and exposed to defamation; e.g. in 1984 <hi rend="italic">Večernji list</hi> published a feuilleton (as mentioned
                previously) on his “traitorous behavior”. </p>
            <p>The change in public climate was noticeably different in the second half of the
                eighties when a liberal press started to publish “floods of forbidden literature”;
                opening also meant an intensified interest for the dissidents.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn28" n="27"> Milovan Đilas “Vlast kao strast,”
                        interviewd by Dina Julius i Dušanka Zeković, <hi rend="italic">Start</hi>,
                        No. 521, January 7, 1989.</note> In an interview to liberal weekly <hi rend="italic">Start</hi> Đilas was presented as a “revolutionary, an apostate,
                dangerous taboo–theme, multi–year political prisoner”; “About Đillas everybody knew
                everything and in fact very little is known and most of all as clichés: He is a
                traitor...”; “how many people know that he has spent his entire life dealing with
                literature? As every man who renounced his glorious past and shifted from ‘good’ to
                ‘evil’ boys, the portrait of Đilas is composed on semi–information, stereotypes, and
                mythologies about ‘the enemy of the state ‘no. 1’ (…) he was “a man who was
                dismissed in 1954. from all of his duties and classified as an anarchist and
                revisionist”; at the same time he was called by the press as ‘the last and largest
                Eastern European dissident after the Saharov rehabilitation’, and also the last
                living member of the pre–war ruling CPY Politburo. That triple position is
                sufficiently bizarre and intriguing to be completely ignored. At the very least, he
                is one of the most controversial witnesses of our recent history.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn29" n="28"> Ibid.</note></p>
            <p> Similar public engagements and even the connection to the same events reflected
                differently to the destiny of individual dissidents. Daniel Ivin, who was not a
                member of the Communist Party, deserved the qualification of the “suspect” by
                participating in the “dissident gathering in Zadar” in 1966 where he was “elected
                president of the publishing council of the first independent newspapers in
                Yugoslavia <hi rend="italic">Slobodna Riječ</hi>”. The magazine was supposed to
                promote “multiparty” system (allegedly under the influence by Miroslav Krleža). Ivin
                was arrested and interned for two months in Belgrade’s central detention center.
                “The conspiracy group” consisting of intellectuals – Mihajlo Mihajlov, Predrag
                Ristić, Marijan Batinić, Franjo Zenko, Miro Glavurtić, Mladen Srbinović, Leonid
                Šejk, Slobodan Mašić, and others – was charged with the constructed indictment which
                included allegations about preparations for the assassination of comrade Tito.”
                After the indictment was dismissed and Ivin was released he got an invitation of St
                Antony’s College and so he went to England (“British diplomacy followed him as” the
                most rational member “of the Yugoslav group of dissidents because he was looking for
                a way how to democratize society”). He then worked at the Schweizerisches
                Ost–Institut in Bern where he published the book <hi rend="italic">Revolution and
                    Evolution in Yugoslavia</hi>. At the end of 1969, he returned to Yugoslavia and
                collaborated on the project of the founding of the Croatian Economic Bank with a
                prominent Croatian communist and politician Većeslav Holjevac. In 1970 he signed a
                contract with Television Zagreb for the series “Croatian Statehood Story” (both
                projects were ultimately not realized due to Holjevac’s death and repression after
                the collapse of Croatian Spring). In the continuation of his career, Ivin will write
                about the most famous Yugoslav dissident Milovan Đilas and about Andrija Hebrang,
                the most influential Croat communist who was killed in unknown circumstances. In the
                late 1980s, he was engaged in Croatia in promoting multiparty reform and human
                    rights.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn30" n="29"> Drago
                        Pilsel, “Uz 80. rođendan Daniela Ivina,” <hi rend="italic">Regional
                            Express</hi>, accessed August 13, 2018, <ref target="http://www.regionalexpress.hr/site/more/uz-80.-roendan-daniela-ivina">http://www.regionalexpress.hr/site/more/uz–80.–roendan–daniela–ivina</ref>.</note>
                In short, despite the dissident label Ivin successfully continued to work in
                Yugoslavia as well as abroad.</p>
            <p> Mihajlo Mihajlov, an assistant at the Faculty of Philosophy in Zadar, had a
                different destiny. Like Ivin and other intellectuals who tried to organize a
                democratic forum in Zadar in 1966 Mihajlov was convinced that “social and political
                conditions have matured for the establishment of competitive organizations to the
                Communist Party”; he was actually exposed to the persecution since 1965 because of
                the essay <hi rend="italic">The Summer of Moscow 1964</hi>, which was categorized as
                a “defamation” insulting the Soviet Union” (in time when Tito was establishing
                closer relations to USSR). Despite the authorities pressure, Mihajlov insisted on
                holding a Zadar summit and launching a magazine with the aim of establishing a
                review of democratic profiles which will become “the core of a democratic
                socio–political movement.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn31" n="30"> K.Spehnjak, “‘Slučaj Mihajlov’ u bilješkama
                        diplomatskih predstavnika Velike Britanije 1966,” in: <hi rend="italic">Disidentstvo u suvremenoj
                        povijesti</hi><hi rend="short_text" xml:space="preserve">, eds. </hi>Kisić
                        Kolanović et al<hi rend="italic">.</hi> (Zagreb: Hrvatski institut za
                        povijest, 2010), 362.</note> He addressed his acquaintances in the West
                (among others PEN Secretary Arthur Miller) and the Yugoslav public with an open
                letter written to Josip Broz Tito.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn32" n="31"> Spehnjak, “Slučaj Mihajlov,” 362.</note> Mihajlov
                was arrested and prosecuted for, among other things, criminal offense “against the
                public order (...) by spreading false news.” Unlike Ivin, who returned to his
                homeland and cooperated with prominent political figures like Većeslav Holjevac,
                Mihajlov was sentenced to a long–term prison after which he went abroad. Along with
                Milovan Đilas, Mihajlov became one of the most famous Yugoslav dissidents whose fate
                was followed by the international public, but as a dissident he did not have any
                significant political influence.</p>
            <p> Some individuals, such as Adem Demaçi and Marko Veselica, condemned for “hostile
                activity” and nationalism, were apostrophized as an Albanian and Croatian “Mandela”
                for serving long–term prison sentences. Prior to the conflict with the Communist
                authorities, Demaçi was – at least as a nominal – part of the “system” (from “Tito’s
                pioneer” to the opposition Albanian revolutionary), and Marko Veselica was one of
                the party personnel who actively participated in the suppression of student protests
                in Zagreb in 1968. A particular chapter on dissidence would be a story on
                intellectuals who confronted Communist authorities in different periods of Yugoslav
                socialism and with various motives. Many intellectuals, especially philosophers and
                sociologists gathered around the
                <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Praxis </hi>magazine, actively participated
                in student protests in 1968. Some of them, especially in Belgrade, experienced the
                exclusion of the Party, various forms of pressures and even dismissals.</p>
            <p> Particularly interesting was the case of Predrag Matvejević. After completing his
                studies, Matvejević spent two years in Paris, where he acquired a Ph.D. in Sorbonne.
                He returned to Yugoslavia at the full swing of the student protest in 1968. The ban
                of his text “What is the common protest of the students of Europe” will be later
                evaluated “as his promotion in the line of disagreements.” A few years later he
                voluntarily “auto–suspended himself” from the League of Communists when “the
                critiques on his account became more and more laud”; he explained that he had joined
                the Party as a student “because he did not appear to be in the rift with the party
                in which were then Miroslav Krleža, Marko Ristic, Ivo Andrić, Ranko Marinković,
                Petar Šegedin, and many others.” Matvejević’s even dare to write an open letter to
                President Tito, in which – despite all his merits – he asked him to depart from his
                duties due to his age. He didn’t suffer any significant consequences.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn33" n="32"> Ingrid Badurina,
                        “Otvorena pisma Predraga Matvejevića,” <hi rend="italic">Start</hi>, January
                        7, 1989, 37, 39.</note></p>
            <p> In the later period of Yugoslavia, when the party was weakened many Yugoslav
                dissidents collaborated “irrespective of whether they were left or right”; Marko
                Veselica stated that “he regularly contacted Đilas and Belgrade lawyer Jovan
                    Barović.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn34" n="33">
                        Željko Krušelj, “Zapadu smetali jugoslavenski disidenti,” <hi rend="italic">Vjesnik</hi>, October 1, October 2, 2005. </note> Mihajlo Mihajlov
                – who had “more favorable status” than other Yugoslav dissidents due to his critical
                observations on the USSR – initiated the establishment of the Committee for Aid to
                Yugoslav dissidents in New York in 1979. The heads of the Committee were Milovan
                Đilas and future Croatian president Franjo Tuđman, later replaced by Vladimir
                    Šeks.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn35" n="34"> Krušelj,
                        “Zapadu smetali.”</note> After the death of Josip Broz Tito and the
                expectations of change, the dissidents were increasingly engaged. In October 1980, a
                group of 36 dissidents in the country sent a letter to the Presidency of the SFRY,
                requesting amnesty for those who were still in jail for verbal delinquency. In
                December 1980 a petition proposing the abolition of Article 133 of the SFRY Criminal
                Code – which sanctioned the false and malicious presentation of social and political
                opportunities in the country – was signed by 102 signatories.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn36" n="35"> Jović, <hi rend="italic">Jugoslavija</hi>, 333.</note></p>
            <p> Due to the general appearance of the collapse of communism “dissidents throughout
                Eastern Europe become louder (especially in Czechoslovakia – with Charter 77; and in
                Poland – with Solidarity)”; this has only slightly affected the activities of
                Yugoslav dissidents.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn37" n="36"> Jović, <hi rend="italic">Jugoslavija</hi>, 333. </note> The first
                organized initiative for democratic changes in Yugoslavia was inspired by the
                critically oriented intelligentsia of “left” provenance. Some of them were
                considered as dissidents or advocated the abolishment of any form of political
                pressure. In 1989 a number of Zagreb intellectuals promoted an “Association for
                Yugoslav Democratic Initiative” (the name of the organization was suggested by
                Branko Horvat and Predrag Vranicki). The president was Branko Horvat, followed by
                Nebojša Popov, while the organizing director was Žarko Puhovski. Other members of
                the board were Bogdan Bogdanović, Milan Kangrga, Lev Kreft, Shkelzen Maliqi, Vesna
                Pešić, Koča Popović, Milorad Pupovac, Ljubisa Ristić, Božidar Gajo Sekulić, Rudi
                Supek, Ljubomir Tadić, Dubravka Ugrešić, Predrag Vranicki, Jug Grizelj, and Nenad
                Zakošek. However, in the atmosphere of ever more pronounced national confrontations
                after democratic elections, the political supremacy was taken by the parties with
                national programs.</p>
            <p> With the collapse of communism, and then the Yugoslav state, dissidents become a
                sort of relic of the past despite the fact that in some cases (like Croatia) some of
                the leading positions were occupied by communist dissidents (Franjo Tuđman, Stipe
                Mesić). New circumstances have also produced new controversies with regard to the
                phenomenon of a dissident. After the dramatic changes, “a few mentioned the
                dissidents and especially praised them.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn38" n="37"> Krušelj, “Zapadu smetali.”</note> One of the
                probable reasons for the restrained attitude toward the dissidents in the
                post–communist period may be found in the difficulties of perception of dissident
                phenomenon; according to Mira Bogdanović, “the thinking of dissidents in former
                Yugoslavia ranged from total denial of their existence (Minić, 1999), to alleged
                dissident status of hundreds of thousands of winter walkers (Mihajlov, 1998).”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn39" n="38"> Mira Bogdanović,
                        “Jugoslavenski disidenti i hladni rat,” accessed June 26, 2018, <ref target="http://www.doiserbia.nb.rs/img/doi/0038-0318/2009/0038-03180902113B.pdf">http://www.doiserbia.nb.rs/img/doi/0038–0318/2009/0038–03180902113B.pdf</ref>.</note>
                The post–communist and post–Yugoslav perspectives imposed new evaluation of dissent
                in Yugoslavia (primary anti–Yugoslav, national state, anti–communism). The
                “inflation” of victims of a regime and “dissidents” after the collapse of communism
                and Yugoslavia – especially in the ranks of “new” political and intellectual elites
                (most commonly converted communists) – certainly dimmed a clearer view of the
                historical retrospective of the Yugoslav dissident.</p>
            <p> It is interesting to note the perception of the “new Croatian dissident” in the
                early 1990s; more precisely, the fate of individuals who “became dissidents and
                exiles from the new state of Croatia” despite the proclamation of democracy. Thus in
                an article “Why did the Croatian dissidents disappear” (dissidents from the period
                of socialist Croatia and Yugoslavia), the author registers the emergence of “new
                    dissidents.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn40" n="39">
                        Jure Ilić, “Zašto su nestali hrvatski disidenti?” Vjesnik, April 4,
                        2001.</note> As a paradigmatic example was the fate of Predrag
                Matvejević, author of “the most famous and most translated contemporary Croatian
                book <hi rend="italic">The Mediterranean Breviary</hi>”; due to his political
                attitude and criticism which directly referred to Croatian president Franjo Tuđman,
                Matvejević become “persona non grata in his homeland or, <hi rend="short_text">more
                    simply – a dissident.</hi>” As noticed by the author it was a paradox since
                Matvejević actively defended dissident Tuđman while he was prosecuted by the
                communist authorities in the early 1980s. Matvejević was then the president of the
                Croatian PEN and advocated suspension of persecution of individuals who opposed the
                communist regime. Only a few years later Matvejević and Tuđman found themselves in
                reverse positions with one significant difference: “In Tuđman case the authorities
                become displeased with him and he was persecuted, and in the case of Matvejević he
                was displeased with authorities so he becomes dissident of his own will.” In the
                category of “new dissidents” – the author also calls them “exiles” – were two
                writers Slavenka Drakulić and Dubravka Ugrešić and two actors Rade Šerbeđija and
                Mira Furlan. As a basic distinction between the “old” and the “new” dissidents
                author emphasize the fact that “virtually none of them was legally persecuted, no
                one of them has been deprived of a right of citizenship;” simply “they didn’t feel
                comfortable under Tuđman’s regime. So they chose their own paths and destinies, not
                wanting to share anything with the rule they perceived as regimes.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn41" n="40"> Ilić, “Zašto su
                        nestali.”</note></p></div>
            <div><head>West and Yugoslav
                        Dissidents</head>
            <p> Probably the most important aspect of Yugoslav dissident status in regard to Titoism
                wasn’t the objective critical potential or the effect of resistance to the
                authorities of the dissidents but the attitude of Western states and their political
                and intellectual elites. In the countries of liberal democracy, the perception of
                Yugoslav dissidents (as well as political emigration) was not the same as those
                towards the opponents to the Soviet Union and other communist states. One of the
                reasons for such distinction was embedded in the fact that Tito’s regime was
                perceived “on the seductive theory of socialism with the ‘human face’” which since
                the 1950s served as an alternative to a rigid Soviet model”; therefore, “it was not
                desirable that dissidents create an image on Tito’s Yugoslavia as an unfree and
                repressive society.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn42" n="41"> Krušelj, “Zapadu smetali.”</note></p>
            <p> In a discussion of “communist renegades” at the meeting of Croatian and Serbian
                historians (under the 10th <hi rend="italic">Dialogue</hi> at the Faculty of
                Philosophy in Osijek, 2005) former dissident Daniel Ivin testified: “The main
                factors of the West were in quite a disagreement with dissidents in Yugoslavia.
                Đilas and then others – <hi rend="italic">Praxis</hi> first, Mihajlov group, then
                the Zagreb Spring and Belgrade Liberals, and others; Yugoslav dissidents were always
                more a nuisance than someone who should be supported ... That is why the West’s
                attitude to dissidents through whole Cold War period was a double–natured: a
                wholehearted support for those inside Soviet bloc and a somewhat confused or
                improper relationship with those in Yugoslavia, often none.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn43" n="42"> Krušelj, “Zapadu
                    smetali.”</note> Ivin’s observance was consistent with the thesis of Mira
                Bogdanović who analyzed the position of Yugoslav dissidents during the Cold War: “In
                Eastern European countries, during the Cold War, dissidents have played a prominent
                role as an instrument of anticommunist ideological subversion. By contrast, Yugoslav
                dissidents have sentenced to marginal position thanks to the peculiar position of
                Yugoslavia between two opposing blocks.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn44" n="43"> Bogdanović, “Jugoslavenski disidenti.”</note></p>
            <p> Similar observations come from one of the most prominent intellectuals in the ranks
                of Croatian political emigration Bogdan Radica, who was in a position to communicate
                directly with some of the most famous Yugoslav dissidents. As an expert on
                geopolitics and international relations and a distinguished US and American culture
                expert Radica often published articles focusing on the relationship of the West –
                primarily America – to the rest of the world (<hi rend="italic">The World Between
                    America and the Soviet Union</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Democracy and Liberation
                    from Communism</hi>, <hi rend="italic">The World Revolution and America</hi>,
                etc. published in <hi rend="italic">Croatian Review</hi> in early 1960s). In his
                critical comments, he also recalls the position of Tito’s Yugoslavia in cold–war
                conditions. Although the system embodied by the Yugoslav sovereign for Radica was a
                negation of liberty, and Tito himself was a communist Machiavellian dictator, he did
                not deny his statehood capacity, above all the ability to “manipulate” the West.
                Thus, he notes that Churchill’s “Oxford and Cambridge boys who were so zealous on –
                so–called – Tito’s charm – while they were in the Bosnian mountains and Dalmatian
                islands” (during WWII), mainly spoke on Josip Broz Tito affirmatively.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn45" n="44"> Bogdan Radica,
                        “Demokracija i oslobođenje od komunizma,” <hi rend="italic">Hrvatska
                            revija</hi>, December 1961, 341.</note> The roots of this phenomenon
                are more intriguing because he thinks that “English Machiavellianism is crueler than
                the one Machiavelli himself ever imagined;” and the Yugoslav leader overtook the
                Englishman himself with his <hi rend="short_text">Machiavellian skills</hi>.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn46" n="45"> Radica, “Demokracija
                        i oslobođenje,” 341.</note></p>
            <p> Concerning this aspect of “the art of ruling”, Radica’s observations on the global
                influences of Tito’s “third path” are also interesting. In his opinion it has
                overshadowed the critical sharpness of the West, leading to a disadvantage of the
                Yugoslav dissidents. In the analysis of the success of the phenomenon of Titoism
                among the small peoples, Radica, not with surprise but also with bitterness, notes
                that “Tito was right” when “politics of his country organized to set aside and see
                what side would be victorious” in the conflict between America and Russia. Tito has
                “given to the intelligentsia and leadership of these peoples a technique and a
                mechanism for exploiting the West, ideologically and economically supported by the
                same West.” Moreover, “although Tito is still a communist who” in reality did not
                change his inner system, that fact did not concern anyone; “American official policy
                has supported Tito’s experiment with financial aid,” factually contributing to
                “increase Titos’s position in that part of the world.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn47" n="46"> Bogdan Radica, “Svijet između
                        Amerike i Sovjetskog Saveza – paradoksi našeg vremena,” <hi rend="italic">Hrvatska revija</hi>, June 1960, 168.</note> Following this
                observations, Radica also notes his own experiences from Cuba were “Russian, Chinese
                and Yugoslav communists ideologists operated by offering their own communist
                example.” What Radica was annoyed with was the case of Tito: “While I was in Cuba
                talking to Castro’s intelligentsia, I was listening to Tito’s fairy tales, not
                through propaganda, spread by Tito’s emissaries, but through what Cuban
                intelligentsia has read about Titoism in North American scientific publications.
                Whenever I was trying to suppress any system of argumentation, I was faced with the
                observation of an American economic writer from the most prominent US publications,
                such as <hi rend="italic">Foreign Affairs</hi> or even <hi rend="italic">Problems of
                    Communism</hi>, which can not be said to be leftist, but rather represent the
                most responsible American point of view. So the USA breaks down and crashes the
                foundations of all its policies.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn48" n="47"> Radica, “Svijet između Amerike,” 174.</note></p>
            <p> Of course, the benevolent relationship between the West and the Tito’s Yugoslavia –
                as Radica registers, reflected in the international circumstances of the divided
                block. First of all the West considered dissidents as “ideological ally in the Cold
                    War.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn49" n="48"> Pavle
                        Rak, “Disidenti, kultura i politika,” accessed June 26, 2018, <ref target="http://www.yurope.com/zines/republika/arhiva/98/192/192_23.HTM">http://www.yurope.com/zines/republika/arhiva/98/192/192_23.HTM</ref>.</note>
                However, in the case of Yugoslavia, the position of dissidents was determined by the
                inherent implications of the ambiguity of Tito’s system. The openness of Yugoslavia
                and the relative freedom of action of the intelligentsia and the media, especially
                in later periods, weakened the interest for the Yugoslav dissidents. Dissident
                movements were certainly under the strong influence of Western perception on dissent
                as a form of struggle for democracy and human rights in a totalitarian environment.
                However, until the collapse of communism in the late eighties, there was no adequate
                social background that could give rise to a more significant autochthonous political
                movement.</p>
            <p> Nevertheless, Western estimates of dissident potential are also interesting to
                consider. Thus Zbigniew Brzezinski, National Security Advisor at the time US
                President Jimmy Carter administration examines in 1978 what will happen with
                Yugoslavia after Tito’s death (which “seeks to ensure the continuity of his truly
                great work through collective leadership”).<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn50" n="49"> Mirko Đekić,
                        <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Upotreba Srbije – optužbe i priznanja Draže Markovića </hi>(Beograd:
                        Beseda, 1990), 82.</note> Despite the recognition of Tito achievement
                “the ultimate goal of the United States in Yugoslavia was the removal of communist
                rule in any form.” But the basic strategic goal of the United States for Yugoslavia
                is to preserve the status quo with respect to Soviet pretensions in the region after
                Titos’s death. As a course of American strategy, he suggests taking the following
                measures: “To constantly and consistently point to the Stalinist tendencies in
                Soviet politics and thus ‘intimidate’ the Yugoslav communists and other leftists in
                the country and the world: – systematically assist and give publicity to various
                opposing groups in Yugoslavia. In connection with this much more ‘advertise’ should
                be put upon the various Yugoslav dissidents. In the same way, as it is done with
                Soviet and Czechoslovak dissidents. These ‘dissidents’ do not have to be highly
                anti–communist, perhaps even better, if they are ‘humanistic’ orientated (like
                members of <hi rend="italic">Praxis</hi> and similar). These actions should be
                maximally linked to the ‘human rights’ campaign and the ‘third basket’ from
                Helsinki, which Yugoslav communists often call upon. Some international
                organizations for political convictions (Amnesty International) can also be used in
                this plan.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn51" n="50"> Đekić,
                            <hi rend="italic">Upotreba Srbije</hi>, 83.</note></p>
            <p> The ratings of the disadvantaged position of Yugoslav dissidents (and political
                emigration from Yugoslavia) in the West – in relation to the dissidents from the
                communist states of the East Bloc, coincide with experiences of the dissidents
                themselves (Marko Veselica, Mihajlo Mihajlov, Zdravko Gvero, Daniel Ivin ...):
                “Dissidents in the former Yugoslavia had utterly different meaning – but also as an
                echo to the West – in comparison to those in the Soviet Union and other
                real–socialist countries.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn52" n="51"> Krušelj, “Zapadu smetali.”</note> In this context
                it is also interesting to note Daniel Ivin’s observation who claims that the posture
                of the West influenced the general attitude of the Yugoslav society towards
                dissidents: “The members of the wider civil and intellectual milieu, who usually
                give tone and color to the whole society, felt disdain to dissidents, so the sour
                and unwelcome support of the West was to a great extent justification for their
                behavior and their conscience. Enjoying certain advantages and benefits of the
                Yugoslav Liberalism of the Communist State vis–à–vis those in the Soviet bloc, those
                members of our society dissident was an unnecessary concern and even in their eyes
                the danger of losing their benefits and advantages. That is why the dissidents in
                Yugoslavia – unlike those in the Soviet bloc who lived only under one malediction –
                of their own authority, seemed to be under the triple curse: from their own
                authorities, then from their own society and partly from the West.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn53" n="52"> Krušelj, “Zapadu
                        smetali.”</note></p></div>
            <div><head>Conclusion</head>
            <p> Yugoslav dissidents have been profiled as a very different set of oppositions to
                communist rule. For these reasons, it is not possible to unambiguously determine the
                character of the Yugoslav dissident. To a large extent, the dissidents were linked
                to the various forms of a critical–oriented intelligentsia and political motives
                that developed after the opening of Yugoslavia towards the West in the early 1950s.
                As a system of authority and values, Titoism was based on ambivalences made up of
                the repression and control exercised by the communist authorities and on the other
                hand by allowing certain liberties whose boundary as the supreme arbitrator was
                mainly determined by Tito himself. Despite the periodic purges of political
                opponents who often become dissidents it can be argued that the development of
                critical thought and peculiar culture of dissent has been a persistent tendency in
                the development of the Yugoslav society. With the collapse of communism and the SFRY
                the Yugoslav dissidents lost importance as a political alternative.</p></div>
        </body>
        <back>
     <div type="bibliography">
         <head>Sources and References</head>
            <listBibl>
                <bibl>Ahtisaari, Martti. <hi rend="italic">Beogradska zadaća – Kako je slaman
                    Mil</hi>ošević. Zagreb: Naklada Szabo A3 data, 2002.</bibl>
                <bibl>Badurina, Ingrid. “Otvorena pisma Predraga Matvejevića.” <hi rend="italic">Start</hi>, January 7, 1989.</bibl>
                <bibl>Banac, Ivo. <hi rend="italic">Acta Turcarum</hi>. Zagreb: Durieux,
                    2006.</bibl>
                <bibl>Bing, Albert. “Disidenti / ‘divergenti’, ljudska prava i osamostaljivanje
                    Hrvatske.” In: <hi rend="italic">Disidentstvo u suvremenoj povijesti,</hi>
                    <hi rend="short_text" xml:space="preserve">edited by </hi>Kisić Kolanović, Nada,
                    Zdenko Radelić, and Katarina Spehnjak<hi rend="italic">.</hi> Zagreb: Hrvatski
                    institut za povijest, 2010.</bibl>
                <bibl>“Bogdan Radica – hrvatska veza sa svijetom.” Hrvatski povijesni portal.
                    Accessed June 18, 2018. <ref target="http://povijest.net/bogdan-radica-hrvatska-veza-sa-svijetom/">http://povijest.net/bogdan–radica–hrvatska–veza–sa–svijetom/</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl>Bogdanović, Mira. “Jugoslavenski disidenti i hladni rat.” Accessed June 26,
                    2018. <ref target="http://www.doiserbia.nb.rs/img/doi/0038-0318/2009/0038-03180902113B.pdf">http://www.doiserbia.nb.rs/img/doi/0038–0318/2009/0038–03180902113B.pdf</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl>Supek, Ivan. <hi rend="italic">Krivovjerac na ljevici</hi>. Zagreb: Globus,
                    1992.</bibl>
                <bibl>Cukić, Mona. “Đorđe Kadijević o Titu: Nije imao obrazovanje ali je znao da
                    uzdigne kulturu.” Zabava | Kurir. Accessed June 18, 2018. <ref target="http://www.kurir.rs/zabava/pop-kultura/dorde-kadijevic-o-titu-nije-imao-obrazovanje-ali-je-znao-da-uzdigne-kulturu">http://www.kurir.rs/zabava/pop–kultura/dorde–kadijevic–o–titu–nije–imao–obrazovanje–ali–je–znao–da–uzdigne–kulturu</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl>Cvetković, Srđan. <hi rend="italic">Portreti disidenata</hi>. Beograd:
                    Institut za savremenu istoriju, 2007.</bibl>
                <bibl>Đekić, Mirko. <hi rend="italic">Upotreba Srbije – optužbe i priznanja Draže
                    Markovića</hi>. Beograd: Beseda, 1990.</bibl>
                <bibl>Furet,
                    François.<hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve"> Prošlost jedne iluzije – Ogled o komunističkoj ideji u XX. Stoljeću</hi>.
                    Zagreb: Politička kultura, 1997.</bibl>
                <bibl>“Václav Havel: From a political dissident to a dissident politician.” Pehe.cz. Accessed August 13, 2018. 
                    <ref target="http://www.pehe.cz/Members/redaktor/vaclav-havel-from-a-political-dissident-to-a">http://www.pehe.cz/Members/redaktor/vaclav–havel–from–a–political–dissident–to–a</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl>Ilić, Jure. “Zašto su nestali hrvatski
                    disidenti?”
                    <hi rend="italic">Vjesnik</hi>, April 4, 2001.</bibl>
                <bibl>Jakovina, Tvrtko. “J.B.T. Historiografija vs. Mitologija. Komunist kojega je
                    Zapad podržavao.” <hi rend="italic">Večernji list</hi>, April 30, 2005.</bibl>
                <bibl>Jergović, Miljenko. “Sumnjivo lice – Kako su izumrli građani u Hrvatskoj.” <hi rend="italic">Jutarnji list</hi>, April 7, 2015.</bibl>
                <bibl>Jović, Dejan. <hi rend="italic">Jugoslavija koja je odumrla</hi>. Zagreb:
                    Prometej, 2003.</bibl>
                <bibl>Milovan Đilas – Vlast kao strast. Interviewd by Julius, Dina and Dušanka Zeković. <hi rend="italic">Start</hi>,
                    January 7, 1989.</bibl>
                <bibl>Krušelj, Željko. “Zapadu smetali jugoslavenski
                    disidenti.”
                    <hi rend="italic">Vjesnik</hi>, October 1 and October 2, 2005.</bibl>
                <bibl>Lasić<hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">, </hi>Stanko.<hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve"> Mladi Krleža i njegovi kritičari 1914.–1924.</hi><hi rend="short_text" xml:space="preserve"> </hi>Zagreb:
                    Globus, 1987.</bibl>
                <bibl>Matvejević, Predrag. “Mjera naše zrelosti.” <hi rend="italic">Školske
                    novine</hi>, January 7, 1982.</bibl>
                <bibl>Matvejević,
                    Predrag.<hi rend="italic"> Jugoslavensvo danas–Pitanja kulture</hi>. Zagreb: Globus, 1982.</bibl>
                <bibl>Menzel, Jiří. “Moja Hrvatska.” <hi rend="italic">HTV</hi>, Documentary, August
                    18, 2011.</bibl>
                <bibl>Mitrović, Andrej. “Javna, tajna i porodična istorija.” Interviewed by Aleksandar Ćirić. <hi rend="italic">Vreme</hi>,
                    January 9, 1999.</bibl>
                <bibl>Petričević, Jure. “Hrvatski nacionalni problem.” <hi rend="italic">Hrvatska
                    revija</hi>, Vol. 2–3, 1964.</bibl>
                <bibl>Pilsel, Drago. “Uz 80. rođendan Daniela Ivina.” Regional Express. Accessed August 13, 2018. <ref target="http://www.regionalexpress.hr/site/more/uz-80.-roendan-daniela-ivina">http://www.regionalexpress.hr/site/more/uz–80.–roendan–daniela–ivina</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl>Radica, Bogdan. “Demokracija i oslobođenje od komunizma.” <hi rend="italic">Hrvatska revija</hi>, December 1961.</bibl>
                <bibl>Radica, Bogdan. “Metapolitika Milovana Đilasa.” <hi rend="italic">Hrvatska
                    revija</hi>, Vol. 3, 1969.</bibl>
                <bibl>Radica, Bogdan. “Svijet između Amerike i Sovjetskog Saveza – paradoksi našeg
                    vremena.” <hi rend="italic">Hrvatska revija</hi>, June 1960.</bibl>
                <bibl>Radica, Bogdan.<hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve"> Hrvatska 1945</hi>.
                    Zagreb: Grafički zavod Hrvatske, 1992.</bibl>
                <bibl>Rak, Pavle. “Disidenti, kultura i politika”. Accessed June 26, 2018. <ref target="http://www.yurope.com/zines/republika/arhiva/98/192/192_23.HTM">http://www.yurope.com/zines/republika/arhiva/98/192/192_23.HTM</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl>Spehnjak, Katarina. “‘Slučaj Mihajlov’ u bilješkama diplomatskih predstavnika
                    Velike Britanije 1966.” In: <hi rend="italic">Disidentstvo u suvremenoj
                        povijesti,</hi>
                    <hi rend="short_text" xml:space="preserve">edited by </hi>Nada Kisić Kolanović,
                    Zdenko Radelić, and Katarina Spehnjak<hi rend="italic">.</hi> Zagreb: Hrvatski
                    institut za povijest, 2010.</bibl>
                <bibl>Taylor, A.J.P. <hi rend="italic">Habsburška monarhija 1809–1918</hi>. Zagreb: Znanje, 1990.</bibl>
                <bibl>Trokut, Vladimir Dodig, interview by Albert Bing,
                    COURAGE–project. December 22, 2016.</bibl>
                <bibl>Vlahović, Branko. “Đilasov san o vlasti.” <hi rend="italic">Večernji
                    list</hi>, November 6, 1984.</bibl>
                <bibl>Župan,
                    Ivica.<hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve"> Pragmatičari, dogmati, sanjari – hrvatska umjetnost i društvo 1950.–ih godina. </hi>Zagreb:
                    Ina industrija nafte d.d. and Meridijani, 2007.</bibl>
            </listBibl></div>
            <div type="summary">
                <docAuthor>Albert Bing</docAuthor>
            <head><hi rend="allcaps">Titoism, dissidents and culture of
                dissent</hi></head>
            <head><hi rend="allcaps">Summary</hi></head>
            <p> The article deals with the phenomenon of specific Yugoslav dissidence and culture of
                dissent, primarily due to the international status of Tito’s Yugoslavia and <hi rend="italic">Titoism</hi> as a system of values and governance. The opening up
                of Yugoslavia to the West after the split with Stalin in 1948 led to the significant
                influence of Western culture on the Yugoslav communist society. This influence
                contributed to the appearance of criticism, which sometimes led to various forms of
                dissidence. However, due to a tolerant attitude of the Western countries towards
                Tito’s communist regime, dissidents did not have the same status as those from the
                Soviet Union and other states of real socialism. Furthermore, Tito’s ambivalent
                cultural politics – as an important aspect of his governance – also affected the
                status of Yugoslav dissidents. During the phases of liberalization of Yugoslav
                society criticism was tolerated and even encouraged to a certain extent. At the same
                time, the Communist party tried to control all aspect of the public sphere. The
                supreme arbitrator was often Tito himself. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="summary" xml:lang="sl">
            <docAuthor>Albert Bing</docAuthor>
            <head><seg rend="allcaps">Titoizem,
                disidenti in kultura nasprotovanja</seg></head>
            <head><hi rend="allcaps">Povzetek</hi></head>
                <p> Prispevek obravnava fenomen specifičnega jugoslovanskega disidentstva (in kulture disidentstva) kot posledico mednarodnega statusa Titove Jugoslavije in <hi rend="italic">titoizma</hi> kot sistema vrednot in upravljanja. Odpiranje Jugoslavije proti Zahodu je po sporu s Stalinom leta 1948 pomembno vplivalo na jugoslovansko komunistično družbo. Vpliv zahodne kulture je porajal razne kritike, kar je včasih pripeljalo do različnih oblik disidentstva. Zaradi strpnega odnosa zahodnih držav do Titovega komunističnega režima pa disidenti niso imeli enakega statusa kot tisti iz Sovjetske zveze in drugih realsocialističnih držav. Poleg tega je tudi Titova ambivalentna kulturna politika kot pomemben vidik njegovega upravljanja vplivala na status jugoslovanskih disidentov. V fazah liberalizacije jugoslovanske družbe so kritike do neke mere tolerirali in celo spodbujali. Hkrati pa je Komunistična partija poskušala nadzorovati vse vidike javne sfere. Vrhovni arbiter je bil pogosto Tito sam.</p></div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>