<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Urban Street Architecture, the K67 KIOSK: a Single Solution for All
                    Problems</title>
                <author>
                    <forename>Marta</forename>
                    <surname>Rendla</surname>
                    <roleName>Dr., znanstvena sodelavka</roleName>
                    <affiliation>Inštitut za novejšo zgodovino</affiliation>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Privoz 11</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>SI-1000 Ljubljana</addrLine>
                    </address>
                    <email>marta.rendla@inz.si</email>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>2023-05-10</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>
                    <orgName xml:lang="sl">Inštitut za novejšo zgodovino</orgName>
                    <orgName xml:lang="en">Institute of Contemporary History</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Privoz 11</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>SI-1000 Ljubljana</addrLine>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>http://ojs.inz.si/pnz/article/view/4169</pubPlace>
                <date>2023</date>
                <availability status="free">
                    <licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title xml:lang="sl">Prispevki za novejšo zgodovino</title>
                <title xml:lang="en">Contributions to Contemporary History</title>
                <biblScope unit="volume">63</biblScope>
                <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
                <idno type="ISSN">2463-7807</idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source, born digital.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc xml:lang="en">
                <p>Contributions to Contemporary History is one of the central Slovenian scientific
                    historiographic journals, dedicated to publishing articles from the field of
                    contemporary history (the 19th and 20th century).</p>
                <p>The journal is published three times per year in Slovenian and in the following
                    foreign languages: English, German, Serbian, Croatian, Bosnian, Italian, Slovak
                    and Czech. The articles are all published with abstracts in English and
                    Slovenian as well as summaries in English.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <projectDesc xml:lang="sl">
                <p>Prispevki za novejšo zgodovino je ena osrednjih slovenskih znanstvenih
                    zgodovinopisnih revij, ki objavlja teme s področja novejše zgodovine (19. in 20.
                    stoletje).</p>
                <p>Revija izide trikrat letno v slovenskem jeziku in v naslednjih tujih jezikih:
                    angleščina, nemščina, srbščina, hrvaščina, bosanščina, italijanščina, slovaščina
                    in češčina. Članki izhajajo z izvlečki v angleščini in slovenščini ter povzetki
                    v angleščini.</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="sl"/>
                <language ident="en"/>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords xml:lang="en">
                    <term>kiosk</term>
                    <term>modular architecture</term>
                    <term>industrial design</term>
                    <term>Slovenia</term>
                    <term>former Yugoslavia</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords xml:lang="sl">
                    <term>kiosk</term>
                    <term>modularna arhitektura</term>
                    <term>industrijski design</term>
                    <term>Slovenija</term>
                    <term>Jugoslavija</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change><date>2023-05-15T08:33:36Z</date><name/></change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <docAuthor>Marta Rendla<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn1" n="*"><hi rend="bold">Dr.,
                        znanstvena sodelavka, Inštitut za novejšo zgodovino, Privoz 11, SI-1000
                        Ljubljana; <ref target="mailto:marta.rendla@inz.si"
                            >marta.rendla@inz.si</ref></hi></note>
            </docAuthor>
            <docImprint>
                <idno type="cobissType">Cobiss tip: 1.01</idno>
                <idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.51663/pnz.63.1.09</idno>
            </docImprint>
            <div type="abstract">
                <head>IZVLEČEK</head>
                <head>URBANA ULIČNA ARHITEKTURA, KIOSK K67: ENA REŠITEV ZA VSE
                        TEŽAVE</head>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Avtorica v prispevku predstavi kompleksno pot razvoja ter
                        evolucijo univerzalno in modularno zasnovanega kioska K67 − znamenitega
                        rdečega kioska slovenskega arhitekta in industrijskega oblikovalca Saše
                        Janeza Mächtiga od njegove zasnove v drugi polovici 60. let, nadgradnje in
                        specializacije glede na funkcijo v 70. letih, do današnjega posodabljanja v
                        interaktivni samooskrbni večnamenski kiosk za enaindvajseto stoletje K21.
                        Kiosk K67 − izdelek urbane ulične industrijsko oblikovane arhitekture je
                        nastal </hi><hi rend="italic)">pod vplivom tedaj aktualnih arhitekturnih
                        gibanj</hi><hi rend="italic"> zaradi naraščajočih </hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >potreb mesta in razvoja urbanih storitvenih dejavnosti.</hi><hi
                        rend="italic"> Mini cestna arhitektura, v katero so umeščali prodajalne
                        časopisov, tobaka, hrane, manjše delavnice, cvetličarne, blagajne za plačilo
                        parkirnine in nakup vstopnic, informacijske pisarne, turistične
                        poslovalnice, vratarnice ipd., je poleg splošne urbane kulture nekdanjega
                        jugoslovanskega prostora postala tudi del urbanega </hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >prostora bivših vzhodno evropskih socialističnih držav</hi><hi
                        rend="italic"> in kultni izdelek ter del kolektivne zavesti in
                    spomina.</hi></p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Ključne besede: kiosk, modularna arhitektura, industrijski
                        design, Slovenija, Jugoslavija</hi></p>
            </div>
            <div type="abstract" xml:lang="en">
                <head>ABSTRACT</head>
                <p><hi rend="italic">In the following contribution, the author presents the complex
                        development and evolution of the universally and modularly designed K67
                        Kiosk – the famous red booth by the Slovenian architect and industrial
                        designer Saša Janez Mächtig – from its conception in the second half of the
                        1960s through its upgrades and specialisation in the 1970s to today’s
                        modernisation as an interactive self-service multipurpose kiosk for the
                        twenty-first century, the K21. The K67 Kiosk – a product of urban street
                        industrial design architecture – was created under the influence of the
                        architectural trends at the time and due to the growing needs of the city
                        and the development of urban service activities. The miniature street
                        architecture, which used to house newspaper, tobacco, and food shops, small
                        workshops, flower shops, parking and ticket booths, information and tourist
                        offices, gatehouses, etc., became a part of the general urban culture of the
                        former Yugoslav territory, the urban space of former Eastern European
                        socialist countries, the collective consciousness and memory, as well as a
                        cult product.</hi></p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Keywords: kiosk, modular architecture, industrial design,
                        Slovenia, former Yugoslavia</hi></p>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div>
                <head>Introduction</head>
                <p>The purpose of the present contribution is to use the example of an industrial
                    design product, the K67 Kiosk, to shed light on the development and role of
                    urban street architecture, designed in the former Yugoslavia in the 1960s. That
                    was the time when Yugoslavia was experiencing dynamic development in all areas
                    of social life after the abandoning the centrally planned socialist economy of
                    the Soviet type, the introduction of self-management in the 1950s, and the
                    transition to an economy with some market elements. To better understand the
                    creation of the K67 Kiosk, designed under the influence of the contemporaneous
                    architectural trends due to the growing needs of the cities and the development
                    of urban service activities, it is necessary to begin by briefly outlining the
                    characteristics of the post-war Yugoslav regime, the role of architecture, and
                    the emergence and rise of Slovenian industrial design. The significance of the
                    K67 Kiosk – an example of mini-architecture suitable for any space with the
                    possibility of combining several smaller units into a larger one – is mainly
                    reflected in the fact that as micro-architecture fascinated with the new
                    emerging materials, it established the social, productive-technological, and
                    commercial aspects of the development of street furniture. The K67 Kiosk became
                    a part of the general urban culture, especially in former Yugoslavia and Eastern European
                    socialist countries.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>From Capitalism to Socialism and the Role of Architecture</head>
                <p>With the introduction of a new political and socio-economic system – socialism –
                    in Yugoslavia after World War II, the processes of communist modernisation,
                    industrialisation, and urbanisation were set in motion in an effort to implement
                    profound social changes. Yugoslavia and Slovenia as its part underwent a major
                    social, economic, and cultural transformation. The Slovenian society gradually
                    transformed from peasant to industrial. After assuming power and introducing
                    socialism, the new communist rulers nationalised all of the important
                    enterprises and imposed new economic conditions as well as a new development
                    policy in accordance with the Soviet model. Initially, this new development
                    policy assumed an accelerated consolidation of the so called material base,
                    while as of the mid-1950s, it also focused on the swift increase of the living
                    standard. The material foundations were to be strengthened by focusing on the
                    construction of basic heavy industry and electrification, while the enhancement
                    of the living standard was to be ensured by extending economic development to
                    all areas of the economy.</p>
                <p>In the early 1950s, Yugoslavia started to build a sort of a third model of
                    socio-economic development – one that was neither capitalist nor centrally
                    planned. It replaced the socialist centrally planned economic and social system
                    with self-management. Thus, it established socialist social ownership, distinct
                    from private and collective property under capitalism as well as from the
                    Soviet-style state socialist ownership. Social ownership as the foundation for
                    self-management meant that companies were owned neither by the state nor by
                    private individuals but rather by all workers. With the introduction of
                    self-management, the decentralisation and relaxation of economic rules in all of
                    the more important areas of economic life took place.</p>
                <p>Although the economic policy after 1958 started to shift towards more balanced
                    investments and the development of activities that affected the living standard,
                    Slovenia’s economic progress during the socialist period was dominated by
                    industrialisation. The latter penetrated Slovenia earlier than the other
                    Yugoslav territories, but still with a significant lag compared to Western and
                    Northern Europe. In the first post-war years, Slovenia was only partially
                    industrialised, but over the next four decades, it became an industrially
                        developed.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn2" n="1">Janez Malačič, »Razvoj
                        prebivalstva Slovenije v povojnem obdobju.« <hi rend="italic">Teorija in
                            praksa: družboslovna revija</hi> 22, no. 4<hi rend="italic">–</hi>5
                        (1985): 402.</note> As employment and personal incomes increased markedly,
                    so did the purchasing power or the living standard of the population. The needs
                    of the consumers increased, and they became more demanding.</p>
                <p>During the socialist period, architecture was seen as an important task of the
                    authorities, aimed at improving the people’s living conditions as well as at
                    increasing the general living standard. Architects and architecture as a
                    profession had a moral duty to contribute to an objective general improvement of
                    the quality of living. This marked a break with the tradition of pre-war
                    architecture, which had focused on design expressiveness. In the new system,
                    architects were assigned the role of illuminators. “Increasing the awareness of
                    our masses and enriching their general culture with basic architectural and
                    urban planning knowledge is one of the tasks of urban planners and architects,”
                    wrote the editorial board of the <hi rend="italic">Arhitekt</hi> magazine at the
                    beginning of its publication based on the summarised conclusions of the 1<hi
                        rend="superscript">st</hi> Consultation of Architects of Yugoslavia in
                    Dubrovnik in 1950.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn3" n="2">»Za napredek naše
                        arhitekture,« <hi rend="italic">Arhitekt</hi> 1, no. 1 (1951): 1.</note> In
                    addition to their traditional tasks, architects were assigned the duty of
                    educating the general public. Both the Yugoslav and the Slovenian Architects’
                    Society actively participated in this process by organising professional
                    seminars, exhibitions at home and abroad, publishing the specialised magazine
                        <hi rend="italic">Arhitekt</hi>, and with many other activities. In this
                    regard, the role of the architect and Professor Edvard Ravnikar from the Faculty
                    of Architecture and Civil and Geodetic Engineering (FAGG) in Ljubljana should be
                        highlighted.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn4" n="3">Andrej Mercina, <hi
                            rend="italic">Arhitekt Ilija Arnautović: Socializem v slovenski
                            arhitekturi</hi> (Ljubljana: Viharnik, 2006), 19.</note>
                </p>
                <p>In the context of the demands for rational and economical production, the focus
                    was on profoundly social and cultural architecture – one that would be “an
                    expression of modern times in the best possible sense”.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn5" n="4">»Za novo arhitekturo,« <hi rend="italic">Arhitekt</hi>
                        3, no. 8 (1953): 1.</note> Like all over Europe, a modern design trend
                    asserted itself, such as had been followed in Scandinavia for a long time. Since
                    the first major Slovenian furniture exhibition, titled <hi rend="italic"
                        >Stanovanje za naše razmere</hi> (Apartment for Our Circumstances), which
                    took place in Ljubljana in 1956, this trend was also adhered to by the Slovenian
                    architects. Slovenian architecture did not follow the development of
                    architecture in the other socialist countries, as the younger-generation
                    architects, led by Edvard Ravnikar, were able to take advantage of the Yugoslav
                    dispute with the Soviet Union in 1948 and sought contacts with the contemporary
                    global architectural trends. Ravnikar’s theses on the importance of
                    architectural theory and the need to broaden the horizons led indirectly to the
                    establishment of contacts with the Swiss and Scandinavian architecture and their
                    ideas on social construction in particular.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn6"
                        n="5">Andrej Hrausky, »Poti sodobne slovenske arhitekture,« in <hi
                            rend="italic">Slovenska kronika XX. stoletja</hi>, ed. Marjan Drnovšek
                        and Drago Bajt (Ljubljana: Nova revija, 1997), 364.</note> Functionalist
                    principles that followed the example of the Swiss-French architect Le Corbusier
                    were applied. The architectural concepts of space were meant to reflect the
                    socialist relations, which were supposed to be evident from the non-elitism of
                    the new concepts, and result in the improvement of everyone’s quality of life.
                    The new urban designs were to generate a sense of belonging to the community.
                    The architectural profession presented advanced architectural designs to a broad
                    circle of people, emphasising economy and new, higher living standards.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>The Emergence and Development of Slovenian Industrial Design</head>
                <p>The professionalisation of Slovenian industrial design in the former Yugoslavia
                    began after World War II. Otherwise, its origins date back to 1919, to the time
                    when the University of Ljubljana was founded. After its establishment in 1920,
                    the Department of Architecture started operating as well.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn7" n="6">
                        <hi rend="italic">Interno študijsko gradivo za predmet Razvoj in teorija
                            oblikovanja</hi> (Ljubljana: ALUO), 129.</note> The emergence of
                    industrial design in Yugoslavia was undoubtedly linked to industrial
                    development, especially to the enormous needs of the post-war wood processing
                    industry, which gradually focused on the production of well-designed and
                    affordable mass-produced furniture. The post-war reconstruction of demolished
                    apartments, the intensive construction of new residential developments and
                    terraced houses in cities and factory settlements in industrial centres, and the
                    construction of entirely new urban settlements called for vast quantities of
                    furniture. In the context of post-war reconstruction and construction, the
                    furniture industry, woodworking technologies, and industrial design developed
                        rapidly.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn8" n="7">Marta Rendla, »Hitro,
                        gospodarno, po meri: sestavljivo sistemsko pohištvo v socializmu,« in <hi
                            rend="italic">Mimohod blaga. Materialna kultura potrošniške družbe na
                            Slovenskem, </hi>ed. Andrej Studen (Ljubljana: Inštitut za novejšo
                        zgodovino, 2019), 165.</note></p>
                <p>In the context of the housing crisis, the new concept of housing construction
                    sought to rationalise the construction of minimum housing with the maximum
                    utility of the differentiated housing areas. At the same time, the apartments
                    needed to be well thought out, efficiently designed, and furnished in a suitable
                    and practical way.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn9" n="8">»Natečaj za
                        stanovanjske bloke v Ljubljani,«<hi rend="italic">Arhitekt</hi> 6, no. 18–19
                        (1956): 7.</note> This resulted in great demand for designers and
                    architects. In the 1960s and 1970s, design in Slovenia was mainly in the domain
                    of architects, as the higher education design studies at the Academy of Fine
                    Arts were not established until 1984. However, the importance of small
                    industrial objects was pointed out by the aforementioned architect and Professor
                    Edvard Ravnikar already at the end of 1948, as he introduced weekly discussions
                    with the students at the Department of Architecture of the University of
                    Ljubljana. From the very beginning, when he became a professor at the Department
                    of Architecture after the end of the war in 1945, Ravnikar, together with other
                    architects, kept underlining the fact that Slovenia, which otherwise had various
                    arts and crafts departments, did not yet have a school of design, either at the
                    university or secondary school level. His efforts yielded results as early as in
                    1946: the Secondary School of Design and Photography (SŠOF) opened its doors in
                    Ljubljana, the capital of Slovenia.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn10" n="9">
                        <hi rend="italic">Interno študijsko gradivo, </hi>132.</note></p>
                <p>The magazine for architecture, urban planning, and applied arts, titled <hi
                        rend="italic">Arhitekt</hi> (1951–1963) and published by the Slovenian
                    Architects’ Society, also endeavoured to assert design as a profession. The rise
                    of design as a discipline began with the introduction of design and development
                    departments in industrial companies in the 1950s. The 1950s can be described as
                    a pioneering period in design. The first development department and design
                    bureau was established in 1952 by the architect, designer, and inventor Niko
                    Kralj after he joined one of the most important companies in the furniture
                    industry: the <hi rend="italic">Stol</hi> factory in Duplica near Kamnik. He
                    persuaded the factory management to abandon licensed products or <hi
                        rend="italic">redesigns</hi> in favour of its own development department and
                    design bureau.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn11" n="10">Ibidem, 133.</note>
                </p>
                <p>In the autumn of 1952, Niko Kralj, who is today considered the pioneer and
                    founder of Slovenian industrial design, also drew up the programme for the first
                    Yugoslav factory service for design and development. In the same year, he also
                    produced the first prototype of a foldable recliner, the Rex chair, nowadays one
                    of the best-known products of Slovenian industrial design. In addition to the
                    Rex chair, Kralj developed other chairs as well, such as the 4455 chair, which
                    represents the first true example of an industrial product made entirely in an
                    industrial way in Slovenia, and the Lupina chair series. The Rex chair, made
                    using the pressed and perforated plywood technology, is still considered as an
                    example of an ergonomically and functionally flawless product. It is an iconic
                    piece that has a place in the collection of the Design Department at the Museum
                    of Modern Art (MoMA) in New York.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn12" n="11">Marta
                        Rendla, <hi rend="italic">»Kam ploveš standard?« Življenjska raven in
                            socializem</hi> (Ljubljana: Inštitut za novejšo zgodovino, 2018),
                    274.</note></p>
                <p>In the 1960s, design asserted its position in society with the establishment of
                    various institutions. The architect Edvard Ravnikar, who was aware of the
                    significance and role of design in the broader social context, criticised the
                    post-war system of architectural education as early as in the 1950s. He also
                    expressed the need to reform it. He believed that architects should expand the
                    spectrum of their work, from designing “the smallest consumer products to
                    planning regional spatial solutions.” In 1959, as part of the education reform,
                    he reached an agreement with the rector of the University of Ljubljana to draw
                    up a radical plan for the reform of the Department of Architecture. As the head
                    of the Faculty of Architecture, he ensured the establishment of the A course
                    (Architecture) and B course (Design) in 1960.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn13"
                        n="12">
                        <hi rend="italic">Interno študijsko gradivo, </hi>134.</note> Based on the
                    Bauhaus models and the contemporaneous Ulm College, the B course was thus
                    introduced on a trial basis in the academic year 1960/61. By implementing the
                    experimental B course of the architecture studies programme, which he carried
                    out for only two years (1960–1962) as an alternative to the conventional system
                    of education at the faculty, Ravnikar monitored and critically evaluated the
                    current issues and placed them in a broader historical, cultural, and
                    contemporary professional context. He ensured that new information was
                    disseminated swiftly within the borders of the former Yugoslavia. He also
                    provided up-to-date information on the achievements of the architectural
                    profession in Western Europe, Scandinavia, and Finland. The B course left its
                    mark on the history of Slovenian design. By combining various scientific
                    disciplines like sociology, psychology, statistics, and geography with certain
                    specialised fields such as urban sociology or social medicine, by bringing
                    together theory and practice, and by using the methodology based on analysis,
                    research, and experimentation, Ravnikar influenced the training of many
                    architects as well as industrial and graphic designers of the post-war
                    generation, despite the fact that the B course was rather short-lived.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn14" n="13">Maja Vardjan, »Metamorfoze sistema kiosk
                        K67,« in <hi rend="italic">Sistemi, strukture, strategije</hi>, ed. Maja
                        Vardjan, (Ljubljana: Muzej za arhitekturo in oblikovanje: Akademija za
                        likovno umetnost in oblikovanje, 2016), 39, 40. Mercina, <hi rend="italic"
                            >Arhitekt</hi>, 19.</note>
                </p>
                <p>In the Slovenian part of Yugoslavia, the formal study of industrial design was,
                    as we have already mentioned, introduced in 1984 at the Academy of Fine Arts
                    with the establishment of the Department of Design and its various design
                    courses (industrial, graphic, unique). One of the initiators of this
                    Department’s establishment was Saša Janez Mächtig, the author of the K67 Kiosk
                    and the protagonist of this article.</p>
                <p>More and more active initiatives were launched to establish connections between
                    industrial design and the economy. After unsuccessful attempts to establish a
                    Centre for Industrial Design in Ljubljana, at the initiative of the Ljubljana
                    City Council and the Ljubljana Chamber of Commerce and Industry, the Biennial of
                    Industrial Design (BIO) was organised in Ljubljana in 1963, bringing together
                    the positive forces from the economic, political, cultural, and professional
                    circles. The newly established Biennial was intended to increase the quality of
                    industrial design and educate the general and professional public through its
                    exhibition activities, while the goal of the Design Centre was to connect
                    designers with the industry. Since then, this international event – an
                    exhibition of well-designed industrial products, visual messages, and design
                    concepts – has been held in Ljubljana every two years, in the years when the
                    Graphic Design Biennial is not taking place. In the former Yugoslavia, design
                    centres were established in Zagreb (<hi rend="italic">Centar za industrijsko
                        oblikovanje</hi> – Industrial Design Centre – in 1964) and Belgrade (<hi
                        rend="italic">Dizajn-Centar</hi> – Design Centre – in 1972).<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn15" n="14">Pika Leban, »Bienale industrijskega
                        oblikovanja od ustanovitve leta 1963 do načrtov za prihodnost« (Thesis,
                        Univerza v Ljubljani: Fakulteta za družbene vede, 2009), 15−19.</note> In
                    1966, Niko Kralj founded the Institute of Design at the Faculty of Architecture and Civil and Geodetic
                    Engineering. In the framework of the Institute, which he headed until his
                    retirement in 1992, Kralj used a modular industrial approach to research
                    ready-to-assemble and separable industrial units or systemic furniture and
                    contributed to the development of design theory.</p>
                <p>Design became increasingly integrated into companies. The leading role was
                    assumed by Iskra from Kranj – the largest electronics, electrical engineering,
                    measuring instruments, drills, telecommunications, consumer goods, etc., company
                    in the former Yugoslavia. In 1962, under the leadership of the designer Davorin
                    Savnik, Iskra opened the first design department in Yugoslavia for developing
                    the industrial, graphic, and unique design. It became a model for Yugoslav
                    design. Iskra’s industrial designers also created distinctive products,
                    especially in the fields of telephony, measuring instruments, and power tools.
                    The ETA 80 telephone, designed by Davorin Savnik in 1978, was the most
                    successful example. With the advent of the electronic circuit, the designer
                    wanted to create as flat a design as possible.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn16"
                        n="15"><hi rend="italic">Interno študijsko gradivo, </hi>136, 137<hi
                            rend="italic">.</hi></note> In 1980, the world’s first phone with a
                    single microchip won the Design Award IF (Industrie Forum) at what was then the
                    world’s largest industrial trade fair in Hannover and the highest industrial
                    design award in Japan. ETA 80 also became the official telephone of the 1980
                    Summer Olympics in Moscow.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn17" n="16">
                        <hi rend="italic">MAO - Eta 80</hi>, accessed May 6, 2023, <ref
                            target="https://mao.si/zbirka/eta-80/"
                            >https://mao.si/zbirka/eta-80/</ref>.</note> Later, it was also included
                    in the collection of New York’s Museum of Modern Art (MoMA).</p>
                <p>In residential architecture, where the primary focus after the war was to provide
                    everyone with a decent housing minimum, we should also mention the leading
                    researchers of residential culture, the architects Marta Ivanšek and her husband
                    France Ivanšek. Fascinated by the humane spirit of modernism and the high
                    standard of living in Sweden, they wanted to transfer and implement their
                    knowledge of and experience with living in Sweden into the Slovenian environment
                    by raising awareness and educating not only the users but also the professional
                    public. To improve the housing culture in Slovenia, they argued in favour of
                    standardising housing construction, residential spaces, and furniture
                    dimensions. They also designed the Svea kitchen, which became a symbol of modern
                    Slovenian kitchen design.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn18" n="17">Martina
                        Malešič, »Arhitekta France in Marta Ivanšek,« in <hi rend="italic"
                            >Arhitekturna zgodovina</hi> (Ljubljana: Znanstvena založba Filozofske
                        fakultete, Zavod za gradbeništvo Slovenije, 2008), 170, 171.</note></p>
                <p>In the 1960s, the general developments and the increasing living standard gave
                    rise to a need and desire for well-designed products that were accessible to
                    everyone. A lifestyle that emphasised youthful and unusual shapes took hold.
                    People were excited about new materials and technologies. After the first wave
                    of the construction and reconstruction of buildings destroyed and damaged during
                    the war, the conditions for the emergence of advanced architectural and urban
                    planning projects were created.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>The K67 Kiosk System</head>
                <p>The K67 Kiosk is an example of urban street architecture design, envisioned in
                    1966–1969 by the young Slovenian architect and industrial designer Saša Janez
                        Mächtig.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn19" n="18"> Saša J. Mächtig’s
                        development as an architect and designer was influenced by the B course of
                        the experimental architecture study programme. Vardjan, »Metamorfoze sistema
                        Kiosk K67,« 39.</note> He got the inspiration for it from the cross-section
                    of two pipes. Two pipes running through each other in installations reminded him
                    of a construction. With the mutual piercing of two plastic tubes, he began to
                    test the possibilities of a modular system that would correspond to the
                    development of new contemporary technologies and materials at the time in the
                    direction of mass industrial production of products for everyday life. By
                    trimming and machining the tubes, he obtained a module.</p>
                <p>The K67 Kiosk is an artistic design product developed in parallel with other
                    projects of Yugoslav functionalism in the context of the urban environment
                    systematisation through the disciplines of architecture, design, and urban
                        planning.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn20" n="19">Ibid.</note> It was created at a time of the expansion of
                    modern lifestyles, increased mobility, and the rise of consumerism. At that
                    time, Yugoslavia was reorienting itself towards the production of consumer goods
                    in an effort to promote the activities that contributed to the improvement of
                    the living standard. It also started to promote tertiary activities such as the
                    hospitality industry, tourism, trade, crafts, housing, municipal utility
                    services, and other non-economic activities.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn21"
                        n="20">Rendla, <hi rend="italic">»Kam ploveš standard?,«</hi> 330, 331.</note>
                    However, in architecture and design, new practices and approaches were
                    encouraged in the context of the new socio-political and economic system.</p>
                <p>The young architect and industrial designer started designing the K67 Kiosk when
                    he was challenged to solve the needs of Ljubljana, the Slovenian capital.
                    Experts saw inadequate street furniture as a pressing problem. Among other
                    things, they characterised the existing kiosks as unsuitable. With Mächtig’s
                    project of prefabricated spatial elements of the kiosk type, which he developed
                    as street furniture for the needs of minimal commercial, labour, and other
                    service activities for the market for the contemporaneous Ljubljana company <hi
                        rend="italic">Magistrat</hi>, he offered an answer to the problems of urban
                    furniture in Ljubljana. As an architect interested in both urbanism and
                    industrial design, he wanted to develop urban street architecture as an
                    organised system. With modular kiosks, he wanted to influence the local
                    authorities, convinced that such a solution would achieve a higher level of
                    standardisation and harmonisation in the city, as he perceived design as a
                    hybrid of the humanities, technical sciences, social sciences, economics, and
                    psychology. He also based his efforts on the principles of Edvard Ravnikar, a
                    professor and architect at the Faculty of Architecture and Civil and Geodetic
                    Engineering in Ljubljana, who advocated, among other things, the principle: “
                        <hi rend="italic">Think globally, act locally</hi>”.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn22" n="21">»Naslednja postaja kiosk, Saša J. Mächtig, arhitekt in
                        industrijski oblikovalec,« <hi rend="italic">RTV 365</hi>, accessed April
                        15, 2023, <ref
                            target="https://365.rtvslo.si/arhiv/dokumentarni-portret/174746857"
                            >https://365.rtvslo.si/arhiv/dokumentarni-portret/174746857</ref>.</note>
                    Aware that he needed to combine not only function and expression but also
                    economics and technology, Mächtig carried out a study of the urban space and the
                    needs of the city’s inhabitants. As an architect, he understood the relationship
                    between products, consumers, and the environment.</p>
                <p>The complex path of the K67 Kiosk’s development began in 1966, when the young
                    architect, based on a few PVC models painted red, started to look for different
                    ways of assembling a system of five interconnected modular elements. These were
                    to be derived from the main crosswise model. The clear geometric format of the
                    crosswise unit was dictated by the design. Mächtig was also aware that the
                    system, as a product, needed to be developed in accordance with the triangle of
                    the design process, consisting of invention, technological production, and
                        marketing.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn23" n="22"> Saša J. Mächtig and Livia
                        Paldi, »Sistem K-67. Intervju s Sašo J. Mächtigom,« in <hi rend="italic"
                            >Next Stop Kiosk = Naslednja postaja Kiosk: Moderna galerija Ljubljana,
                            29. 10. – 30.11. 2003</hi> (Ljubljana: Moderna galerija = Modern Art
                        Museum; Frankfurt am Main: Revolver – Archiv für aktuelle Kunst, 2003),
                        149.</note>
                </p>
                <p>He actively put himself in the role of a marketer and promoter. He proposed that
                    the Imgrad company from Ljutomer – the company that started producing the Kiosks
                    – introduce an internal newsletter titled <hi rend="italic">Kontakti</hi> and
                    brochures called <hi rend="italic">Informacije</hi>. Both <hi rend="italic"
                        >Kontakti</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Informacije</hi> were, among other
                    things, intended to promote products and, above all, help penetrate foreign
                        markets.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn24" n="23"> Špela Šubic, »Oblikovalec
                        Saša J. Mächtig,« in<hi rend="italic"> Sistemi, strukture, strategije</hi>,
                        ed. Maja Vardjan, 71.</note>
                </p>
                <p>According to the opinion of some, with the design and material, as well as
                    colour, Mächtig decided to make the K67 Kiosk outstandingly eye-catching. He
                    associated it with the trend of brightly coloured plastic objects, which
                    reinforced the cult of accessories whose colours and forms represented a
                    reckoning with the traditional grey functionalist past.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn25" n="24">Ibid., 73.</note> As production developed, the K67
                    Kiosk started to appear in other colours as well, as customers imagined the
                    colours of the Kiosks according to the activities they were intended to serve.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn26" n="25">Ana Panič, »Kiosk K67 ali blišč in
                        beda nekega razvojnega preboja,« in <hi rend="italic">Made in YU 2015</hi>,
                        ed. Tanja Petrović and Jernej Mlekuž (Ljubljana: Založba ZRC, ZRC SAZU,
                        2016), 154, 155.</note></p>
                <p>The K67 Kiosk system was the result of socialism with elements of the
                    market economy and the beginnings of a private market economy in the 1960s. Its
                    position and transformative capacity opened up much room for it to function in
                    various social, political, and economic contexts.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn27" n="26">Vardjan, »Metamorfoze sistema kiosk K67,« 38,
                        39.</note></p>
                <p>Working outside the constraints of a single discipline, interdisciplinary
                    integration, the multifunctionality of objects, the inseparability of design
                    from the society, the considerable importance of research, education, and
                    collaboration between the university and the industry, and the necessity of the
                    interplay between design and architecture were all of crucial importance for
                    Mächtig’s way of thinking and practice of design. The K67 Kiosk was a modern
                    object, as it could be folded, disassembled, and transformed. It represented a
                    structure and exhibited features that were considered modern at the time. In the
                    1960s, the idea of modularity was prominent. The whole world was looking for
                    modular solutions, as a lot of potential was seen in industrial architecture.
                    The search for modular solutions was supported by technological advances in the
                    aerospace industry, which was undergoing revolutionary changes at the time. The
                    K67 Kiosk was created at a time of the dynamic development of the modern way of
                    life, the progress of science and technology, the rise of motorisation, the
                    media, and the birth of a socialist consumer society.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn28" n="27">»Naslednja postaja kiosk.«</note>
                </p>
                <p>The 1960s were an extraordinary period for the development of architecture.
                    Alongside the utopian projects that emerged abroad and in various geographical
                    and cultural contexts as alternatives to the established ways of living, in
                    Yugoslavia, architecture using a refined and specific language of late modernism
                    developed. The K67 Kiosk reflects Mächtig’s belief in technology, mass
                    production, systematic urban growth, infrastructure, and flexible, dynamic, and
                    mobile structures. He drew on the current architectural movements of the time.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn29" n="28">Vardjan, »Metamorfoze sistema kiosk
                        K67,« 42.</note>
                </p>
                <p>The K67 Kiosk was realised in the sense of mass production and broad use for
                    service activities in the street. It was created in the region located between
                    East and West – in the space that allowed for mutual cultural exchange. With
                    ideas of temporariness, mobility, adaptability, and prefabrication, the 1960s
                    architecture often approached the discipline of industrial design. The K67 Kiosk
                    represents a fusion of architecture and industrial design as well. It is
                    associated with architecture primarily through space, scale, and function.
                    Meanwhile, its modular structure, production method, materiality, and image
                    correspond to the principles of industrial design. When the conceptual design
                    was first presented in 1967, Saša J. Mächtig wrote that “ <hi rend="italic">the
                        Kiosk, understood in the modern sense, allows for growth and change.
                        Regarding its meaning, it is similar to Scandinavian furniture systems,
                        while in terms of its design feeling, it is akin to a car body.</hi>”<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn30" n="29">Ibidem, 45.</note> The K67 Kiosk – whose
                    design was friendly, cute, heartwarming, revolutionary, and bold for the times –
                    embodied inventive modular construction with the slogan “<hi rend="italic">a
                        single solution for all problems</hi>” and the following instructions for
                    use: “<hi rend="italic">Buy, set up, operate!</hi>”<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn31" n="30">Ibid., 43−45. »Naslednja postaja kiosk.«</note>
                </p>
                <p>As the modular Kiosk was a technical innovation, it was patented in 1967 and
                    named K67 after this year. In 1968, it was prepared for serial production by a
                    company Imgrad from the north-eastern part of Slovenia, where it was
                    manufactured and exported until 2000 after the company had purchased the patent
                    from the Ljubljana-based marketing company Magistrat International. It was first
                    presented to the Slovenian public in 1969 with the exhibition of a prototype in
                    the Slovenian provincial town of Ljutomer. In 1970, after it was featured in the
                    most competent design magazine in the world – the British <hi rend="italic"
                        >Design</hi> magazine, followed by a wave of international publicity around
                    Europe, the USA, and Japan – it also enjoyed a major marketing boost.</p>
                <p>As the first generation of the K67 Kiosk, made of reinforced polyester and
                    polyurethane in a “sandwich” construction, did not anticipate such a high
                    demand, the architect, soon after this success, developed a composite kiosk
                    construction: the second-generation K67 Kiosk. The first generation of the K67
                    Kiosk system was characterised by the monolithic form of its primary spatial
                    elements and based on five modular spatial elements, three of which – the cross,
                    the corridor, and the triangular elements – were mass-produced and could be
                    expanded, complemented, and shifted to form various spatial configurations. The
                    primary elements were complemented by a series of secondary, tertiary, and
                    quaternary ones, ranging from various façade fillings to canopies and interior
                    furnishings. The structure consisted of a double shell of reinforced polyester
                    and intermediate insulation.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn32" n="31">Saša J.
                        Mächtig, »Kiosk K67, I. generacija,« in <hi rend="italic">Sistemi,
                            strukture, strategije</hi>, ed. Maja Vardjan, 102.</note>
                </p>
                <p>The second generation of Kiosks introduced technological improvements and
                    optimised the production process. The key innovation was the construction of a
                    slightly convex load-bearing shell, which, unlike the original monolithic
                    structure, could be dismantled. The basic elements of the second-generation
                    Kiosk were the ceiling, floor shell, and four corner columns. Side components
                    such as shop, window, door, and blank façade elements could be inserted between
                    them. With the second generation of Kiosks, the designer reduced the production
                    time and simplified transport. For the second-generation Kiosk, the thickness of
                    the elements was increased to 10 cm from the previous 8 cm. The basic unit of
                    the K67 street furniture system became the zero series; while the new unit,
                    which replaced the basic unit in 1972, is the best known today.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn33" n="32">Šubic, »Oblikovalec Saša J. Mächtig,« 72,
                        Mächtig, »Kiosk K67, II. generacija,« 116.</note>
                </p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="Rendla_1.jpg" height="500px"/>
                    <head>Photo 1: Ljubljana, April 30, 1980. Photo: Rudi Paškulin, from the
                        photographic collection of the Exportprojekt, kept by: MNZS.</head>
                </figure>
                <p>After 1976, intensive specialisation of the K67 Kiosk system took place. The K67
                    Kiosk was used for newspaper and tobacco shops, small workshops, florists,
                    parking ticket facilities, information offices, tourist offices, porters’
                    lodges, etc. Special projects of bivouacs for mountain shelters, standardised
                    hydrometeorological stations, and the project of a Kiosk with a container for
                    selling fruits and vegetables were developed as well. Among the completed
                    projects, the following, which were the most demanding in the technical sense,
                    stood out: Kiosks as reporter booths at the Kantrida Stadium in Rijeka, Croatia;
                    K67 elements as sanitary facilities; transparent triangular units for the
                    police; and the food Kiosk projects. Food Kiosks included units with the
                    equipment for the quick preparation of snacks and drinks, storage, self-service
                    machines, and toilets. In 1980, a test Kiosk specialising in food was set up at
                    Ljubljana Castle in the capital of Slovenia, called <hi rend="italic">Lačni
                        zmaj</hi> (Hungry Dragon). In 1977, during the K67 Kiosk’s specialisation,
                    its author Saša Janez Mächtig explained in the factory newsletter <hi
                        rend="italic">Kontakti</hi> that <hi rend="italic">“the Kiosk, which is the
                        most demanding element of street furniture in terms of volume, represents
                        the core and starting point for a more comprehensive micro-location layout,
                        as it brings together a number of accompanying functional elements of the
                        equipment – such as wastebaskets, information elements, advertising
                        graphics, lighting, greenery, benches, etc. – all in accordance with the
                        requirements of the specific location, of course.”</hi><note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn34" n="33">Saša J. Mächtig, »Fenomeni v urbanskem okolju,« <hi
                            rend="italic">Kontakti</hi> 1, (1977): 5, 6.</note></p>
                <p>Large quantities of the K67 Kiosk were sold throughout the former Yugoslavia and
                    elsewhere. It was copied by other manufacturers as well, and it can be said that
                    it embodied the Eastern European kiosk culture. The K67 Kiosk as a unifying and
                    unified object was compatible with the system that did not allow the free market
                    mechanisms to operate. The time in which it was conceived called for rationality
                    and economy. Using a single solution for several purposes was therefore very
                    appropriate. With its multifunctionality, the K67 Kiosk became a characteristic
                    urban space object in the Eastern European socialist countries. At the height of
                    modernist architecture, it was defined as an international style, as it was
                    easily adapted to both Western capitalism and Eastern communism. Today, it is
                    spread all over the world in 7,500 iterations. It was sold to the countries of
                    the former Soviet Union and to the West (to Germany, Switzerland, France, the
                    United States of America, Canada), the Middle East (especially to Iraq and
                    Jordan), as well as to Kenya, Australia, New Zealand, and Japan.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn35" n="34">Mateja Panter, »K67, kiosk, ki je po 50
                        letih spet oživel. Po evropskih mestih spet srečujemo legendarni kiosk
                        slovenskega oblikovalca in arhitekta Saše Janeza Mächtiga,« <hi
                            rend="italic">Dnevnik</hi>, July 9, 2018, <ref
                            target="https://www.dnevnik.si/1042832279"
                            >https://www.dnevnik.si/1042832279</ref>.</note></p>
                <p>The K67 Kiosk represented a breakthrough innovation, as before the rise of
                    industrialisation and the development of new technologies, kiosks would mostly
                    be built as mini-architectures or small houses using ordinary construction
                    methods rather than as products designed and produced according to the
                    industrial logic of mass production. The Kiosk module defined the scope of the
                    workspace: its dimensions were intended for a minimal workspace. By designing
                    the cell, Mächtig worked within the constraints of the existing system and in
                    the direction of discovering further needs. He systematically looked for
                    concrete solutions and attempted to put them into practice.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn36" n="35">Vardjan, »Metamorfoze sistema kiosk K67,« 43−45.
                        »Naslednja postaja kiosk.«</note></p>
                <p>He was system-oriented in his planning, developing all projects as branching
                    systems of variations and combinations that would often go beyond the scope of
                    the individual tasks. The systemic orientation was based on the growing needs to
                    take into account the individual wishes of the users as well as on the
                    contemporaneous structuralist architectural projects during the 1960s and 1970s.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn37" n="36">Vardjan, »Metamorfoze sistema kiosk
                        K67,« 46.</note> As a capsule architecture project, the K67 Kiosk is also a
                    clearly structured system whose modular elements provide numerous possibilities
                    for assembly, growth, and adaptation.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="Rendla_2.jpg" height="500px"/>
                    <head>Photo 2: Ljubljana, May 1977.<lb/>Photo: Janez Pukšič, from the
                        photographic collection of the Delo newspaper, kept by: MNZS</head>
                </figure>
                <p>The K67 Kiosk system was based on a series of hierarchically designed components.
                    The primary elements were defined by the supporting structure represented by the
                    various housing models, while the secondary elements or components such as
                    windows, walls, and doors were inserted into the supporting structure. The
                    housings allowed for horizontal as well as vertical stacking into linear or
                    spatially varied combinations. The broad range of accessories allowed for even
                    greater variability. Together, these elements formed diverse spatial structures
                    and embodied the constant potential for change and growth.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn38" n="37">Ibid.</note></p>
                <p>As micro-architecture fascinated by the introduction of new materials, the K67
                    system challenged the social, production-technological, and market aspects of
                    the development of street furniture and became a part of the general urban
                    culture, especially in Eastern Europe. It represented temporary modernism at a
                    time when monumental modernism was on the rise in the former Yugoslavia. As
                    temporary installations in the public space, the Kiosks were strategically
                    adapted to the flow of people. The K67 Kiosk system highlighted the
                    commercialisation of space as an important urban value. It was a substantive
                    invention, pointing out the new values in society.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn39" n="38">Marjetica Potrč, »Kiosk je bil fenomen,« in <hi
                            rend="italic">Sistemi, strukture, strategije</hi>, ed. Maja Vardjan, 77.</note>
                </p>
                <p>The work of the architect and industrial designer Mächtig is inseparably linked
                    to the concept of streets and street furniture. The significant impact of the
                    K67 Kiosk in the Slovenian territory in the 1960s was based on the connection
                    between modular architecture and urban service activities. With its flexible,
                    multifunctional structure that could be infinitely expanded in countless
                    assemblies and configurations, the K67 Kiosk, with its smooth plastic shell,
                    became a distinctive street feature of many urban centres. On the occasion of
                    the exhibition dedicated to the Kiosk in the Museum of Architecture and Design
                    in Ljubljana (26 November 2015 – 3 April 2016), the organisers wrote that the
                    artist as a designer was well-aware of the social significance of street
                    furniture design and therefore also understood that its elements dictated the
                    pulse of the city and influenced the quality of the citizens’ everyday life.</p>
                <p>The K67 Kiosk has become and remains an attribute of the Slovenian architect and
                    designer Saša Janez Mächtig and one of the historical milestones of Slovenian
                    design.</p>
                <p>The red kiosk, as it came to be known, also existed in white, green, yellow,
                    orange, and blue versions. The citizens of the former Yugoslavia still remember
                    it as a red kiosk selling hot dogs and sausages.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn40" n="39">Panič, »Kiosk K67 ali blišč in beda nekega razvojnega
                        preboja,« 154, 155.</note></p>
                <p>The Kiosks provided space for activities that did not require a permanent
                    location. They became spots that sold newspapers and tobacco, fast food, snacks,
                    ice cream, flowers, tickets, and so on. They were used to pay parking fees and
                    provide tourist information, as well as functioned as gatehouses in front of
                    various establishments. They were also used by shoemakers, locksmiths, and
                    sports commentators, served as shelters and reception areas, as well as provided
                    room for security guards and reception units.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn41"
                        n="40">
                        <hi rend="italic">Znameniti kiosk, ki je iz Ljutomera osvajal svet. S
                            slovitim kioskom Kiosk K67 je Ljutomer tesno povezan, saj so te
                            modularne kioske izdelovali v ljutomerskem podjetju Imgrad</hi>,
                        accessed May 11, 2021, <ref
                            target="https://www.prlekija-on.net/lokalno/20341/znameniti-kiosk-ki-je-iz-ljutomera-osvajal-svet.html"
                            >https://www.prlekija-on.net/lokalno/20341/znameniti-kiosk-ki-je-iz-ljutomera-osvajal-svet.html</ref>.</note>
                    In the mid-1980s in Novo mesto, the capital of one of Slovenia’s provinces,
                    seven units of the K67 Kiosk made up the <hi rend="italic">Slavček</hi> bar, for
                    example. The establishment was set up by a restaurateur from Novo mesto together
                    with his wife, a cook. As it happened, the K67 Kiosk was the cheapest option for
                    building a pub at the time. The couple bought seven of them and assembled them
                    into a structure. Then they also excavated a basement. The <hi rend="italic"
                        >Slavček</hi> bar, which was later sold by the owners’ son, was probably the
                    only K67 Kiosk with a basement in the world.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn42"
                        n="41">Igor Vidmar, »Slavček ni umrl, postal je dediščina,« <hi
                            rend="italic">Dolenjski list</hi>, July 7, 2021, <ref
                            target="https://www.dolenjskilist.si/2021/06/13/249567/novice/dolenjska/Slavcek_ni_umrl_postal_je_dediscina/"
                            >https://www.dolenjskilist.si/2021/06/13/249567/novice/dolenjska/Slavcek_ni_umrl_postal_je_dediscina/</ref>.</note>
                    K67 Kiosks hosted small private businesses even before the collapse of the state
                    and the system – even before the transition to a free-market economy in the
                    1990s.</p>
                <p>Subject to constant adaptation and temporariness, the K67 Kiosk was present in
                    the public space and asserted its personal modernism. Designed primarily for
                    urban areas, it was conceived as a project to systematise the urban environment.
                    It was designed as an open structure, capable of change. It could be connected
                    to the infrastructure network – connections such as water, sewerage,
                    electricity, and telephone. This included the possibility of underground
                    installations to avoid interfering with the design of the module itself.
                    Pre-manufactured on a component-by-component basis, it arrived fully assembled
                    and ready to be connected to the existing installations. Using new technologies
                    and materials that were in vogue at the time – such as reinforced polyester and
                    polyurethane – it was an innovative and practical solution. The elements of the
                    K67 system combined with complementary street furniture units such as
                    wastebaskets offered a wide range of possibilities to create an identity for a
                    wide variety of environments. The Slovenian architect and designer also derived
                    other street furniture systems from the open structure of the Kiosk,
                    implementing them as a connecting element of the city and contributing to its
                    comprehensiveness, recognisability, and better orientation.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn43" n="42">Vardjan, »Metamorfoze sistema kiosk K67,«
                    47.</note></p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Breakthrough and International Visibility</head>
                <p>A review of the K67 Kiosk in the English <hi rend="italic">Design</hi> magazine –
                    according to the kiosk’s author, it was the first industrial design magazine at
                    the time in the world – represented the first international recognition of
                    architect Saša Janez Mächtig and his now iconic Kiosk. In 1969, the Slovenian
                    architect attended a congress of the International Council of Societies of
                    Industrial Design (ICSID World Design Congress) in London, where he met many
                    publishers, editors, and contributors of the <hi rend="italic">Design</hi>
                    magazine. As they were interested in his work, he showed them the slides made
                    for the exhibition of the prototype Kiosk at the location of its construction.
                    In the spring of 1970, he received a copy of the <hi rend="italic">Design</hi>
                    magazine with a two-page review of the K67 Kiosk with a full-page colour
                    photograph titled <hi rend="italic">Low life from the streets</hi>. The Kiosk
                    was presented as an example of urban design. It was also included in the list of
                    the 25 best-designed Yugoslav products. It was ranked 11<hi rend="superscript"
                        >th</hi> on the list that the renowned design theory expert Goroslav Keller
                    compiled for the <hi rend="italic">Start</hi> magazine. After the review in the
                        <hi rend="italic">Design</hi> magazine, the K67 Kiosk was invited to be
                    included in the collection of one of the most influential modern art museums in
                    the world, the New York Museum of Modern Art, MoMA. In 1970, the latter was
                    preparing an exhibition of Italian design, a part of which was devoted to
                    modular industrial architecture. Many top Italian designers were invited. When
                    the organisers noticed that modular architecture was also emerging elsewhere,
                    they offered to include the K67 Kiosk into the MoMA collection. Technological,
                    social, or aesthetic innovation are among the main criteria for the inclusion of
                    works into this collection, as the Museum is dedicated exclusively to modern art
                    and aims to integrate diverse artistic practices into its programme, with
                    architecture and design representing crucial parts of this effort.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn44" n="43">Juliet Kinchin, »Zbirka inovativnih
                        oblikovalskih praks,« in <hi rend="italic">Sistemi, strukture,
                            strategije</hi>, ed. Maja Vardjan, 81.</note>
                    In 1971, the K67 Kiosk became the second Yugoslav product alongside Marko Turk’s
                        microphone<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn45" n="44">Marko Turk’s microphone
                        was included in the MoMA Museum’s permanent collection in 1963.</note> to be
                    included in the collection of the world’s first museum of contemporary
                    industrial design. The MoMA Museum curator placed it in the Environments
                    category. The curator’s design programme and the way of setting up the
                    forthcoming exhibition of Italian design titled <hi rend="italic">Italy: the New
                        Domestic Landscape, Achievements, and Problems of Italian Design</hi>,
                    organised by the MoMA Museum, both emphasised the environment. The 1972
                    exhibition of Italian design included the concept of environments as one of its
                    key themes. The participants were asked to propose micro-environments within the
                    spatial constraints of 3.6 metres in height, 4.8 metres in width, and 4.8 metres
                    in depth. Each environment had to be prefabricated and packed in a standard
                    shipping container. The exhibition of Italian design and the K67 Kiosk represent
                    important milestones in the design development of these achievements, as they
                    take into account industrially produced individual units as well as the urban
                    whole. The exhibition of Italian design, which promoted new talents and
                    encouraged the exploration of innovative design practices, expressed a desire
                    for change through a combination of critical interventions and radical and
                    practical solutions. It was one of the landmark design exhibitions of the 20<hi
                        rend="superscript">th</hi> century.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn46" n="45"
                        >Kinchin, »Zbirka inovativnih oblikovalskih praks,« 82.</note> The inclusion
                    of the K67 Kiosk in the collection of the New York Museum of Modern Art – with
                    its tradition of collecting and presenting architecture as a replicable object
                    of design and a crucial contributor to the discourse on sustainability,
                    architectural invention, material research, and urbanism – represented an
                    incredible breakthrough as well as a challenge in terms of planning the
                    exportation of the Kiosks.</p>
                <p>Unfortunately – due to a fire in the Imgrad company, which produced the Kiosks –
                    the Slovenian architect and industrial designer was only able to take limited
                    advantage of the significant international recognition of the K67 Kiosk when it
                    won the global competition for street furniture in the Munich pedestrian zone
                    and for certain other needs of the 1972 Olympic Games in Munich, Germany. Thus,
                    only the Olympic Sailing Centre in Kiel was equipped with K67 Kiosks.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn47" n="46">Šubic, »Oblikovalec Saša J. Mächtig,«
                        65.</note></p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>The Kiosk’s Second Life</head>
                <p>The second life of the K67 Kiosk refers to the phenomenon of the Kiosk today.
                    Nowadays, it appears in various roles: as an icon of the 20<hi
                        rend="superscript">th</hi>-century industrial design and a coveted
                    collectors’ item; a decayed and abandoned object in the cities of South-Eastern
                    Europe; a nostalgic memory of youth and socialism; a phenomenon and foundation
                    for research and artistic projects; as well as a live organism capable of
                    constant regeneration.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn48" n="47">Vardjan,
                        »Metamorfoze sistema kiosk K67,« 48.</note> As an artistic artefact, it has
                    its place in museums and books, and it is also food for thought. Because of its
                    social function, it became a part of the collective consciousness and memory.
                    With its colours and presence, it made a profound impact on its surroundings. As
                    urban street architecture set in the public space, it promoted the everyday
                    activities of the street or everyday space.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn49"
                        n="48">Potrč, »Kiosk je bil fenomen,« 77.</note> In the opinion of the
                    Slovenian artist Marjetica Potrč, it was a substantive invention and a living
                    laboratory in the right place at the right time.</p>
                <p>Due to its distinctive character, the Kiosk still possesses a strong image today.
                    As an accent, it is integrated into either historical or contemporary
                    environments on unexpectedly equal terms.</p>
                <p>Since as early as 1971, the K67 Kiosk has been included in the collection of the
                    New York Museum of Modern Art (MoMA) as a retrospective of the best examples of
                        20<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>-century design. In 2018, it became a part
                    of the MoMA Museum’s major retrospective exhibition titled <hi rend="italic"
                        >Toward a Concrete Utopia: Architecture in Yugoslavia, 1948–1980</hi>. In
                    the context of a Times Square Design Lab project,<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn50" n="49">The Times Square Design Lab is an initiative to
                        implement and test various ideas regarding the public space in the immediate
                        vicinity of Broadway. It provides solutions for seating, public signage, and
                        storage in the squares. In some cases, the initiative involves new design
                        ideas, and in others classic designs sharing the characteristic that they “
                            <hi rend="italic">embody the creative spirit of New York and offer
                            original solutions for a better pedestrian experience in a busy
                            location</hi>”.</note> a K67 Kiosk also appeared in Times Square in the
                    heart of New York City and remained there until the middle of the spring of
                    2019. At the intersection of the 45<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> and 46<hi
                        rend="superscript">th</hi> Streets and Broadway, it served as an information
                    hub for the Times Square design pavilion and the NYCxDESIGN event.</p>
                <p>When the Kiosk was set up, Tim Tompkins, President of Times Square Alliance,
                    which manages the public space of this New York’s square, said the following:
                        <hi rend="italic">“We like the Kiosk so much that we bought it and brought
                        it here to keep it forever. We do not know exactly what to put in it yet,
                        because it can serve many purposes – as a tourist information spot, selling
                        food and drink, or maybe books and newspapers. But first, it will provide
                        tourist information.”</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn51" n="50">A. J.,
                            <hi rend="italic">Kultni kiosk Saše Mächtiga kraljuje sredi newyorškega
                            vrveža - RTV SLO</hi>, accessed April 17, 2023, <ref
                            target="https://www.rtvslo.si/kultura/vizualna-umetnost/kultni-kiosk-sase-maechtiga-kraljuje-sredi-newyorskega-vrveza/487724"
                            >https://www.rtvslo.si/kultura/vizualna-umetnost/kultni-kiosk-sase-maechtiga-kraljuje-sredi-newyorskega-vrveza/487724</ref>.
                    </note></p>
                <p>At the client’s request, the author, in collaboration with skilled contractors,
                    had the Kiosk restored to its original 1966 colour combination: bright red for
                    the main structure and dark brown for the prefabricated walls.</p>
                <p>The President of Times Square Alliance further explained: <hi rend="italic">“Half
                        a million people pass through Times Square every day, so this is a great
                        venue for promotion. We would like to bring a bit of Europe to the new
                        world, some beauty to a less beautiful place, and, if you like, some
                        socialism to this centre of capitalism.”</hi><note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn52" n="51">Ibid.</note></p>
                <p>Currently, K67 Kiosks are being revived in some places. Thanks to their
                    construction and modular system, which allows for addition, subtraction,
                    modification, and upgrading, the Kiosk is nowadays often used in completely new
                    functions. Well-preserved specimens are highly sought-after and are being
                    restored. For example, the German designer Martin Ruge von Löw became interested
                    in the Kiosk when he came across it in Poland. He decided to search for the
                    product and restore it. At his initiative, in September 2018, a K67 Kiosk
                    started operating in Berlin as the city’s smallest restaurant in the open-air
                    inner square of the Art Nouveau Mykita complex in the iconic Kreuzberg
                        district.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn53" n="52"> Panter, »K67, kiosk, ki
                        je po 50 letih spet oživel.«</note></p>
                <p>Furthermore, in 2007, the University of Weimar brought a Kiosk from Warsaw and
                    used it as an information point in front of the building where the first Bauhaus
                    school had been located.</p>
                <p>The transformative capacity of the K67 Kiosk was most evident in the context of
                    “do-it-yourself” projects, unplanned individual initiatives, and various
                    processes of self-organisation. In this context, the K67 Kiosk appears as a kind
                    of folk architecture. The practice revealed all that was unpredictable,
                    changeable, and temporary. On the one hand, the Kiosk appears as an object
                    belonging to a planned city – a city adhering to a set of modern planning rules
                    – while on the other hand, it appears as an object belonging to an “open city” –
                    a city that allows and enables random changes and developments.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn54" n="53">Vardjan, »Metamorfoze sistema kiosk K67,«
                        48.</note></p>
                <p>Some people underline it as a system that, with its design, still offers
                    universal solutions today. The abovementioned internationally active Slovenian
                    artist Marjetica Potrč calls it strategic architecture. Her art installation <hi
                        rend="italic">Next Station Kiosk</hi>, presented in 2003 at the Ljubljana
                    Modern Art Museum, presents the idea or potential of a mobile dwelling. With
                    this installation, Potrč answers a provocative question posed by the English <hi
                        rend="italic">Design </hi>magazine, which, when the Kiosk was unveiled in
                    1970, wondered whether the architect would be able to develop the K67 system in
                    the direction of becoming a dwelling,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn55" n="54"
                        >Ibid., 48−50.</note> as, at the time when the K67 Kiosk was created, it was
                    natural to think about mobile housing units for the mobile individual. For
                    example, in America at the time, temporary mobile architecture – such as the
                    poor living in trailers – was formally compared, in the pejorative sense, with
                    the informal city, which was perceived as a place of chaos and disorder.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn56" n="55"> Potrč, »Kiosk je bil fenomen,«
                        77.</note></p>
                <p>Because it was so widespread, the K67 Kiosk, which some critics described as
                    dispersed network architecture, was also researched by Helge Kühnel from Berlin
                    for Amsterdam’s Publicplan.</p>
                <p>“<hi rend="italic">The Kiosk Shots</hi>” project, initiated by Publicplan
                    Amsterdam, aims to evaluate the K67 design product and draw attention to its
                    exceptional role in the Eastern European urban environment. The project of
                    collecting and mapping the K67 Kiosks intends to create a general overview –
                    documentation about the Eastern European urban environment. The project, whose
                    purpose is to demonstrate the individual diversity and variety of a design
                    product placed in a public environment, will provide a virtual online overview
                    of the presence of the K67 Kiosks scattered throughout Eastern Europe (at
                        www.publicplan.com/K67).<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn57" n="56">»<hi
                            rend="italic">Saša Maechtig, Kiosk K67, 1966</hi>. Zavod Big,« accessed
                        May 9, 2021, <ref
                            target="https://zavodbig.com/portfolio-items/sasa-maechtig-kiosk-k67-1966/"
                            >https://zavodbig.com/portfolio-items/sasa-maechtig-kiosk-k67-1966/</ref>.</note></p>
                <p>The process of the evaluation of the K67 Kiosk is also accompanied by a number of
                    artistic projects. In addition to the abovementioned Slovenian artist Marjetica
                    Potrč, who combined K67 units with South American “palafitos“ – wooden houses
                    raised on stilts – in her installation “<hi rend="italic">Next Stop Kiosk”</hi>,
                    Magnus Bärtås, a Swedish artist ˮ, arranged K67 units in front of a black
                    background in his photo series “<hi rend="italic">Satellites</hi>ˮ. The
                    important role of the Kiosks in the former Yugoslavia was also documented by the
                    project “<hi rend="italic">Mutations</hi>” a few years ago. Above all, the K67
                    Kiosk has become a part of the history and identity of the former Yugoslavia and
                    also a part of a wider and global design heritage.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn58" n="57">Ibid.
                    </note></p>
                <p>In 2013, the K67 Kiosk was also issued as a commemorative stamp from the <hi
                        rend="italic">Slovensko industrijsko oblikovanje</hi> (Slovenian Industrial
                    Design) series. On the occasion of the stamp’s presentation, a K67 Kiosk was set
                    up in the courtyard of the Museum of Architecture and Design in Ljubljana, where
                    a Post of Slovenia counter operated. The counter sold the newly issued postage
                    stamps as well as a commemorative stamp “ <hi rend="italic">K67 Kiosk – Day
                        One</hi>”.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn59" n="58">Aleksandra Zorko, »Kultni
                        kiosk K67 na poštni znamki,« <hi rend="italic">Deloindom, </hi>November 21,
                            2013, <ref
                            target="https://old.delo.si/druzba/panorama/deloindom-kultni-kiosk-k67-na-postni-znamki.html"
                            >https://old.delo.si/druzba/panorama/deloindom-kultni-kioAndresk-k67-na-postni-znamki.html</ref>.
                    </note></p>
                <p>The revival and restoration of the Kiosks are quite important for Slovenian
                    design. The retired director of the Institute for the Protection of Cultural
                    Heritage in Novo mesto decided to preserve the seven units of the abandoned K67
                    Kiosk that had made up the former <hi rend="italic">Slavček</hi> bar, which I
                    already mentioned in this article and which were, until recently, waiting for
                    better times. He persuaded several institutions to join him in the attempt to
                    save the Kiosks and negotiated a donation with their last owner. The Novo mesto
                    unit of the Institute for the Protection of Cultural Heritage provided the
                    required storage space, while the Lower Carniola Museum took on the role of the
                    recipient of the donation. The Mayor of Novo mesto also participated in the
                    coordination with the companies technically involved in the decommissioning and
                    transport. They also sought advice from Saša Janez Mächtig, the creator of the
                    K67 Kiosk, and from the private car painting and body repair company that
                    restored the K67 Kiosks now exhibited in New York, Berlin, Zurich, and
                    elsewhere. The idea is to soon reopen the renovated <hi rend="italic"
                        >Slavček</hi> bar at a suitable location in Novo mesto.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn60" n="59">Vidmar, »Slavček ni umrl, postal je
                    dediščina.«</note></p>
                <p>Currently, the industrial designer and architect Mächtig is drawing on the
                    experience with the functionally and commercially successful K67 Kiosk to design
                    the new K21 system of modular multifunctional self-service units. The new
                    generation of Kiosks is also designed in a systemic way, with modular
                    biomorphically shaped basic units derived from structures and patterns from
                    nature. Once again, the architect envisioned the individual units meeting the
                    minimum requirements of modern working and living. The new Kiosk’s use is
                    expected to be similar to that of the first and second-generation Kiosks. It
                    will be possible to use it for mobile homes, information points, small cafés,
                    retail, and other service activities. The architect envisaged that the wall
                    elements or fillings of the 21<hi rend="superscript">st</hi>-century Kiosk could
                    be designed as information displays, while solar panels could be installed on
                    the roof to ensure energy independence.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn61" n="60"
                        >Saša J. Mächtig, »Sistem Kiosk 21,« in <hi rend="italic">Sistemi, strukture, strategije</hi>, ed. Maja Vardjan, 214.</note> In February 2019, he presented the system at the <hi
                        rend="italic">Architecture Inventura 2019</hi> exhibition in the large
                    reception hall of the <hi rend="italic">Cankarjev dom</hi> cultural and congress
                    centre in Ljubljana. The Slovenian designer says his Kiosk is an example of an
                    industrial product for the people, that it has not changed over the years, and
                    that it still fulfils the purpose of providing people with the minimum
                    workplace. Progress has not tossed it aside, and the Kiosk design from the year
                    1966 has survived.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn62" n="61">Panter, »K67, kiosk,
                        ki je po 50 letih spet oživel.«</note></p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Conclusion</head>
                <p>With its flexible modular multifunctional structure, the possibility of infinite
                    expansion in countless assemblies and configurations, and its smooth plastic
                    shell, the K67 Kiosk system, designed by the Slovenian industrial designer and
                    architect Saša Janez Mächtig in 1966 as a project of prefabricated spatial
                    elements of the kiosk type for the needs of minimal commercial, labour, and
                    other service activities for the market, has become a characteristic street
                    feature characterising many urban centres, especially in Eastern Europe. As
                    micro-architecture fascinated by the introduction of new materials, it
                    challenged the social, production-technological, and market aspects of the
                    development of street furniture and became a part of the general urban culture.
                    The significant impact of the K67 Kiosk in the Slovenian territory at the time
                    of its creation was based on the connection between modular architecture and
                    urban service activities. Thanks to its open structure and multifunctionality,
                    the versatile, modularly designed K67 Kiosk was easily integrated into a variety
                    of environments.</p>
                <p>Nowadays, it appears in various roles: as an icon of the 20<hi rend="superscript"
                        >th</hi>-century industrial design and a coveted collectors’ item; an
                    artwork in museums and books; a decayed and abandoned object in the cities of
                    South-Eastern Europe; a nostalgic memory of youth and socialism; a phenomenon
                    and foundation for research and artistic projects; as well as a live organism
                    capable of constant regeneration. The hybrid architectural and industrial design
                    object has become a cult product and a part of the collective consciousness and
                    memory.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="bibliography">
                <head>Literature and Sources</head>
                <list>
                    <head>Archive sources</head>
                    <item>MNZS − Muzej novejše in sodobne zgodovine Slovenije:<list>
                            <item>Fototeka. </item>
                        </list></item>
                </list>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Literature</head>
                    <bibl>»Natečaj za stanovanjske bloke v Ljubljani.«<hi rend="italic">
                            Arhitekt</hi> 6, no. 18–19 (1956): 7.</bibl>
                    <bibl>»Za napredek naše arhitekture.« <hi rend="italic">Arhitekt</hi> 1, no. 1
                        (1951): 1.</bibl>
                    <bibl>»Za novo arhitekturo.« <hi rend="italic">Arhitekt</hi> 3, no. 8 (1953):
                        1.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Hrausky, Andrej. »Poti sodobne slovenske arhitekture.« In <hi
                            rend="italic">Slovenska kronika XX. stoletja</hi>, edited by Marjan
                        Drnovšek and Drago Bajt, 364<hi rend="italic">–</hi>366. Ljubljana: Nova
                        revija, 1997.</bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="italic">Interno študijsko gradivo za predmet Razvoj in teorija
                            oblikovanja</hi>. Ljubljana: ALUO.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Kinchin, Juliet. »Zbirka inovativnih oblikovalskih praks.« In<hi
                            rend="italic"> Sistemi, strukture, strategije</hi>, edited by Maja
                        Vardjan, 81−84. Ljubljana: Muzej za arhitekturo in oblikovanje: Akademija za
                        likovno umetnost in oblikovanje, 2016.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Leban, Pika. »Bienale industrijskega oblikovanja od ustanovitve leta 1963
                        do načrtov za prihodnost.« Thesis, Univerza v Ljubljani: Fakulteta za
                        družbene vede, 2009.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Mächtig, Saša J. »Fenomeni v urbanskem okolju.« <hi rend="italic"
                            >Kontakti</hi>, 1, 1977.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Mächtig, Saša J. »Kiosk K67, I. generacija.« In <hi rend="italic">Sistemi,
                            strukture, strategije</hi>, edited by Maja Vardjan, 102−115. Ljubljana:
                        Muzej za arhitekturo in oblikovanje: Akademija za likovno umetnost in
                        oblikovanje, 2016.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Mächtig, Saša J. »Sistem Kiosk 21.« In <hi rend="italic">Sistemi,
                            strukture, strategije</hi>, edited by Maja Vardjan, 214, 215. Ljubljana:
                        Muzej za arhitekturo in oblikovanje: Akademija za likovno umetnost in
                        oblikovanje, 2016.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Mächtig, Saša J., and Paldi, Livia. »Sistem K-67. Intervju s Sašo J.
                        Mächtigom.« In <hi rend="italic">Next Stop Kiosk = Naslednja postaja Kiosk:
                            Moderna galerija Ljubljana, 29. 10. – 30.11. 2003</hi>, 148−151.
                        Ljubljana: Moderna galerija = Modern Art Museum; Frankfurt am Main: Revolver
                        – Archiv für aktuelle Kunst, 2003.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Malačič, Janez. »Razvoj prebivalstva Slovenije v povojnem obdobju.« <hi
                            rend="italic">Teorija in praksa: družboslovna revija</hi> 22, no. 4–5
                        (1985): 402–414.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Malešič, Martina. »Arhitekta France in Marta Ivanšek.« In <hi
                            rend="italic">Arhitekturna zgodovina</hi>, 166−75. Ljubljana: Znanstvena
                        založba Filozofske fakultete, Zavod za gradbeništvo Slovenije, 2008.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Mercina, Andrej.<hi rend="italic"> Arhitekt Ilija Arnautović: Socializem v
                            slovenski arhitekturi</hi>. Ljubljana: Viharnik, 2006.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Panič, Ana. »Kiosk K67 ali blišč in beda nekega razvojnega preboja.« In
                            <hi rend="italic">Made in YU 2015</hi>, edited by Tanja Petrović and
                        Jernej Mlekuž, 154−163. Ljubljana: Založba ZRC, ZRC SAZU, 2016.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Panter, Mateja. »K67, kiosk, ki je po 50 letih spet oživel. Po evropskih
                        mestih spet srečujemo legendarni kiosk slovenskega oblikovalca in arhitekta
                        Saše Janeza Mächtiga.« <hi rend="italic">Dnevnik</hi>, July 9, 2018. <ref
                            target="https://www.dnevnik.si/1042832279"
                            >https://www.dnevnik.si/1042832279</ref>. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Potrč, Marjetica. »Kiosk je bil fenomen.« In<hi rend="italic"> Sistemi,
                            strukture, strategije</hi>, edited by Maja Vardjan, 77−80. Ljubljana:
                        Muzej za arhitekturo in oblikovanje: Akademija za likovno umetnost in
                        oblikovanje, 2016.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Rendla, Marta. »Hitro, gospodarno, po meri: sestavljivo sistemsko pohištvo
                        v socializmu.« In <hi rend="italic">Mimohod blaga. Materialna kultura
                            potrošniške družbe na Slovenskem, </hi>edited by Andrej Studen, 165−85.
                        Ljubljana: Inštitut za novejšo zgodovino, 2019.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Rendla, Marta. <hi rend="italic">»Kam ploveš standard?« Življenjska raven
                            in socializem.</hi> Ljubljana: Inštitut za novejšo zgodovino,
                        2018.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Šubic, Špela. »Oblikovalec Saša J. Mächtig.« In<hi rend="italic"> Sistemi,
                            strukture, strategije</hi>, edited by Maja Vardjan, 65−76. Ljubljana:
                        Muzej za arhitekturo in oblikovanje: Akademija za likovno umetnost in
                        oblikovanje, 2016.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Vardjan, Maja. »Metamorfoze sistema kiosk K67.« In<hi rend="italic">
                            Sistemi, strukture, strategije</hi>, edited by Maja Vardjan, 38−50.
                        Ljubljana: Muzej za arhitekturo in oblikovanje: Akademija za likovno
                        umetnost in oblikovanje, 2016.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Vidmar, Igor. »Slavček ni umrl, postal je dediščina.« <hi rend="italic"
                            >Dolenjski list</hi>, June 6, 2021. <ref
                            target="https://www.dolenjskilist.si/2021/06/13/249567/novice/dolenjska/Slavcek_ni_umrl_postal_je_dediscina/"
                            >https://www.dolenjskilist.si/2021/06/13/249567/novice/dolenjska/Slavcek_ni_umrl_postal_je_dediscina/</ref>.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Zorko, Aleksandra. »Kultni kiosk K67 na poštni znamki.« <hi rend="italic"
                            >Deloindom, </hi>November 21, 2013. <ref
                            target="https://old.delo.si/druzba/panorama/deloindom-kultni-kioAndresk-k67-na-postni-znamki.html"
                            >https://old.delo.si/druzba/panorama/deloindom-kultni-kioAndresk-k67-na-postni-znamki.html</ref>.
                    </bibl>
                </listBibl>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Website content</head>
                    <bibl>J. A. <hi rend="italic">Kultni kiosk Saše Mächtiga kraljuje sredi
                            newyorškega vrveža. RTV SLO.</hi> Accessed April 17, 2023. <ref
                            target="https://www.rtvslo.si/kultura/vizualna-umetnost/kultni-kiosk-sase-maechtiga-kraljuje-sredi-newyorskega-vrveza/487724"
                            >https://www.rtvslo.si/kultura/vizualna-umetnost/kultni-kiosk-sase-maechtiga-kraljuje-sredi-newyorskega-vrveza/487724</ref>. </bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="italic">MAO - Eta 8.</hi> Accessed May 6, 2023, <ref
                            target="https://mao.si/zbirka/eta-80/"
                            >https://mao.si/zbirka/eta-80/</ref>.</bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="italic">RTV 365</hi>, »Naslednja postaja kiosk, Saša J. Mächtig,
                        arhitekt in industrijski oblikovalec.« Accessed April 15, 2023, <ref
                            target="https://365.rtvslo.si/arhiv/dokumentarni-portret/174746857"
                            >https://365.rtvslo.si/arhiv/dokumentarni-portret/174746857</ref>.</bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="italic">Saša Maechtig, Kiosk K67, 1966</hi>. Zavod Big. Accessed
                        May 9, 2021. <ref
                            target="https://zavodbig.com/portfolio-items/sasa-maechtig-kiosk-k67-1966/"
                            >https://zavodbig.com/portfolio-items/sasa-maechtig-kiosk-k67-1966/</ref>.</bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="italic">Znameniti kiosk, ki je iz Ljutomera osvajal svet. S
                            slovitim kioskom Kiosk K67 je Ljutomer tesno povezan, saj so te
                            modularne kioske izdelovali v ljutomerskem podjetju Imgrad</hi>.
                        Accessed May 11, 2021, <ref
                            target="https://www.prlekija-on.net/lokalno/20341/znameniti-kiosk-ki-je-iz-ljutomera-osvajal-svet.html"
                            >https://www.prlekija-on.net/lokalno/20341/znameniti-kiosk-ki-je-iz-ljutomera-osvajal-svet.html</ref>.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
            <div type="summary">
                <docAuthor>Marta Rendla</docAuthor>
                <head>URBANA ULIČNA ARHITEKTURA, KIOSK K67: ENA REŠITEV ZA VSE TEŽAVE</head>
                <head>POVZETEK</head>
                <p>V prispevku avtorica na primeru oblikovalskega izdelka, kioska sistema K67, oriše
                    razvoj in vlogo urbane ulične industrijsko oblikovane arhitekture, zasnovane v
                    šestdesetih letih prejšnjega stoletja v nekdanji Jugoslaviji v času dinamičnega
                    razvoja mest in naraščajočih potreb mesta. Umetniški oblikovalski izdelek je
                    nastal po opustitvi centralno planskega socialističnega gospodarstva po
                    sovjetskem vzoru in uvedbi samoupravljanja v petdesetih letih ter njegovem
                    prehodu na gospodarstvo s poudarjenimi elementi trga v šestdesetih letih 20.
                    stoletja. Poudari, da je v okoliščinah socialistične modernizacije slovenske in
                    jugoslovanske družbe kiosk K67 slovenskega arhitekta in industrijskega
                    oblikovalca Saše Janeza Mächtiga zaradi svoje socialne funkcije v oblikovanju
                    javnega prostora in vsakdana ljudi postal brezčasen ter del kolektivne zavesti
                    in spomina državljanov nekdanje Jugoslavije.</p>
                <p>Znameniti rdeči kiosk, zasnovan v duhu poznega modernizma leta 1967, je nastal
                    kot del večjega projekta – mesta. Socialistični koncept urbanega prostora je
                    predvideval družbeno usmerjeno kolektivno gradnjo večstanovanjskih zgradb in
                    sosesk, ki naj bi generirale zavest o pripadnosti skupnosti. Ljudje so se takrat
                    navduševali nad novimi materiali in tehnologijami in v različnih geografskih in
                    kulturnih kontekstih so kot alternativa uveljavljenim načinom bivanja vznikali
                    utopični projekti. Univerzalno zasnovani in modularno sestavljivi kiosk K67 je
                    takrat mladi arhitekt projektiral za potrebe minimalnih trgovskih, delovnih in
                    drugih storitvenih dejavnosti za trg kot cestno opremo za tedanje ljubljansko
                    podjetje Magistrat. Do danes je s svojo široko uporabnostjo in večnamenskostjo
                    umeščanja različnih storitvenih dejavnosti, kot so prodajalne hitre prehrane,
                    časopisja, tobaka, vozovnic, vstopnic, cvetja, recepcije, stražarnice ipd.,
                    prehodil kompleksno pot razvoja.</p>
                <p>Do druge polovice šestdesetih let, ko je kiosk začel svoje življenje, je
                    Jugoslavija že imela za seboj povojno obnovo in izgradnjo bazične težke
                    industrije. Intenzivno se je tudi že usmerjala v razvijanje dejavnosti, ki
                    vplivajo na življenjsko raven. Slovenska družba v Jugoslaviji se je preobrazila
                    iz ruralne v industrijsko. Spremenile so se navade, vrednote, odnos do
                    materialnih dobrin, možnosti trošenja in tudi zahteve prebivalstva. Utrjevanje
                    in širjenje sodobnega urbanega življenja tudi izven urbanih okolij, povečana
                    kupna moč in dvig življenjskega standarda so spodbudili odzivanje industrijske
                    proizvodnje na potrebe trga. S pojavom množične motorizacije, razmaha medijev in
                    potrošništva se je gospodarstvo preusmerjalo v krepitev lahke industrije in
                    terciarnih dejavnosti, kot so gostinstvo, turizem, trgovina, obrt, druge
                    storitvene in stanovanjsko-komunalne dejavnosti.</p>
                <p>Kot izziv na reševanje takratnih potreb mesta se je v želji, da bi v mestu
                    dosegli višjo raven standardizacije in harmonije, rodila ideja o modularno
                    zasnovanem mobilnem kiosku- Preživel je vse do danes. V sodobni stvarnosti se
                    pojavlja v različnih vlogah: kot ikona oblikovanja 20. stoletja in zaželen
                    zbirateljski predmet, kot propadel in zapuščen objekt v mestih jugovzhodne
                    Evrope, kot nostalgičen spomin na mladost in socializem, kot fenomen in
                    izhodišče raziskovalnih in umetniških projektov ter kot živ organizem, ki je
                    sposoben nenehne regeneracije. Je na poti vstopa v novo življenje kot K21,
                    interaktivni samooskrbni večnamenski kiosk za enaindvajseto stoletje.</p>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
