<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Hour of European Truth for Slovenian Intellectuals<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn2" n="*">The research was carried out in the framework of the
                        research programme P6-0281 <hi rend="italic">Politična zgodovina</hi> [Political History], which is
                        co-financed by the Slovenian Research and Innovation Agency (ARIS) from the
                        state budget.</note></title>
                <author>
                    <forename>Marko</forename>
                    <surname>Zajc</surname>
                    <roleName>PhD</roleName>
                    <roleName>Research Counsellor</roleName>
                    <affiliation>Institut of Contemporary History</affiliation>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Privoz 11</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>SI-1000 Ljubljana</addrLine>
                    </address>
                    <email>marko.zajc@inz.si</email>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>2023-09-25</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>
                    <orgName xml:lang="sl">Inštitut za novejšo zgodovino</orgName>
                    <orgName xml:lang="en">Institute of Contemporary History</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Privoz 11</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>SI-1000 Ljubljana</addrLine>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>http://ojs.inz.si/pnz/article/view/4219</pubPlace>
                <date>2023</date>
                <availability status="free">
                    <licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title xml:lang="sl">Prispevki za novejšo zgodovino</title>
                <title xml:lang="en">Contributions to Contemporary History</title>
                <biblScope unit="volume">63</biblScope>
                <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
                <idno type="ISSN">2463-7807</idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source, born digital.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc xml:lang="en">
                <p>Contributions to Contemporary History is one of the central Slovenian scientific
                    historiographic journals, dedicated to publishing articles from the field of
                    contemporary history (the 19th and 20th century).</p>
                <p>The journal is published three times per year in Slovenian and in the following
                    foreign languages: English, German, Serbian, Croatian, Bosnian, Italian, Slovak
                    and Czech. The articles are all published with abstracts in English and
                    Slovenian as well as summaries in English.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <projectDesc xml:lang="sl">
                <p>Prispevki za novejšo zgodovino je ena osrednjih slovenskih znanstvenih
                    zgodovinopisnih revij, ki objavlja teme s področja novejše zgodovine (19. in 20.
                    stoletje).</p>
                <p>Revija izide trikrat letno v slovenskem jeziku in v naslednjih tujih jezikih:
                    angleščina, nemščina, srbščina, hrvaščina, bosanščina, italijanščina, slovaščina
                    in češčina. Članki izhajajo z izvlečki v angleščini in slovenščini ter povzetki
                    v angleščini.</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="sl"/>
                <language ident="en"/>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords xml:lang="en">
                    <term>intellectuals</term>
                    <term>Euroscepticism</term>
                    <term>EU accession</term>
                    <term>Slovenian politics</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords xml:lang="sl">
                    <term>intelektualci</term>
                    <term>evroskepticizem</term>
                    <term>približevanje EU</term>
                    <term>slovenska politika</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change><date>2023-09-26T08:52:08Z</date>
                    <name>Mihael Ojsteršek</name>
                    <desc>Pretvorba iz DOCX v TEI, dodatno kodiranje</desc>
                </change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <docAuthor>Marko Zajc<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn1" n="**"><hi rend="bold">PhD, Research Fellow,
                Institute of Contemporary History, Privoz 11, SI-1000 Ljubljana;
                <ref target="mailto:marko.zajc@inz.si">marko.zajc@inz.si</ref></hi></note></docAuthor>
            <docImprint>
                <idno type="cobissType">Cobiss tip: 1.01</idno>
                <idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.51663/pnz.63.2.04</idno>
            </docImprint>
            <div type="abstract">
                <head>IZVLEČEK</head>
                <head>URA EVROPSKE RESNICE ZA SLOVENSKE INTELEKTUALCE</head>
                <p><hi rend="italic">V prispevku avtor predstavi in analizira politično aktivnost
                        slovenskih opozicijskih intelektualcev med približevanjem Slovenije Evropski
                        uniji (obdobje 1995–97). Del intelektualcev iz kroga Nove revije je poleti
                        1997 objavil javno pismo »Ura evropske resnice za Slovenijo«, v katerem so
                        kritizirali družbene in politične razmere in slabo vladno politiko
                        približevanja EU in Natu. Podpisniki javnega pisma so tedanjo vladavino
                        liberalnodemokratske stranke (LDS), ki je bila naslednica uradne mladinske
                        organizacije v socializmu, razumeli kot nedemokratično vladavino nekdanjih
                        komunistov, ki imajo v rokah vse niti oblasti. Pri približevanju EU so
                        nasprotovali sporazumu z Italijo glede kupovanja slovenskih nepremičnin
                        (t. i. španski kompromis). Čeprav so bili načeloma za članstvo v EU, so v
                        svojem aktivizmu sodelovali tudi s skupino odkritih evroskeptikov. V prvem
                        delu prispevka avtor predstavi slovensko politiko v devetdesetih letih 20.
                        stoletja, v drugem delu na kratko opiše proces pridruževanja Slovenije EU in
                        Natu. V tretjem delu pojasni predzgodovino in delovanje obravnavane skupine
                        intelektualcev, v četrtem pa analizira javno pismo in odzive v javnosti. V
                        zaključku avtor postavi vprašanje, ali so bili omenjeni akterji
                        evroskeptiki. Po njegovem mnenju koncept evroskepticizma ne pomaga razumeti
                        kompleksnih in ambivalentnih odnosov političnih akterjev do Evrope in EU.
                        Avtor na koncu prispevka poudari trajektorijo slovenske protikomunistične
                        politične misli do sodobnosti.</hi></p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Ključne besede: intelektualci, evroskepticizem, približevanje
                        EU, slovenska politika </hi></p>
            </div>
            <div type="abstract" xml:lang="en">
                <head>ABSTRACT</head>
                <p><hi rend="italic">In this paper, the author presents and analyses the political
                        activity of Slovenian opposition intellectuals during the period of
                        Slovenia's EU accession (1995-97). In the summer of 1997, a group of
                        intellectuals from the Nova revija circle published a letter to the public
                        titled "The Hour of European Truth for Slovenia", in which they criticised
                        the social and political situation and the government's poor policy on EU
                        and NATO accession. . The signatories of the letter perceived the then rule
                        of the Liberal Democratic Party (LDS), the successor of the official youth
                        organisation under socialism, as undemocratic rule by former communists who
                        held all the strings of power. They opposed the agreement with Italy on the
                        purchase of Slovenian real estate (the so-called Spanish Compromise).
                        Although in principle they were in favour of EU membership, they also
                        collaborated in their activism with a group of outspoken Eurosceptics. In
                        the first part of the paper, the author presents Slovenian politics in the
                        1990s, while in the second part he briefly describes the process of
                        Slovenia's accession to the EU and NATO. In the third part, the author
                        describes the background and activities of the group of intellectuals in
                        question. The fourth part analyses the public letter and public reactions to
                        this. In the conclusion, the author poses the question whether the authors
                        of The Hour of European Truth were Eurosceptics. In his opinion, the concept
                        of Euroscepticism does not help us understand the complex and ambivalent
                        attitudes of political actors towards Europe and the EU. In conclusion, the
                        author highlights the trajectory of Slovenian anti-communist political
                        thought up to the present day.</hi></p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Key words: intellectuals, Euroscepticism, EU accession,
                        Slovenian politics</hi></p>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div>
                <head>Slovenian Politics after 1990</head>
                <p>When the domination of the League of Communists ended in 1990, the Slovenian
                    critical intellectuals of the late Yugoslav socialist period, known in Slovenian
                    historiography under the label of the <hi rend="italic">Nova revija</hi> circle
                    and labelled by the authorities at the time as the “bourgeois right”,<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn3" n="1">Božo Repe, <hi rend="italic">Viri o
                            demokratizaciji in osamosvojitvi Slovenije. 1. del: Opozicija in
                            oblast</hi> (Ljubljana: Arhivsko društvo Slovenije, 2002), 98. Igor
                        Omerza, <hi rend="italic">Veliki in dolgi pohod Nove revije</hi> (Celovec:
                        Mohorjeva, 2015), 112–98. </note> who had already had their time under the
                    spotlights. The winner of the first multi-party elections in 1990 was the
                    anti-communist Demos coalition, supported intellectually by the abovementioned
                    group of thinkers, many of whom went on to assume political functions. The most
                    prominent intellectuals of this circle (France Bučar, Spomenka Hribar, Dimitrij
                    Rupel) were active in the Slovenian Democratic Union within the Demos
                        coalition.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn4" n="2">Rosvita Pesek, <hi
                            rend="italic">Osamosvojitev Slovenije</hi> (Ljubljana: Nova revija,
                        2007), 113. Zdenko Čepič, »Demos prevzame oblast,« in <hi rend="italic"
                            >Slovenska novejša zgodovina. Od programa zedinjena Slovenija do
                            mednarodnega priznanja Republike Slovenije, 1848</hi>‒<hi rend="italic"
                            >1992</hi>, eds. Jasna Fischer et al. (Ljubljana: Mladinska knjiga and
                        Inštitut za novejšo zgodovino, 2005), 1290. </note> However, this period of
                    general social acceptance did not last long.</p>
                <p>Already in the immediate aftermath of the Slovenian War of Independence and the
                    three-month moratorium on Slovenian emancipation, the Demos coalition started to
                    fall apart. At the third congress of the Slovenian Democratic Union in October
                    1991, the party split into the nationalist National Democrats (who were in the
                    majority and took over the succession) and the “intellectualist” and “moderate”
                    Democratic Party. Towards the end of 1991, the Demos coalition disintegrated,
                    and the government led by the Christian Democrat Lojze Peterle struggled on
                    until 15 May 1992, when the Assembly confirmed the first government of the
                    Liberal Democrat Janez Drnovšek.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn5" n="3">Zdenko
                        Čepič, “Razpad Demosa in padec njegove vlade,” in <hi rend="italic"
                            >Slovenska novejša zgodovina</hi>, 1364. </note> The government
                    consisted of the Liberal Democrats (the successors of the socialist youth
                    organisation), the Social Democrats, the Greens and the Democrats (formerly
                    members of the Demos coalition), and the Socialists (the successors to the
                    former Socialist Alliance of Working People). The Liberal Democracy of Slovenia
                    (LDS) won the elections for the new ninety-member National Assembly on 6
                    December 1992 with a substantial lead amounting to 23 % of votes, while the
                    Slovenian Christian Democrats (SKD) came second with 15 % and the United List of
                    Social Democrats (ZLSD) third with 14 %. Janez Drnovšek, who built his own grand
                    coalition after a long negotiation with all parties in the Parliament, retained
                    the position of President of the Government. While his coalition did not include
                    all parliamentary parties, it did bring together the parties originating from
                    the former regime (LDS and ZLSD) and the parties of the former Demos coalition
                    (the Slovenian Social Democratic Party or the SDSS, the SKD, and the Greens).
                    The government was sworn in on 25 January 1993.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn6"
                        n="4">Jure Gašparič, <hi rend="italic">Slovenski parlament:
                            Politično-zgodovinski pregled od začetka prvega do konca šestega mandata
                            1992–2014</hi> (Ljubljana: Inštitut za novejšo zgodovino, 2014), <ref
                            target="http://www.sistory.si/SISTORY:ID:26950"
                            >http://www.sistory.si/SISTORY:ID:26950</ref>, Prvo mandatno obdobje – v
                        znamenju tranzicije. </note></p>
                <p>The broad coalition was based on the conviction that during the consolidation of
                    the young Slovenian state, the government needed as much support as possible,
                    especially to ensure accession to the European Union and NATO. As Tjaša Konovšek
                    points out in her contribution on the LDS party, the relationship between the
                    parties that emerged during the first mandate was complex and inconsistent, but
                    Drnovšek’s leadership of the economic recovery enjoyed relatively extensive
                    public support.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn7" n="5">Tjaša Konovšek,
                        “Formiranje Liberalne demokracije Slovenije in njene politike 1992–1996,” in
                            <hi rend="italic">Narod – politika – država: idejnopolitični značaj
                            strank na Slovenskem od konca 19. do začetka 21. stoletja</hi>, eds. Jurij
                        Perovšek and Mojca Šorn (Ljubljana: Inštitut za novejšo zgodovino,
                        2020), 276. </note> In March 1994, Drnovšek managed to consolidate the
                    liberal-democratic political option by merging the Liberal Democratic Party and
                    other smaller parties into the so-called Liberal Democracy of Slovenia (with the
                    same acronym, LDS). However, the grand coalition started to disintegrate during
                    this same period. A few days after the Liberals merged into “the first normal
                    party of post-socialism”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn8" n="6">Dejan Pušenjak,
                        “Združena LDS stavi tudi na to, da Slovenci niso prav neumni,” <hi
                            rend="italic">Delo</hi>, 14 March 1994, 2.</note> – as Slavoj Žižek, the
                    unofficial LDS ideologue, commented on the merger of the centre parties – the
                    Slovenian public was shocked by the so-called Depala vas affair. On 21 March
                    1994, members of the military Special Forces radically exceeded their powers and
                    violently arrested a police associate.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn9" n="7">
                        Miha Đ. Štamcar and Jani Sever, “Ustavite Paravomo!,” <hi rend="italic"
                            >Mladina</hi>, 22 March 1994, 1.</note> In the Parliament, the President
                    of the Government proposed the dismissal of Defence Minister Janez Janša, who
                    was objectively responsible for the incident. The affair occurred due to the
                    issue of control over the Slovenian security forces, symbolised by the dispute
                    between the President of Slovenia Milan Kučan and Defence Minister Janez Janša,
                    and the delimitation of competencies between the civilian and military spheres.
                    The debate in Parliament propelled Janša – an anti-communist social democrat
                    (previously a member of the League of Communists), publicly renowned as an
                    “emancipator” (<hi rend="italic">osamosvojitelj</hi>) – to the position of the
                    most prominent political figure of the Slovenian political right. As stated by
                    Jure Gašparič, the debate was extremely charged with political issues, with
                    speakers raising questions regarding the political past, conspiracies taking
                    place in the background, the political relations between the left and right wing
                    and reflecting on the very essence of Slovenian democracy. Loud protests in
                    support of Janša were organised in front of the Parliament and members of the
                    special police were present in the building.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn10"
                        n="8">Marko Jakopec, “Janez Janša ni več obrambni minister,” <hi
                            rend="italic">Delo</hi>, 29. March 1994, 1.</note> Interestingly, the
                    opposition voted against his dismissal and SDSS left the government coalition.
                    The government held on until the end of its mandate, albeit in tumultuous
                    circumstances. The right-wing coalition partner SKD would often support the
                    opposition in parliamentary debates, for example regarding the attitude towards
                    World War II. Due to the dismissal of the Minister of Economy from the ranks of
                    the government’s left-wing partner ZLSD, the latter was also dissatisfied with
                    Drnovšek’s coalition.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn11" n="9">Gašparič, <hi
                            rend="italic">Slovenski parlament</hi>, Prvo mandatno obdobje – v
                        znamenju tranzicije.</note>
                </p>
                <p>At the 10 November 1996 elections, LDS once again received the largest share of
                    the votes, but the Parliament still found itself in a stalemate. Forty-five
                    seats went to the right-wing parties (SDS,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn12"
                        n="10">In March 1996, the SDSS changed its name to Social Democrats of
                        Slovenia - SDS. At that time, they also left the Socialist
                        International.</note> the Slovenian People’s Party or SLS, and SKD), while
                    the remainder, including the two ethnic minority MPs that supported Drnovšek,
                    also received forty-five seats. The President of Slovenia reappointed Janez
                    Drnovšek as the formateur, and months of dramatic political upheaval followed.
                    At the beginning of January 1997, a member of the SKD switched sides to join
                    Drnovšek, who was then elected as President of the Government with a single-vote
                    advantage. However, he failed to ensure enough votes during the vote on the
                    government and the crisis continued. The political drama ended with the
                    approximation between the Liberal Democrats and the centre-right Slovenian
                    People’s Party according to the principle of “building bridges between the left
                    and the right”. In addition to LDS and SLS, the smaller Democratic Party of
                    Pensioners of Slovenia (DeSUS) also joined the government, which was sworn in on
                    24 February 1997. The coalition was very diverse. It was an alliance of two
                    ideologically and socially completely different parties, barely able to govern
                    together effectively. The situation in the National Assembly was confusing, as
                    it often seemed that SLS belonged to the opposition rather than the
                        coalition.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn13" n="11">Tjaša Konovšek,
                        “Prekletstvo številke 45: konstituiranje slovenskega državnega zbora in
                        vlade v letih 1996–1997,” <hi rend="italic">Prispevki za novejšo
                            zgodovino</hi> 60, No. 2 (2020), 168‒89.</note></p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Slovenia’s Accession to the EU and NATO</head>
                <p>Most political actors in Slovenia understood Slovenian emancipation and
                    democratisation in the context of its approach to the European Community, which
                    was simultaneously undergoing processes of accelerated integration. The
                    otherwise fragmented Slovenian political elite saw the processes of separation
                    from Yugoslavia (emancipation), the establishment of multi-party parliamentarism
                    and the introduction of the capitalist economy as compatible with the prospect
                    of the country’s accession to the EU. The EU member states recognised Slovenia
                    on 15 January 1992. On 29 January 1992, Slovenia applied for full membership of
                    the Council of Europe and was admitted on 14 May 1993. Soon after independence,
                    Slovenia established strong connections with Brussels by signing the EU-Slovenia
                    Cooperation Agreement on 5 April 1993.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn14" n="12">
                        “Slovenija v EU, Predstavništvo Evropske komisije v Sloveniji,” <hi
                            rend="italic">Časovnica Slovenije v EU</hi>, <ref
                            target="https://slovenia.representation.ec.europa.eu/o-nas/casovnica-slovenije-v-eu_sl"
                            >https://slovenia.representation.ec.europa.eu/o-nas/casovnica-slovenije-v-eu_sl</ref>,
                        accessed 1 September 2023.</note> Sloveniaִ’s greatest obstacle to EU
                    accession were its bilateral relations with Italy, burdened by a traumatic
                    history of nationalist struggles, Italian expansionism, fascism, World War II,
                    Slovenian and Croatian wartime resistance, post-war violence, minority issues
                    and border changes after World War II.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn15" n="13">
                        Milica Kacin Wohinz and Nevenka Troha (eds.), <hi rend="italic"
                            >Slovene-Italian Relations 1880‒1956: Report of the Slovene-Italian
                            Historical and Cultural Commission</hi> (Ljubljana: Nova revija, 2001),
                            <ref target="https://hdl.handle.net/11686/file25868"
                            >https://hdl.handle.net/11686/file25868</ref>. </note> The open border
                    and other issues between Yugoslavia and Italy were not resolved until as late as
                    1975 with the so-called Treaty of Osimo and 1983 with the so-called Rome
                    Agreement, which among other things, provided for compensation for nationalised
                    or confiscated property of those inhabitants of Istria who moved to Italy (the
                    so-called <hi rend="italic">optants</hi> or <hi rend="italic">ezuli</hi>) from
                    Zone B of the Free Trieste Territory.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn16" n="14">
                        Viljenka Škorjanec, <hi rend="italic">Osimska pogajanja</hi> (Koper:
                        Annales, 2007), 243–63. </note>
                </p>
                <p>At the beginning of 1992, Italy was shaken by corruption scandals involving the
                    Socialist Party (<hi rend="italic">Partito Socialista Italiano</hi>).
                    Nevertheless, on 28 June 1992, the Italian Socialists managed to form a
                    government under Giuliano Amato, which lasted ten months. During the change of
                    the neighbouring country’s government on 31 July 1992, the young Slovenian
                    diplomacy managed to reach an agreement on the succession of the 49 agreements
                    concluded between Yugoslavia and Italy.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn17" n="15">
                        Marko Kosin, “Slovenska manjšina v slovensko-italijanskih odnosih,
                        (kronološki pregled za obdobje od osamosvojitve 1991 do konca 1995),” <hi
                            rend="italic">Razprave in gradivo</hi> 33 (1998): 65.</note> Two years
                    later, another change in the Italian policy towards Slovenia was once again
                    influenced by internal political changes. Because of the corruption that came to
                    light, the once glorious Socialist Party with a century-old tradition fell
                    apart, and the new populist right took advantage of this. At the beginning of
                    May 1994, Silvio Berlusconi, the leader of the populist <hi rend="italic">Forza
                        Italia</hi> party, formed a government together with the post-fascist AN
                        (<hi rend="italic">Alleanza Nazionale</hi>, led by Gianfranco Fini) and the
                    regionalist and right-wing LN (<hi rend="italic">Lega Nord</hi>, led by Umberto
                    Bossi). The new government immediately adopted an unfriendly stance towards
                    Slovenia. While Slovenia kept paying its share of compensation for the seized
                    property within the agreed deadlines, Italy would not withdraw the relevant
                    money from the account. Nevertheless, it demanded the return of real estate in
                    kind and therefore opposed Slovenia’s accession to the EU or the conclusion of
                    the Association Agreement. Before signing the Europe Agreement on EU
                    Association, Slovenia thus faced an Italian blockade. Moreover, Article 68 of
                    the Slovenian Constitution prohibited foreigners from owning real estate in
                    Slovenia. On 10 October 1994, after lengthy negotiations with the Italian
                    Foreign Minister Antonio Martino, the Slovenian Foreign Minister in Drnovšek’s
                    government, the Christian Democrat Lojze Peterle, initialled the so-called
                    “Aquileia Declaration” in Aquileia, but the Slovenian government later withdrew
                    from it. The controversy stemmed from the fourth point of the initialled
                    Declaration, which stipulated that the Slovenian side had to establish the
                    extent of the publicly-owned real estate formerly owned by Italian citizens and
                    freeze its sale until Slovenian legislation allowed for foreign ownership.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn18" n="16">Irena Krapež, Diplomacija kot instrument zunanje politike: odnosi med Slovenijo in
                        Italijo (diplomsko delo, Filozofska fakulteta, 2009), <ref
                            target="http://dk.fdv.uni-lj.si/magistrska/pdfs/mag_krapez-irena.pdf"
                            >http://dk.fdv.uni-lj.si/magistrska/pdfs/mag_krapez-irena.pdf</ref>,
                        110.</note> The critics of the Declaration accused Peterle of naivety:
                    allegedly, the Slovenian side had foolishly agreed to preferential rights for
                    the so-called <hi rend="italic">optants</hi> with extensive consequences without
                    receiving in return an equally principled right to property that had previously
                    belonged to Slovenians and had then been expropriated during fascism.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn19" n="17">Mojca Drčar Murko, "Kazen za naivnost,"
                            <hi rend="italic">Delo</hi>, 22 October 1994, 6.</note> Peterle, who had
                    already announced his resignation as Foreign Minister before Aquileia, had to
                    defend himself in Parliament, claiming that he had not been negotiating the sale
                    of Slovenian territory. The opposition party SDSS, which profiled itself as the
                    loudest right-wing party, declared the Declaration a sell-out of Slovenian land
                    and accused the government of lacking dignity and being subservient to Italy.
                    President of the Government Drnovšek dismissed Peterle from his post as Foreign
                    Minister and temporarily took over as Minister of Foreign Affairs himself.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn20" n="18">Ana Galjot and Vilma Brodnik, “Iz
                        zgodovine vključevanja Slovenije v Evropsko unijo,” <hi rend="italic"
                            >Zgodovina v šoli</hi> 12, No. 3-4 (2004), 36-40, 37.</note>
                </p>
                <p>At the beginning of 1995, the Italian government changed yet again. The new
                    technical government of Alberto Dini was not preoccupied with securing support
                    for the next elections, and talks resumed. Seeking help in the dispute, Slovenia
                    turned to Javier Solana, the Foreign Minister of Spain, which held the EU
                    presidency in the second half of 1995. Romano Prodi’s centre-left government
                    showed more understanding towards lifting the blockade. The solution proposed by
                    Solana was named the Spanish or the Solana Compromise. Among other things, the
                    Compromise stipulated that subject to reciprocity, EU citizens who had resided
                    in Slovenia without interruption for at least three years had the right to
                    purchase real estate from the date the Agreement came into force. Slovenia also
                    committed to guaranteeing the right to buy property for all EU citizens within
                    four years of the Agreement’s entry into force (subject to reciprocity) – i.e.,
                    at the time of its associate membership and before full membership of the EU.
                    Before ratifying the Association Agreement (1997), Slovenia had to amend Article
                    68 of its Constitution accordingly.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn21" n="19">
                        Božo Cerar, “Španski kompromis,” in <hi rend="italic">Osamosvojitev,
                            Prispevki za enciklopedijo slovenske osamosvojitve, državnosti in
                            ustavnosti, </hi>ed. Dimitrij Rupel (Ljubljana: Nova univerza, 2021),
                        299.</note> In April 1996, the Slovenian Parliament adopted the Spanish
                    compromise proposal. In addition to the LDS and SKD coalition, the proposal was
                    also supported by ZLSD and the far-right Slovenian National Right (SND), while
                    SLS, the nationalist Slovenian National Party (SNS) and the Democratic Party of
                    Slovenia (DS) were against it. Interestingly, Janša’s Slovenian Democratic Party
                    (SDS) did not explicitly oppose the proposal.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn22"
                        n="20">Saša Vidmajer, “Parlament odprl pot pridruževanju k EU,” <hi
                            rend="italic">Delo</hi>, 12 April 1996, 1. </note> On 14 July 1997, the
                    Parliament adopted an amendment to the controversial Article 68 of the
                    Constitution, and the following day, it ratified the Association Agreement with
                    the EU. Slovenia became an associate member of the EU.</p>
                <p>According to Slovenian public opinion, accession to the EU enjoyed overwhelming
                    support among the Slovenian public. During the 1996 Slovenian public opinion
                    survey, respondents were asked whether Slovenia would benefit from becoming a
                    full member of the EU. 57 % answered in the affirmative, and 15.2 % in the
                    negative, whilst 27.8 % did not respond.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn23" n="21"
                        ><hi rend="italic">Vrednote v prehodu II, Slovensko javno
                            mnenje 1990‒1998</hi>, ed. Niko Toš (Ljubljana: Fakulteta za družbene vede, 2021),
                            <ref
                            target="https://www.cjm.si/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/VREDNOTE-2-WEB.pdf"
                            >https://www.cjm.si/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/VREDNOTE-2-WEB.pdf</ref>.</note>
                    The relationship between the public and NATO was more complicated. In the 1991
                    Slovenian public opinion survey, respondents were asked what they believed would
                    be the best foreign policy for Slovenia in the future. Most respondents – 44.1%
                    – chose Western Europe, 39.1 % supported neutrality, while only 4.4 % opted for
                    NATO and the United States. Similar results regarding the same question were
                    established in 1992, while 8.5 % chose NATO and the USA in 1993 and 9.4 % in
                    1994. In 1994, the public opinion survey also asked people about the country’s
                    security policy. When asked whether they supported NATO membership, the majority
                    of respondents – 44.2 – answered yes, 32.7 % neither opposed nor supported the
                    idea, only 8.6 respondents opposed NATO membership, while 14.6 % could not
                    decide. However, in 1996, as many as 55.4 % of respondents were in favour of
                    NATO membership.</p>
                <p>According to opinion polls, the support for NATO membership gradually increased,
                    but it never reached the same level of support as full EU membership. During
                    this period, most parliamentary parties supported NATO accession (with the
                    exception of the nationalist SNS). The political will to bring Slovenia closer
                    to NATO was first clearly stated in the amendments to the Resolution on the
                    National Security Strategy of the Republic of Slovenia, adopted by the National
                    Assembly in January 1994. Based on the relevant decision of the Slovenian
                    Parliament, on 30 March 1994, Slovenia was among the first to join the
                    Partnership for Peace (PfP) and became an Associate Partner of the North
                    Atlantic Assembly (NAA) in the same year. At the end of January 1996, Slovenia
                    became a full member of the North Atlantic Cooperation Council (NACC). The
                    political decision in favour of NATO membership was unequivocally expressed in
                    the Decision of the National Assembly, adopted on 11 April 1996, which states
                    that “the Republic of Slovenia wishes to guarantee its fundamental security
                    interests within the framework of the collective defence system made possible by
                    NATO membership”.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn24" n="22">“Slovenija v Natu,”
                            <hi rend="italic">gov.si</hi>, <ref
                            target="https://www.gov.si/teme/slovenija-v-natu/"
                            >https://www.gov.si/teme/slovenija-v-natu/</ref>, accessed 20 August
                        2023.</note> Although in June 1997, all political parties supported
                    accession to the North Atlantic Alliance with the Parliamentary Declaration on
                    NATO Accession, the administration of US President Bill Clinton decided not to
                    support Slovenia’s immediate entry into NATO. Thus, only Poland, the Czech
                    Republic and Hungary joined NATO in July 1997.</p>
                <p>A consultative referendum on Slovenia’s accession to the EU and NATO was held on
                    23 March 2003. 60.44 % of eligible voters participated in the EU referendum.
                    89.64 % of these were in favour of the EU, while only 10.36 % voted against
                        it.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn25" n="23">“Poročilo o izidu glasovanja in
                        izidu referenduma o pristopu Republike Slovenije k Evropski uniji, ki je bil
                        23. marca 2003,” <hi rend="italic">Državna volilna komisija</hi>, <ref
                            target="https://www.dvk-rs.si/fileadmin/user_upload/dokumenti/volitve/referendum_2003_1/porocilo-o-referendumu-EU.pdf"
                            >https://www.dvk-rs.si/fileadmin/user_upload/dokumenti/volitve/referendum_2003_1/porocilo-o-referendumu-EU.pdf</ref>.
                    </note> On the other hand, 60.43 % of eligible voters took part in the
                    referendum on NATO accession, but only two thirds (66.08 %) supported it, while
                    one third (33.92 %) were against it.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn26" n="24">
                        “Poročilo o izidu glasovanja in izidu referenduma o pristopu Republike
                        Slovenije k Organizaciji severnoatlantske pogodbe (NATO), ki je bil 23.
                        marca 2003,” <hi rend="italic">Državna volilna komisija</hi>, <ref
                            target="https://www.dvk-rs.si/fileadmin/user_upload/dokumenti/volitve/referendum_2003_1/porocilo-o-referendumu-NATO.pdf"
                            >https://www.dvk-rs.si/fileadmin/user_upload/dokumenti/volitve/referendum_2003_1/porocilo-o-referendumu-NATO.pdf</ref>.
                    </note> Slovenia became a full member of NATO on 24 February 2004, when the
                    Parliament ratified the North Atlantic Treaty. Slovenia became a full EU member
                    on 1 May 2004, when as many as ten countries joined the European Union during
                    its most extensive enlargement in history.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Pro-European Eurosceptics?</head>
                <p>The <hi rend="italic">Nova revija</hi> magazine was founded in 1982 by the
                    middle-generation opposition intellectuals and culture professionals. The
                    contemporaneous communist authorities in Slovenia allowed and financed the
                    establishment of the magazine but simultaneously monitored its contributors.
                    People joined the circle of the <hi rend="italic">Nova revija</hi> magazine in
                    various ways.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn27" n="25">Omerza, <hi rend="italic"
                            >Veliki in dolgi pohod Nove revije, </hi>112.</note> The core consisted
                    of intellectuals also known as the critical generation, who had previously
                    contributed to two cultural magazines in the 1950s and 1960s: <hi rend="italic"
                        >Revija 57</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Perspektive</hi>.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn28" n="26">Božo Repe, <hi rend="italic">Obračun s
                            Perspektivami</hi> (Ljubljana: Znanstveno in publicistično središče,
                        1990).</note> The authorities abolished both, the former in 1958 and the
                    latter in 1964. As elsewhere in Central Eastern Europe, the “normalisation” of
                    culture in relation to the West represented one of the crucial demands of the
                    reformist intellectual circles. In addition to existentialism, the critical
                    generation reflected on the phenomenological tradition, especially Heidegger’s
                    philosophy. Heidegger represented a major influence on Dušan Pirjevec (deceased
                    1977), a philosopher, comparativist and prominent intellectual of the Partisan
                    generation who oscillated between the status of regime intellectual and the role
                    of dissident.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn29" n="27">Balázs Trencsényi, Michal
                        Kopeček, Luka Lisjak Gabrijelčič, Maria Falina, Monika Baár and Maciej
                        Janowski, <hi rend="italic">A History of Modern Political Thought in East
                            Central Europe. Vol. 2, Negotiating Modernity in the Short Twentieth
                            Century and Beyond. Pt. 1, 1918‒1968</hi> (New York: Oxford University
                        Press, 2018), 401. Jure Ramšak<hi rend="italic">, (Samo)upravljanje
                            intelekta, Družbena kritika v poznosocialistični Sloveniji</hi>
                        (Ljubljana: Modrijan, 2019), 89‒92.</note> After Pirjevec’s death, his
                    tradition was continued by the philosophers of the phenomenological orientation,
                    Tine Hribar and Ivo Urbančič, as well as by Dimitrij Rupel, the sociologist of
                    culture and comparativist. In addition to the culture professionals and
                    philosophers who based their critique of society on Pirjevec’s theses, the legal
                    and social theorists who formulated a critical outlook based on Luhmann and
                    Habermas’s theories of society also found their way into the circle of the <hi
                        rend="italic">Nova revija</hi> magazine. The most renowned representatives
                    of this trend were France Bučar and Jože Pučnik who was imprisoned twice for his
                    critical writing and later emigrated to Germany where he lectured on
                        sociology.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn30" n="28">Rosvita Pesek, “Jože
                        Pučnik - dlje kot drugi,” <hi rend="italic">Studia Historica Slovenica</hi>
                        11, No. 2/3 (2011): 439‒62.</note> Another prominent group consisted of
                    established but non-conformist poets and writers, e.g., Drago Jančar, Niko
                    Grafenauer, Dane Zajc and Boris A. Novak. Although most of the intellectuals
                    involved were men, the magazine was also co-created by a few influential women.
                    The most well-known woman intellectual of the <hi rend="italic">Nova revija</hi>
                    magazine circle being sociologist Spomenka Hribar, who developed social critique
                    through her attitude towards the more traumatic episodes of contemporary history
                    using the concept of national reconciliation.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn31"
                        n="29">Spomenka Hribar, “Krivda in greh,” in <hi
                            rend="italic">Kocbekov Zbornik</hi>, ed. Dimitrij Rupel (Maribor: Obzorja, 1987), 61.</note>
                    In the second half of the 1980s, the <hi rend="italic">Nova revija</hi> circle
                    intensified their opposition activities. After the dispute with the Serbian
                    cultural opposition in 1985 over the future of Yugoslavia, this group of
                    opposition intellectuals entered the political arena by publishing the 57 <hi
                        rend="superscript">th</hi> issue of <hi rend="italic">Nova revija</hi>
                    (Contributions to the Slovenian National Programme), where they demanded greater
                    independence for Slovenia, the abolition of the communist monopoly and a free
                        economy.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn32" n="30">Aleš Gabrič, "Zaostrenost
                        mednacionanih odnosov," in <hi rend="italic">Slovenska novejša
                            zgodovina</hi>, 1171.</note> Between 1989 and 1990, they were
                    enthusiastically involved in the formation of opposition parties (notably the
                    Slovenian Democratic Union, headed by Dimitrij Rupel) and the Demos coalition.
                    After the first multi-party elections in the spring of 1990, many members of
                    this circle assumed important political functions. France Bučar became the
                    Speaker of Parliament, Dimitrij Rupel the Minister of Foreign Affairs and
                    Spomenka Hribar a Member of Parliament.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn33" n="31"
                        >Zdenko Čepič, “Demos prevzame oblast,” in <hi rend="italic">Slovenska
                            novejša zgodovina</hi>, 1290. </note> During this period, the newspaper
                    publishing company <hi rend="italic">Nova revija</hi> was established, which
                    carried out major publishing projects in addition to publishing the eponymous
                    magazine in the 1990s. During the economic crisis of 2008–10, the company ran
                    into financial difficulties. The final issue of the magazine was published in
                    2010 and the company filed for bankruptcy in 2014.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn34" n="32">“Nova revija v stečaju: prodaja ustanoviteljske
                        pravice Inštituta Nove revije,” <hi rend="italic">Dnevnik</hi>, 17 May 2014,
                            <ref target="https://www.dnevnik.si/1042659861"
                            >https://www.dnevnik.si/1042659861</ref>, accessed 20 August
                        2023.</note>
                </p>
                <p>Following Slovenian independence, the political and worldview differences between
                    the former members of the <hi rend="italic">Nova revija</hi> intellectual circle
                    became apparent. Dimitrij Rupel established himself as an active member of the
                    ruling LDS party and was elected Mayor of Ljubljana in 1994.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn35" n="33">Jana Taškar, “Dr. Rupel je ljubljanski župan,” <hi
                            rend="italic">Delo</hi>, 19 December 1994, 1. </note> On 18 April 1992,
                    Spomenka Hribar published an article titled <hi rend="italic">Ustavimo
                        desnico</hi> (Stop the Right), in which she cautioned against the excessive
                    advance of the right wing, which – among other things – was detrimental to the
                    process of national reconciliation.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn36" n="34">
                        Spomenka Hribar, “Ustavimo desnico,” <hi rend="italic">Sobotna priloga</hi>,
                        18 April 1992, 24, 25.</note> Following this, Spomenka Hribar was labelled a
                    leftist by the political right. In the period of Drnovšek’s governments
                    (1992–2000), the majority of the <hi rend="italic">Nova revija</hi> circle moved
                    closer to the contemporaneous political right. The opposition at the time was
                    associated with the <hi rend="italic">Nova revija</hi> circle due to its
                    conviction that the former communist elite remained in power, obstructed the
                    transition to true democracy and a “fair” economy, and controlled the media and
                    cultural policy. Although they accepted the thesis of the “communist continuity”
                    and sympathised with the right-wing opposition, the renowned members of the <hi
                        rend="italic">Nova revija</hi> circle considered themselves free-thinking
                    and cosmopolitan intellectuals who respected diversity, human rights and liberal
                    democracy (e.g., Drago Jančar, France Bučar).<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn37"
                        n="35">Drago Jančar, “Egiptovski lonci mesa,”<hi rend="italic">Sobotna
                            priloga</hi>, 1. 10. 1994, 30.</note></p>
                <p>The European orientation was not an issue for the <hi rend="italic">Nova
                        revija</hi> intellectuals, although they had a negative opinion of the
                    Slovenian approach to the EU. The European Union of the contemporary political
                    and economic reality was not Europe according to the concepts of the former
                    dissident intellectuals. The dissonance between the ideal and the political
                    reality was particularly acute in the spring of 1996 during parliamentary
                    debates on the “Spanish Compromise”. In the Parliament, France Bučar, who was an
                    opposition MP of the Democratic Party during this period, pointed out that the
                    government’s insistence on EU accession was paranoid, while in his opinion, the
                    Spanish proposal actually represented a compromise with the Italians. “Our
                    country’s agreement to it will be a mutilation of Slovenian identity,” Bučar
                    declared dramatically in the National Assembly on 2 April 1996.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn38" n="36">Urša Izgoršek, “Španski predlog na
                        prepihu razprave v Državnem zboru”, <hi rend="italic">Delo</hi>, 3 April
                        1996, 2.</note> During the same period, an initiative called <hi
                        rend="italic">Gibanje 23. december</hi> (the 23 December Movement) emerged,
                    warning MPs not to vote against the Constitution and threatening a
                    constitutional dispute.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn39" n="37">N. R.,
                        “Opozorilo poslancem državnega zbora,” Delo, 10 April 1996, 2.</note> While
                    the 23 December Movement, led by dentist Borut Korun, remained on the margins of
                    the political arena (together with SNS), it was Slovenia’s most visible
                    Eurosceptic initiative. In the publication titled <hi rend="italic">Danes
                        Slovenija in nikdar več?</hi> (Slovenia Today and Never Again), published at
                    the beginning of 1997, the Movement released a statement in which it strongly
                    opposed the Republic of Slovenia’s accession to the EU, as it would result in a
                    land sell-out, economic disaster and the death of the nation. The 23 December
                    Movement supported a politically independent and neutral Republic of
                        Slovenia.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn40" n="38">“Izjava Gibanja 23.
                        December,” in <hi rend="italic">Danes Slovenija in nikdar več?,</hi> ed. Borut
                        Korun (Velenje: self-published, 1997), 194. </note> The Movement
                    maintained good relations with the <hi rend="italic">Nova revija</hi> circle, as
                    the abovementioned publication also included contributions written by France
                    Bučar and Tone Jerovšek, who might not have shared the Movement’s entirely
                    negative views on the EU but nevertheless strongly opposed the “Spanish
                    Compromise”. In his contribution, France Bučar underlined that Slovenia had
                    agreed to give Italians a four-year pre-emptive right to buy real estate before
                    other foreign nationals. While the Compromise stipulated that all EU citizens
                    who had resided in Slovenia for at least three years would enjoy the same
                    rights, according to Bučar, Italians almost exclusively met these criteria.
                    According to him, to agree to the Compromise was to accept the opinion that
                    Slovenia was in the Italian sphere of interest and a semi-colonial state. How to
                    proceed? A sound legal and political strategy for accession to the EU should be
                    drawn up, and above all, not everyone who called for sober reflection should be
                    branded a Eurosceptic.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn41" n="39">France Bučar,
                        “Kako naprej,” in <hi rend="italic">Danes Slovenija in nikdar več?</hi>, 194.</note></p>
                <p>The cooperation between the <hi rend="italic">Nova revija</hi> circle and the 23
                    December Movement culminated in April and May 1997, when Slovenian politics was
                    preparing to amend the Constitution and ratify the Association Agreement. The 23
                    December Movement submitted an initiative for a preliminary legislative
                    referendum on the ratification of the EU Association Agreement. France Bučar was
                    among those who signed the referendum initiative. Fortunately for the
                    government, the Parliament’s legal advisors determined that the referendum
                    initiative had not been submitted correctly, so the planned vote on the
                    constitutional amendment was not jeopardised.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn42"
                        n="40">Mateja Babič, “Pobuda za referendum ni bila vložena pravilno,” <hi
                            rend="italic">Delo</hi>, 9 May 1997, 1.</note> Moreover, a group of 38
                    intellectuals, mainly from the <hi rend="italic">Nova revija</hi> circle, wrote
                    a public letter stating that the Parliament could only ratify the Association
                    Agreement between Slovenia and the EU without the annex containing the “Spanish
                    Compromise”, as the latter was supposedly contrary to the Constitution. They
                    stated that they supported Slovenia’s accession to the EU but that the imposed
                    “Spanish Compromise” negated the very purpose of joining. The signatories were
                    clear: they pointed out that joining under such conditions turned Slovenia into
                    a protectorate and denied the purpose of its independence. In short: first a
                    referendum, then a constitutional amendment and only then ratification of the
                        Agreement.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn43" n="41">Marko Jakopec and
                        Vladimir Vodušek, “DZ lahko ratificira sporazum o pridružitvi samo brez
                        aneksa,” <hi rend="italic">Delo</hi>, 9 May 1997, 2. </note> The
                    commentators of <hi rend="italic">Delo</hi> newspaper, who supported the
                    government policy, described the initiators of the referendum and the
                    signatories of the above statement as Eurosceptics. The journalist Gorazd Bohte
                    declared: “It is ironic and paradoxical that the very group that prides itself
                    on the plebiscite is now striving to prevent what we decided in 1990.”<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn44" n="42">Gorazd Bohte, “Evroskeptiki po
                        slovensko,” <hi rend="italic">Delo</hi>, 9 May 1997, 2.</note> Vladimir
                    Vodušek commented that the initiators of the referendum and the circle of the
                        <hi rend="italic">Nova revija</hi> magazine had embarrassed the government
                    party SLS, as well as the opposition (SDS and SKD). While this circle
                    represented intellectual support for these parties, the leaders of the
                    right-wing parliamentary parties, on the other hand, could not afford to speak
                    out against the ratification and EU membership.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn45"
                        n="43">Vladimir Vodušek, “Španski jezdeci in španski borci,” <hi
                            rend="italic">Delo</hi>, 10 May 1997, 3.</note>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>The European Hour</head>
                <p>The early summer of 1997 was critical for Slovenian foreign policy. On 7 July
                    1997, Italian President Luigi Scalfaro visited Slovenia, confirming Italy’s
                    support for Slovenian entry into the EU.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn46" n="44"
                        > Saša Vidmajer, “Prvi obisk italijanskega predsednika v Sloveniji,” <hi
                            rend="italic">Delo</hi>, 8 July 1997, 1. </note> On 8 July 1997, the
                    first NATO summit since 1994 was held in Madrid. It was also attended by the
                    President of the Government Drnovšek and Foreign Minister Zoran Thaler. Slovenia
                    was not invited to the first round of enlargement. Although there was unofficial
                    talk of only three countries being invited, the other candidates remained
                    hopeful, as the final decision was not adopted until after prolonged
                        negotiations.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn47" n="45">Stojan Žitko, “Vrh je
                        v prvi širitveni krog Nata soglasno povabil samo tri države,” <hi
                            rend="italic">Delo</hi>, 9 July 1997, 1. </note> The foreign political
                    cold shower coincided with a meeting of the Parliament’s Constitutional
                    Commission, which discussed amendment of Article 68 of the Constitution in view
                    of the EU Association Agreement. Although the opposition agreed to amend the
                    constitutional article, there were still differences with regard to its wording
                    and the necessary quorum in Parliament.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn48" n="46">
                        Jana Taškar, “Ustavna komisija odločila, zdaj je na vrsti Državni zbor,” <hi
                            rend="italic">Delo</hi>, 10 July 1997, 2. </note> Nevertheless, the
                    National Assembly adopted the constitutional amendment with a large majority on
                    14 July. However, the opposition’s affirmative vote did not mean it supported
                    the government’s policy. The SDS leader Janez Janša explained the opposition’s
                    dilemma very clearly. According to him, Slovenia faced two bad choices: it had
                    to decide whether to join the EU under discriminatory conditions or exclude
                    itself from the first round of EU membership candidates by not adapting its
                    legislation. The fault, of course, lay with the government, which lacked a
                    suitable foreign policy strategy. Meanwhile, Lojze Peterle, the former Minister
                    of Foreign Affairs and leader of the opposition SKD party, regretted that “his”
                    Aquileia Agreement, which had allegedly been more favourable for Slovenia, had
                    not been adopted.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn49" n="47">Marko Jakopec, “Večina
                        poslanskih skupin je podpirala spremembe ustave,” <hi rend="italic"
                            >Delo</hi>, 15 July 1997, 2. </note> On the following day, the EU
                    Association Agreement ratification was put to a vote. Of the 85 MPs present, 70
                    voted in favour of the Agreement. The opposition underlined the differences
                    compared to the Agreements of other Associate Members. By doing so it attempted
                    to highlight the government’s inferior and submissive foreign policy while at
                    the same time presenting support for the ratification as a constructive stance –
                    or, moreover, as a solution to the misguided policies of Drnovšek’s
                        government.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn50" n="48">Matjaž Albreht, “Še ena
                        vroča izredna seja o pridružitvenem sporazumu,” <hi rend="italic">Delo</hi>,
                        16 July 1997, 2. </note>
                </p>
                <p>The political developments of July 1997 embarrassed both the government and the
                    opposition. The government parties showed considerable originality in convincing
                    the public that Slovenia’s exclusion from the first round of NATO enlargement
                    was not a foreign policy failure. On the other hand, the opposition had to come
                    up with awkward explanations why it kept voting in favour of the constitutional
                    changes it disagreed with. In such a political climate, 31 intellectuals<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn51" n="49">Signed by the following intellectuals:
                        Drago Jančar, Angelos Baš, Aleš Berger, Janez Bernik, Viktor Blažič,
                        Katarina Bogataj Gradišnik, France Bučar, Drago Demšar, Stane Gabrovec,
                        Kajetan Gantar, Janez Gradišnik, Niko Grafenauer, Andrej Hieng, Andrej
                        Inkret, Milček Komelj, Lojze Kovačič, Edvard Kovač, Lojze Lebič, Joža
                        Mahnič, Saša Markovič, Janez Pogačnik, Jože Pučnik, Primož Simoniti,
                        Jaroslav Skrušny, Jože Snoj, Rudi Šeligo, Alojz Šuštar, Drago Tršar, Ivan
                        Urbančič, Dane Zajc, Aleksander Zorn.</note> gathered around the <hi
                        rend="italic">Nova revija</hi> magazine addressed an open letter of more
                    than 14 pages to the public, titled “The Hour of European Truth for
                    Slovenia”.</p>
                <p>The signatories saw Slovenian reality most grimly: “We, the undersigned Slovenian
                    intellectuals, artists and scientists – /…/ –with regret conclude that Slovenia,
                    seven years after the first democratic elections, is increasingly lagging behind
                    European cultural and democratic standards. The ever-clearer distancing of
                    Slovenia from the circle of countries which are ready for acceptance into the
                    European integration is primarily the result of the fact that the internal life
                    of our state is becoming less and less dynamic, more and more channelled into
                    old frameworks, and consequently development is blocked.” They pointed out “the
                    painful process of the Slovenian accession to NATO” and “the uncertain prospects
                    for full membership of the European Union.” Supposedly, this was a warning that
                    Slovenians should no longer ignore.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn52" n="50">
                        Drago Jančar, France Bučar, Niko Grafenauer, Jože Pučnik, Primož Simoniti,
                        Jože Snoj, Rudi Šeligo and Ivan Urbančič, <hi rend="italic">Ura evropske
                            resnice za Slovenijo / The Hour of European Truth for Slovenia</hi>
                        (Ljubljana: Nova revija, 1997), 33.</note></p>
                <p>The authors of the open letter claimed that Slovenia was ruled by a “continuity”
                    of the former communist regime. “Almost all the centres of power are occupied by
                    people whose way of thinking and methods of governing have been shaped by the
                    one-party system.” Privatisation had been poorly implemented, while
                    denationalisation of assets once nationalised by the communist regime had been
                    too slow. The former Party officials had become the new owners of companies and
                    various speculators had seized new business opportunities. Furthermore, workers
                    were not protected. The trade unions of the former regime were linked to the
                    government and did not protect workers, while the authorities obstructed the new
                    unions. The media were secretly controlled and manipulated by the government.
                    Because of post-communist continuity, true pluralisation of media space was
                    impossible This problem was revealed in all its drastic post-communist
                    dimensions during the NATO accession negotiations. After the USA had reacted
                    negatively to Slovenia’s NATO membership bid, some magazines – following the
                    President’s response – strived to portray the decision as irrational or as a
                    result of the Russia-US conflicts, while some of the press even allegedly
                    crossed all the lines of proper journalistic reporting and fundamental culture.
                    Although Slovenian culture represented the essence of the Slovenian nation, it
                    had not flourished since the attainment of independence but had instead been
                    pushed to the periphery by the authorities. Culture had no influence on society.
                    The attitude towards the communist past was also problematic: instead of
                    condemning communist crimes, the deliberate falsification of history continued.
                    This reinforced the ideological and political continuity of the former regime,
                    which the Slovenian Parliament needed to condemn.</p>
                <p>The public letter devoted much attention to the EU accession process. The
                    negotiations on Slovenian accession were supposedly led by incompetent people.
                    The government did not know how to apply the principles of European diplomacy
                    (consistent negotiations defending Slovenia’s interests) and instead resorted to
                    “Balkan double-dealing, amateurish improvisation and misleading assurances”.
                    Slovenia was expected to meet conditions unlike any other EU Associate Member
                    State. “These conditions are contained in what is now finally known as the
                    ‘Spanish compromise’, which for a long time was hidden by the government from
                    the public. Following this compromise, Slovenia has been relegated to an
                    exceptionally subordinate position. /…/ The government – through its
                    incompetence, vacillation, concealment and manipulation of the media – has led
                    us into a situation in which we must face the actual fact that none of the
                    solutions will be good for Slovenia.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn53" n="51">
                        Ibidem, 53.</note>
                </p>
                <p>The document was presented to the public on 9 July, the day when NATO leaders
                    rejected Slovenia’s request.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn54" n="52">C. R.,
                        “Odprto pismo intelektualcev,” <hi rend="italic">Delo</hi>, 10 July 1997, 1.
                    </note> On 18 July, a public presentation was organised after the Constitution
                    had been amended and the Association Agreement ratified. “There is no doubt
                    whether we are entering Europe or not because we are already in Europe and have
                    always been in Europe,” stated Niko Grafenauer, President of the <hi
                        rend="italic">Nova revija</hi> Club. According to a <hi rend="italic"
                        >Delo</hi> journalist, the presentation was attended by many intellectuals
                    and prominent politicians. Janez Janša, the leader of the opposition party SDS,
                    was received with particular respect and a representative of the centre-right
                    governmental SLS was also present. The journalist underlined the bombastic words
                    of the speakers about the danger of Slovenia becoming a northern Sicily, while
                    some people observed that the entire situation was reminiscent of Bolshevism and
                    fascism. A barrage of harsh criticism was hurled at the press, especially <hi
                        rend="italic">Delo</hi> newspaper, supposedly just a humble servant of the
                    ruling regime.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn55" n="53">Mateja Babič, “Trenutek
                        prigriznjenih idej,” <hi rend="italic">Delo</hi>, 19 July 1997, 2.</note>
                </p>
                <p>Boris Jež, a commentator of the most influential newspaper <hi rend="italic"
                        >Delo</hi>, described the public letter written by the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Nova revija</hi> circle as an “eruption of reason”, which in his opinion,
                    had certainly been provoked by the rejection of Slovenia on its path towards
                    NATO. However, Jež ironically stated: “Of course, the cream of the nation’s
                    intelligentsia will refuse to admit that it is descending into the trivialities
                    of daily political commentary.” Jež firmly rejected the signatories’ dramatic
                    thesis that everything in Slovenia was wrong. While he admitted that many things
                    were indeed wrong, he also wondered what the signatories of the open letter –
                    who were exceedingly influential in society and in some cases had also held
                    important functions in recent years– had actually done to remedy the situation.
                    Jež pointed out that the sculptor Drago Tršar was also among the signatories –
                    the one and the same who had, under communism, erected a monument to the
                    socialist revolution in front of the Parliament. Instead of educating Slovenians
                    about their history, Tršar should give back the fees he had received for the
                    monuments from the former regime, Jež stated rather harshly.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn56" n="54">Boris Jež, “Izbruh razuma,” <hi rend="italic"
                            >Delo</hi>, 11 July 1997, 3.</note></p>
                <p>Among the responses to The Hour of European Truth, the reactions of two former
                    members of the <hi rend="italic">Nova revija</hi> circle, Dimitrij Rupel and
                    Veljko Rus, were the most interesting. Rupel was very critical of his
                    colleagues. He noted that the initiators of the 23 December Movement, which
                    opposed Slovenia’s full EU membership, were among the signatories. In his
                    opinion, SDS and Janez Janša were usually behind these groups. These people were
                    convinced that Slovenia and especially their group were European enough on their
                    own and that Slovenia would finally be completely Europeanised once it
                    recognised this group’s authority and power. Rupel argued that in listing the
                    faults of Slovenian society, the authors of the open letter had deliberately
                    neglected to mention the indecencies committed by the adherents of the
                    right-wing parties. He found the denigration of the media – the fourth branch of
                    power in democratic societies – unjustified and unusual, convinced that the main
                    purpose of the open letter was to encourage resistance towards Europe. Rupel
                    believed that the potential exclusion of Slovenia from Europe would not mean
                    preserving traditional Slovenian values but rather mass emigration and
                        assimilation.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn57" n="55">Dimitrij Rupel, “Urica
                        domačih resnic,” <hi rend="italic">Sobotna priloga</hi>, 19 July 1997, 38.
                    </note> Meanwhile, Veljko Rus defined the European Hour of Truth as an
                    “anti-communist manifesto”. He found that the signatories believed that all
                    problems stemmed from the assumption that the former Party members still pulled
                    all the strings of social development. Only a single therapy fit this diagnosis:
                    removing all the representatives of the continuity. However, who were these
                    people, really? It was obvious that they were not only members of left-wing
                    parties, as the former communist personnel were scattered throughout the
                    political landscape. How could this removal be achieved? Certainly not
                    democratically. According to Rus, a spontaneous rotation of the elites would
                    supposedly solve these problems. In his opinion, the analysis “according to
                    which Slovenia’s main problem consists of the ‘representatives of the
                    continuity’ is more than irrational and completely unproductive.”<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn58" n="56">Veljko Rus, “Antikomunistični manifest,”
                            <hi rend="italic">Sobotna priloga</hi>, 26 July 1997, 30. </note></p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Conclusion</head>
                <p>Were the signatories of The Hour of European Truth Eurosceptics? If we consider
                    the basic literature on the phenomenon of Euroscepticism, we can at least
                    conclude that the question is incorrect. The theorists and historians of
                    Euroscepticism agree that this is a political concept that can only be
                    understood in the proper social and historical context. The editors of <hi
                        rend="italic">The Routledge Handbook of Euroscepticism (</hi>2018) identify
                    three crucial problems regarding the notion of Euroscepticism: 1. the term was
                    coined by non-academics using academic jargon; 2. Euroscepticism is ultimately a
                    negative construction and in its simplest form, it means opposition to some
                    aspects of European integration; 3. the term’s genesis draws attention to
                    temporal and geographical particularities.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn59"
                        n="57">Benjamin Leruth, Nicholas Startin, and Simon Usherwood, “Defining
                        Euroscepticism, From a broad concept to a field of study,” in <hi
                            rend="italic">The Routledge Handbook of Euroscepticism</hi>, eds. Benjamin
                        Leruth, Nicholas Startin, and Simon McDougall Usherwood, (London:
                        Routledge, 2018), 4. </note> Euroscepticism varies considerably in whether
                    it assumes soft or hard forms. It also differs in terms of its role in the
                    Member States’ political history. The expression “Euroscepticism” may only
                    pertain to the EU or represent an overall condemnation of the European ideal.
                    Attempts to historicise and compare various facets of Euroscepticism are still
                        rare.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn60" n="58">Mark Gilbert and Daniele
                        Pasquinucci, “Introduction,” in 
                            <hi rend="italic">Euroscepticisms: The Historical Roots of a Political
                            Challenge</hi>, eds. Mark Gilbert and Daniele Pasquinucci (Leiden and Boston: Brill 2020), 1–9.</note>
                </p>
                <p>Given the ambivalent political position of the <hi rend="italic">Nova revija</hi>
                    circle regarding EU accession, a brief analysis of the use of the term Europe in
                    the open letter in question is undoubtedly warranted. Where is Europe? The
                    authors defined Europe as the very place where Slovenia must be included (the
                    road to Europe). However, Europe has always been “here”. The authors were
                    convinced of the ontological European nature of Slovenia. As they stated,
                    Slovenia was supposed to be “in its originality European from the very
                    beginning”. What is Europe? We can identify four “aggregate states” of Europe:
                    a) the ideal society (“the highest European cultural, ethical, political, legal
                    and economic standards in public life”); b) the protector of Slovenian identity,
                    which will safeguard the Slovenian nation from the imperialism of superpowers;
                    c) Europe as the “anti-Balkan”, the negation of all that is “Balkan”; d) Europe
                    as seen as the opposite of communism, which is why Slovenia will not become
                    European until it condemns the former communist regime.</p>
                <p>Presently (2023), the ideology of the “communist continuity” is defended and
                    developed by the SDS party, which has, under the leadership of Janez Janša (the
                    party’s leader since 1993), evolved from a non-communist social democracy
                    through a centre-right conservative party to a right-wing populist party, yet it
                    remains within the framework of the European People’s Party.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn61" n="59">Jurij Hadalin, “Kaj bi rekel Henrik Tuma? Od
                        Socialdemokratske stranke Slovenije do Slovenske demokratske stranke,” <hi
                            rend="italic">Prispevki za novejšo zgodovino</hi> 61, No. 3 (2021),
                        237–61, <ref target="https://doi.org/10.51663/pnz.61.3.10"
                            >https://doi.org/10.51663/pnz.61.3.10</ref>. </note> A great deal has
                    happened since 1997. Many of the signatories of the Declaration have distanced
                    themselves from Janša and his policies, though some of them have remained silent
                    sympathisers. The main difference between the views of today’s Slovenian
                    populist right and the ideology of the anti-communist intellectuals in 1997 lies
                    in their attitude towards the concept of Europe. The former idealisation of the
                    European Union has been replaced by scepticism against “cultural Marxism”<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn62" n="60">For example: Borut Korun, “Neomarksizem
                        ali kulturni marksizem,” <hi rend="italic">demokracija.si</hi>, 6 March
                        2022, <ref
                            target="https://demokracija.si/fokus/neomarksizem-ali-kulturni-marksizem/"
                            >https://demokracija.si/fokus/neomarksizem-ali-kulturni-marksizem/</ref>,
                        accessed 20 August 2023.</note>, “Soros”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn63"
                        n="61">For example: J. B., “George Soros, kralj propagande: Milijarder po
                        svetu plačuje najmanj 253 organizacij, prek katerih vpliva na globalne
                        medije,” <hi rend="italic">demokracija.si</hi>, 9 December 2022, <ref
                            target="https://demokracija.si/fokus/george-soros-kralj-propagande-milijarder-po-svetu-placuje-najmanj-253-organizacij-prek-katerih-vpliva-na-globalne-medije/"
                            >https://demokracija.si/fokus/george-soros-kralj-propagande-milijarder-po-svetu-placuje-najmanj-253-organizacij-prek-katerih-vpliva-na-globalne-medije/</ref>,
                        accessed 20 August 2023.</note> and “LGTBQ ideology”<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn64" n="62">For example: Peter Truden, “Starši, pozor! Golobova
                        vlada namerava vpeljati LGBT ideologijo v šole,” <hi rend="italic"
                            >demokracija.si</hi>, 15 May 2022, <ref
                            target="https://demokracija.si/fokus/starsi-pozor-golobova-vlada-namerava-vpeljati-lgbt-ideologijo-v-sole/"
                            >https://demokracija.si/fokus/starsi-pozor-golobova-vlada-namerava-vpeljati-lgbt-ideologijo-v-sole/</ref>,
                        accessed 20 August 2023.</note>. While the 1997 Hour of European Truth
                    attempted to reconcile Slovenian nationalism with the cosmopolitan
                    liberal-democratic paradigm, the contemporary populist right resorts to
                    anti-migrant rhetoric and overt racism while disseminating conspiracy theories
                    such as “The Great Replacement theory”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn65" n="63">
                        For example: “Noro! Evropski parlament trdi, da je velika demografska
                        zamenjava teorija zarote,“ <hi rend="italic">demokracija.si</hi>, 22
                        November 2022, <ref
                            target="https://demokracija.si/tujina/noro-evropski-parlament-trdi-da-je-velika-demografska-zamenjava-teorija-zarote/"
                            >https://demokracija.si/tujina/noro-evropski-parlament-trdi-da-je-velika-demografska-zamenjava-teorija-zarote/</ref>,
                        accessed 20 August 2023.</note> and even “Eurabia”,<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn66" n="64">“Šifra: Eurabija,” <hi rend="italic"
                            >demokracija.si</hi>, 2 June 2018, <ref
                            target="https://demokracija.si/tujina/sifra-eurabija/"
                            >https://demokracija.si/tujina/sifra-eurabija/</ref>, accessed 20 August
                        2023.</note> the conspiracy theory embraced by the Norwegian terrorist
                    Breivik, who massacred 77 people on the island of Utøya on 22 July 2011.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn67" n="65">Eirikur Bergmann, “The Eurabia conspiracy
                        theory,” in <hi rend="italic">Europe, Continent of Conspiracies: Conspiracy
                            Theories in and about Europe</hi>, eds. Andreas Önnerfors, and André Krouwel (London and New York: Routledge, 2021), 36–53. </note></p>
                <p>In 1997, critical intellectuals who supported EU accession, albeit on their
                    terms, cooperated politically with the greatest opponents of EU accession. While
                    in 1997, SDS and its leader maintained a healthy distance towards any
                    Euroscepticism, in 2023, the former leader of the 23 December Movement, Borut
                    Korun, regularly publishes his comments in the SDS party magazine. He has not
                    changed his attitude towards the European Union. In an interview for <hi
                        rend="italic">Demokracija</hi> magazine in May 2023, Korun proudly
                    identified himself as a Eurosceptic and highlighted his role in the 23 December
                    Movement, which had advocated for Slovenia to remain a neutral, independent
                        oasis.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn68" n="66">Metod Berlec, “(INTERVJU)
                        Borut Korun: Ta vlada se je odrekla slovenskemu narodu,”<hi rend="italic"
                            >demokracija.si, </hi>29 May 2023, <ref
                            target="https://demokracija.si/fokus/intervju-borut-korun-ta-vlada-se-je-odrekla-slovenskemu-narodu/"
                            >https://demokracija.si/fokus/intervju-borut-korun-ta-vlada-se-je-odrekla-slovenskemu-narodu/</ref>,
                        accessed 20 August 2023. </note> Korun is obviously now more acceptable for
                    SDS than in 1997, which is not surprising, as, according to the words of the SDS
                    leader at the Economic Forum in Karpacz, Poland, on 6 September 2022, “the
                    future of the European Union is not in a European federation, but rather in a
                    European Union of nations”.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn69" n="67">C. R.,
                        “Predsednik SDS Janez Janša na Poljskem: Prihodnost Evropske unije ni v
                        evropski federaciji, temveč v Evropski uniji narodov,”<hi rend="italic"
                            >demokracija.si</hi>, 6. September 2022, <ref
                            target="https://demokracija.si/fokus/predsednik-sds-janez-jansa-na-poljskem-prihodnost-evropske-unije-ni-v-evropski-federaciji-temvec-v-evropski-uniji-narodov/"
                            >https://demokracija.si/fokus/predsednik-sds-janez-jansa-na-poljskem-prihodnost-evropske-unije-ni-v-evropski-federaciji-temvec-v-evropski-uniji-narodov/</ref>,
                        accessed 20. August 2023.</note> The concept of Euroscepticism does not help
                    us understand the trajectories of the critical attitudes towards Europe and the
                    EU in Slovenia. Achieving this goal calls for a detailed political-historical
                    study with strong emphasis on the history of political thought, the history of
                    discourse and the micro-history of the actors involved.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="bibliography">
                <head>Sources and Literature</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Literature</head>
                    <bibl>“Izjava Gibanja 23. December.” In <hi rend="italic">Danes Slovenija in
                            nikdar več?.</hi> Edited by Borut Korun, 194. Velenje: self-published,
                        1997.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Bergmann, Eirikur. “The Eurabia conspiracy theory.” In <hi rend="italic"
                            >Europe, Continent of Conspiracies: Conspiracy Theories in and about
                            Europe</hi>. Edited by Andreas Önnerfors and André Krouwel, 36–53.
                        London and New York: Routledge, 2021.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Bučar, France. “Kako naprej.” In <hi rend="italic">Danes Slovenija in
                            nikdar več?</hi>. Edited by Borut Korun, 184. Velenje: self-published,
                        1997.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Cerar, Božo. “Španski kompromis.” In <hi rend="italic">Osamosvojitev,
                            Prispevki za enciklopedijo slovenske osamosvojitve, državnosti in
                            ustavnosti. </hi>Edited by Dimitrij Rupel, 299. Ljubljana: Nova
                        univerza, 2021.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Čepič, Zdenko. “Demos prevzame oblast.” In <hi rend="italic">Slovenska
                            novejša zgodovina. Od programa Zedinjena Slovenija do mednarodnega
                            priznanja Republike Slovenije, 1848‒1992</hi>. Edited by Jasna Fischer
                        et al., 1290‒94. Ljubljana: Mladinska knjiga and Inštitut za novejšo
                        zgodovino, 2005.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Čepič, Zdenko. “Razpad Demosa in padec njegove vlade.” In <hi
                            rend="italic">Slovenska novejša zgodovina. Od programa Zedinjena
                        Slovenija do mednarodnega priznanja Republike Slovenije, 1848‒1992</hi>.
                        Edited by Jasna Fischer et al., 1364‒67. Ljubljana: Mladinska knjiga and
                        Inštitut za novejšo zgodovino, 2005.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Gabrič, Aleš. "Zaostrenost mednacionanih odnosov." In <hi rend="italic"
                            >Slovenska novejša zgodovina. Od programa Zedinjena Slovenija do
                            mednarodnega priznanja Republike Slovenije, 1848‒1992</hi>. Edited by
                        Jasna Fischer et al., 1171. Ljubljana: Mladinska knjiga and Inštitut za
                        novejšo zgodovino, 2005.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Galjot, Ana, and Vilma Brodnik. “Iz zgodovine vključevanja Slovenije v
                        Evropsko unijo.” <hi rend="italic">Zgodovina v šoli</hi> 12, No. 3-4 (2004):
                        36-40. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Gašparič, Jure. <hi rend="italic">Slovenski parlament:
                            Politično-zgodovinski pregled od začetka prvega do konca šestega mandata
                            1992 – 2014</hi>. Ljubljana: Inštitut za novejšo zgodovino, 2014. <ref
                            target="http://www.sistory.si/SISTORY:ID:26950"
                            >http://www.sistory.si/SISTORY:ID:26950</ref>.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Gilbert, Mark, and Daniele Pasquinucci. “Introduction.” In <hi
                            rend="italic">Euroscepticisms: The Historical Roots of a Political
                            Challenge. </hi>Edited by Mark Gilbert, and Daniele Pasquinucci, 1–9.
                        Leiden: Brill 2020.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Hribar, Spomenka. “Krivda in greh.” In <hi rend="italic">Kocbekov zbornik.
                        </hi>Edited by Dimitrij Rupel. Maribor: Obzorja, 1987. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Jančar, Drago, France Bučar, Niko Grafenauer, Jože Pučnik, Primož
                        Simoniti, Jože Snoj, Rudi Šeligo, and Ivan Urbančič. <hi rend="italic">Ura
                            evropske resnice za Slovenijo / The Hour of European Truth for
                            Slovenia</hi>. Ljubljana: Nova revija, 1997.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Kacin Wohinz, Milica and Nevenka Troha (eds.). <hi rend="italic"
                            >Slovene-Italian Relations 1880-1956: Report of the Slovene-Italian
                            Historical and Cultural Commission</hi>. Ljubljana: Nova revija, 2001.
                            <ref target="https://hdl.handle.net/11686/file25868"
                            >https://hdl.handle.net/11686/file25868</ref>. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Konovšek, Tjaša. “Formiranje Liberalne demokracije Slovenije in njene
                        politike 1992–1996.” In <hi rend="italic">Narod – politika – država:
                            idejnopolitični značaj strank na Slovenskem od konca 19. do začetka 21.
                            stoletja</hi>. Edited by Jurij Perovšek and Mojca Šorn, 276–80.
                        Ljubljana: Inštitut za novejšo zgodovino, 2020. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Konovšek, Tjaša. “Prekletstvo številke 45: konstituiranje slovenskega
                        državnega zbora in vlade v letih 1996–1997.” <hi rend="italic">Prispevki za
                            novejšo zgodovino</hi> 60, No. 2 (2020): 168‒89.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Kosin, Marko. “Slovenska manjšina v slovensko-italijanskih odnosih,
                        (kronološki pregled za obdobje od osamosvojitve 1991 do konca 1995).” <hi
                            rend="italic">Razprave in gradivo</hi> 33 (1998): 57‒97.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Krapež, Irena. "Diplomacija kot instrument zunanje
                            politike: odnosi med Slovenijo in Italijo." Diplomsko delo, Filozofska fakulteta, Ljubljana, 2009. <ref
                            target="http://dk.fdv.uni-lj.si/magistrska/pdfs/mag_krapez-irena.pdf"
                            >http://dk.fdv.uni-lj.si/magistrska/pdfs/mag_krapez-irena.pdf</ref>. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Leruth, Benjamin, Nicholas Startin, and Simon Usherwood. “Defining
                        Euroscepticism, From a broad concept to a field of study.” In <hi
                            rend="italic">The Routledge Handbook of Euroscepticism. </hi>Edited by
                        Benjamin Leruth, Nicholas Startin and Simon McDougall Usherwood. London:
                        Routledge, 2018. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Omerza, Igor. <hi rend="italic">Veliki in dolgi pohod Nove revije</hi>.
                        Celovec: Mohorjeva, 2015. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Pesek, Rosvita. “Jože Pučnik - dlje kot drugi.” <hi rend="italic">Studia
                            Historica Slovenica</hi> 11, No. 2/3 (2011): 439‒62.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Pesek, Rosvita. <hi rend="italic">Osamosvojitev Slovenije</hi>. Ljubljana:
                        Nova revija, 2007.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Ramšak<hi rend="italic">, </hi>Jure. <hi rend="italic">(Samo)upravljanje
                            intelekta, Družbena kritika v poznosocialistični Sloveniji</hi>.
                        Ljubljana: Modrijan. 2019.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Repe, Božo. <hi rend="italic">Obračun s Perspektivami</hi>. Ljubljana:
                        Znanstveno in publicistično središče, 1990.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Repe, Božo. <hi rend="italic">Viri o demokratizaciji in osamosvojitvi
                            Slovenije. 1. del: Opozicija in oblast.</hi> Ljubljana: Arhivsko društvo
                        Slovenije, 2002. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Škorjanec, Viljenka. <hi rend="italic">Osimska pogajanja</hi>. Koper:
                        Annales, 2007. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Trencsényi, Balázs, Michal Kopeček, Luka Lisjak Gabrijelčič, Maria Falina,
                        Monika Baár, and Maciej Janowski (eds). <hi rend="italic">A History of Modern
                            Political Thought in East Central Europe. Vol. 2, Negotiating Modernity
                            in the Short Twentieth Century and Beyond. Pt. 1, 1918-1968</hi>. New
                        York: Oxford University Press, 2018. </bibl>
                </listBibl>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Newspaper sources</head>
                    <bibl>Albreht, Matjaž. “Še ena vroča izredna seja o pridružitvenem sporazumu.”
                            <hi rend="italic">Delo</hi>, July 16, 1997, 2. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Babič, Mateja. “Pobuda za referendum ni bila vložena pravilno.” <hi
                            rend="italic">Delo</hi>, May 9, 1997, 1.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Babič, Mateja. “Trenutek prigriznjenih idej.” <hi rend="italic">Delo</hi>,
                        July 19, 1997, 2.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Bohte, Gorazd. “Evroskeptiki po slovensko.” <hi rend="italic">Delo</hi>,
                        May 9, 1997, 2.</bibl>
                    <bibl>C. R. “Odprto pismo intelektualcev.” <hi rend="italic">Delo</hi>, July 10,
                        1997, 1. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Drčar Murko, Mojca. "Kazen za naivnost." <hi rend="italic">Delo</hi>,
                        October 22, 1994, 6.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Hribar, Spomenka. “Ustavimo desnico.” <hi rend="italic">Sobotna
                            priloga</hi>, April 18, 1992, 24, 25.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Izgoršek, Urša. “Španski predlog na prepihu razprave v Državnem zboru.”
                            <hi rend="italic">Delo</hi>, April 3, 1996, 2.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Jakopec, Marko. “Janez Janša ni več obrambni minister.“ <hi rend="italic"
                            >Delo</hi>, March 29, 1994, 1.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Jakopec, Marko. “Večina poslanskih skupin je podpirala spremembe ustave.”
                            <hi rend="italic">Delo</hi>, July 15 1997, 2. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Jakopec, Marko, and Vladimir Vodušek. “DZ lahko ratificira sporazum o
                        pridružitvi samo brez aneksa.” <hi rend="italic">Delo</hi>, May 9, 1997, 2. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Jančar, Drago. “Egiptovski lonci mesa.” <hi rend="italic">Sobotna
                            priloga</hi>, October 1, 1994, 30.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Jež, Boris. “Izbruh razuma.” <hi rend="italic">Delo</hi>, 11 July 1997,
                        3.</bibl>
                    <bibl>N. R. “Opozorilo poslancem državnega zbora.” <hi rend="italic">Delo</hi>,
                        April 10, 1996, 2.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Pušenjak, Dejan. “Združena LDS stavi tudi na to, da Slovenci niso prav
                        neumni.” <hi rend="italic">Delo</hi>, March 14, 1994, 2.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Rupel, Dimitrij. “Urica domačih resnic.” <hi rend="italic">Sobotna
                            priloga</hi>, July 19, 1997, 38. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Rus, Veljko. “Antikomunistični manifest.” <hi rend="italic">Sobotna
                            priloga</hi>, July 26, 1997, 30. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Štamcar, Miha Đ., and Jani Sever. “Ustavite Paravomo!.” <hi rend="italic"
                            >Mladina</hi>, March 22, 1994, 1.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Taškar, Jana. “Dr. Rupel je ljubljanski župan.” <hi rend="italic"
                            >Delo</hi>, December 19, 1994, 1. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Taškar, Jana. “Ustavna komisija odločila, zdaj je na vrsti Državni zbor.”
                            <hi rend="italic">Delo</hi>, July 10, 1997, 2. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Vidmajer, Saša. “Parlament odprl pot pridruževanju k EU.” <hi
                            rend="italic">Delo</hi>, April 12, 1996, 1. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Vidmajer, Saša. “Prvi obisk italijanskega predsednika v Sloveniji.” <hi
                            rend="italic">Delo</hi>, July 8, 1997, 1. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Vodušek, Vladimir. “Španski jezdeci in španski borci.”<hi rend="italic"
                            >Delo</hi>, May 10, 1997, 3.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Žitko, Stojan. “Vrh je v prvi širitveni krog Nata soglasno povabil samo
                        tri države.” <hi rend="italic">Delo</hi>, July 9, 1997, 1. </bibl>
                </listBibl>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Online resources</head>
                    <bibl>“Noro! Evropski parlament trdi, da je velika demografska zamenjava teorija
                        zarote.“ <hi rend="italic">demokracija.si,</hi> November 22, 2022. Accessed
                        20 August 2023. <ref
                            target="https://demokracija.si/tujina/noro-evropski-parlament-trdi-da-je-velika-demografska-zamenjava-teorija-zarote/"
                            >https://demokracija.si/tujina/noro-evropski-parlament-trdi-da-je-velika-demografska-zamenjava-teorija-zarote/</ref>. </bibl>
                    <bibl>“Šifra: Eurabija.” <hi rend="italic">demokracija.si</hi>, June 2, 2018.
                        Accessed 20 August 2023. <ref
                            target="https://demokracija.si/tujina/sifra-eurabija/"
                            >https://demokracija.si/tujina/sifra-eurabija/</ref> . </bibl>
                    <bibl>B., J. “George Soros, kralj propagande: Milijarder po svetu plačuje
                        najmanj 253 organizacij, prek katerih vpliva na globalne medije.” <hi
                            rend="italic">demokracija.si</hi>, December 9, 2022. Accessed 20 August
                        2023. <ref
                            target="https://demokracija.si/fokus/george-soros-kralj-propagande-milijarder-po-svetu-placuje-najmanj-253-organizacij-prek-katerih-vpliva-na-globalne-medije/"
                            >https://demokracija.si/fokus/george-soros-kralj-propagande-milijarder-po-svetu-placuje-najmanj-253-organizacij-prek-katerih-vpliva-na-globalne-medije/</ref>. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Berlec, Metod. “(INTERVJU) Borut Korun: Ta vlada se je odrekla slovenskemu
                        narodu.” <hi rend="italic">demokracija.si, </hi>May 29, 2023. Accessed 20
                        August 2023. <ref
                            target="https://demokracija.si/fokus/intervju-borut-korun-ta-vlada-se-je-odrekla-slovenskemu-narodu/"
                            >https://demokracija.si/fokus/intervju-borut-korun-ta-vlada-se-je-odrekla-slovenskemu-narodu/</ref>. </bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="italic">Dnevnik</hi>. “Nova revija v stečaju: prodaja
                        ustanoviteljske pravice Inštituta Nove revije.” 17 May 2014. Sccessed 20
                        August 2023. <ref target="https://www.dnevnik.si/1042659861"
                            >https://www.dnevnik.si/1042659861</ref>.</bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="italic">Državna volilna komisija</hi>. “Poročilo o izidu
                        glasovanja in izidu referenduma o pristopu Republike Slovenije k Evropski
                        uniji, ki je bil 23. marca 2003.” Accessed August 20, 2023. <ref
                            target="https://www.dvk-rs.si/fileadmin/user_upload/dokumenti/volitve/referendum_2003_1/porocilo-o-referendumu-EU.pdf"
                            >https://www.dvk-rs.si/fileadmin/user_upload/dokumenti/volitve/referendum_2003_1/porocilo-o-referendumu-EU.pdf</ref>. </bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="italic">Državna volilna komisija</hi>. “Poročilo o izidu
                        glasovanja in izidu referenduma o pristopu Republike Slovenije k
                        Organizaciji severnoatlantske pogodbe (NATO), ki je bil 23. marca 2003.”
                        Accessed August 20, 2023. <ref
                            target="https://www.dvk-rs.si/fileadmin/user_upload/dokumenti/volitve/referendum_2003_1/porocilo-o-referendumu-NATO.pdf"
                            >https://www.dvk-rs.si/fileadmin/user_upload/dokumenti/volitve/referendum_2003_1/porocilo-o-referendumu-NATO.pdf</ref>. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Korun, Borut. “Neomarksizem ali kulturni marksizem.” <hi rend="italic"
                            >demokracija.si</hi>, March 6, 2022. Accessed 20 August 2023. <ref
                            target="https://demokracija.si/fokus/neomarksizem-ali-kulturni-marksizem/"
                            >https://demokracija.si/fokus/neomarksizem-ali-kulturni-marksizem/</ref>. </bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="italic">Portal GOV.SI</hi>. “Slovenija v Natu.” Accessed August
                        20, 2023. <ref target="https://www.gov.si/teme/slovenija-v-natu/"
                            >https://www.gov.si/teme/slovenija-v-natu/</ref>.</bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="italic">Predstavništvo Evropske komisije v Sloveniji</hi>.
                        “Slovenija v EU.” Accessed September 1, 2023. <ref
                            target="https://slovenia.representation.ec.europa.eu/o-nas/casovnica-slovenije-v-eu_sl"
                            >https://slovenia.representation.ec.europa.eu/o-nas/casovnica-slovenije-v-eu_sl</ref>. </bibl>
                    <bibl>R., C. “Predsednik SDS Janez Janša na Poljskem: Prihodnost Evropske unije
                        ni v evropski federaciji, temveč v Evropski uniji narodov.” <hi
                            rend="italic">demokracija.si</hi>, September 6, 2022. Accessed 20.
                        August 2023. <ref
                            target="https://demokracija.si/fokus/predsednik-sds-janez-jansa-na-poljskem-prihodnost-evropske-unije-ni-v-evropski-federaciji-temvec-v-evropski-uniji-narodov/"
                            >https://demokracija.si/fokus/predsednik-sds-janez-jansa-na-poljskem-prihodnost-evropske-unije-ni-v-evropski-federaciji-temvec-v-evropski-uniji-narodov/</ref>. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Truden, Peter. “Starši, pozor! Golobova vlada namerava vpeljati LGBT
                        ideologijo v šole.” <hi rend="italic">demokracija.si</hi>, May 15, 2022.
                        Accessed 20 August 2023. <ref
                            target="https://demokracija.si/fokus/starsi-pozor-golobova-vlada-namerava-vpeljati-lgbt-ideologijo-v-sole/"
                            >https://demokracija.si/fokus/starsi-pozor-golobova-vlada-namerava-vpeljati-lgbt-ideologijo-v-sole/</ref>.
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="italic">Vrednote v prehodu II, Slovensko javno
                            mnenje 1990‒1998</hi>. Edited by Niko Toš. Ljubljana: Fakulteta za družbene vede, 2021.
                            <ref
                            target="https://www.cjm.si/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/VREDNOTE-2-WEB.pdf"
                            >https://www.cjm.si/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/VREDNOTE-2-WEB.pdf</ref>.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
            <div type="summary">
                <docAuthor>Marko Zajc</docAuthor>
                <head>URA EVROPSKE RESNICE ZA SLOVENSKE INTELEKTUALCE</head>
                <head>POVZETEK</head>
                <p>V prispevku avtor predstavi in analizira politično aktivnost slovenskih
                    opozicijskih intelektualcev med približevanjem Slovenije EU (obdobje 1995–97).
                    Del intelektualcev iz kroga Nove revije je poleti 1997 objavil javno pismo »Ura
                    evropske resnice za Slovenijo«, kritiko družbenih in političnih razmer ter slabe
                    vladne politike približevanja EU in Natu. Podpisniki javnega pisma so tedanjo
                    vladavino liberalnodemokratske stranke (LDS), ki je bila naslednica uradne
                    mladinske organizacije v socializmu, razumeli kot nedemokratično vladavino
                    nekdanjih komunistov, ki imajo v rokah vse niti oblasti. Pri približevanju EU so
                    nasprotovali sporazumu z Italijo glede kupovanja slovenskih nepremičnin (t. i.
                    španski kompromis), ki so ga imeli za odpoved slovenski suverenosti. Čeprav so
                    se načeloma strinjali s članstvom v EU, so v svojem aktivizmu sodelovali tudi s
                    skupino odkritih evroskeptikov. V prvem delu prispevka avtor predstavi slovensko
                    politiko v devetdesetih letih 20. stoletja, v drugem na kratko opiše proces
                    pridruževanja Slovenije EU in Natu. V tretjem delu pojasni predzgodovino in
                    delovanje obravnavane skupine intelektualcev, v četrtem pa analizira javno pismo
                    in odzive v javnosti. V zaključku avtor postavi vprašanje, ali so bili omenjeni
                    akterji evroskeptiki. Po njegovem mnenju koncept evroskepticizma ne pomaga
                    razumeti kompleksnih in ambivalentnih odnosov političnih akterjev do Evrope in
                    EU. Poudari trajektorijo slovenske protikomunistične politične misli do
                    sodobnosti. Glavna razlika med pogledi današnje slovenske populistične desnice
                    in ideologijo protikomunističnih intelektualcev iz leta 1997 je v njihovem
                    odnosu do koncepta Evrope. Nekdanjo idealizacijo EU je zamenjala skepsa do
                    »Bruslja«, »kulturnega marksizma«, »Sorosa« in »ideologije LGBTQ«. Medtem ko je
                    »ura evropske resnice« iz leta 1997 poskušala uskladiti slovenski nacionalizem s
                    kozmopolitsko liberalnodemokratično paradigmo, se sodobna populistična desnica
                    zateka k protimigrantski retoriki, hkrati pa sprejema in širi »alt-right«
                    teorije zarote, kot je »teorija velike zamenjave«.</p>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
