<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Carniolan Savings Bank and Slovenian-German relations in 1908 and
                    1909</title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename>Nataša</forename>
                        <surname>Henig Miščič</surname>
                        <roleName>M.Sc.</roleName>
                        <roleName>junior researcher</roleName>
                        <affiliation>Institute of Contemporary History</affiliation>
                        <address>
                            <addrLine>Kongresni trg 1</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>SI – 1000 Ljubljana</addrLine>
                        </address>
                        <email>natasa.henig@inz.si</email>
                    </name>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>2020</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>
                    <orgName xml:lang="sl">Inštitut za novejšo zgodovino</orgName>
                    <orgName xml:lang="en">Institute of Contemporary History</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Kongresni trg 1</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>SI-1000 Ljubljana</addrLine>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>http://ojs.inz.si/pnz/article/view/790</pubPlace>
                <date>2020</date>
                <availability status="free">
                    <licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title xml:lang="sl">Prispevki za novejšo zgodovino</title>
                <title xml:lang="en">Contributions to Contemporary History</title>
                <biblScope unit="volume">60</biblScope>
                <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
                <idno type="ISSN">2463-7807</idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source, born digital.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc xml:lang="en">
                <p>Contributions to Contemporary History is one of the central Slovenian scientific
                    historiographic journals, dedicated to publishing articles from the field of
                    contemporary history (the 19th and 20th century).</p>
                <p>The journal is published three times per year in Slovenian and in the following
                    foreign languages: English, German, Serbian, Croatian, Bosnian, Italian, Slovak
                    and Czech. The articles are all published with abstracts in English and
                    Slovenian as well as summaries in English.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <projectDesc xml:lang="sl">
                <p>Prispevki za novejšo zgodovino je ena osrednjih slovenskih znanstvenih
                    zgodovinopisnih revij, ki objavlja teme s področja novejše zgodovine (19. in 20.
                    stoletje).</p>
                <p>Revija izide trikrat letno v slovenskem jeziku in v naslednjih tujih jezikih:
                    angleščina, nemščina, srbščina, hrvaščina, bosanščina, italijanščina, slovaščina
                    in češčina. Članki izhajajo z izvlečki v angleščini in slovenščini ter povzetki
                    v angleščini.</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="sl"/>
                <language ident="en"/>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords xml:lang="en">
                    <term>Carniolan Savings Bank</term>
                    <term>depositors</term>
                    <term>boycott</term>
                    <term>bank run</term>
                    <term>withdrawals</term>
                    <term>government securities</term>
                    <term>mortgage loans</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords xml:lang="sl">
                    <term>Kranjska hranilnica</term>
                    <term>vlagatelji</term>
                    <term>bojkot</term>
                    <term>naval</term>
                    <term>umik</term>
                    <term>državni vrednostni papirji</term>
                    <term>hipotekarna posojila</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change>
                    <date>2020-14-04</date>
                    <name>Neja Blaj Hribar</name>
                    <desc>Pretvorba iz DOCX v TEI, dodatno kodiranje</desc>
                </change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <docAuthor>Nataša Henig Miščič<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn1" n="*"> M.Sc., junior
                    researcher, Institute of Contemporary History, Kongresni trg 1, SI-1000
                    Ljubljana, <ref target="mailto:natasa.henig@inz.si">natasa.henig@inz.si</ref>
                </note></docAuthor>
            <docImprint>
                <idno type="cobissType">Cobiss Type: 1.01</idno>
                <idno type="UDC">UDC: </idno>
            </docImprint>

            <div type="abstract" xml:lang="sl">
                <head>IZVLEČEK</head>
                <head>KRANJSKA HRANILNICA IN SLOVENSKO-NEMŠKI ODNOSI LETA 1908 IN 1909</head>
                <p><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Nacionalna nasprotja v avstro-ogrski
                        monarhiji so se ob koncu 19. stoletja vse bolj zaostrovala in prišlo je do
                        nacionalne polarizacije. V zadnjih desetletjih pred izbruhom prve svetovne
                        vojne so nacionalna nasprotja dosegla velike razsežnosti. Vrhunec
                        slovensko-nemških spopadov na Kranjskem predstavljajo protinemške
                        demonstracije v Ljubljani leta 1908, ki so pripeljale do korenitih sprememb
                        v političnem, gospodarskem in družbenem življenju. V članku je predstavljen
                        pomen, ki ga je imela Kranjska hranilnica v slovenskem prostoru v začetku
                        20. stoletja. Prispevek posebej obravnava posledice, s katerimi se je
                        hranilnica soočala po septembrskih dogodkih leta 1908, ki so močno
                        zaznamovali njeno delovanje.</hi></p>
                <p><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Ključne besede: Kranjska hranilnica,
                        vlagatelji, bojkot, naval, umik, državni vrednostni papirji, hipotekarna
                        posojila</hi></p>
            </div>
            <div type="abstract">

                <head>ABSTRACT</head>
                <p><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">At the end of the 19</hi><hi
                        rend="italic superscript" style="font-size:10pt"
                        >th</hi><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve"> century, the Austro-Hungarian Monarchy experienced national polarisation. During the last decades before the outbreak of World War I, national contradictions reached considerable proportions. The Slovenian-German conflicts in Carniola culminated in the anti-German riots in Ljubljana in 1908, which led to radical changes in the political, economic, and social life. Paper presents the importance of the Carniolan Savings Bank in the Slovenian territory at the beginning of the 20</hi><hi
                        rend="italic superscript" style="font-size:10pt"
                    >th</hi><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve"> century. The article deals specifically with the consequences faced by the Carniolan Savings Bank after the events of September 1908, which strongly affected its operations.</hi></p>
                <p><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Keywords: Carniolan Savings Bank,
                        depositors, boycott, bank run, withdrawals, government securities, mortgage
                        loans</hi></p>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div>
                <head>Introduction </head>
                <p><hi style="font-size:12pt">During the last decades before the outbreak of World
                        War I, the national contradictions between the national movements reached
                        great proportions in the Austro-Hungarian Monarchy. In the province of
                        Carniola, the conflicts between the Slovenian and German national groups
                        culminated in September 1908, when it came to the turning point in their
                        relations. The anti-German riots in Ljubljana let to radical changes in the
                        political, economic, and social life. The conflicts did not subside until as
                        late as the onset of World War I. Mutual accusations and suspicions were a
                        part of everyday life. Many Slovenian investors withdrew their savings from
                        the Carniolan Savings Bank, mostly because it was considered as the German
                        financial pillar in the province of Carniola. Carniolan Savings Bank had
                        been established and operated in the territory traditionally populated by
                        Slovenians, who spoke Slovenian. It predominantly collected deposits and
                        managed credit activity in Carniola. Therefore, it is paradoxical that the
                        Carniolan Savings Bank was considered a German institution, although it had
                        never publicly or openly declared itself as either a Slovenian or German
                        financial institution. Such indifference</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn2" n="1"> For further information about
                            the concept of <hi rend="italic">national indifference</hi>, see Rogers
                            Brubaker, <hi rend="italic">Ethnicity without Groups</hi> (Cambridge,
                            London: Harvard University Press, 2006). 12. Tara Zahra, “Imagined
                            Noncommunities: National Indifference as a Category of Analysis,” <hi
                                rend="italic">Slavic Review</hi>, 69, No. 1 (spring 2010): 98–99.
                        </note><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve"> was opted for by the Board regardless of the national affiliation of the members of the Savings Bank Association. The goal was to attract as many depositors as possible. The statute of the Savings Bank stated that membership in the association and the Board did not depend on nationality, and all Austro-Hungarian citizens with a permanent address in Ljubljana could become members.</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn3" n="2">
                            SI_ZAL_LJU/0362, f. 18, Statuten und Geschäftsordnung der krainischen
                            Sparkasse in Laibach, 24 December 1867, 2. More about organisations and
                            ethnic groups in: Brubaker, <hi rend="italic">Ethnicity without
                                groups</hi>, 16.
                    </note><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve"> Nevertheless, the Carniolan Savings Bank maintained this status until the disintegration of the Austro-Hungarian Monarchy in 1918. </hi></p>
                <p><hi style="font-size:12pt">Savings banks had a significant impact on the changes,
                        required for the mobilisation of financial resources from the social strata
                        that had had no access to banking services before. Furthermore, savings
                        banks introduced dispersed financial resources to the financial market by
                        directing capital into mortgage loans and government securities.</hi><note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn4" n="3"> Carolin Thol, <hi rend="italic">Poverty
                            Relief and Financial Inclusion. Savings Banks in Nineteenth Century
                            Germany</hi> (Brussels: WSBI−ESBG The Voice of Savings and Retail
                        Banking, 2016), 18, available at: <ref
                            target="https://www.wsbi-esbg.org/SiteCollectionDocuments/8119_ESBG_BRO_STUDY.pdf"
                                ><hi rend="Spletna_povezava"
                                >https://www.wsbi-esbg.org/SiteCollectionDocuments/8119_ESBG_BRO_STUDY.pdf</hi></ref>.
                        Cristian Dirningen, “Historic Dimension of Corporate Social Responsibility
                        (CSR) of Savings Banks − the Austrian Example,” the 9<hi rend="superscript"
                            >th</hi> European Symposium on Savings Banks History, European Savings
                        Banks: From Social Commitment to Corporate Social Responsibility, Madrid 4−5
                        May 2006. <hi rend="italic">Perspectives</hi>, 55, 2007, 12–13, available
                        at: <ref
                            target="https://www.wsbi-esbg.org/SiteCollectionDocuments/Perspectives%2055.pdf"
                            >https://www.wsbi-esbg.org/SiteCollectionDocuments/Perspectives%2055.pdf</ref>.</note></p>
                <p><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve">This article deals specifically with the consequences that the Carniolan Savings Bank faced after the events of September 1908, which had strongly affected its operations. Deposit withdrawals were a common reaction of the population during the periods of different economic, political, and war crises. Savings bank deposits often dropped during or after systematic commercial crises. </hi><hi
                        rend="italic" style="font-size:12pt">Bank
                        runs</hi><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve"> are events when debt holders of a single bank or savings bank demand redemption. The rapid withdrawal of deposits usually forces a contraction of credit.</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn5" n="4"> Charles
                            W Calomiris and Gary Gorton, “The Origins of Banking Panics: Models,
                            Facts, and Bank Regulation,” in: <hi rend="italic">Financial Markets and
                                Financial Crises</hi>, ed. Glenn R. Hubbard (Chicago, London: The
                            University of Chicago Press, 1991), 111−15, available at: <ref
                                target="https://pdfs.semanticscholar.org/d9d7/bf9c964fd2c1e2ea2828bb8805861ffe4425.pdf?_ga=2.174581930.988668068.1571398679-579497628.1571398679"
                                >https://pdfs.semanticscholar.org/d9d7/bf9c964fd2c1e2ea2828bb8805861ffe4425.pdf?_ga=2.174581930.988668068.1571398679-579497628.1571398679</ref>.</note>
                    <hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve">The </hi><hi rend="italic"
                        style="font-size:12pt"
                        >runs</hi><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve"> in question were triggered by fears regarding solvency and the repayment of deposits. The Carniolan Savings Bank tried to restore the trust of its clients, while at the same time attempting to hedge its deposits in times of high risk. It had to ensure the security of their business and invested money. The savings deposits that the Carniolan Savings Bank had to pay off to their depositors between October 1908 and June 1909 far exceeded all of its available cash.</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn6" n="5"> SI AS
                            437, f. 38, Zgodovina hranilnice od 1909 do 1918, 1.</note></p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Slovenian − German relations before 1908</head>
                <p><hi style="font-size:12pt">At the end of the 19</hi><hi rend="superscript"
                        style="font-size:12pt"
                        >th</hi><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve"> century, the Austro-Hungarian Monarchy experienced national polarisation.</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn7" n="6"> For
                            further information, see Pieter M. Judson, <hi rend="italic">The
                                Habsburg Empire. A New History</hi> (Cambridge, MA: Belknap, 2016),
                            9−11.</note><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve"> It was not enough to be just Slovenian or German: it was necessary to show nationality in public. National struggles also intensified in the Slovenian territory at the turn of the 20</hi><hi
                        rend="superscript" style="font-size:12pt"
                        >th</hi><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve"> century.</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn8" n="7"> Andrej
                            Pančur, “Nacionalni spori,” in: <hi rend="italic">Slovenska novejša
                                zgodovina. Od programa Zedinjena Slovenija do mednarodnega priznanja
                                Republike Slovenije: 1848−1992</hi>, <hi rend="italic">I</hi>, ed.
                            Jasna Fischer et al. (Ljubljana: Mladinska knjiga, Inštitut za novejšo
                            zgodovino, 2005),
                        36.</note><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve"> The national-political differentiation was followed by battles between the national movements. Differentiation began in the 1860s and early 1870s. During this period, it was characteristic that at the local elections, people would usually decide either in favour of the Slovenian national party, its programme and performance or against it. The opposite side consisted of people who, for some reason, did not support the Slovenian party and were satisfied with the traditional leading role of the German language and culture,</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn9" n="8"> See also
                            Judson, <hi rend="italic">The Habsburg Empire</hi>,
                        299−300.</note><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve"> people who believed that national differences were not as important as constitutional developments, the fight for their preservation, and the promotion of liberal ideas.</hi><hi rend="Footnote_Characters" xml:space="preserve"> </hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn10" n="9"> Vasilij
                            Melik, “Politične razmere na Štajerskem v času Napotnika,” in: <hi
                                rend="italic">Slovenci 1848−1918. Razprave in članki</hi> (Maribor:
                            Litera, 2002), 608. </note></p>
                <p><hi style="font-size:12pt">National differentiation developed differently in each
                        province. The province of Carniola was traditionally populated by
                        Slovenians, who spoke Slovenian. The relative proportion of Germans in
                        Ljubljana was always modest. However, in Lower Styria, for example, the
                        situation was completely different. Germans lost the countryside, but
                        retained the control of the city curiae in Celje, Maribor, and Ptuj until
                        the dissolution of the Monarchy, while Slovenians were a part of a larger
                        territory with a German majority and a German centre. In Lower Styria, after
                        1878, all electoral districts of the peasant curia – and after 1907, all of
                        the rural state electoral districts – were in the hands of
                        Slovenians.</hi><note place="foot"
                            xml:id="ftn11" n="10"> Melik, “Politične razmere,” 608-09. Pančur,
                            “Nacionalni spori,” 37.</note></p>
                <p><hi style="font-size:12pt">From 1848 until the collapse of the Austro-Hungarian
                        Monarchy, the Carniolan German vision of the Slovenian national community
                        barely changed, although smaller developments are still noticeable. Until
                        the end of the 1870s, the German side did not oppose the Slovenian wishes
                        for all-round progress but believed that the Slovenian nation had, until
                        then, been underdeveloped and not fit to lead a completely independent life.
                        They perceived the obvious and comprehensive development of Slovenians as of
                        the 1880s as artificial – supported by the contemporaneous state and
                        government of Eduard Taaffe to the detriment of Germans.</hi><note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn12" n="11"> Janez Cvirn, “Nemško gledanje na
                        Slovence (1848–1914),” in: <hi rend="italic">Sosed v ogledalu soseda. Od
                            1848 do danes</hi>, ed. Franc Rozman (Ljubljana: Nacionalni komite za
                        zgodovinske vede Republike Slovenije, 1995), 55, 58–60. </note>
                </p>
                <p><hi style="font-size:12pt">Both national movements – German and Slovenian – would
                        use a variety of resources for defence and offence.</hi><note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn13" n="12"> Ibid., 60–61.</note><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve"> Conflicts between the members of the German and Slovenian national groups quickly developed into physical altercations. Fights between Slovenians and Germans became constant, especially during Slovenian cultural and social events, which the Germans understood as demonstrations against German domination. Germans initiated disorders in the predominantly German Celje, while its opposite was the predominantly Slovenian Ljubljana. The 1903 spring demonstrations in Croatia therefore also triggered a solidarity movement in the Slovenian territory. During May and June 1903, several political protests took place against Ban Khuen Hédervári in Ljubljana, Celje, Slovenj Gradec, Trieste, Gorica, Šempeter, Nabrežina, as well as in smaller rural towns. All of these were invoked by the joint efforts of the Slovenian political parties. The gathering in Ljubljana turned into anti-German demonstrations. Protesters started throwing stones into the German </hi>
                    <hi rend="italic" style="font-size:12pt"
                        >Kazina</hi><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve"> building, and the police had to deal with the demonstrators. Consequently, Prime Minister Ernest von Koerber decided to prevent the visit of the Dalmatian, Istrian, and Slovenian deputies to the Emperor.</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn14" n="13">
                            Pančur, “Nacionalni spori,” 38. Andrej Studen, “Protinemški izgredi v
                            Ljubljani leta 1903,” <hi rend="italic">Prispevki za novejšo
                                zgodovino</hi>, 38, No. 1–2 (1998): 15, 20.</note>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>September events in Ptuj and Ljubljana</head>
                <p><hi style="font-size:12pt">The many excesses provide ample evidence that over
                        time, the national struggle could attain the dimension of a “life-and-death
                        struggle”. The contradictions between the Slovenian and German population
                        had reached great proportions, full of intolerance and hatred on all sides
                        during the last decades before the outbreak of the World War I. The
                        September 1908 events, beginning with the German protests in Ptuj and
                        culminating in anti-German demonstrations in Ljubljana, were among the most
                        prominent conflicts.</hi><note place="foot"
                            xml:id="ftn15" n="14"> Vasilij Melik, “Problemi slovenske družbe
                            1897–1914,” in: <hi rend="italic">Slovenci 1848–1918. Razprave in
                                članki</hi> (Maribor: Litera, 2002), 601.</note></p>
                <p><hi style="font-size:12pt">The annual assembly of the St. Cyril and Methodius
                        Society (</hi><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:12pt">Družba sv. Cirila in
                        Metoda</hi><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve"> – CMD), a national defence school organisation, represented a cause for German demonstrations. The CMD leaders chose Ptuj because they wanted to show that this city was not </hi><hi
                        rend="italic" style="font-size:12pt"
                        >German</hi><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve">, but </hi><hi
                        rend="italic" style="font-size:12pt"
                        >Slovenian</hi><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve">. The Styrian Germans were not impressed by this decision. They wanted to underline precisely the opposite; that Ptuj had always been and will remain </hi><hi
                        rend="italic" style="font-size:12pt">German</hi><hi style="font-size:12pt">.
                        The German population was unsuccessful in its efforts to make the
                        authorities ban the CMD assembly, announced for 13 September 1908. The first
                        anti-Slovenian demonstrations took place on the evening of 12 September. The
                        first serious incident occurred immediately after a train had arrived at the
                        Ptuj Railway Station. On the next day, German counter-revolutionary
                        demonstrations broke out, leading to physical conflicts between the
                        Slovenian and German movements. The German demonstrators disrupted the CMD
                        assembly in front of the National House.</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn16" n="15"> Branko Goropevšek, “Odmev in
                            pomen septembrskih dogodkov leta 1908. Spomin na 90-letnico dogodkov,”
                            in: <hi rend="italic">Slovenija 1848−1998. Iskanje lastne poti</hi>,
                            eds. Stane Granda and Barbara Šatej (Ljubljana: Zveza zgodovinskih
                            društev Slovenije, 1998), 115−16.</note></p>
                <p><hi style="font-size:12pt">According to Branko Goropevšek, the Ptuj events would
                        probably have remained less noticeable, had they not triggered an outburst
                        of national feelings that engulfed the other Slovenian territories and
                        resulted in anti-German demonstrations, particularly in Ljubljana. The
                        Slovenian population prepared a series of protests in Styrian cities and
                        villages.</hi>
                    <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn17" n="16"> Ibid.,
                            116–18.</note></p>
                <p><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve">The reports of the events in Ptuj provoked Slovenian demonstrations in Ljubljana. In the capital city of the province of Carniola, on 15 September, the town council protested strongly against the Ministry of the Interior. Two days later, on 17 September, the Slovenian youth organised demonstrations against the German Student Society of </hi><hi
                        rend="italic" style="font-size:12pt">Carniola</hi><hi style="font-size:12pt"
                        >, which held its general assembly. On the following day, the demonstrations
                        had become widespread. They lasted for three days, from 18 to 20 September.
                        Because of the attacks against German shops, artisans, and traders, the
                        Government ordered the gendarmerie and the army to intervene. On the evening
                        of 20 September, the army fired at the protesters. During the shooting, they
                        killed the student Ivan Adamič and Rudolf Lunder, an employee of the
                        national printing office.</hi><note
                            place="foot" xml:id="ftn18" n="17"> “Septembrski dogodki,” in: <hi
                                rend="italic">Ilustrirana zgodovina Slovencev</hi>, ed. Marko Vidic
                            (Ljubljana: Mladinska knjiga, 1999), 282. Pančur, “Nacionalni spori,”
                            38.</note></p>
                <p><hi style="font-size:12pt">The Mayor of Ljubljana Ivan Hribar dedicated a whole
                        chapter of his memoirs to the September events. He detailed the development
                        of these events in Ljubljana and specifically focused on the military
                        procedures: “There was, of course, much excitement around the city. The
                        crowd was the angriest because of the military presence and its directly
                        inappropriate behaviour, as it was, in many many cases, later possible to
                        determine. They were not satisfied with setting up cordons in the streets:
                        some of the troops even walked into public shops and threw people
                        out</hi><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:12pt">.</hi><hi
                        style="font-size:12pt">”</hi><note
                            place="foot" xml:id="ftn19" n="18"> Ivan Hribar, <hi rend="italic">Moji
                                spomini. Od 1853. do 1910. leta</hi>, <hi rend="italic">I</hi>
                            (Ljubljana, 1928),
                        342.</note><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve"> Regarding the responsibility for the unpleasant events of 20 September, when Lunder and Adamič lost their lives, Hribar wrote: “You got what you wanted! I have just received a report that the army opened fire and that several people were killed. I refuse to take responsibility by myself, and I blame you for the spilt blood!”</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn20" n="19"> Ibid.,
                            346.</note>
                    <hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve">Hribar was the only one to write about the boycott of the German merchants and actions regarding the elimination of German inscriptions. </hi></p>
                <p><hi style="font-size:12pt">Anton Bonaventura Jeglič, the Archbishop of Ljubljana,
                        briefly described the events in his diary. On 22 September 1908 – regarding
                        the events that had taken place between Friday, 18 September, and Sunday, 20
                        September – he wrote that terrible riots took place in Ljubljana and that
                        Slovenians were breaking windows and damaging German-owned buildings. He
                        believed that these events had been caused by “the general incitement of one
                        nation against the other and the German demonstrations against Slovenians in
                        Ptuj.” He was very pleased to emphasise that the Slovenian People’s Party
                        did not participate in the riots and that only liberals were
                        affected.</hi><note place="foot"
                            xml:id="ftn21" n="20"> Anton Bonaventura Jeglič, <hi rend="italic"
                                >Jegličev dnevnik, znanstvenokritična izdaja</hi>, eds. Blaž Otrin
                            and Marija Čipić Rehar (Celje: Celjska Mohorjeva družba, 2015),
                            425−26.</note><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve"> In his next announcement, he corrected his misstatement, underlining that there were not three deaths but two and that the funeral was a powerful demonstration. In his opinion, the representatives of the Slovenian Liberals tried to take advantage of the situation in order to regain their leading political position in Carniola.</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn22" n="21">
                            Ibid.</note><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve"> However, in the article titled </hi><hi
                        rend="italic" style="font-size:12pt">To the Faithful of the Diocese of
                        Ljubljana</hi><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve"> [</hi><hi
                        rend="italic" style="font-size:12pt">Vernikom ljubljanske
                        škofije</hi><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve">] published in the </hi><hi
                        rend="italic" style="font-size:12pt">Škofijski list</hi><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve"> newspaper, he considered the moral principles in the broader context of the German–Slovenian relations. He condemned the September demonstrations of both nations: “What happened in Ptuj against Slovenians merely entailed sins against the Christian love towards one’s neighbours; and what happened in Ljubljana against Germans – the senseless destruction of windows and damage to the property of others – are mortal sins, not merely against love, but also against the justice that we owe to our neighbour. In addition, newspapers incited, maintained, and encouraged the sinful hostility and acts of sinful revenge in Styria and Carniola.”</hi>
                    <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn23" n="22"> Anton
                            Bonaventura Jeglič, “Vernikom ljubljanske škofije,” <hi rend="italic"
                                >Škofijski list</hi>, No. 8 (1908), 115.</note>
                </p>
                <p><hi style="font-size:12pt">Fran Šuklje only mentioned the September events in his
                        memoirs and judged them with the following words: “The events in Ljubljana,
                        however, went far beyond what was commonly in our thoughts. In particular,
                        they had a bad influence on the already compromised position of Prime
                        Minister Baron Beck. In his government programme, Beck tried to reconcile
                        the national oppositions and strived to achieve national reconciliation and
                        settlement. Due to the events that took place in Ljubljana on and after 19
                        September and because of the ‘Germanised’ strongholds in Lower Styria and
                        Klagenfurt, the reconciliation that Beck’s policy is based on is
                        impossible.”</hi><note place="foot"
                            xml:id="ftn24" n="23"> Fran Šuklje, <hi rend="italic">Iz mojih spominov,
                                II.</hi> (Ljubljana: Slovenska matica, 1995), 202.</note>
                    <hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve">Šuklje devoted more attention to the annexation of Bosnia and Herzegovina, in particular to the Provincial Assembly elections on 14 December 1908, won by the Catholic Slovenian People’s Party. </hi></p>
                <p><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve">A conflict also ensued regarding the inscriptions on the stores in Ljubljana. On 21 September 1908, the </hi><hi
                        rend="italic" style="font-size:12pt">Slovenski
                        narod</hi><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve"> newspaper published an article titled </hi><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve">Only Slovenian Captions </hi><hi
                        style="font-size:12pt">[</hi><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:12pt">Samo
                        slovenske napise</hi><hi style="font-size:12pt">]: “Today at noon, our
                        people acted in accordance with self-help principles. In groups, they
                        approached, completely peacefully and with dignity, the shops of tradesmen
                        that have, until today, displayed bilingual captions. They demanded that the
                        owners remove them. Almost everywhere, this happened completely peacefully
                        and without any commotion.”</hi><note
                            place="foot" xml:id="ftn25" n="24"> “Samoslovenske napise,” <hi
                                rend="italic">Slovenski narod</hi>, 21 September 1908,
                        1.</note><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve"> After the German inscriptions on shops had been removed, Slovenians started boycotting German merchants and artisans. The Germans saw economic interests as the causes of the riots. German newspapers wrote that the most recent anti-German movement had been only an introduction to full-scale economic war.</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn26" n="25"> Dragan
                            Matić, <hi rend="italic">Nemci v Ljubljani 1848−1918</hi> (Ljubljana:
                            Oddelek za zgodovino Filozofske fakultete, 2002), 347−48.
                        </note><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve"> The Germans responded in kind: their newspapers, for example </hi><hi
                        rend="italic" style="font-size:12pt">Laibacher
                    Zeitung</hi><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve">, promoted purchases from German merchants exclusively. </hi></p>
                <p><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve">The September events were well-covered by the Slovenian press. Although the Catholic newspaper </hi><hi
                        rend="italic" style="font-size:12pt"
                        >Slovenec</hi><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve"> initially devoted less attention to the events in Ptuj, on 21 September, it published a special issue about the incidents and fatalities in Ljubljana. On the other hand, as early as on 14 September, the </hi><hi
                        rend="italic" style="font-size:12pt">Slovenski
                        narod</hi><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve"> newspaper reported about the events in Ptuj on the cover. </hi><hi
                        rend="italic" style="font-size:12pt">Slovenski
                        narod</hi><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve"> devoted its full attention to all the events taking place until the end of the month. Both newspapers supported and called for economic pressure and the “each to their own” action. Therefore, in the </hi><hi
                        rend="italic" style="font-size:12pt">Slovenski narod</hi><hi
                        style="font-size:12pt">, we can read the following: “The movement for the
                        Slovenian economic independence begins to spread. It must reach all facets
                        of society. Slovenian traders and craftsmen also need to take part in this
                        movement. […] They must avoid everything that strengthens their opponents.
                        Slovenian merchants and tradesmen who serve the German monetary institutions
                        should be held responsible for their unforgivable sin. […] Those who are
                        wrongly against this should be aware that we will stand up against them as
                        we stand against anybody who frequents German shops […] Slovenians, where is
                        your national pride?!”</hi><note
                            place="foot" xml:id="ftn27" n="26"> “Gibanje za gospodarsko osamosvoto,”
                                <hi rend="italic">Slovenski narod</hi>, 28 September 1908,
                        2.</note></p>
                <p><hi style="font-size:12pt">According to Dragan Matić, the September events in
                        Ljubljana were an unusual episode for the German population, which they
                        themselves had no influence on. According to the testimony of the Mayor of
                        Ljubljana Ivan Hribar, the unfortunate bullets that killed Lunder and Adamič
                        were fired on an officer’s orders. The blame for this was initially assigned
                        to the Provincial President Baron Teodor Schwarz, as he allowed the army to
                        fire warning shots.</hi><note place="foot"
                            xml:id="ftn28" n="27"> Matić, <hi rend="italic">Nemci v Ljubljani</hi>,
                            354.</note><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve"> On the other hand, the military authorities justified the use of weapons and considered it as absolutely legal. The blame that this happened at all, however, was ultimately attributed to the civil authorities, the inadequate and insensitive behaviour of the provincial presidency, and the political uncertainty of the city authorities, which concealed the fact that they had a severe problem with the military assistance and with Lt. Mayer, who arbitrarily used weapons. In this way, he did more harm than good and effectively assumed a decisive role in suppressing the demonstrations.</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn29" n="28"> Marjan
                            Matjašič, “Stališče vojaških oblasti do nemirov septembra 1908 v
                            Ljubljani,” <hi rend="italic">Kronika</hi>, 32, No. 1 (1984):
                        31</note>
                </p>
                <p><hi style="font-size:12pt">The profound and irreversible consequences of the
                        September events were felt everywhere. Although the broken windows in
                        Ljubljana were swiftly repaired and many offenders received monetary and
                        prison sentences, distrust and hatred between the Slovenian and German
                        people kept intensifying. Most of the changes took place in Ljubljana. One
                        of the examples was the city’s external appearance, which changed completely
                        and has been, since that time, completely Slovenian. The German and
                        bilingual inscriptions on shops disappeared and were replaced by Slovenian
                        signs exclusively. In Goropevšek’s opinion, the annexation of Bosnia and
                        Herzegovina a few weeks after the September events played a crucial role in
                        the fact that the September riots were promptly replaced by other topics,
                        including the momentous international political crisis that followed in the
                        subsequent months.</hi><note place="foot"
                            xml:id="ftn30" n="29"> Goropevšek, “Odmev in pomen,”
                    120.</note></p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>The Carniolan Savings Bank between the Slovenian-German political and national
                    struggles</head>
                <p><hi style="font-size:12pt">A long period of peace until the end of the 19</hi><hi
                        rend="superscript" style="font-size:12pt"
                        >th</hi><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve"> century had spurred on economic development, especially industry. However, the time after the turn of the century brought about increasing political tensions, both in Austro-Hungary and globally. The increasingly disturbing factors of the Monarchy’s economic development at the beginning of the 20</hi><hi
                        rend="superscript" style="font-size:12pt"
                        >th</hi><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve"> century included national tensions.</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn31" n="30"> Hedwig
                            Fritz, <hi rend="italic">150 Jahre Sparkassen in Österreich.
                                Geschichte</hi> (Wien: Sparkassenverl., 1972),
                        482−84.</note><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve"> During this period, the movements in the securities markets were significant. The Austro-Hungarian National Bank was forced to lower the interest rate due to the extensive supply of free capital. On the other hand, the time before the onset of World War I was marked by a growth in deposits, which remained steady even if considerably slower than in the previous period. There were several reasons for this. Initially, the founding activities of savings banks slowed down and diminished after, in general, reaching the greatest intensity between 1860 and 1880 in the Austrian part of the Monarchy.</hi><note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn32" n="31"> In Carniola, this process started
                        somewhat later, during the 1870s. − Žarko Lazarević and Jože Prinčič, <hi
                            rend="italic">Bančniki v ogledalu časa</hi>. <hi rend="italic"
                            >Življenjske poti slovenskih bančnikov v 19. in 20. stoletju</hi>
                        (Ljubljana: ZBS Združenje bank Slovenije, 2005), 41−42.
                        </note><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve"> Furthermore, the beginning of the 20</hi><hi
                        rend="superscript" style="font-size:12pt"
                        >th</hi><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve"> century brought about the rapid development of other financial institutions such as credit cooperatives, joint-stock companies, and banks.</hi><note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn33" n="32"> Fritz, <hi rend="italic">150 Jahre</hi>,
                        485−86. </note>
                </p>
                <p><hi style="font-size:12pt">In the Austro-Hungarian Monarchy, significant changes
                        of the credit system occurred between the turn of the century to the
                        beginning of World War I. In the new system, savings banks assumed a less
                        prominent position, while banks, joint-stock companies, and credit
                        cooperatives were given priority. They also developed more quickly than
                        savings banks. The savings activities of the population turned to the
                        long-term forms of saving, which yielded higher profits and were subject to
                        more favourable savings conditions.</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn34"
                        n="33"> Alois Brusatti, <hi rend="italic">Die Habsburgischermonarchie
                            1848−1918, Bd 1, Die Wirtschaftliche Entwicklung</hi> (Wien: Verlag der
                        Österreichischen Akademie der Wissenschaften, 1973), 363.</note></p>
                <p><hi style="font-size:12pt">The political and social differences between the
                        individual nations in the Austro-Hungarian Monarchy kept growing despite the
                        economic integration, which accelerated in the second half of the 19</hi><hi
                        rend="superscript" style="font-size:12pt"
                        >th</hi><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve"> century.</hi><note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn35" n="34"> Roman Sandgruber, <hi rend="italic"
                            >Ökonomie und Politik. Österreichische Wirtschaftsgeschichte vom
                            Mittelalter bis zur Gegenwart</hi> (Wien: Ueberreuter, 1995), 293,
                        311.</note><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve"> However, the Austro-German economic strength was not enough to dominate the huge empire, and a dialogue with the different nationalities was crucial. The most urgent task, however, was to bridge the huge gap between the urban, industrialised, and largely rural, traditional areas.</hi><note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn36" n="35"> Susanne Wurm, “The Development of
                        Austrian Financial Institutions in Central, Eastern and South-Eastern
                        Europe. Comparative European Economic History Studies,” <hi rend="italic"
                            >Working Paper Series</hi>, No. 31 (2006): 21, available at: <ref
                            target="http://citeseerx.ist.psu.edu/viewdoc/download?doi=10.1.1.527.9024&amp;rep=rep1&amp;type=pdf"
                                ><hi rend="Spletna_povezava"
                                >http://citeseerx.ist.psu.edu/viewdoc/download?doi=10.1.1.527.9024&amp;rep=rep1&amp;type=pdf</hi></ref>.</note></p>
                <p><hi style="font-size:12pt">In the beginning of the 1880s, Slovenian politicians
                        attempted to take control of the Carniolan Savings Bank. They wanted to
                        assume control, particularly in order to prevent its support of the German
                        cultural and other societies. Moreover, their aim was to prevent any
                        attempts at the establishment of a German system of people’s education,
                        which was one of the objectives of the Carniolan Savings Bank’s management.
                        Slovenian politicians endeavoured to establish a savings bank under the
                        control of the Provincial Assembly, in which Slovenians had a majority, but
                        failed. Simultaneously, there were tendencies to defend the
                        national-economic positions and institutions of Germans in Carniola. German
                        politicians strived to defend the Carniolan Savings Bank, which was
                        considered as the financial pillar of Germans in Carniola.</hi><note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn37" n="36"> Matić, <hi rend="italic">Nemci v
                            Ljubljani</hi>, 349. </note>
                </p>
                <p><hi style="font-size:12pt">In case of financial institutions, it was vital that
                        they had Slovenian leadership and management, as this was in the Slovenian
                        national interest. Otherwise, the institutions were placed on the opposite
                        end of the political and national spectrum, as was the case with the
                        Carniolan Savings Bank.</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn38" n="37"> Žarko
                        Lazarević, <hi rend="italic">Plasti prostora in časa. Iz gospodarske
                            zgodovine Slovenije prve polovice 20. stoletja</hi> (Ljubljana: Inštitut
                        za novejšo zgodovino, 2009),
                        315.</note><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve"> The Carniolan Savings Bank was not only considered as an economic but also the political symbol of German power in Carniola.</hi><note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn39" n="38"> Matić, <hi rend="italic">Nemci v
                            Ljubljani</hi>, 349. Lazarević and Prinčič, <hi rend="italic">Bančniki v
                            ogledalu časa</hi>, 41−42.
                    </note><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve"> In addition to the accusations that it had aligned with the German side, Slovenians reproached the Carniolan Savings Bank with ignoring the Slovenian institutions. This was one of the main reasons why, in the eyes of Slovenians, it continued to be seen as a German monetary institution. </hi></p>
                <p><hi style="font-size:12pt">Over the entire period from 1881 to 1914, the growth
                        of deposits in almost all savings banks reached an annual average of 4 to 5
                        %, with the exception of few individual savings banks, among them, in 1908,
                        the Carniolan Savings Bank. The overall development of savings banks was
                        particularly favourable in the years between 1908 and 1910, when growth in
                        the amount of 6 to 7 % was recorded.</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn40"
                        n="39"> Fritz, <hi rend="italic">150 Jahre</hi>,
                        486.</note><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve"> In 1908, the highest increase in deposits was recorded, amounting to K 316,594,440, which was 45.4 % more than the year before. In this year, almost 95 % of all savings banks in the Austrian part of the Monarchy recorded growth on the passive side of the balance sheet. The exception was the province of Carniola, where a decrease of about 4.5 % was recorded as a result of a </hi><hi
                        rend="italic" style="font-size:12pt"
                        >run</hi><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve"> on the Carniolan Savings Bank in Ljubljana. Apart from the Carniolan Savings Bank, all other monetary institutions in Carniola showed an increase in deposits.</hi><note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn41" n="40">
                        <hi rend="italic">Statistik der Sparkassen in den im Reichsrate Vertretenen
                            Königreichen und Ländern für das Jahr 1908. Bearbeitet von dem Bureau
                            der K. K. Statistischen Zentralkommision. XCI. Band, 3. Heft</hi> (Wien:
                        Aus der Kaiserlich-Königlichen Hof- und Staatsdrukerei, 1911),
                        XXVII−XXVIII.</note></p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>The bank run and boycott of the Carniolan Savings Bank in 1908 and 1909</head>
                <p><hi style="font-size:12pt">In the last decade before the outbreak of World War I,
                        in an extremely tense political situation, Slovenian politicians decided to
                        hinder the Carniolan Savings Bank’s activities. They encouraged massive
                        savings withdrawals and undermined the confidence in the Bank’s credibility
                        by spreading fabricated rumours of business irregularities and insolvency.
                        After the German inscriptions had been removed from the shops, a resolute
                        boycott of German merchants and the run on the Carniolan Savings Bank began.
                        Many people, especially from the countryside, kept withdrawing their savings
                        from the Carniolan Savings Bank day after day.</hi>
                    <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn42" n="41"> Matić, <hi rend="italic">Nemci v
                            Ljubljani</hi>, 439. Lazarević and Prinčič, <hi rend="italic">Bančniki v
                            ogledalu časa</hi>,
                        41−42.</note><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve"> The main reason for this reaction was the Carniolan Savings Bank’s reputation as a German monetary institution.</hi><note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn43" n="42"> Matić, <hi rend="italic">Nemci v
                            Ljubljani</hi>,
                        347.</note><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve"> Its management dedicated an entire section of the 1908 annual report to the September events: “First, we must remember the rush, which occurred in September against our institution. […] For no reason, a dishonest, defamatory, and hostile attack on the leadership of our institution was initiated – an insult to the memory of men who had gained innocent merits for our land, and no one yet dared to take their honour and honesty. They argued that our institution was no longer safe. […] The instigators walked from house to house to scare our investors, claiming that they would lose all of their money in our institution.”</hi><note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn44" n="43">
                        <hi rend="italic">Kranjska hranilnica v letu 1908</hi> (Ljubljana: Kleinmayr
                        &amp; Bamberg, 1909).</note></p>
                <p><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve">Slovenians were informed about “the bank run” by the liberal newspaper </hi><hi
                        rend="italic" style="font-size:12pt">Slovenski
                        narod</hi><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve">, which openly called for a boycott of the Carniolan Savings Bank and encouraged a swift response of Slovenian depositors, who were to withdraw their savings. Therefore, on 26 September 1908, an article titled </hi><hi
                        rend="italic" style="font-size:12pt">Važen gospodarski nasvet</hi>
                    <hi style="font-size:12pt">[</hi><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:12pt"
                        >Important Economic Advice</hi><hi style="font-size:12pt">] was published,
                        emphasising the possibility of monetary losses due to withdrawals during the
                        month. Furthermore, people could lose the right to collect interest rates.
                        In the article, special attention was paid to Slovenian readers, who were
                        warned that all Slovenian monetary institutions would be accepting account
                        ledgers belonging to the Carniolan Savings Bank. These Slovenian
                        institutions also offered the potential depositors to withdraw cash from the
                        old account ledgers or to provide them with new account ledgers in the
                        amount of their accounts at the Carniolan Savings Bank.</hi><note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn45" n="44"> “Važen gospodarski nasvet,” <hi
                            rend="italic">Slovenski narod</hi>, 26 September 1908, No. 225,
                        4.</note>
                </p>
                <p><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve">On 8 October 1908, the Carniolan Provincial Government published a report in </hi><hi
                        rend="italic" style="font-size:12pt">the Laibacher Zeitung</hi><hi
                        style="font-size:12pt">, signed by Count Ludovik Marquis de Gozani,
                        Councillor and Provincial Commissioner of the Carniolan Savings Bank, and
                        Janko Kremenšek, the Regional Government Councillor. The report discloses
                        the findings of the audit that the Carniolan Savings Bank carried out
                        pursuant to the law, and the savings deposits were as safe as possible. Any
                        fear of losses was therefore unjustified and unfounded.</hi>
                    <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn46" n="45"> Matić, <hi rend="italic">Nemci v
                            Ljubljani</hi>,
                        349.</note><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve"> Naturally, the Carniolan Savings Bank was not happy that the official state institutions examined its business: it confirmed that it had not found any realistic reasons for the fear of the depositors, which had spread among the people.</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn47" n="46">
                            Lazarević and Prinčič, <hi rend="italic">Bančniki v ogledalu časa</hi>,
                            42.</note><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve"> On 15 October 1908, the </hi><hi
                        rend="italic" style="font-size:12pt">Slovenski
                        narod</hi><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve"> newspaper published what was, according to the author, an expert article about the final account and the annual report of the Carniolan Savings Bank for the business year 1907. The author paid special attention to the audit, which was, in his opinion, completely inadequate. It was disputable that the authorities had only spent a single day on reviewing all of the Carniolan Savings Bank’s books. In addition, the author considered the official statement by the Government Commissioner of the Carniolan Savings Bank Count Gozani and the regional government official Kremenšek. Again, the time they had spent to prepare and write their reviews of the business books in the first half of 1908 was questionable and too short. Based on these arguments, the author of the article concluded that both the audit and the inspection carried out by government representatives were completely unprofessional. Most of all, he was disturbed by the fact that the review was not carried out by Slovenian experts.</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn48" n="47">
                            “Kranjska hranilnica,” <hi rend="italic">Slovenski narod</hi>, 15
                            October 1908, 1.</note></p>
                <p><hi style="font-size:12pt">On 20 October 1908, the management of the Carniolan
                        Savings Bank convened an extraordinary session of the General Assembly of
                        their Association because of the situation followed by the wave of
                        accelerated deposit withdrawals. Ottomar Bamberg, the president of the
                        Carniolan Savings Bank, informed the members of the delicate situation and
                        the condition of the funds invested in the Savings Bank. Between 19
                        September and 19 October 1908, a million crowns had been deposited, while
                        the Bank had been forced to pay out more than 6 million crowns, which meant
                        that the amount of deposits had decreased by 7.5 % in a single month. To
                        cover the difference, the Bank used cash, credits, and a portion of the
                        state securities. Bamberg recalled all the previous crises and tried to
                        reassure the members of the Association with the fact that even if the
                        depositors took out all money, the Bank would still have a reserve fund of 9
                        million crowns at its disposal. He concluded his speech optimistically with
                        the following words: “Excessive withdrawals have caused some inconvenience,
                        but this is merely transient.”</hi><note
                            place="foot" xml:id="ftn49" n="48"> SI AS 437, f. 10, Ottomar Bamberg,
                            Geehrte Generalversammlung!, 20 October 1908, 1−2. Matić, <hi
                                rend="italic">Nemci v Ljubljani</hi>, 352.</note>
                </p>
                <p><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve">The article that followed the extraordinary session of the General Assembly of the Carniolan Savings Bank Association, published in the </hi><hi
                        rend="italic" style="font-size:12pt">Slovenski narod</hi>
                    <hi style="font-size:12pt">newspaper on 30 October 1908, underlined the
                        following: “The Carniolan Savings Bank counts on the fact that the deposits
                        would not be repaid and that the management knows how to handle the
                        situation by employing certain new business tactics they deem
                        appropriate.”</hi><note place="foot"
                            xml:id="ftn50" n="49"> “Kranjska hranilnica,” <hi rend="italic"
                                >Slovenski narod</hi>, 30 October 1908, 1.</note>
                    <hi style="font-size:12pt">The author of this comment devoted special attention
                        to the Carniolan Savings Bank’s credit policy of mortgaging loans issued in
                        Carniola. The problem arose as soon as the Savings Bank started cancelling
                        this type of loans in the province of Carniola. In the author’s opinion, the
                        Savings Bank violated the provisions of § 17 of its Regulations, according
                        to which it was obligated to first collect all of the loans issued in other
                        parts of the Monarchy.</hi>
                    <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn51" n="50">
                            Ibid.</note></p>
                <p><hi style="font-size:12pt">The money that the Carniolan Savings Bank had to pay
                        out to its depositors between October 1908 and June 1909 far exceeded all of
                        its available cash. Deposits had been in decline for several years. In
                        addition, the sale of securities had not satisfied the growing demand.
                        Therefore, the Savings Bank stopped approving new loans and started
                        realising mortgages and municipal loans – not merely in Carniola, but in the
                        other parts of the Monarchy as well. In order to secure money without
                        compromising its reserve fund, the Savings Bank started selling its real
                        estate.</hi><note place="foot"
                            xml:id="ftn52" n="51"> SI AS 437, f. 38 Zgodovina hranilnice od 1909 do
                            1918, 1.</note></p>
                <p><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:12pt">Table 1</hi><hi style="font-size:12pt">.
                        The mortgage loans of Carniolan Savings Bank from 1901 until 1913</hi></p>
                <table rend="rules">
                    <row>
                        <cell rend="center"
                            ><hi rend="bold" style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve">Year </hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="center" cols="3"><hi rend="bold" style="font-size:12pt">Mortgage
                                loans for the province of Carniola at a lower interest
                            rate</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="center" cols="3"><hi rend="bold" style="font-size:12pt">Mortgage
                                loans for the province of Carniola at the regular interest
                            rate</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="center" cols="3"
                            ><hi rend="bold" style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve">Mortgage loans for other provinces </hi></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell rend="left"/>
                        <cell rend="left"><hi style="font-size:12pt">New loans</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="left"><hi style="font-size:12pt">Refunded amount</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="left"><hi style="font-size:12pt">At the end of year</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="left"><hi style="font-size:12pt">New loans</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="left"><hi style="font-size:12pt">Refunded amount</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="left"><hi style="font-size:12pt">At the end of year</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="left"><hi style="font-size:12pt">New loans</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="left"><hi style="font-size:12pt">Refunded amount</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="left"><hi style="font-size:12pt">At the end of year</hi></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell rend="center"><hi style="font-size:12pt">1901</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="right"><hi style="font-size:12pt">3,360</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="right"><hi style="font-size:12pt">30,294</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="right"><hi style="font-size:12pt">715,402</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="right"><hi style="font-size:12pt">651,561</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="right"><hi style="font-size:12pt">434,442</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="right"><hi style="font-size:12pt">12,613,015</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="right"><hi style="font-size:12pt">10,000</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="right"><hi style="font-size:12pt">1,088,638</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="right"><hi style="font-size:12pt">17,759,443</hi></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell rend="center"><hi style="font-size:12pt">1902</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="right"><hi style="font-size:12pt">2,650</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="right"><hi style="font-size:12pt">38,286</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="right"><hi style="font-size:12pt">639,766</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="right"><hi style="font-size:12pt">1,100,581</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="right"><hi style="font-size:12pt">600,193</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="right"><hi style="font-size:12pt">13,233,609</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="right"><hi style="font-size:12pt">1,893,007</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="right"><hi style="font-size:12pt">845,274</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="right"><hi style="font-size:12pt">18,807,178</hi></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell rend="center"><hi style="font-size:12pt">1903</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="right"><hi style="font-size:12pt">400</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="right"><hi style="font-size:12pt">36,402</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="right"><hi style="font-size:12pt">603,764</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="right"><hi style="font-size:12pt">918,020</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="right"><hi style="font-size:12pt">437,171</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="right"><hi style="font-size:12pt">13,714,458</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="right"><hi style="font-size:12pt">1,090,592</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="right"><hi style="font-size:12pt">1,044,626</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="right"><hi style="font-size:12pt">18,853,091</hi></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell rend="center"><hi style="font-size:12pt">1904</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="right"><hi style="font-size:12pt">1,600</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="right"><hi style="font-size:12pt">26,995</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="right"><hi style="font-size:12pt">578,369</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="right"><hi style="font-size:12pt">907,026</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="right"><hi style="font-size:12pt">490,367</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="right"><hi style="font-size:12pt">14,131,117</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="right"><hi style="font-size:12pt">5,523,000</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="right"><hi style="font-size:12pt">2,387,799</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="right"><hi style="font-size:12pt">21,988,340</hi></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell rend="center"><hi style="font-size:12pt">1905</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="right"><hi style="font-size:12pt">800</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="right"><hi style="font-size:12pt">30,233</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="right"><hi style="font-size:12pt">548,935</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="right"><hi style="font-size:12pt">616,569</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="right"><hi style="font-size:12pt">529,356</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="right"><hi style="font-size:12pt">14,218,329</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="right"><hi style="font-size:12pt">2,125,570</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="right"><hi style="font-size:12pt">1,894,714</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="right"><hi style="font-size:12pt">22,219,194</hi></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell rend="center"><hi style="font-size:12pt">1906</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="right"><hi style="font-size:12pt">2,600</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="right"><hi style="font-size:12pt">32,194</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="right"><hi style="font-size:12pt">519,341</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="right"><hi style="font-size:12pt">1,429,118</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="right"><hi style="font-size:12pt">802,606</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="right"><hi style="font-size:12pt">14,844,840</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="right"><hi style="font-size:12pt">1,622,974</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="right"><hi style="font-size:12pt">1,328,927</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="right"><hi style="font-size:12pt">22,513,242</hi></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell rend="center"><hi style="font-size:12pt">1907</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="right"><hi style="font-size:12pt">5,140</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="right"><hi style="font-size:12pt">32,887</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="right"><hi style="font-size:12pt">491,594</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="right"><hi style="font-size:12pt">1,294,200</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="right"><hi style="font-size:12pt">832,736</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="right"><hi style="font-size:12pt">15,306,304</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="right"><hi style="font-size:12pt">287,625</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="right"><hi style="font-size:12pt">784,388</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="right"><hi style="font-size:12pt">22,016,476</hi></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell rend="center"><hi style="font-size:12pt">1908</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="right"><hi style="font-size:12pt">300</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="right"><hi style="font-size:12pt">31,577</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="right"><hi style="font-size:12pt">460,316</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="right"><hi style="font-size:12pt">730,333</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="right"><hi style="font-size:12pt">644,617</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="right"><hi style="font-size:12pt">15,392,020</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="right"><hi style="font-size:12pt">19,000</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="right"><hi style="font-size:12pt">1,680,469</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="right"><hi style="font-size:12pt">20,355,004</hi></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell rend="center"><hi style="font-size:12pt">1909</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="right"><hi style="font-size:12pt">2,066</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="right"><hi style="font-size:12pt">24,411</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="right"><hi style="font-size:12pt">437,971</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="right"><hi style="font-size:12pt">486,873</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="right"><hi style="font-size:12pt">1,927,275</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="right"><hi style="font-size:12pt">13,951,618</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="right"><hi style="font-size:12pt">5,000</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="right"><hi style="font-size:12pt">14,032,095</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="right"><hi style="font-size:12pt">6,327,910</hi></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell rend="center"><hi style="font-size:12pt">1910</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="right"><hi style="font-size:12pt">2,000</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="right"><hi style="font-size:12pt">16,960</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="right"><hi style="font-size:12pt">423,011</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="right"><hi style="font-size:12pt">1,169,187</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="right"><hi style="font-size:12pt">462,659</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="right"><hi style="font-size:12pt">14,658,146</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="center"><hi style="font-size:12pt">/</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="right"><hi style="font-size:12pt">896,196</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="right"><hi style="font-size:12pt">5,431,713</hi></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell rend="center"><hi style="font-size:12pt">1911</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="right"><hi style="font-size:12pt">1,000</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="right"><hi style="font-size:12pt">24,226</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="right"><hi style="font-size:12pt">399,785</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="right"><hi style="font-size:12pt">1,078,558</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="right"><hi style="font-size:12pt">440,104</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="right"><hi style="font-size:12pt">15,296,600</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="center"><hi style="font-size:12pt">/</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="right"><hi style="font-size:12pt">440,553</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="right"><hi style="font-size:12pt">4,991,159</hi></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell rend="center"><hi style="font-size:12pt">1912</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="right"><hi style="font-size:12pt">1,000</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="right"><hi style="font-size:12pt">15,516</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="right"><hi style="font-size:12pt">385,268</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="right"><hi style="font-size:12pt">689,760</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="right"><hi style="font-size:12pt">517,835</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="right"><hi style="font-size:12pt">15,468,525</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="center"><hi style="font-size:12pt">/</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="right"><hi style="font-size:12pt">326,781</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="right"><hi style="font-size:12pt">4,664,378</hi></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell rend="center"><hi style="font-size:12pt">1913</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="right"><hi style="font-size:12pt">2,000</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="right"><hi style="font-size:12pt">26,824</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="right"><hi style="font-size:12pt">360,444</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="right"><hi style="font-size:12pt">604,600</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="right"><hi style="font-size:12pt">614,078</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="right"><hi style="font-size:12pt">15,459,046</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="center"><hi style="font-size:12pt">/</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="right"><hi style="font-size:12pt">141,040</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="right"><hi style="font-size:12pt">4,523,337</hi></cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p style="text-align:center;">Source: <hi rend="italic">Rechnungs–Abschluss der
                        krainischen Sparkasse des Jahres 1901−1913</hi></p>
                <p><hi style="font-size:12pt">The statistics indicate how successfully the Carniolan
                        Savings Bank discharged obligations from debtors who lived outside Carniola.
                        Table 1 shows the level of mortgage loans for the debtors from Carniola with
                        the regular interest rate that remained at the same level in 1908 as in the
                        previous years. A major change occurred in 1909, as the approved loans
                        amounted to only 25 % of the discharged obligations. Although the level
                        decreased by 9 % at the end of 1909, in the following years, fluctuations in
                        this section were less frequent, since the Savings Bank granted more newly
                        approved loans. At the end of the year, the balance reached the pre-crisis
                        level. However, the amount of discharged obligations for all those who lived
                        in the other parts of the Monarchy peaked in 1909, when 14 million crowns
                        were paid to the Carniolan Savings Bank. At the end of the year, the amount
                        reached only 31 % of the one from the previous year. During the next few
                        years, the Carniolan Savings Bank did not approve new mortgage loans to
                        people from the other parts of Austro-Hungarian Monarchy.</hi>
                    <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn53" n="52">
                            <hi rend="italic">Kranjska hranilnica v Ljubljani v letu 1909</hi>
                            (Ljubljana: Kleinmayr &amp; Bamberg, 1910).</note></p>
                <p><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve">One of the leaders of the struggle against the Carniolan Savings Bank was Ivan Hribar, who approved the scandalous articles in the </hi><hi
                        rend="italic" style="font-size:12pt">Slovenski
                        narod</hi><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve"> newspaper and submit the interpellation in the Imperial Council in December 1908.</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn54" n="53"> Matić,
                                <hi rend="italic">Nemci v Ljubljani</hi>, 352.</note>
                    <hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve">Hribar first spoke about the Carniolan Savings Bank in the Imperial Council on 4 December 1908. On this occasion, he submitted an interpellation against the head of the Ministry of Justice because of the retraction of articles and notices in the </hi><hi
                        rend="italic" style="font-size:12pt">Slovenski
                        narod</hi><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve"> newspaper, discussing various topics regarding the Carniolan Savings Bank. His speech was published in the same newspaper; while later, all the articles presented by him at the December session were published in a special brochure.</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn55" n="54"> Ivan
                            Hribar, <hi rend="italic">Kranjska hranilnica</hi> (Ljubljana: Narodna
                            Tiskarna, 1909), 1−23.</note>
                </p>
                <p><hi style="font-size:12pt">On the provincial level, Dr Ivan Oražen held speeches
                        against the Savings Bank in the Carniolan Provincial Assembly in January
                        1909. A very heated debate developed at the seventh session of the Carniolan
                        Provincial Assembly on 15 January 1909. Dr Ivan Oražen collected and
                        presented all the arguments against the Savings Bank, mentioned until that
                        moment. He spoke about the inadequate security of deposits and the reserve
                        fund; the exchange rate loses because of the unsuitable real estate
                        investment policy; and about the lack of government control over the
                        business operations of the Carniolan Savings Bank. He was particularly
                        disturbed by the distribution of its net income, mostly intended for German
                        institutions and German national interests. Provincial President Baron
                        Schwarz and Josef Schwegel spoke at the session as well. They defended the
                        Carniolan Savings Bank and tried to justify its operations.</hi>
                    <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn56" n="55">
                            <hi rend="italic">Stenografični zapisnik sedme seje deželnega zbora
                                kranjskega v Ljubljani dne 15. januarja 1909</hi>, 199, 201–04,
                            available at: <ref
                                target="https://www.dlib.si/stream/URN:NBN:SI:doc-UUJMEUO1/590bbe26-3404-4471-833e-6111ceabb8b2/PDF"
                                    ><hi rend="Spletna_povezava"
                                    >https://www.dlib.si/stream/URN:NBN:SI:doc-UUJMEUO1/590bbe26-3404-4471-833e-6111ceabb8b2/PDF</hi></ref><hi
                                rend="Spletna_povezava">.</hi></note></p>
                <p><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve">Shortly thereafter, on 24 January 1909, Dr Oražen once again spoke about the Carniolan Savings Bank at a meeting in the Town Home in response to the Savings Bank representatives who had prepared comments on his exhaustive speech in the Carniolan Provincial Assembly. The management of the Carniolan Savings Bank published an article titled </hi><hi
                        rend="italic" style="font-size:12pt"
                        >Erklärung</hi><hi rend="Footnote_Characters" xml:space="preserve"> </hi><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve">(Explanation) in the </hi><hi
                        rend="italic" style="font-size:12pt">Laibacher Zeitung</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn57" n="56">
                            “Erklärung,” <hi rend="italic">Laibacher Zeitung</hi>, 22 January 1909,
                            147−48.</note><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve"> newspaper, rejecting all accusations against the Savings Bank. Afterwards, the article was translated and published in the Slovenian language in a special brochure.</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn58" n="57">
                            <hi rend="italic">V pojasnilo</hi> (Ljubljana: Kleinmayr &amp; Bamberg,
                            1909), 1−8.
                        </note><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve"> In his speech in the Town Home, Dr Oražen once again listed all the complaints against the Savings Bank but did not present any new arguments. He therefore concluded the speech with the following words: “However, it remains unfortunate that the Carniolan Savings Bank is an association of 65 members, harmful to us and our political life.”</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn59" n="58">
                            Hribar, <hi rend="italic">Kranjska hranilnica</hi>,
                        40.</note><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve"> The </hi><hi
                        rend="italic" style="font-size:12pt">Slovenski narod</hi>
                    <hi style="font-size:12pt">newspaper published the speech on the following day,
                        but it had to be retracted. The retraction of the article caused Ivan Hribar
                        to submit a new interpellation at a session of the Imperial Council on 29
                        January 1909. The text of Oražen’s speech at the Town Home can also be found
                        in the aforementioned brochure containing the articles that Ivan Hribar had
                        submitted during the interpellation at the December session of the Imperial
                        Council in 1908.</hi><note place="foot"
                            xml:id="ftn60" n="59"> Ibid., 36−40.</note>
                </p>
                <figure>
                    <head>Chart 1: Deposits of the Carniolan Savings Bank from 1901 to 1913</head>
                    <graphic url="chart1.jpg" height="700px"/>
                    <p><hi style="text-align:center">Source: <hi rend="italic">Statistik der
                                Sparkassen in den im Reichsrate Vertretenen Königreichen und Ländern
                                für das Jahr (1901−1913)</hi></hi></p>
                </figure>
                <p><hi style="font-size:12pt">The following months were more peaceful: even the</hi>
                    <hi rend="italic" style="font-size:12pt">Slovenski narod</hi>
                    <hi style="font-size:12pt">newspaper refrained from publishing any more articles
                        analysing the business operations of the Carniolan Savings Bank. It did not
                        write about the Carniolan Savings Bank again until after its regular General
                        Assembly session of 15 April 1909. The newspapers containing the article
                        discussing the annual report of Carniolan Savings Bank were retracted, which
                        resulted in Ivan Hribar’s new interpellation against the Minister of
                        Justice. At the April session, the Savings Bank’s management adopted the
                        annual report and final annual account for the business year of 1908. In his
                        report, President Bamberg mentioned that the amount of money invested in the
                        Savings Bank had decreased to 52,656,217 crowns at the end of 1908, which
                        was 22.27 % less in comparison with the previous year. He tried to improve
                        the morale with the fact that accelerated withdrawals had actually increased
                        the security of savings of the depositors who had not withdrawn their money
                        from the Savings Bank. Furthermore, he pointed out that the reserve fund had
                        remained untouched.</hi><note place="foot"
                            xml:id="ftn61" n="60">
                            <hi rend="italic">Kranjska hranilnica v letu 1908</hi>. Matić, <hi
                                rend="italic">Nemci v Ljubljani</hi>, 353.</note>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>The impact of the bank run and boycott on the business of the Carniolan
                    Savings Bank</head>
                <p><hi style="font-size:12pt">The chart showing the comparison of the number of
                        newly issued and paid off savings booklets best illustrates the bank run and
                        boycott of the Carniolan Savings Bank. Although the number of newly issued
                        booklets had been declining since the beginning of the 20</hi><hi
                        rend="superscript" style="font-size:12pt"
                    >th</hi><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve"> century, the biggest difference occurred in 1908, followed by 1909, when the number of paid off savings booklets far exceeded that of the newly issued ones. </hi></p>
                <figure>
                    <head>Chart 2: Changes of the number of newly issued and paid off savings
                        booklets of the Carniolan Savings Bank</head>
                    <graphic url="chart2.jpg" height="700px"/>
                    <p><hi style="text-align:center">Source: <hi rend="italic">Statistik der
                                Sparkassen in den im Reichsrate Vertretenen Königreichen und Ländern
                                für das Jahr (1901−1913)</hi></hi></p>
                </figure>
                <p><hi style="font-size:12pt">Although the decline in the number of newly issued
                        account ledgers in the case of the Carniolan Savings Bank is a good
                        indicator of the influence of the bank run and boycott of 1908 and 1909 on
                        the Savings Bank’s operations, the trend of the number of account ledgers is
                        not necessarily an indicator of a decrease of money invested in a savings
                        bank. During the period under consideration, there were 12 regulatory
                        savings banks operating in the province of Carniola. In addition to the
                        Carniolan Savings Bank, two more had fewer newly issued savings ledgers than
                        the liquidated ones in 1908 and 1909. The Kočevje Savings Bank had 37 more
                        closed accounts, and yet this had no effect on the amount of the received
                        deposits. In the Kranj Savings Bank, the number of closed deposit accounts
                        exceeded that of newly opened ones by 289 and the bank in question received
                        less money from depositors, but the deficit was covered with capitalised
                        interests.</hi><note place="foot"
                            xml:id="ftn62" n="61">
                            <hi rend="italic">Statistik der Sparkassen für das Jahr 1908</hi>, 6,
                            22.</note></p>
                <figure>
                    <head>Chart 3: The ratio between the inflow of deposits and deposit withdrawals
                        in the province of Carniola</head>
                    <graphic url="chart2.jpg" height="700px"/>
                    <p><hi style="text-align:center">Source: Source: <hi rend="italic">Statistik der
                                Sparkassen in den im Reichsrate Vertretenen Königreichen und Ländern
                                für das Jahr 1908</hi></hi></p>
                </figure>
                <p><hi style="font-size:12pt">The 1908 official statistical report of the Austrian
                        Statistical Office discussed the deposit increases and decreases in Carniola
                        specifically. The report also includes a spreadsheet listing, on the one
                        hand, all savings banks in the province of Carniola with a positive balance
                        between received and paid out money; and, on the other hand, the Carniolan
                        Savings Bank. The Carniolan Savings Bank experienced a loss of more than 15
                        million crowns or 22.27 %, while the other savings banks in that province
                        recorded an increase in deposits of more than 10 million crowns or 22.42
                        %.</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn63"
                            n="62"> Ibid.,
                        XXVII.</note><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve"> The author of the report emphasised that the level of deposits in Carniola, decreased by more than 5 million crowns or 4.46 %, had resulted from the run on the Carniolan Savings Bank.</hi><note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn64" n="63"> Ibid.</note></p>
                <p><hi style="font-size:12pt">The management of the Carniolan Savings Bank found
                        that investing in mortgage loans was no longer profitable. Moreover, this
                        money was less liquid and did not provide security during unpredictable
                        events. The management was aware that the Savings Bank needed to invest an
                        adequate part of its deposits in simple and highly liquid assets. At the
                        extraordinary meeting of the General Assembly of the society of the
                        Carniolan Savings Bank on 20 October 1908, President Bamberg discussed the
                        solutions in case of new attacks. He suggested the following: “</hi><hi
                        rend="italic" style="font-size:12pt">Changes in business policy are
                        necessary; we need to take care of greater investments in goods because our
                        investments in real estate exceeded the usual 60 % and reached 63 %. We have
                        to reduce mortgage loans</hi><hi style="font-size:12pt">.”</hi><note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn65" n="64"> SI AS 437, f. 10, Ottomar Bamberg,
                        “Geehrte Generalversammlung!” 20 October 1908, 3.
                    </note><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve"> For these reasons, the Savings Bank decided to change its investment policy. As the chart shows, the Savings Bank prioritised investments in government securities, which exceeded the mortgage credit investments. </hi></p>
                <figure>
                    <head>Chart 4: Comparison of the amount of money invested in mortgage loans and
                        securities</head>
                    <graphic url="chart2.jpg" height="700px"/>
                    <p><hi style="text-align:center">Source: Source: <hi rend="italic"
                                >Rechnungs–Abschluss der krainischen Sparkasse des Jahres
                                1901−1913</hi></hi></p>
                </figure>
                <p><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve">In order to secure money without compromising its reserve fund, the Carniolan Savings Bank started selling its real estate. It sold the building of the </hi><hi
                        rend="italic" style="font-size:12pt">old shooting
                        range</hi><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve"> in Ljubljana in 1910, while in the following year, it sold its houses in Trieste.</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn66" n="65"> SI AS
                            437, f. 38 Zgodovina hranilnice od 1909 do 1918,
                        1−2.</note><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve"> At the regular General Assembly on 29 June 1909, it adopted the decision to increase the deposit interest rate from 4 % to 4.5 %. The aim of this measure was to attract as many new depositors as possible. Notwithstanding, the measure did not achieve much success because it other financial institutions soon followed suit, including the Carniolan Savings Bank’s biggest competitor: the Ljubljana City Savings Bank.</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn67" n="66">
                            <hi rend="italic">Kranjska hranilnica v Ljubljani v letu 1909</hi>. AS
                            437, f. 38 Zgodovina hranilnice od 1909 do 1918, 1−2.</note></p>
                <p><hi style="font-size:12pt">The liquidation of the Carniolan Savings Bank’s
                        pawnshop was a measure taken by the Savings Bank as a response to the
                        boycott in 1908 and 1909. The decision to dissolve it was adopted at an
                        extraordinary General Assembly session of 20 October 1908.</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn68" n="67">
                            “Auflassung des Pfandamtes der Krainische Sparkasse,” <hi rend="italic"
                                >Laibacher Zeitung</hi>, 7 November 1908,
                        2358.</note><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve"> During its existence, the Carniolan Savings Bank established several institutions with various charitable purposes. The first of these was a pawnshop, which started operating in 1835. This institution functioned until 1910 when it was finally liquidated as a consequence of the 1908 boycott. The pawnshop had opened for business on 4 November 1835, on the 15</hi><hi
                        rend="superscript" style="font-size:12pt"
                        >th</hi><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve"> anniversary of the Carniolan Savings Bank. The Savings Bank had unused money that remained in the cash register. Therefore, the management decided to use that money to establish a special pawnshop. The purpose of this institution was to act for the public good, especially for the benefit of the poorest inhabitants of Carniola.</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn69" n="68"> SI AS
                            437, f. 38, Ustanovitev Kranjske hranilnice,
                        11–12.</note><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve"> The pawnshops, financed by savings banks, enabled the most deprived to escape the clutches of moneylenders to whom they paid exorbitant interest rates.</hi><note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn70" n="69"> Francisco Comin, “Historical Roots of
                        the Social Commitment of Savings Banks in Spain − From Charity to Corporate
                        Social Responsibility (1835−2002). The 9<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>
                        European Symposium on Savings Banks History, European Savings Banks: From
                        Social Commitment to Corporate Social Responsibility, Madrid 4−5 May 2006,”
                            <hi rend="italic">Perspectives</hi>, No. 55 (2007): 29, available at:
                            <ref
                            target="https://www.wsbi-esbg.org/SiteCollectionDocuments/Perspectives%2055.pdf"
                            >https://www.wsbi-esbg.org/SiteCollectionDocuments/Perspectives%2055.pdf</ref>.</note><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve"> During the first years of its operation, the pawnshop showed a considerable annual turnover. For this reason and because it protected people from usury, it quickly became popular among the poorer social strata. Nevertheless, the expectations of the Savings Banks’ management that the loans they gave to the pawnshop would turn a profit were not fulfilled. The expenditures of the pawnshop exceeded its income, and the Savings Bank had to cover this loss from its own income.</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn71" n="70">
                            <hi rend="italic">Kranjska hranilnica v Ljubljani 1910</hi> (Ljubljana:
                            Kleinmayr &amp; Bamberg
                        1911).</note><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve"> The pawnshop operated with loss until 1896, and then started showing a slight profit as of 1897. The profit was very modest and insufficient to cover employee salaries.</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn72" n="71"> SI AS
                            437, f. 10, Ausserordentliche Generalversammlung vom 20. Oktober 1908,
                            No. 3989, Antrag wegen Auflassung des Pfandamts.
                        </note><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve"> As of 1 December 1908, the pawnshop no longer accepted items, and the liquidation of this institution was completed on 1 January 1910.</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn73" n="72"> SI AS
                            437, f. 38 Zgodovina hranilnice od 1909 do 1918,
                        3.</note><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve"> The response of the </hi><hi
                        rend="italic" style="font-size:12pt">Slovenski
                        narod</hi><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve"> newspaper to the decision of the Carniolan Savings Bank to close the pawnshop was very negative. The article published on 25 May 1909 stated the following: “The Carniolan Savings Bank eliminated the pawnshop simply to prevent the people who had broken the windows of the institution’s building from getting anything from it.”</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn74" n="73">
                            “Renitetna hranilnica,” <hi rend="italic">Slovenski narod</hi>, 25 May
                            1909,
                        2.</note><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve"> The Ljubljana Municipal Council established its own pawnshop, which opened on 1 December 1909 as a response to this move of the Carniolan Savings Bank.</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn75" n="74">
                            “Ljubljanski občinski svet. Poročila personalnega in pravnega odseka,”
                                <hi rend="italic">Slovenski narod</hi>, 21 July 1909, 3.
                            “Ljubljanski občinski svet. Mestna zastavljalnica,” <hi rend="italic"
                                >Slovenski narod</hi>, 9 December 1909, 2.</note></p>
                <p><hi style="font-size:12pt">Every year, the Carniolan Savings Bank would dedicate
                        a certain amount to various institutions from its net profit. In the very
                        tough circumstances, the peak of the September 1908 events brought a
                        significant change. Under pressure, the Savings Bank decided to only donate
                        money to those who remained loyal to it.</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn76" n="75">
                            <hi rend="italic">Kranjska hranilnica v Ljubljani v letu
                            1908</hi>.</note><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve"> However, the donations were only reduced in 1909, which was a direct consequence of the boycott. In the next year, they returned to the pre-crisis levels. Nevertheless, in the following years, the Carniolan Savings Bank provided the highest support to German institutions such as the Philharmonic Society in Ljubljana, the Theaterverein, the German kindergartens in Ljubljana, Tržič, Zagorje, and Kočevje, and to the Kranj section of the German Mountain Society.</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn77" n="76"> SI AS
                            437, f. 38, Zgodovina hranilnice od 1909 do 1918, 3−4.</note>
                </p>
                <p><hi style="font-size:12pt">At the General Assembly on 30 December 1909, the
                        management of the Society of the Carniolan Savings Bank made a decision to
                        change the inscription on the building: since then, it was in the Slovenian
                        language. Moreover, it started publishing its annual reports in the
                        Slovenian language. Nevertheless, this financial institution was still
                        considered as the German financial pillar in the province of Carniola and
                        would continue to be seen as such until the very disintegration of the
                        Austro-Hungarian Monarchy in 1918.</hi><note
                            place="foot" xml:id="ftn78" n="77"> Ibid., 5.</note></p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Conclusion </head>
                <p><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve">The Carniolan Savings Bank found itself entangled in the Slovenian-German conflicts. It had to deal with considerable pressures as well as an extensive run on its deposits after the national struggles had culminated in September 1908. The 1908 crisis was a local phenomenon in the province of Carniola, starting with the news of the Carniolan Savings Bank’s insolvency. Bank runs were a common feature of crises and played a prominent role in monetary history: deposit withdrawals were a common reaction of the population during the periods of insecurity. The Carniolan Savings Bank strived to restore the trust of its clients while at the same time attempting to hedge its deposits in times of high risk. Based on its rulebook, a savings bank could refuse to pay out higher amounts; however, the Carniolan Savings Bank always tried to be consistent and satisfy all the demands of its depositors. It wanted to ensure the security of its business and invested money. </hi></p>
                <p><hi style="font-size:12pt">With the September events and the subsequent boycott
                        affecting the operations of the Carniolan Savings Bank, 1908 was a turning
                        point in many aspects. Although the management of this financial institution
                        tried to be more accessible for the Slovenian part of the population by
                        publishing materials in the Slovenian language, the institution was
                        nevertheless closed on several levels. This was confirmed with the
                        orientation of its charitable activities only to “those who remained loyal
                        to them” and did not encroach on the money invested in the Savings Bank.
                        Still, the Carniolan Savings Bank retained its leading position in Carniola
                        in almost all business segments, especially regarding the investments in
                        government securities and the high amount of its reserve fund. On the other
                        hand, the Ljubljana City Savings Bank got closer with the money gained from
                        the depositors, while the City municipality opened its own pawnshop.
                        However, it is very difficult to estimate how much damage the Carniolan
                        Savings Bank actually suffered in the long term. The numbers confirm that it
                        recovered very quickly after the massive withdrawals had stopped in the
                        second half of 1909. Nevertheless, only a few years afterwards – in 1912 and
                        1913 – a new crisis started in the Balkans, while World War I, in
                        particular, brought new challenges and even more radical changes.</hi></p>
            </div>

        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="biblography">
                <head>Literature and Sources</head>

                <list type="unordered">
                    <head><hi style="font-size:10pt">Archive material:</hi></head>
                    <item><hi style="font-size:10pt">SI AS, Arhiv Republike Slovenije / Archive of
                            Republic Slovenia:</hi><list>
                            <item><hi style="font-size:10pt">SI AS 437 − Hranilnica Dravske
                                    banovine.</hi>
                            </item>
                        </list></item>
                    <item><hi style="font-size:10pt">SI_ZAL_LJU, Zgodovinski arhiv Ljubljana /
                            Historical Archive Ljubljana:</hi>
                        <list type="unordered">
                            <item><hi style="font-size:10pt">SI_ZAL_LJU/0362 − Zbirka muzeja
                                    denarnih zavodov Slovenije, Ljubljana (1873−1966).</hi>
                            </item>
                        </list></item>
                </list>
                <listBibl>
                    <head><hi style="font-size:10pt">Newspapers:</hi></head>
                    <bibl><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Laibacher Zeitung.</hi></bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">Slovenski narod. </hi></bibl>
                </listBibl>
                <listBibl>
                    <head><hi style="font-size:10pt">Published sources:</hi>
                    </head>
                    <bibl><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">Hribar, Ivan. </hi><hi
                            rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Kranjska
                        hranilnica.</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve"> Ljubljana: Narodna Tiskarna, 1909.</hi></bibl>
                    <bibl><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">Hribar, Ivan. </hi><hi
                            rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Moji spomini. Od 1853. do 1910.
                            leta</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">, </hi><hi
                            rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">I</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt">.
                            Ljubljana: 1928.</hi></bibl>
                    <bibl><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">Jeglič, Anton Bonaventura. </hi><hi
                            rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Jegličev dnevnik,
                            znanstvenokritična izdaja</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt">. Ed. Blaž
                            Otrin and Marija Čipić Rehar. Celje: Celjska Mohorjeva družba,
                            2015.</hi></bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Kranjska hranilnica v Ljubljani v
                            letu 1908</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt">. Ljubljana: Kleinmayr &amp;
                            Bamberg, 1909.</hi></bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Kranjska hranilnica v Ljubljani v
                            letu 1909</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt">. Ljubljana: Kleinmayr &amp;
                            Bamberg, 1910.</hi></bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Kranjska hranilnica v Ljubljani v
                            letu 1910</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt">. Ljubljana: Kleinmayr &amp;
                            Bamberg, 1911.</hi></bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Rechnungs–Abschluss der
                            krainischen Sparkasse des mit derselben vereinigten Pfandamtes und
                            Creditvereins am Schlusse des Jahres 1901</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt"
                            >. Laibach: Verlag der krainischen Sparkasse, 1902.</hi></bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Rechnungs–Abschluss der
                            krainischen Sparkasse des mit derselben vereinigten Pfandamtes und
                            Creditvereins am Schlusse des Jahres 1902</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt"
                            >. Laibach: Verlag der krainischen Sparkasse, 1903.</hi></bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Rechnungs–Abschluss der
                            krainischen Sparkasse des mit derselben vereinigten Pfandamtes und
                            Creditvereins am Schlusse des Jahres 1903</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt"
                            >. Laibach: Verlag der krainischen Sparkasse, 1904.</hi></bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Rechnungs–Abschluss der
                            krainischen Sparkasse des mit derselben vereinigten Pfandamtes und
                            Creditvereins am Schlusse des Jahres 1904</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt"
                            >. Laibach: Verlag der krainischen Sparkasse, 1905.</hi></bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Rechnungs–Abschluss der
                            krainischen Sparkasse des mit derselben vereinigten Pfandamtes und
                            Creditvereins am Schlusse des Jahres 1905</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt"
                            >. Laibach: Verlag der krainischen Sparkasse, 1906.</hi></bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Rechnungs–Abschluss der
                            krainischen Sparkasse des mit derselben vereinigten Pfandamtes und
                            Creditvereins am Schlusse des Jahres 1906</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt"
                            >. Laibach: Verlag der krainischen Sparkasse, 1907.</hi></bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Rechnungs–Abschluss der
                            krainischen Sparkasse des mit derselben vereinigten Pfandamtes und
                            Creditvereins am Schlusse des Jahres 1907</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt"
                            >. Laibach: Verlag der krainischen Sparkasse, 1908.</hi></bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Rechnungs–Abschluss der
                            krainischen Sparkasse des mit derselben vereinigten Pfandamtes und
                            Creditvereins am Schlusse des Jahres 1908</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt"
                            >. Laibach: Verlag der krainischen Sparkasse, 1909.</hi></bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Rechnungs–Abschluss der
                            krainischen Sparkasse des mit derselben vereinigten Pfandamtes und
                            Creditvereins am Schlusse des Jahres 1909</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt"
                            >. Laibach: Verlag der krainischen Sparkasse, 1910.</hi></bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Rechnungs–Abschluss der
                            krainischen Sparkasse des mit derselben vereinigten Pfandamtes und
                            Creditvereins am Schlusse des Jahres 1910</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt"
                            >. Laibach: Verlag der krainischen Sparkasse, 1911.</hi></bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Rechnungs–Abschluss der
                            krainischen Sparkasse des mit derselben vereinigten Pfandamtes und
                            Creditvereins am Schlusse des Jahres 1911</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt"
                            >. Laibach: Verlag der krainischen Sparkasse, 1912.</hi></bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Rechnungs–Abschluss der
                            krainischen Sparkasse des mit derselben vereinigten Pfandamtes und
                            Creditvereins am Schlusse des Jahres 1912</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt"
                            >. Laibach: Verlag der krainischen Sparkasse, 1913.</hi></bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Rechnungs–Abschluss der
                            krainischen Sparkasse des mit derselben vereinigten Pfandamtes und
                            Creditvereins am Schlusse des Jahres 1913</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt"
                            >. Laibach: Verlag der krainischen Sparkasse, 1914.</hi></bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Statistik der Sparkassen in den
                            im Reichsrate Vertretenen Königreichen und Ländern für das Jahr 1901.
                            Bearbeitet von dem Bureau der K. K. Statistischen
                            Zentral–Kommision</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">. LXX </hi><hi
                            rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Band, 2. Heft</hi><hi
                            style="font-size:10pt">. Wien: Aus der Kaiserlich-Königlichen Hof- und
                            Staatsdrukerei, 1903.</hi></bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Statistik der Sparkassen in den
                            im Reichsrate Vertretenen Königreichen und Ländern für das Jahr 1902.
                            Bearbeitet von dem Bureau der K. K. Statistischen
                            Zentral–Kommision</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">. </hi><hi
                            rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">LXXII. Band, 2. Heft</hi><hi
                            style="font-size:10pt">. Wien: Aus der Kaiserlich-Königlichen Hof- und
                            Staatsdrukerei, 1905.</hi></bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Statistik der Sparkassen in den
                            im Reichsrate Vertretenen Königreichen und Ländern für das Jahr 1903.
                            Bearbeitet von dem Bureau der K. K. Statistischen
                            Zentral–Kommision</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">. </hi><hi
                            rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">LXXVI. Band, 2. Heft</hi><hi
                            style="font-size:10pt">. Wien: Aus der Kaiserlich-Königlichen Hof- und
                            Staatsdrukerei, 1905.</hi></bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Statistik der Sparkassen in den
                            im Reichsrate Vertretenen Königreichen und Ländern für das Jahr 1904.
                            Bearbeitet von dem Bureau der K. K. Statistischen
                            Zentral–Kommision</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">. </hi><hi
                            rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">LXXX. Band, 1. Heft</hi><hi
                            style="font-size:10pt">. Wien: Aus der Kaiserlich-Königlichen Hof- und
                            Staatsdrukerei, 1906.</hi></bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Statistik der Sparkassen in den
                            im Reichsrate Vertretenen Königreichen und Ländern für das Jahr 1905.
                            Bearbeitet von dem Bureau der K. K. Statistischen
                            Zentral–Kommision</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">. </hi><hi
                            rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">LXXXII. Band, 2. Heft</hi><hi
                            style="font-size:10pt">. Wien: Aus der Kaiserlich-Königlichen Hof- und
                            Staatsdrukerei, 1907.</hi></bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Statistik der Sparkassen in den
                            im Reichsrate Vertretenen Königreichen und Ländern für das Jahr 1906.
                            Bearbeitet von dem Bureau der K. K. Statistischen
                            Zentral–Kommision</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">. </hi><hi
                            rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">LXXXVI. Band, 4. Heft</hi><hi
                            style="font-size:10pt">. Wien: Aus der Kaiserlich-Königlichen Hof- und
                            Staatsdrukerei, 1909.</hi></bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Statistik der Sparkassen in den
                            im Reichsrate Vertretenen Königreichen und Ländern für das Jahr 1907.
                            Bearbeitet von dem Bureau der K. K. Statistischen
                            Zentralkommision</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">. </hi><hi
                            rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">LXXXVIII. Band, 4. Heft</hi><hi
                            style="font-size:10pt">. Wien: Aus der Kaiserlich-Königlichen Hof- und
                            Staatsdrukerei, 1910.</hi></bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Statistik der Sparkassen in den
                            im Reichsrate Vertretenen Königreichen und Ländern für das Jahr 1908.
                            Bearbeitet von dem Bureau der K. K. Statistischen
                            Zentralkommision</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">. </hi><hi
                            rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">XCI. Band, 3. Heft</hi><hi
                            style="font-size:10pt">. Wien: Aus der Kaiserlich-Königlichen Hof- und
                            Staatsdrukerei, 1911.</hi></bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Statistik der Sparkassen in den
                            im Reichsrate Vertretenen Königreichen und Ländern für das Jahr 1909.
                            Bearbeitet von dem Bureau der K. K. Statistischen
                            Zentralkommision</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">. </hi><hi
                            rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">XCIII. Band, 2. Heft</hi><hi
                            style="font-size:10pt">. Wien: Aus der Kaiserlich-Königlichen Hof- und
                            Staatsdrukerei, 1912.</hi></bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Statistik der Sparkassen in den
                            im Reichsrate Vertretenen Königreichen und Ländern für das Jahr 1910.
                            Bearbeitet von dem Bureau der K. K. Statistischen
                            Zentralkommision</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">. </hi><hi
                            rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">7. Band, 2. Heft</hi><hi
                            style="font-size:10pt">. Wien: Aus der Kaiserlich-Königlichen Hof- und
                            Staatsdrukerei, 1912.</hi></bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Statistik der Sparkassen in den
                            im Reichsrate Vertretenen Königreichen und Ländern für das Jahr 1911.
                            Bearbeitet von dem Bureau der K. K. Statistischen Zentralkommision. 10.
                            Band, 1.
                        Heft.</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve"> Wien: Aus der Kaiserlich-Königlichen Hof- und Staatsdrukerei, 1913.</hi></bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Statistik der Sparkassen in den
                            im Reichsrate Vertretenen Königreichen und Ländern für das Jahr 1912.
                            Bearbeitet von dem Bureau der K. K. Statistischen
                            Zentralkommision</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">. </hi><hi
                            rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">12. Band, 2.
                        Heft.</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve"> Wien: Aus der Kaiserlich-Königlichen Hof- und Staatsdrukerei, 1915.</hi></bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Statistik der Sparkassen in den
                            im Reichsrate Vertretenen Königreichen und Ländern für das Jahr 1913.
                            Bearbeitet von dem Bureau der K. K. Statistischen
                            Zentralkommision</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">. </hi><hi
                            rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">15. Band, 1.
                        Heft.</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve"> Wien: Aus der Kaiserlich-Königlichen Hof- und Staatsdrukerei, 1916.</hi></bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Stenografični zapisnik sedme seje
                            deželnega zbora kranjskega v Ljubljani dne 15. januarja
                            1909</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">. Available at: </hi><ref
                            target="https://www.dlib.si/stream/URN:NBN:SI:doc-UUJMEUO1/590bbe26-3404-4471-833e-6111ceabb8b2/PDF"
                                ><hi rend="Spletna_povezava"><seg style="font-size:10pt"
                                    >https://www.dlib.si/stream/URN:NBN:SI:doc-UUJMEUO1/590bbe26-3404-4471-833e-6111ceabb8b2/PDF</seg></hi></ref><hi
                            rend="Spletna_povezava"><seg style="font-size:10pt">.</seg></hi></bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">V pojasnilo</hi><hi
                            style="font-size:10pt">. Ljubljana: Kleinmayr &amp; Bamberg,
                        1909.</hi></bibl>
                </listBibl>

                <listBibl>
                    <head><hi style="font-size:10pt">Literature:</hi></head>
                    <bibl><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">Brubaker, Rogers. </hi><hi
                            rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Ethnicity without groups</hi><hi
                            style="font-size:10pt">. Cambridge, London: Harvard University Press,
                            2006.</hi></bibl>
                    <bibl><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">Brusatti, Alois. </hi><hi
                            rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Die Habsburgischermonarchie
                            1848−1918, Bd 1, Die Wirtschaftliche Entwicklung</hi><hi
                            style="font-size:10pt">. Wien: Verlag der Österreichischen Akademie der
                            Wissenschaften, 1973.</hi>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">Calomiris, Charles W. and Gorton, Gary. “The Origins of Banking Panics: Models, Facts, and Bank Regulation.” In: </hi>
                        <hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Financial Markets and Financial
                            Crises</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">, ed. Glenn R. Hubbard, 109−74. Chicago, London: The University of Chicago Press, 1991. Available at: </hi>
                        <ref
                            target="https://pdfs.semanticscholar.org/d9d7/bf9c964fd2c1e2ea2828bb8805861ffe4425.pdf?_ga=2.174581930.988668068.1571398679-579497628.1571398679"
                                ><hi rend="Spletna_povezava"><seg style="font-size:10pt"
                                    >https://pdfs.semanticscholar.org/d9d7/bf9c964fd2c1e2ea2828bb8805861ffe4425.pdf?_ga=2.174581930.988668068.1571398679-579497628.1571398679</seg></hi></ref><seg
                            style="font-size:10pt">.</seg></bibl>
                    <bibl><hi style="font-size:10pt">Comin, Francisco. “Historical roots of the
                            social commitment of savings banks in Spain − From charity to corporate
                            social responsibility (1835−2002). 9</hi><hi rend="superscript"
                            style="font-size:10pt"
                            >th</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve"> European Symposium on Savings Banks History, European Savings Banks: From Social Commitment to Corporate Social Responsibility, Madrid 4−5 May 2006.” </hi><hi
                            rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt"
                            >Perspectives</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">, No. 55 (2007): 27−33. Available at: </hi><ref
                            target="https://www.wsbi-esbg.org/SiteCollectionDocuments/Perspectives%2055.pdf"
                                ><hi rend="Spletna_povezava"><seg style="font-size:10pt"
                                    >https://www.wsbi-esbg.org/SiteCollectionDocuments/Perspectives%2055.pdf</seg></hi></ref><hi
                            rend="Spletna_povezava"><seg style="font-size:10pt">.</seg></hi></bibl>
                    <bibl><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">Cvirn, Janez. “Nemško gledanje na Slovence (1848−1914).” In: </hi><hi
                            rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Sosed v ogledalu soseda. Od 1848 do
                            danes</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt">, ed. Franc Rozman, 55−77.
                            Ljubljana: Nacionalni komite za zgodovinske vede Republike Slovenije,
                            1995.</hi></bibl>
                    <bibl><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">Dirningen, Cristian. “Historic dimension of corporate social responsibility (CSR) of savings banks − the Austrian example. 9th European Symposium on Savings Banks History, European Savings Banks: From Social Commitment to Corporate Social Responsibility, Madrid 4−5 May 2006.” </hi><hi
                            rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt"
                            >Perspectives</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">, No. 55 (2007): 9–18. Available at: </hi><ref
                            target="https://www.wsbi-esbg.org/SiteCollectionDocuments/Perspectives%2055.pdf"
                                ><hi rend="Spletna_povezava"><seg style="font-size:10pt"
                                    >https://www.wsbi-esbg.org/SiteCollectionDocuments/Perspectives%2055.pdf</seg></hi></ref><hi
                            rend="Spletna_povezava"><seg style="font-size:10pt">.</seg></hi></bibl>
                    <bibl><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">Fritz, Hedwig. </hi><hi
                            rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">150 Jahre Sparkassen in Österreich.
                            Geschichte</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt">. Wien: Sparkassenverl,
                            1972.</hi></bibl>
                    <bibl><hi style="font-size:10pt">Judson, Pieter M. </hi><hi rend="italic"
                            style="font-size:10pt">The Habsburg Empire. A New History</hi>. <hi
                            style="font-size:10pt">Cambridge, MA: Belknap, 2016.</hi></bibl>
                    <bibl><hi style="font-size:10pt">Lazarević, Žarko. </hi><hi rend="italic"
                            style="font-size:10pt">Plasti prostora in časa. Iz gospodarske zgodovine
                            Slovenije prve polovice 20. stoletja</hi>. <hi style="font-size:10pt"
                            >Ljubljana: Inštitut za novejšo zgodovino, 2009.</hi></bibl>
                    <bibl><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">Lazarević, Žarko and Prinčič, Jože. </hi><hi
                            rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Bančniki v ogledalu
                            časa</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">. </hi><hi
                            rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Življenjske poti slovenskih
                            bančnikov v 19. in 20. stoletju</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt">.
                            Ljubljana: ZBS Združenje bank Slovenije, 2005.</hi></bibl>
                    <bibl><hi style="font-size:10pt">Matić, Dragan. </hi><hi rend="italic"
                            style="font-size:10pt">Nemci v Ljubljani 1848−1918</hi>. <hi
                            style="font-size:10pt">Ljubljana: Oddelek za zgodovino Filozofske
                            fakultete, 2002.</hi></bibl>
                    <bibl><hi style="font-size:10pt">Matjašič, Marjan. “Stališče vojaških oblasti do
                            nemirov septembra 1908 v Ljubljani.” In: </hi><hi rend="italic"
                            style="font-size:10pt">Kronika,</hi>
                        <hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">32, No. 1 (1984): 28–35. </hi>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">Melik, Vasilij “Politične razmere na Štajerskem v času Napotnika.” In: </hi><hi
                            rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Slovenci 1848</hi><hi
                            style="font-size:10pt">−</hi><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt"
                            >1918. Razprave in
                        članki</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">, 608−20. Maribor: Litera 2002. </hi></bibl>
                    <bibl><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">Melik, Vasilij. “Problemi slovenske družbe 1897-1914.” In: </hi><hi
                            rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Slovenci 1848</hi><hi
                            style="font-size:10pt">−</hi><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt"
                            >1918. Razprave in članki</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt">, 600−07.
                            Maribor: Litera 2002.</hi></bibl>
                    <bibl><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">Sandgruber, Roman. </hi><hi
                            rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Ökonomie und Politik.
                            Österreichische Wirtschaftsgeschichte vom Mittelalter bis zur
                            Gegenwart</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt">. Wien: Ueberreuter,
                        1995.</hi></bibl>
                    <bibl><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">“Septembrski dogodki.” In: </hi><hi
                            rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Ilustrirana zgodovina
                            Slovencev</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">, ed. Marko Vidic, 282. Ljubljana: Mladinska knjiga, 1999. </hi></bibl>
                    <bibl><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">Studen, Andrej. “Protinemški izgredi v Ljubljani leta 1903.” </hi><hi
                            rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Prispevki za novejšo
                        zgodovino</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">, 38, No. 1−2 (1998): 15−21. </hi></bibl>
                    <bibl><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">Thol, Carolin. </hi><hi
                            rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Poverty relief and financial
                            inclusion. Savings banks in nineteenth century
                            Germany</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">. Brussels: WSBI−ESBG The Voice of Savings and Retail Banking, 2016. Available at: </hi><ref
                            target="https://www.wsbi-esbg.org/SiteCollectionDocuments/8119_ESBG_BRO_STUDY.pdf"
                                ><hi rend="Spletna_povezava"><seg style="font-size:10pt"
                                    >https://www.wsbi-esbg.org/SiteCollectionDocuments/8119_ESBG_BRO_STUDY.pdf</seg></hi></ref><hi
                            rend="Spletna_povezava"><seg style="font-size:10pt">.</seg></hi></bibl>
                    <bibl><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">Wurm, Susanne. “The Development of Austrian Financial Institutions in Central, Eastern and South-Eastern Europe. Comparative European Economic History Studies.” </hi><hi
                            rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Working Paper
                            Series</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">, No. 31 (2006): 7−72. Available at: </hi><ref
                            target="http://citeseerx.ist.psu.edu/viewdoc/download?doi=10.1.1.527.9024&amp;rep=rep1&amp;type=pdf"
                                ><hi rend="Spletna_povezava"><seg style="font-size:10pt"
                                    >http://citeseerx.ist.psu.edu/viewdoc/download?doi=10.1.1.527.9024&amp;rep=rep1&amp;type=pdf</seg></hi></ref><hi
                            rend="Spletna_povezava"><seg style="font-size:10pt">.</seg></hi></bibl>
                    <bibl><hi style="font-size:10pt">Zahra, Tara. “Imagined Noncommunities: National
                            Indifference as a Category of Analysis.” </hi><hi rend="italic"
                            style="font-size:10pt">Slavic Review</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt">,
                            69, No. 1 (spring 2010): 93−119. Available at: </hi><ref
                            target="https://www.researchgate.net/publication/313457649_Imagined_Noncommunities_National_Indifference_as_a_Category_of_Analysis"
                                ><hi style="font-size:10pt"
                                >https://www.researchgate.net/publication/313457649_Imagined_Noncommunities_National_Indifference_as_a_Category_of_Analysis</hi></ref>.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
            <div type="summary" xml:lang="sl">
                <docAuthor><hi style="font-size:10pt">Nataša Henig Miščič</hi>
                </docAuthor>
                <head><hi style="font-size:10pt">KRANJSKA HRANILNICA IN SLOVENSKO-NEMŠKI ODNOSI LETA
                        1908 IN 1909</hi></head>
                <head><hi style="font-size:10pt">POVZETEK</hi></head>
                <p><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">Kranjska hranilnica se je znašla v neprijetnem položaju, vpletena v konflikte slovenskega in nemškega narodnega gibanja, ter se je bila primorana spoprijeti z velikim političnim in gospodarskim pritiskom. Potem ko so v drugi polovici septembra leta 1908 napetosti dosegle vrhunec, se je soočala z večmesečnim </hi><hi
                        rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt"
                    >navalom</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">, ki je terjal visoke zneske izplačanega denarja iz hranilnice. Kriza v letu 1908 je lokalni pojav na Kranjskem, začela pa se je z novico o insolventnosti Kranjske hranilnice. Množično dvigovanje denarja iz finančnih zavodov je bil zelo pogost pojav v različnih krizah in predstavlja logičen odziv prebivalstva v času negotovosti. Slovenski politiki so v izjemno napetih političnih razmerah spodbujali množičen umik prihrankov in se na vsak način trudili spodkopati zaupanje v verodostojnost hranilnice s širjenjem neresničnih govoric o poslovnih nepravilnostih in insolventnosti. Slovenski vlagatelji so množično dvigovali svoje prihranke tudi zaradi nemškega predznaka Kranjske hranilnice. Hranilne vloge, ki jih je hranilnica izplačala svojim vložnikom med oktobrom 1908 in junijem 1909, so daleč presegale vso njeno razpoložljivo gotovino. Hranilnica je začela prodajati svoje vrednostne papirje, ampak to ni zadoščalo naraščajočim zahtevam. Zato je prekinila izdajo novih hipotekarnih kreditov in začela realizacijo posojil, ne le v deželi, ampak tudi v drugih delih monarhije. Kljub temu da je hranilnica leta 1909 zamenjala napis na svoji stavbi, ki je bil od takrat naprej v slovenskem jeziku, je še naprej veljala za nemški finančni steber na Kranjskem. Ta status je obdržala vse do konca obstoja avstro-ogrske monarhije leta 1918. V tem obdobju se ji je po višini vloženega denarja, ki ga je pridobila od vlagateljev, postopoma približevala Mestna hranilnica ljubljanska, ki je leta 1909 odprla tudi svoje Kreditno društvo in finančno pripomogla k ustanovitvi nove mestne zastavljalnice. Kranjska hranilnica je kljub vsemu obdržala vodilni položaj na Kranjskem v skoraj vseh poslovnih segmentih, zlasti pri naložbah v državne vrednostne papirje in visokih zneskih rezervnega sklada. Bila je osrednji finančni zavod v pokrajini in zelo pomemben dejavnik gospodarskega razvoja. Zato ni bilo nepomembno, kdo je imel nadzor nad njenim delovanjem. </hi></p>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
