<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="sl">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Family Networks and the “Generational Key” in the Renewed Approaches of
                    Social Questioning of the Slovak Elite at the Beginning of the 20<hi
                        rend="superscript">th</hi>Century</title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename>Etienne</forename>
                        <surname>Boisserie</surname>
                        <roleName>Associate Professor</roleName>
                        <roleName>PhD</roleName>
                        <affiliation>Central –European, Czech and Slovak history at the National
                            Institute for Eastern Languages and Civilizations, INALCO</affiliation>
                        <address>
                            <addrLine>Paris</addrLine>
                        </address>
                        <email>eboisserie@gmail.com</email>
                    </name>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>2017-10-02</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>
                    <orgName xml:lang="sl">Inštitut za novejšo zgodovino</orgName>
                    <orgName xml:lang="en">Institute of Contemporary History</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Kongresni trg 1</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>SI-1000 Ljubljana</addrLine>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>http://ojs.inz.si/pnz/article/view/245</pubPlace>
                <date>2017</date>
                <availability status="free">
                    <licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title xml:lang="sl">Prispevki za novejšo zgodovino</title>
                <title xml:lang="en">Contributions to Contemporary History</title>
                <biblScope unit="volume">57</biblScope>
                <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
                <idno type="ISSN">2463-7807</idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source, born digital.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc xml:lang="en">
                <p>Contributions to Contemporary History is one of the central Slovenian scientific
                    historiographic journals, dedicated to publishing articles from the field of
                    contemporary history (the 19th and 20th century).</p>
                <p>The journal is published three times per year in Slovenian and in the following
                    foreign languages: English, German, Serbian, Croatian, Bosnian, Italian, Slovak
                    and Czech. The articles are all published with abstracts in English and
                    Slovenian as well as summaries in English.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <projectDesc xml:lang="sl">
                <p>Prispevki za novejšo zgodovino je ena osrednjih slovenskih znanstvenih
                    zgodovinopisnih revij, ki objavlja teme s področja novejše zgodovine (19. in 20.
                    stoletje).</p>
                <p>Revija izide trikrat letno v slovenskem jeziku in v naslednjih tujih jezikih:
                    angleščina, nemščina, srbščina, hrvaščina, bosanščina, italijanščina, slovaščina
                    in češčina. Članki izhajajo z izvlečki v angleščini in slovenščini ter povzetki
                    v angleščini.</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="sl"/>
                <language ident="en"/>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords xml:lang="en">
                    <term>Slovakia</term>
                    <term>cultural history</term>
                    <term>Kingdom of Hungary</term>
                    <term>Czech-Slovak mutuality</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords xml:lang="sl">
                    <term>Slovaška</term>
                    <term>kulturna zgodovina</term>
                    <term>Kraljevina Ogrska</term>
                    <term>češko-slovaška vzajemnost</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change>
                    <date>2017-11-20</date>
                    <name>Neja Blaj Hribar</name>
                    <desc>Pretvorba iz DOCX v TEI, dodatno kodiranje</desc>
                </change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <docAuthor> Etienne Boisserie<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn1" n="*">
                    <hi rend="bold" xml:space="preserve">Associate Professor, PhD, Central –European, Czech and Slovak history at the National Institute for Eastern Languages and Civilizations (INALCO, Paris), </hi><ref
                        target="mailto:eboisserie@gmail.com"><hi rend="bold"
                            >eboisserie@gmail.com</hi></ref>
                </note>
            </docAuthor>
            <docImprint>
                <idno type="cobissType">Cobiss type: 1.01</idno>
                <idno type="UDC">UDC: 323.15(439.2=162.4)"1900/1914"</idno>
            </docImprint>
            <div type="abstract" xml:lang="sl">
                <head>IZVLEČEK</head>
                <head>DRUŽINSKE VEZI IN »GENERACIJSKI KLJUČ« V PRENOVLJENIH PRISTOPIH K DRUŽBENEMU
                    VREDNOTENJU SLOVAŠKE ELITE NA ZAČETKU 20. STOLETJA</head>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Do devetdesetih let 19. stoletja so večino javnih zadev glede
                        slovaških elit urejali v majhnem mestu Turčiansky Sväty Martin v okraju
                        Turiec v skladu z dolgoročnim programom, zasnovanim leta 1861, ki se je z
                        uporabo klasičnega pristopa iz 2. polovice štiridesetih let 19. stoletja
                        osredotočal predvsem na jezik in državno individualnost Slovakov v odnosu z
                        Madžari in Čehi.</hi></p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">V začetku 20. stoletja je prišlo do preobrata, ki je korenito
                        spremenil glavno os javnih in družbenih dejavnosti v okolju izobraženih
                        Slovakov. Ta preobrat je sovpadal z nastopom nove generacije, na katero so
                        vplivale osebne izkušnje, pridobljene v tujem okolju med študijem v
                        imperiju, posebno na češkem ozemlju, pa tudi v tujini. Pri tem so imele
                        velik vpliv tudi dolgotrajne družinske vezi in lokalna oziroma regionalna
                        solidarnost. Članek preučuje, kako in v kakšnem obsegu so ti dejavniki
                        korenito prenovili pristop k družbeni refleksiji v večinoma slovaških
                        okrajih v Kraljevini Ogrski v prvem desetletju 20. stoletja.</hi></p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Ključne besede: Slovaška, kulturna zgodovina, Kraljevina
                        Ogrska, češko-slovaška vzajemnost</hi></p>
            </div>
            <div type="abstract">
                <head>ABSTRACT</head>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Until the 1890s, most public affairs surrounding the Slovak
                        elites were managed from the small town of Turčianský Sväty Martin in the
                        Turiec County, based on a long-lasting programme drawn up in 1861 that was
                        mainly focused, in a classical approach from the late 1840s, on the language
                        and national individuality of the Slovaks vis-à-vis both Hungarians and
                        Czechs.</hi></p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">A shift occurred in the early 1900s, having since deeply
                        modified the main axis of the public and social activities in the educated
                        Slovak milieu. This shift coincided with an emerging new generation
                        influenced by a foreign experience observed personally during their studies
                        in the Empire, especially in the Czech Lands, and sometimes abroad.
                        Furthermore, it was based on long-standing family ties and local/regional
                        solidarities. This paper studies the manner and extent to which these
                        factors renewed the approach of social reflection in mostly Slovak Counties
                        of the Kingdom of Hungary in the first decade of the 20</hi><hi
                        rend="italic superscript">th</hi><hi rend="italic"> century.</hi></p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Keywords: Slovakia, cultural history, Kingdom of Hungary,
                        Czech-Slovak mutuality</hi></p>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>Social and family relationships in the Slovak patriotic milieu in the second half
                    of the 19<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> century have not yet been studied
                    methodically through an approach combining the kinship dimension and “generation
                    dynamics”.</p>
                <p>The notion of “kinship fronts”, as used by Giovanni Levi, is fruitful in both its
                    dimensions: the first links families in the sense of non-co-resident groups with
                    kinship ties, relations by marriage or the emerging fictional kinship relations.
                    The second dimension, which is vertical, is comprised of “clienteles,
                    protections and loyalty networks” which explain the behaviours and strategies of
                    families or individuals from a historical perspective, keeping in mind that each
                    family nucleus acts in a composite social network. The notion helps document the
                    hypothesis of deep continuity in the Slovak patriotic milieu and its local and
                    regional dimensions. It also enables the observation of the diversification and
                    transformation of patriotic activities, all from the cultural and literary
                    sphere to the sphere of politics in the wider sense, including the economy and
                    education.</p>
                <p>The “generation” question is observed by keeping in mind the limits of an overly
                    strict approach as highlighted by Jean-Pierre Azéma,<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn2" n="1"> Jean-Pierre <hi rend="smallcaps">Azéma</hi>, “La clef
                            générationnelle<hi rend="italic">,</hi>” [The generational key]
                        <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Vingtième Siècle, </hi>22 (1989):
                        3–10.</note> and we refer rather to what can be called an “ideological
                    system” defined as “what belongs to all and is the dominating question of the
                    moment, the question that emerges during the ‘period of receptiveness’ and
                    formation.” It must be underlined that “philosophical answers and political
                    stances can be diverging or contradictory, but they nevertheless form a
                        system.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn3" n="2"> Michel Winock,
                        <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">L’Effet de génération. Une brève histoire des intellectuels français </hi>[The
                        generational effect. A brief history of French intellectuals] (Paris:
                        Thierry Marchaisse, 2011), 11.</note> The cohort as such is insufficient;
                    many
                    <hi rend="color(262626)" xml:space="preserve">singularities have to be taken into account, such as references to different founding events and social profiles. </hi>It
                    has to be approached cautiously, but it does offer keys to analyse the divisions
                    and dynamics of this milieu.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn4" n="3">
                        Jean-François Sirinelli, “<hi rend="italic">Génération et histoire
                            politique,</hi>” [Generations and political history]
                        <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Vingtième Siècle, </hi>22 (1989):
                        71.</note></p>
                <p>Having set aside the kinship dimension in its quantitative aspects, we will here
                    insist mainly on two aspects: the first one is the evolution of networks from
                    the geographical point of view, and the second one is the turn of generations,
                    i.e. the pillars and tools of the new approach that can be observed from the
                    mid-1890s until the middle of the following decade.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>The Genesis of the Intellectual Shift</head>
                <div>
                    <head>Towards a geographical extension</head>
                    <p>One of the weaknesses of a cultural and voluntary action lies in its narrow
                        geographical base. This action was historically based in three small
                        counties at the north of the Kingdom (Liptov, Orava, and Turiec) and
                        connected with the mid-sized cities in the surrounding counties. The main
                        patriotic activities were concentrated in this area, especially in Martin,
                        with the Slovak National Party or SNS (founded in 1871), the press (mostly
                        one daily and one monthly newspaper that can be considered as the sole
                        political and cultural papers), and the main non-confessional associations. </p>
                    <p>The leading position of Martin was challenged in the 1890s. This challenge
                        came from networks built and developed in Prague and Vienna, where a handful
                        of Slovak students had organized themselves in small groups and had been
                        developing connections and solidarities for about a decade. Coming mostly
                        from the Orava-Liptov-Turiec triangle, they were inspired by what is usually
                        called “the spirit of Martin” [<hi rend="italic">Martinský duch</hi>]. Some
                        others were from what is called “Western Slovakia”<note place="foot"
                            xml:id="ftn5" n="4"> In the narrow sense of the word, “Western Slovakia”
                            is the region located to the North-West of Bratislava, extending to the
                            border with Moravia. In the broader sense, it refers to the long strip
                            of land situated between the two rivers of Váh and Moravia.</note>,
                        where connections with Vienna and South Moravia were more frequent. The
                        region, which was less influenced by the “historical core” of the movement
                        and more connected to non-Hungarian parts of the monarchy, had already been
                        organized based on the economic proximity and agricultural networks.
                        Moreover, it was one of the regions active in creating cooperatives in the
                        mid-century period and was close to Pressburg, where active upper-middle
                        class Slovak patriots worked mostly as lawyers, organizing critics of the
                        “conservative” or “old” centre, i.e. Martin. To name but two of those
                        involved in what Pavol Blaho later called “the Awakening of the West”<note
                            place="foot" xml:id="ftn6" n="5"> SNA, BA, of. Blaho, carton (c.) 76,
                            inv. č. (No.) 2059<hi rend="color(FF0000)">.</hi></note>: Jozef Dérer
                        and Miloš Štefanovič, who were both lawyers in Bratislava and close friends.
                        Although they had connections with the Party in Martin, they both developed
                        harsh criticism towards what is frequently referred to as the “old”
                        centre”, especially the latter of the two, who is seen as <hi rend="italic"
                            >enfant terrible</hi> of the Slovak politics.<note place="foot"
                            xml:id="ftn7" n="6"> About Miloš Štefanovič and his role in redefining
                            the Slovak national programme, see Milan Podrimavský,
                            <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Slovenská národná strana v druhej polovici 19. storočia </hi>[The
                            Slovak National Party in the second half of the 19<hi rend="superscript"
                                >th</hi> century] (Bratislava: SAV, 1983).</note></p>
                    <p>Both of them are also interesting as representatives of what can be
                        considered in hindsight as the transitional generation or “the intermediate
                        outside-Martin generation“, embedded between a classical, language-focused
                        approach to the national question and its further development. Both men
                        belonged to families involved in the main cultural and political events,
                        including the voluntary actions from the 1840s to the 1850s. Miloš
                        Štefanovič was one of the most prominent figures of this generation. His
                        patriotic pedigree was irreproachable: his father Samuel was one of the 22
                        members of the Permanent National Committee founded after the adoption of
                        the 1861 Memorandum in Martin.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn8" n="7"> See
                            <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Slovenské národné zhromaždenie v Turčianskom Sv. Martine 1861 </hi>[The
                            1861 Slovak national assembly of Turčianský Sväty Martin] (T. S. Martin:
                            Matica slovenská, 1941). František Bokes,
                            <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Dokumenty k slovenskému národnému hnutia, I </hi>[Documents
                            on the Slovak National Movement. 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> volume]
                            (Bratislava: SAV, 1962), 323.</note> The importance of Miloš Štefanovič
                        in patriotic action relied on the two-fold long-standing family involvement
                        in it – the manner in which he challenged the options adopted in the 1870s
                        and the manner in which he shook the entire patriotic landscape. This is
                        also a clue to the increasing role of the Western counties, including
                        Pressburg, in the Slovak politics at the beginning of the 1890s. Miloš
                        Štefanovič was a lawyer working in the city from 1887, having started his
                        career at Dula’s office in Martin. He was highly esteemed and one of the
                        “four stars” of the Slovak lawyers, alongside the Mudroň brothers and Štefan
                            Fajnor.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn9" n="8"> Ivan Thurzo,
                            <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Medzi vrchmi a na rovine </hi>[Between
                            the hills and in the plains] (Bratislava: Tatran, 1987), 51. About
                            Fajnor and his role as a lawyer, see also Štefan Janšák,
                            <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Život Štefana Fajnora </hi>[Life
                            of Štefan Fajnor] (Bratislava: Biblioteka, 1935), 172–75. <term>Dula,
                                Matúš (1846-1926)</term>
                        </note></p>
                    <p>Both Jozef and Miloš took in young people coming to Pressburg in the 1890s,
                        and both were in touch with the Viennese and Moravian activists and openly
                        challenged the classical mode of action.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>The Hlas and its Impact</head>
                    <p>The 1890s were a time of renewal instigated by critics of the passive
                        politics which was initiated in the 1870s. The most important impetus for
                        the renewal of political action in the broader sense of the word was the
                        creation of the <anchor xml:id="OLE_LINK11"/><hi rend="italic">Hlas</hi>
                        review in 1898. <hi rend="italic">Hlas</hi> attracted and brought together a
                        new generation. Critical of Martin, this generation was headed by two former
                        figures of the voluntary milieu of Vienna and Prague in the preceding
                        decade, i.e. Pavol Blaho and Vavro Šrobár. Both were medics, the first from
                        the West, the second from Liptov; both were born in 1867; the first studied
                        in Vienna, the second in Prague; and both either founded or led the most
                        representative Slovak students’ associations in the respective cities: the
                        “Národ” in Vienna, and the “Detvan” in Prague.<note place="foot"
                            xml:id="ftn10" n="9"> About Národ, see SNA, of. Blaho<index
                                indexName="XE">
                                <term>Blaho, Pavel (1867-1927)</term>
                            </index>, c. 76, No. 2038. About the Detvan, see LA SNK, Martin,
                            C 1438.</note> Both men were brought up in the classical conservative
                        atmosphere of the late 1870s and the early 1880s.<note place="foot"
                            xml:id="ftn11" n="10"> LA SNK, 42 X 22, “Šrobár a jeho doba.”</note> As
                        Anton Štefánek later pointed out about Šrobár, “when he arrived in Prague,
                        […] he was a nationalist in the old meaning of the term. He read the
                        <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Národnie Noviny </hi>[National
                        journal], admired Hurban-Vajansky’s poetry and the Russophile trend, and
                        read Russian writers extensively, mainly Tolstoy”. Both Blaho and Šrobár
                        though were deeply influenced by the political transformations they observed
                        in Vienna and Prague respectively, particularly by the emergence of the
                        “progressive” current in the Czech Lands: a more radical, nationally and
                        socially focused trend in the Czech politics that challenged the classical
                        “activist” orientation of the still dominant Young-Czech elite.<note
                            place="foot" xml:id="ftn12" n="11"> Jiří Kořalka, <hi rend="italic">Češi
                                v habsburské říši a v Evropě
                            1815</hi>–<hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">1914 </hi>[The Czechs
                            in the Habsburg Empire and in Europe] (Prague: Argo, 1996). Jan Křen,
                                <hi rend="italic">Konfliktní společenství. Češi a Němci
                            1780</hi>–<hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">1918 </hi>[Conflicting
                            Societies. Czechs and Germans 1780-1918] (Prague: Academia, 1990). In
                            English, see Bruce M. Garver, <hi rend="italic">The Young Czech Party
                                1874</hi>–<hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">1901. The Emergence of a Multi-party System </hi>(New
                            Haven: Yale University Press, 1978). </note></p>
                    <p>Some of their early “political” activities were linked to the Detvan
                        association created in 1882. Nevertheless, until the end of the 1890s,
                        Detvan was dominated by “the spirit of Martin” [<hi rend="italic">Martinský
                            duch</hi>] and reluctant to support the idea of a review that would
                        challenge the official politics of Martin.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn13"
                            n="12"> “Z korešpondencie predsaviteľov českého a slovenského národného
                            hnutia na prelome 19. a 20. storočia,” [From the correspondence between
                            Czech and Slovak national movement at the turn of the 20<hi
                                rend="superscript">th</hi> century] <hi rend="italic">Historický
                                časopis</hi>, 17 (1969): 270–84.</note></p>
                    <p>The <hi rend="italic">Hlas</hi> was published after quite a long period of
                        preparation. It had initially been conceived in 1896. In Šrobár’s words, its
                        “aim was to shake the youth so that they could shake the people.”<note
                            place="foot" xml:id="ftn14" n="13"> LA SNK, 37 BB 11.</note> Personal
                        and financial problems delayed its publication, which took place only in
                        1898. Besides Šrobár and Blaho, the <hi rend="italic">Hlas</hi> involved the
                        young Fedor Houdek (born in 1877) whose position in the business families of
                        the Liptov is well known.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn15" n="14"> Fedor
                            Houdek’s mother was a Makovický, a member of one of the most influential
                            families in the Slovak business environment of the Liptov County. – See
                            Zdenko Ďuriška,
                            <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Medzi mlynmi a bankami. Dejiny rodu Makovickovcov </hi>[Between
                            mills and banks. The history of the Makovický family] (Martin: SGHS,
                            2007). He studied at the Prague Academy of Commerce between 1894 and
                            1897 and was a member of the “Detvan”. He then returned to Liptov to
                            work in his father’s firm and at the Credit bank [Úverná banka] of
                            Ružomberok.</note> Šrobár had no doubt as to the significance of this
                        creation. In a long letter to Žigmund Pauliny-Tóth, who belonged to one of
                        Martin’s most important Slovak families and headed the first Slovak bank
                        – the Tatra banka – at the time, he was quite clear on that point: “I think
                        we are opening a new era in Slovakia, a new period of awakening, a new era
                        of the Slovak life reformation. But, for now, it is still far away.”<note
                            place="foot" xml:id="ftn16" n="15"> LA SNK, A 1505, Šrobár to
                            Pauliny-Tóth, 13 June 1898. </note></p>
                    <p>The main target of those called “hlasists” was “Štúrism”, named after Ľudovít
                        Štúr, who codified the Slovak language. Combined with the mighty Russophilia
                        that impregnated the Slovak movement, “Štúrism” was considered an ideology
                        that led to a weakening of political and cultural action and to sterile
                        conservatism. Because of it, the “really practical” and “concrete” work was
                        forgotten for years, if not decades, and the Slovak mainstream gradually
                        moved away from the people. This people’s dimension of politics had to be
                        reintroduced in any kind of activities under the motto of “concrete small
                        social work”, which was adapted from the Czech Lands; it implied the
                        education and information campaigns, creation of cultural or educational
                        associations on a very local basis, and spreading of technical and
                        scientific knowledge among people. The <hi rend="italic">Hlas</hi> was also
                        a weapon against renouncement, with the political passivity of the SNS being
                        analysed as such.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn17" n="16"> Vavro Šrobár,
                            “Počiatky slovenského obrodenia,” [The beginnings of the Slovak
                            awakening] in: <hi rend="italic">Sborník slovenskej mladeže,</hi>
                            [Slovak youth collection] 1909, 141.</note> When assessing the preceding
                        decade in 1908, Šrobár underlined that, “at that time, there was absolutely
                        no autonomous political movement in Slovakia. The Slovak intelligentsia was
                        declining year by year as the cruel Hungarian liberal regime had pushed it
                        out of public politics and restricted it to the private sphere. Between the
                        Slovak intelligentsia and the Slovak people, an unbridgeable rift was
                        growing; people had lost their leaders, and their leaders had lost the
                        battle. [...] Some were certain that our liberation would come from the
                        East, others assured with the same certainty that it would come from the
                        West, from the dynasty. This had only one consequence on the Slovak life: it
                        fell asleep”.</p>
                    <p>At the turn of the century and a few more years afterwards, the hlasists
                        worked along another new trend in the Slovak intelligentsia, the
                            Catholics<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn18" n="17"> R. Holec,
                            <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Tragédia v Černovej a slovenská spoločnosť </hi>[The
                            Tragedy of Černová<index indexName="XE">
                                <term>Černová</term>
                            </index> and Slovak society] (Martin: Matica slovenská, 1997), 21–24.
                        </note>, in order to develop what was called “concrete small social work”.
                        This was the Slovak version of the Czech “small work”, which mostly
                        consisted of evening lectures and conferences, and establishment of cultural
                        and educational associations and cooperatives, especially in the rural
                        milieu. Despite the ambitious aims, a low level of professionalism in the
                        editing board remained a problem and so did the lack of fervour as well as
                        the passivity. Houdek openly expressed his deepest concern regarding the
                        overall evolution of the Slovak activist landscape in a letter sent to
                        Masaryk in November of 1901. “As a careful observer of our [Slovak] life,
                        you certainly did not miss a sad fact: those who came back to Slovakia with
                        the best ideas in their heart and full of moral fervour fell into lethargy,
                        into moral and physical laziness. Some of them fell more slowly, others more
                        rapidly. Slovakia looks like a fairy-tale castle where princes come to undo
                        the spell but are bewitched themselves and remain prisoners.”<note
                            place="foot" xml:id="ftn19" n="18"> Fedor Houdek<index indexName="XE">
                                <term>Houdek, Fedor (1877-1953)</term>
                            </index> to Masaryk<index indexName="XE">
                                <term>Masaryk, Tomáš garrigue (1850-1935)</term>
                            </index>, 4 November 1901, in: Jan Rychlík, ed., <hi rend="italic"
                                >Korespondence T. G. Masaryk – slovenští veřejní činitelé</hi>
                            [Correspondence T. G. Masaryk – Slovak public activists] (Prague:
                            Masarykův ústav AV ČR, 2007), 73.</note></p>
                    <p>In the same letter, he deeply regretted Šrobár’s “disappointing” attitude
                        during the last months and his disagreements with Blaho that weighed on the
                            <hi rend="italic">Hlas</hi> action. Houdek also stated that the
                        “awakening work” too often fell on the individuals’ shoulders, more than on
                        the organized groups.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn20" n="19"> Ibid.,
                            74.</note> This assessment was in many ways confirmed by Šrobár himself
                        who, one year later, wrote to Masaryk: “Blaho let [the <hi rend="italic"
                            >Hlas</hi>] fall, as he said, because of the lack of co-workers. The
                        real reason though is that during the last period, the <hi rend="italic"
                            >Hlas</hi> sailed into the waters of the clericals and, as a
                        consequence, the youth educated in the spirit of the Czech realism turned
                        away from him [Šrobár].”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn21" n="20"> Šrobár to
                            Masaryk, 16 December 1902. – Rychlík, ed.,
                            <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Korespondence, </hi>81,
                            82.</note> In addition, the administration of the review was something
                        of a mess, subscriptions went partly unpaid and distribution remained
                            poor.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn22" n="21"> SNA, of. Blaho, c. 52,
                            No. 1706 to 1708. Subscription is a long-standing problem of the review.
                            See for instance Šrobár<index indexName="XE">
                                <term>Šrobár, Vavro (1867-1950)</term>
                            </index> to Masaryk<index indexName="XE">
                                <term>Masaryk, Tomáš garrigue (1850-1935)</term>
                            </index>, 16 December 1902. – Rychlík, ed.,
                            <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Korespondence, </hi>81,
                            82.</note> The <anchor xml:id="OLE_LINK12"/><hi rend="italic">Hlas</hi>
                        finally died out in 1904. In many respects, it suffered the same problems as
                        the ones that affected all political and publishing activities of the Slovak
                        patriots: personal misunderstandings and rivalries, but mainly dilettantism.
                        If we consider its content and impact, the <hi rend="italic">Hlas</hi> can
                        nevertheless be assumed to having shaken up the entire landscape and become
                        the centre of an in-depth renewal that melded a generation of young men born
                        mostly in the late 1870s and early 1880s – a renewal that lasted until the
                        eve of the war, after which that same generation took up the torch and
                        founded a new review called <hi rend="italic">Prúdy,</hi> explicitly
                        referring to the <hi rend="italic">Hlas</hi>.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>New Local Dynamics at the Eve of the 20<hi rend="bold superscript">th</hi>
                    <hi rend="bold">Century</hi></head>
                <p>At the turn of the century, the geographical balance in the Slovak politics
                    slightly changed. The emergence of new cities and regions started to act as a
                    counterweight to Martin’s influence. This was especially the case in Western
                    Slovakia and the cities of Skalica, Myjava, Senica and Pressburg, and of
                    Liptovský Mikuláš and Ružomberok in the Liptov. Some more isolated cities
                        <anchor xml:id="OLE_LINK9"/>also (re-)emerged, such as Trnava, Nové Mesto
                    nad Váhom and Tisovec, where the leading figures or families organized the
                    “Slovak national life”.</p>
                <p>The pillar of this renewal was the education, which applied to various fields
                    where issues regarding peasants and the youth were important<hi rend="bold"
                        >.</hi></p>
                <p>Health was one of the main concerns: “the fight against alcoholism goes hand in
                    hand with the emancipating economic fight”, underlined Blaho in the already
                    mentioned booklet “The Awakening of the West”.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn23"
                        n="22"> SNA, of. Blaho, c. 76, No. 2059, 15.</note> The 1901 establishment
                    of an “abstinent circle” in Blaho’s city of Skalica was a small local event,
                    even if the “circle” was able to rely on as few as 80 members during its first
                    year of activity. Nevertheless, the network slowly grew. The year 1904 saw the
                    first peak of education activities in the West, including conferences about
                    alcoholism and dairy farming, and more than 20 conferences on other local or
                    global economic questions and various topics of popular education, as well as
                    the amateur theatre, which was an important and already developed part of the
                    inclusive work on a local basis. This dynamic spread to agricultural
                    cooperatives, from the Skalica cooperative to smaller structures in the
                    surrounding areas. At the same time, small municipal libraries were opened,
                    sometimes in private houses, and sometimes with the help of the Slovak catholic
                    clergy that played an important role in the West. The third important step, as
                    far as the West was concerned, was the opening of the House of the Peasant on
                    the main Skalica square in 1905. The House, which was initiated by Blaho, soon
                    transformed Skalica into the capital city of the Slovak peasantry.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn24" n="23"> SNA, of. Blaho, c. 47, No.
                        1559-1590.</note> Skalica became the place of the “Peasants’ congress”, an
                    event that, each year from 1906 onwards, lasted for three or four days and was
                    filled with conferences on health, technical progress, and political and
                    economic education. An important part of it was devoted to joint activities (and
                    notably cautiously prepared lunches and walks). As time went by, the core of
                    participants to this congress expanded, gradually including new activists
                    attracted by what was becoming a proper challenge for the “old centre”, i.e.
                    Martin.</p>
                <p>In the mid-1900s, Western Slovakia’s dynamic also relied on Pressburg’s renewed
                    place in the overall patriotic landscape. The quite diverse city had a centre
                    that blended the old families from the patriotic milieu and outsiders coming
                    mostly from the surrounding Western counties. The old Štefanovič, Dérer, and
                    another lawyer, Štefan Fajnor,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn25" n="24"> About
                        the Fajnors and their importance in the second half of the 19<hi
                            rend="superscript">th</hi> century, see for instance Štefan Janšák,
                        <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Život Štefana Fajnora </hi>[The Life
                        of Štefan Fajnor] (Bratislava: Biblioteka, 1933).</note> went on to help in
                    building and strengthening this network. Their sons and daughters, and some of
                    their close friends (Anton Štefánek and Milan Ivanka for instance) carried on
                    their work, alongside the leading Catholic priests such as Ferdinand Juriga<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn26" n="25"> About Juriga and his implication in
                        Slovak politics at that time, see mostly Miroslav Pekník, ed.,
                        <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Ferdinand Juriga. Ľudový smer slovenskej politiky </hi>[Ferdinand
                        Juriga. The populist direction of Slovak politics] (Bratislava: Veda,
                        2009).</note> and a handful of young social democrats. They were all born in
                    the period between 1876 and 1884. Famously, Jozef Dérer’s son, Ivan, who was
                    introduced into politics through the Catholic circles which, as he explained in
                    his unpublished memoirs, “had somehow built a close contact with the mass of
                    people like nobody had before”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn27" n="26"> LA SNK,
                        85 C 33. </note>, benefited from the aura of his father, his closeness to
                    the Štefanovič family (he was about to marry one of Štefanovič’s daughters) and
                    a good relationships with the Fajnors. At that time, Štefanovič was at the top
                    of his reputation, and had gone to Martin to head the Tatra banka, which was
                    facing huge financial difficulties. As such, this unusual choice brought by an
                    “outsider” to the Martin milieu was one of the clues to a new balance in the
                    movement.</p>
                <p>The diversification of the Slovak press was another clue. It came from the
                    Catholic initiatives but also from some of the prominent business families of
                    the Liptov County (mainly the Stodolas and the Makovickýs), who financed the
                    main projects. The classical scheme was the following: the contestations or new
                    options were financed and supported by the elders and organized by the youth.
                    Such press was far from being professional and many projects failed due to
                    persistent dilettantism and regional or personal rivalries combined with weak
                    readership. The financial weakness and dependency on a number of influential
                    families who also had to keep a balanced position between the “old” and the
                    “new” was a constant problem. Despite these weaknesses, the failed experience in
                    the press business helped strengthen certain networks of the young generation
                    who challenged the still-leading centre of Martin.</p>
                <p>For their part, both Blaho and Hodža gradually forged new tools to be utilised in
                    the lower- and middle-class Slovak peasantry. Milan Hodža was one of the
                    youngest active leaders in the very early 20<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>
                    century. He was born in 1878 in Sučany, just a few kilometres from Martin, and
                    belonged to the famous Hodža family; his great-uncle was one of the three
                    Captains of the 1848 Slovak uprising and a long-time friend of Ľudovít Štúr.
                    Milan was also the son of Sučany’s pastor, and, as such, an important figure in
                    Turiec’s religious and cultural life. He studied in Kolozsvár and Budapest and
                    soon started to pay great attention to the “national question”.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn28" n="27"> About that period, see the apologetic
                        chapter written by Ivan
                        Thurzo<hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">. </hi>– Ivan Thurzo and Alena
                        Bartlová,
                        <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Slovenský Perikles </hi>[The Slovak
                        Pericles] (Bratislava: VSSS, 2008).</note> His first public activities were
                    in journalism as he contributed to the <hi rend="italic">Slovenské listy</hi>
                    and <hi rend="italic">Hlas</hi>. In 1900, he became editor-in-chief of <hi
                        rend="italic">Slovenský denník</hi> and relatively soon started to focus
                    more on the politics rather than journalism. Despite the deeply ambiguous
                    positions, he mostly considered the old strategy of the Slovak National Party
                    (SNS) a failure that left the Slovak people unable to face the Magyarization
                    process. Influenced by the Czech “small work”, he openly considered that the SNS
                    did not pay enough attention to social and economic quest, therefore causing
                    severe stagnation. In his opinion, the “peasant question” was the one that had
                    to be urgently resolved and, like Blaho, he paid huge attention to the situation
                    of peasants. However, unlike Blaho, Hodža strove to remain in touch with the SNS
                    and Martin in order to be elected into the party’s councils and to share the
                    burden within them.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn29" n="28"> SNA, f. SNS, Kniha
                        zápisníc. </note> Moreover, in 1903, he created the
                    <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Slovenský týždenník </hi>weekly, which
                    became an influential paper spreading agrarianism, taking advantage of the
                    passing of the <hi rend="italic">Hlas</hi> the following year. Active and
                    skilful, Hodža was elected to the Parliament in Budapest in 1906. Building on
                    this success, he strengthened his position in the party and pushed for the
                    introduction of an “agrarian” chapter in its programme.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn30" n="29"> Ľubomír Lipták, dir., <hi rend="italic">Politické
                            strany na Slovensku
                        (1860</hi>–<hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">1989) </hi>[The political
                        Parties in Slovakia (1860–1989)] (Bratislava: Archa,
                        1992)<hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">, </hi>43.</note></p>
                <p>The building of agrarianism in Slovakia was a showcase of its internal tensions
                    and divisions.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn31" n="30"> Vladimír Zuberec, “<hi
                            rend="italic">Formovanie slovenského národného hnutia v rokoch
                            1900</hi>–<hi rend="italic">1918,</hi>” [The formation of the Slovak
                        national movement, 1900–1918] <hi rend="italic">Historický časopis,</hi> 20
                        (1972): 205–46.</note> The “agrarian” movement of Skalica, and as such
                    Blaho, were sharply criticized by the SNS, which considered Blaho to excessively
                    challenge its authority due to the movement’s own actions. Hodža took advantage
                    of these tensions, notably in a meeting of the SNS Council in 1908, where he
                    sought the introduction of his own projects.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn32"
                        n="31"> SNA, f. SNS, Kniha zápisníc, 83, 84.</note> Hodža’s ambitions suited
                    the need of the SNS to weaken Blaho’s positions and indirectly the positions
                    held by some of those who helped him build the alternatives outside of Martin’s
                    moral <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">imperium. </hi>The SNS favoured
                    Hodža’s strategy,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn33" n="32"> SNA, f. SNS, Kniha
                        zápisníc, 74.</note> and he was soon able to organize a Congress of the
                    Slovak peasants in Budapest in 1908.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn34" n="33">
                        Milan Podrimavský, “Organizácia Slovenskej národnej strany v rokoch
                        1900–1914,” [The organization of the SNS in the years 1900-1914] <hi
                            rend="italic">Historický časopis,</hi> 25 (1977): 193, 194.</note>
                    Although the Czech model remained an inspiration, efforts were divided along a
                    line that separated groups according to geographical (West <hi rend="italic"
                        >vs</hi> Martin) and generational lineages. It is also worth noting that the
                    geographical factor could be compared with the type of family connections that
                    were at stake. The competition in projects for an economic organization of the
                    Slovak peasantry became less aggressive at the eve of the 1910s. The founding of
                    the Central Cooperative [<hi rend="italic">Ústredné družstvo,</hi> ÚD] in 1912
                    ended this second phase of agrarianism.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn35" n="34">
                        Samuel Cambel, <hi rend="italic">Štátnik a národnohospodár Milan
                            Hodža</hi><index indexName="XE">
                            <term>Hodža, Milan (1878-1944)</term>
                        </index><hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve"> 1878</hi>–<hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">1944 </hi>[Statesman
                        and economist Milan Hodža. 1878–1944] (Bratislava: Veda, 2001).</note> At
                    that moment, the old Blaho–Hodža tensions eased because of the emergence of new
                    divisions mostly involving young Catholic priests. The ÚD had gathered
                    first-rank activists of agrarianism for a decade – Blaho<index indexName="XE">
                        <term>Blaho, Pavel (1867–1927)</term>
                    </index>, Hodža –<index indexName="XE">
                        <term>Hodža, Milan (1878-1944)</term>
                    </index>, as well as Kornel Stodola from the business group of Liptov, Skalica’s
                        priest<index indexName="XE">
                        <term>Stodola, Kornel (1866-1946)</term>
                    </index> Ľudovít Okánik<index indexName="XE">
                        <term>Okánik, Ľudovít (1869-1934)</term>
                    </index> (also Blaho’s brother-in-law)<index indexName="XE">
                        <term>Blaho, Pavel (1867-1927)</term>
                    </index>, Milan Ivanka<index indexName="XE">
                        <term>Ivanka, Milan (1876-1950)</term>
                    </index>, one of the few Slovaks who managed to be elected to the Budapest
                        Parliament<index indexName="XE">
                        <term>Budapest</term>
                    </index>,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn36" n="35"> M. Ivanka (1876–1950)<index
                            indexName="XE">
                            <term>Ivanka, Milan (1876-1950)</term>
                        </index> was born in 1876 in T. S. Martin in a small noble family of the
                        Turiec. After finishing school in Martin, he studied law in Budapest and
                        returned to Martin to work in Pavol Mudroň and Matúš Dula’s office. In 1904,
                        he moved to Trnava to open his own practice and married the grand-daughter
                        of Michal Miloslav Hodža. He belonged to the so-called “realist” fraction of
                        the Slovak intelligentsia promoting the “small work”. He played an active
                        part in creating the <hi rend="italic">Hospodárska banka</hi> [Economic
                        bank], and helped in some Slovak candidates’ campaigns in Western Slovakia.
                        He was therefore elected to the Parliament in Budapest to represent Pezinok
                        (in the suburb of Pressburg) in 1907 (election cancelled the following year
                        as Ivanka was sentenced to a year’s imprisonment for anti-Hungarian
                        activities).</note> as well as Anton Štefánek<index indexName="XE">
                        <term>Štefánek, Anton (1877-1964)</term>
                    </index>, who had long been following the first circle.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn37" n="36"> Anton Štefánek (1877–1964) was the son of a shoemaker
                        from Záhorie in Western Slovakia. As a young boy, he lived in Vienna where
                        he frequented the “Tatran” and the “Národ” circles. He maintained strong
                        connections with the liberals of the <hi rend="italic">Hlas</hi> and created
                        the <hi rend="italic">Slovenský obzor</hi> in Budapest in 1907 along with
                        M. Hodža and J. Ruman. In the following years he became editor of the <hi
                            rend="italic">Ľudové noviny</hi> (1908-1910) in Skalica where he worked
                        with Pavol Blaho, whom he met during the “Tatran” period in Vienna. He
                        finally started to work as editor of Hodža’s <hi rend="italic">Slovenský
                            denník</hi>. </note> The creation of the ÚD was an important step that
                    strengthened the existing networks and stimulated the independent economic
                    coordination of the Slovak rural milieu.</p>
                <p>This new organization was comprised of two clearly identifiable generations: the
                    first openly challenged the SNS strategy, the impasse of which it saw as it grew
                    up. It was made up of men born between 1865 and 1875. Some of them did not live
                    in Martin or even Turiec and they shared their first political experiences in
                    the large cities of Cisleithania, Prague and especially Vienna. The second
                    generation included men born in the 1880s, who were often high up in the
                    patriotic movement and based in its most important centres. They had benefited
                    from the transformation of the industrial and business environment enabled by
                    the economic rise of the Kingdom of Hungary during the “liberal” period<hi
                        rend="italic">.</hi> Those young men combined the high-level education,
                    dynamic family networks and experience acquired abroad, where their “elders”
                    surrounded them. The same type of social composition can be found in other
                    fields that developed at the same time, such as the banking system.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn38" n="37"> About the banking system, see mostly
                        Štefan Horváth and Ján Valach, eds., <hi rend="italic">Peňažníctvo na
                            Slovensku do roku 1918</hi> [Finances in Slovakia until 1918]
                        (Bratislava: VTEL, 1975). Recently Roman Holec,
                        <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Tatra banka v zrkadle dejín </hi>[The
                        Tatra bank in the mirror of history] (Bratislava: AEP, 2007).</note> This
                    structure was based on the dynamics of the Liptov, where the Stodolas and mainly
                    the Makovickýs were found at the very centre of a dense family network built
                    over two generations.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn39" n="38"> Z. Ďuriška, <hi
                            rend="italic">Medzi mlynmi.</hi> For another type of family network, see
                        also Zdenko
                        Ďuriška,<hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve"> Pálkovci. Príbeh rodu garbiarských podnikateľov z Liptova</hi>
                        [The Pálkos. History of a Liptov tanneries family] (Martin: SGHS,
                        2013).</note></p>
                <p>Another type of initiative favoured the strengthening of the above links among
                    activists, i.e. the care for renewing relations with the Czech Lands. We will
                    mention only two of the main topics. The more “ritual” one is the Luhačovice
                    meetings that, under the aegis of the Czech association <hi rend="italic"
                        >Českoslovanská jednota</hi> [Czechoslav Unity]<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn40" n="39"> About the creation of the Jednota and its role in
                        this initiative, see Michal Stehlík, <hi rend="italic">Češi a Slováci
                            1882</hi>–<hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">1914. Nezřetelnost společné cesty </hi>[Czechs
                        and Slovaks 1882–1914. The indistinct nature of common paths] (Prague:
                        Togga, 2009). </note>, gathered Slovaks and Czechs each year in a small
                    thermal city of Southern Moravia, where Blaho worked for years during each
                    summer. It was based on old relations created earlier in the Czech Lands. Julius
                    Markovič, for instance, who headed the Popular bank [<hi rend="italic">Ľudová
                        banka</hi>] in Nové Mesto nad Váhom, played a crucial role in attracting the
                    Czech counterparts and businessmen.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn41" n="40">
                        LA SNK, 42 I 327, p. 2.</note> Beyond their crucial role in the renewal of
                    Czech-Slovak relations,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn42" n="41"> SNA, of.
                        Houdek, c. 5, II/3, No. 160, Taborský to Houdek, Prague, 10 April
                        1908.</note> the Luhačovice meetings favoured the development of exchanges
                    – mostly from Slovakia to the Czech Lands.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn43"
                        n="42"> Rudolf Pilat and Josef Rotnágl to Fedor Houdek, Prague, 12 July 1912
                        (SNA, of. Houdek, c. 5, II/3, No. 160). The Jednota regularly acted as a
                        go-between (see for instance letter of Rotnágl to Houdek, Prague, 2 May
                        1913. – Ibid.).</note> The more long-term-oriented new dimension of it was
                    constant help in sending young Slovak students who were poor or not allowed to
                    study in the Kingdom of Hungary to the Czech Lands. Blaho was one of the most
                    active go-betweens of those exchanges that also broadly involved “Western”
                    activists like Dérer, Ivanka and Bella.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn44" n="43">
                        With M. M. Bella for instance, see, SNA, of. Blaho, c. 4, No. 78, 15 October
                        1913. With Dérer, see ibid.<hi rend="italic">,</hi> c. 5, No. 134, letters
                        from September to December 1910.</note> The relative success of these
                    initiatives can also be observed through the proposals of the Czechs to receive
                    the young Slovaks.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn45" n="44"> SNA, of. Blaho, c.
                        33, No. 1434. See also Rotnágl to Šrobár, Prague, 11 November 1912 (SNA, of.
                        Šrobár, c. 5, No. 337).</note> Despite all the efforts they deployed over
                    those years, the Slovak activists faced low financial capacities of the <hi
                        rend="italic">Jednota</hi> and of their own resources.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn46" n="45"> Rotnágl and Ivan Klima to Houdek, Prague, 2 December
                        1911 (SNA, of. Houdek, c. 5, II/3, No. 160) and Rotnágl to Houdek, Prague,
                        17 September 1911. – Ibid..</note> To a certain extent, the positive
                    atmosphere surrounding this help for young students ended in 1912–1913.</p></div>
                <div><head>Overcoming the Lasting Obstacles Within the Slovak Social Politics: <hi
                        rend="italic bold"
                    >Prúdy</hi><hi rend="bold" xml:space="preserve"> and the Prudists</hi></head>
                <p>All these evolutions had an impact on the national movement activities around
                    1910, as it diversified, with clearer diverging options appearing and the new
                    divisions becoming more politically orientated and less dependent on regional
                    differences, yet it still built on a generational and confessional factor – the
                    latter being more important that the former.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn47"
                        n="46"> As an illustration of this deep political fracture, see the
                        correspondence between Ivan Dérer and Pavol Blaho in 1911 (SNA, of. Blaho,
                        c. 4, No. 734) and between Šrobár and Štefanek the following year (SNA, of
                        Šrobár, c. 5, No. 295).</note> Like the <hi rend="italic">Hlas</hi> at the
                    end of the 19<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> century, this new step was mainly
                    the result of the obvious lasting deficiencies in the extension of political and
                    social education and the will showed by a handful of young men to overcome
                    them.</p>
                <p>At the end of the decade, learning from <hi rend="italic">Hlas</hi>’s experience
                    and failures, a fledgling Committee of the Slovak youth decided to publish a
                    review called <hi rend="italic">Prúdy,</hi> where young patriots from prominent
                    families played the leading role.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn48" n="47">
                        Marián Hronský, “K politickému profilu generácie okolo časopisu Prúdy
                        (Prúdistov) (1910–1914),” [About the political profile of the generation
                        around the review Prúdy (1909–1914)] <hi rend="italic">Historický
                            časopis,</hi> 23 (1975): 509–31.</note> Two of them, whose paths were
                    archetypal of the generation who took up the hlasist torch, illustrated a deep
                    link between the new and the old generation; they also grew up in a perfectly
                    patriotic milieu and their fathers experienced both changes and limitations in
                    the Slovak politics. Many of them were Lutherans who matured at a time when
                    efforts to financially strengthen the business and voluntary milieu were somehow
                    more efficient. The first of them was Ivan Markovič, born in 1888. He was the
                    son of Julius, a man who financed the SNS and activities connected to it and who
                    was convicted in the notorious “Nitra trial” of 1902.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn49" n="48"> Julius Markovič,
                        <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Nitrianský politický trestný proces: politická úvaha </hi>[The
                        Nitra political trial: political reflexion] (Turč. Sv. Martin, 1903).</note>
                    The second, Juraj Slávik<index indexName="XE">
                        <term>Slávik, Juraj (1890–1969)</term>
                    </index>, was also a young man born in 1890. He was the son of Ján<index
                        indexName="XE">
                        <term>Slávik, Ján (1855–1934)</term>
                    </index>, Zvolen’s pastor, who was discreetly critical of Martin and expressed
                    his satisfaction at how the hlasists “set the nation in motion”, despite some
                    reserves he had regarding the harsh anticlericalism evident in some of its main
                        representatives.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn50" n="49"> LA SNK, 5 A 15,
                        letter, 6 May 1910 to Jur Janoška.</note> As a clear evidence of the
                    evolution that occurred in the 1900s, the Czechs were active participants in the
                        <hi rend="italic">Prúdy.</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn51" n="50">
                        Namely Bohdan Pavlů<index indexName="XE">
                            <term>Pavlů, Bohdan (1883-1938)</term>
                        </index>, Czech hlasist who studied law in Prague, Vienna and Budapest,
                        became a journalist and worked for the <hi rend="italic">Slovenský
                            týždenník</hi> [<hi rend="italic">The Slovak weekly</hi>] between 1905
                        and 1910, for <hi rend="italic">Čas</hi> [<hi rend="italic">Time</hi>]
                        between 1907 and 1910, and then for the Czech
                            <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Národní listy </hi>[<hi
                            rend="italic">National Letters</hi>]. The other important Czech was
                        František Votruba<index indexName="XE">
                            <term>Votruba, František (1880-1953)</term>
                        </index>. Born near Tábor in southern Bohemia, he worked in Slovakia in the
                        1900s where he made contact with young Slovak writers. From 1911 onwards, he
                        was responsible for<index indexName="XE">
                            <term>Tábor</term>
                        </index> the section “Slovenské věci” [Slovak affairs] of the
                        <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Čas </hi>(about Votruba, see
                        <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Votrubov sborník </hi>[Votruba’s
                            collection<index indexName="XE">
                            <term>Votruba, František (1880-1953)</term>
                        </index>] (Bratislava, 1954), 107–61).</note></p>
                <p>Most of its editorial board agreed with the old hlasist message and the two
                    generations melded and reinforced the dynamics. In his correspondence, Ivan
                    Markovič summed up two important elements of the situation: firstly, the
                    heritage of the <hi rend="italic">Hlas</hi> and Šrobár; and secondly, the
                    remaining problem of a narrow social and cultural base: “We observed that links
                    inside the youth are weak, that we do not really know each other and that few
                    people know us, and when we want to talk together, we have no place to do
                        it.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn52" n="51"> LA SNK, A 970, Markovič to
                        Neckar, 24 September 1909.</note> His description of <hi rend="italic"
                        >Prúdy</hi>’s aims recalls those of the <hi rend="italic">Hlas</hi>: “It
                    will have two functions: publicizing the spiritual fruits of the youth’s work
                    and informing the youth on events, trends and opinions in the Slovak life […] in
                    economics, in politics and also in literature, arts and science.”<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn53" n="52"> Ibid<hi rend="italic">.</hi>
                    </note> He explained that the review should “reflect the spiritual life of the
                    Slovak youth”,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn54" n="53"> Ibid., 14 October
                        1909.</note> prepare ”fighting issues”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn55"
                        n="54"> Ibid., 15 January 1910.</note> and also welcome elder fighters, as
                    long as they challenge the conservative policy of Martin. In that respect,
                    Markovič vehemently defends Šrobár<index indexName="XE">
                        <term>Šrobár, Vavro (1867–1950)</term>
                    </index>’s contribution to the review in interesting terms that show the respect
                    he earned in the young generation: “Šrobár<index indexName="XE">
                        <term>Šrobár, Vavro (1867–1950)</term>
                    </index>’s article testifies that <hi rend="italic">Prúdy</hi> would like to
                    make space for any opinion, and even for the opinions of the elders [at that
                    time Šrobár<index indexName="XE">
                        <term>Šrobár, Vavro (1867–1950)</term>
                    </index> was 43 years old], as long as they relate to the youth, its work and
                    its role. […] Šrobár<index indexName="XE">
                        <term>Šrobár, Vavro (1867–1950)</term>
                    </index> is an unquestionable spiritual tree of the Slovak awakening. For this
                    reason, his opinions have to be taken into account.”<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn56" n="55"> Ibid., 17 March 1910.</note></p>
                <p>This question of the youth, which was of central significance at that time,
                    brought all efforts together. Although this initiative was more elite-focused,
                    it carefully resounded in all types of social politics and education activities
                    during the following years. It was consciously devoted to underlining the impact
                    of those actions and the manner in which its influence was spreading. Štefánek
                    summed up the difference by using the classical Martin orientation: “Here, it
                    was not only about diverging opinions or differences in work methods in general.
                    It was not only what we call the fight of the youth against the eldest… but a
                    fundamental transformation in political and working methods…”<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn57" n="56"> LA SNK, 42 X 22.</note> In order to help this
                    transformation, shares in <hi rend="italic">Prúdy</hi> were offered from
                        April<hi rend="color(FF0000)"> </hi>1910 in order to create a consortium to
                    provide aid for the review and establish the “Prúdy’s Library” collection of
                    popular and scientific booklets.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn58" n="57">
                        LA SNK, A 970, Markovič and Pavlů<index indexName="XE">
                            <term>Pavlů, Bohdan (1883-1938)</term>
                        </index> to Neckar, 4 April 1910.</note></p>
                <p>This was also when the first project for a Slovak “daily” newspaper actually
                    succeeded. Interestingly, the initiative was a genuine blend of different
                    generations that have previously been discussed. Hodža’s first attempts failed
                    due to inexperience, weak resources and narrow audience. After his election in
                    1906, the need for a daily paper that would spread political information
                    emerged. The human and financial context in many ways facilitated the project.
                    Amongst others, Hodža, Bella<index indexName="XE">
                        <term>Bella, Matej Metod (1869–1947)</term>
                    </index>, Ivan Daxner, Šrobár<index indexName="XE">
                        <term>Šrobár, Vavro (1867–1950)</term>
                    </index>, Ľudovít Medvecký, and Fedor Houdek took part in the final meeting of
                    21 November 1909 in
                    Vrútky<hi rend="color(FF0000)" xml:space="preserve">. </hi>The editorial board
                    was to be headed by Hodža and Štefánek.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn59" n="58">
                        SNA, of. Houdek, c. 32, No. 215/3.</note> The strength of Liptov capital in
                    the project is attested to by the fact that Šrobár<index indexName="XE">
                        <term>Šrobár, Vavro (1867–1950)</term>
                    </index>, Peter Makovický, and Houdek led the consortium, all of them drawing on
                    their Liptov business networks. These publishing initiatives lasted long enough
                    to structure the political debate until the breakout of war. Besides the already
                    mentioned activists, various circles with the same background were strengthened
                    by these initiatives, as were their experience, networks and ability to shake up
                    the old SNS. However, the latter remained dominant and almost unchallenged as
                    the structure that was to unite “the different orientations of the nation”.</p>
                <p>Apart from a few exceptions, all of the main figures had fathers or forefathers
                    who were members of the main cultural associations, very frequently board
                    members, and a huge majority of them were subscribers to the main Slovak press
                    editions, shareholders or guarantors in their publishing houses, shareholders in
                    Slovak banks or holders of reciprocal stakes in their businesses. Many of their
                    fathers were famous in the milieu because of their involvement as lawyers, bank
                    founders, businessmen or Lutheran clergymen.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn60"
                        n="59"> See Ľudovít Šenšel, <hi rend="italic">Pätdesiat rokov Tranoscia.
                            1898</hi>–<hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">1948 </hi>[50 years of
                        Tranoscius] (Liptovský Mikuláš, 1948), 14.</note> Some of them personally
                    benefitted from marrying into important families, like Jozef Gregor-Tajovský for
                    instance. Belonging to the prominent and aspiring young Prudists, he was a
                    talented writer who married Anna Lilgová (known as Gregorová in Slovak literary
                    history), the daughter of an influential family belonging to Martin’s Slovak
                        bourgeoisie,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn61" n="60"> See Hana Gregorová,
                        <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Spomienky </hi>[Memories]
                            (Bratislava<index indexName="XE">
                            <term>Bratislava</term>
                        </index>: Tatran, 1979). To go deeper on this aspect, see another
                        illustration in: Ján Hrušovský,
                        <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Starý Martin v živote a ľudoch </hi>[Old
                        Martin in its life and people] (Martin, 1947) [New edition:
                        <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Obrázky starého Martina </hi>[Images
                        of the old Martin]<hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">, </hi>(Martin:
                        Matica slovenská, 2010)].</note> and played a decisive role in the evolution
                    of the new party programme in 1913.</p>
                <p>In conclusion, there are three points that should be highlighted. Firstly, the
                    transformation of the action and ideological references in the active fraction
                    of the patriotic movement included a shift in its geographical centres and
                    external influences – mostly from the Czech Lands. It is worth noting that, save
                    for a few exceptions, none of them originated from Martin. This is a first clue
                    to the decreasing influence of the city and its institutions in favour of the
                    neighbouring cities in the Liptov area and Western Slovakia. Secondly,
                    challenging the classical politics of Martin did not necessarily mean breaking
                    with its heritage. Most of the young activists simply could not conceive acting
                    without at least a tacit agreement from the “capital city”, i.e. Martin; in the
                    first part of the 1910s, they even accumulated enough influence and support to
                    join its structures and eventually play a decisive part in drawing up its
                    renewed programme in 1913. This inclusion in party politics is partly due to the
                    idea in which unity had to prevail in an otherwise unfavourable cultural and
                    political atmosphere. In many cases, newcomers used the same tools as their
                    elders in the mid-1890s. Finally, the relationships they developed with their
                    Czech counterparts – as they obviously benefited from their stays in
                    Prague – created some common solidarities that allowed easier cooperation during
                    the First World War and enabled them to play a leading role in the internal
                    shift towards the Czechoslovak project in 1918. This shift was accelerated by
                    the war, the growing contestation of the Party’s passive position, and political
                    opportunity. Moreover, those involved in the <hi rend="italic">Hlas</hi> and
                    their “heirs” at the <hi rend="italic">Prúdy</hi> took a firm lead in the Slovak
                    politics at the end of 1918, as five out of 15 members of the first provisional
                    Slovak government of December 1918 belonged to the <hi rend="italic">Hlas</hi>
                    first editorial board, while a handful of others were involved in the <hi
                        rend="italic">Prúdy</hi> and various circles active in the “small social
                    work”, including the cooperatives or support to Slovak youth. Most of these men,
                    who steeped in the history and contradictions of patriotic action, would become
                    the backbone of (Czecho-)Slovak politics throughout the interwar period. The
                    depth of their connections as well as their shared “Hungarian period” history,
                    solidarities and hatred are one of the many keys that can help observe the first
                    Czechoslovak Republic and the Slovak role therein.</p>
            </div>

        </body>
        <back>
            <div>
                <head>Sources and Literature</head>
                <list type="unordered">
                    <head>Archive sources:</head>
                    <item>SNA, BA – Slovak National Archive, Bratislava:<list>
                            <item>Personal collection Blaho.</item>
                            <item>Personal collection Houdek.</item>
                            <item>Personal collection Šrobár.</item>
                            <item>SNS, Kniha zápisníc.</item>
                        </list></item>
                    <item>LA SNK, Martin – Literary archive, Slovak National Library, Martin :<list>
                            <item>A 970. Ivan Markovič’s letters.</item>
                            <item>A 1505. Fond A. Pisatelia korešpondencie.</item>
                            <item>C 1438.Fond 16. Spoločnosti.</item>
                            <item>5 A 15. Jur Janoška collection.</item>
                            <item>37 BB 11. Halaša-Mudroň collection.</item>
                            <item>42 I 327. Štefánek collection.</item>
                            <item>42 X 22. Štefánek collection.</item>
                            <item>42 X 22.Štefánek collection.</item>
                            <item>85 C 33.Dérer collection.</item>
                        </list></item>
                </list>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Literature:</head>
                    <bibl>Azéma, Jean-Pierre. “La clef générationnelle.” [The generational key]
                        <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Vingtième Siècle, </hi>22 (1989):
                        3–10.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Bokes, František.  <hi rend="italic">Dokumenty k slovenskému národnému
                            hnutia, I.</hi> [Documents on the Slovak National Movement. 1<hi
                            rend="superscript">st</hi> volume] Bratislava: SAV, 1962.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Cambel, Samuel. <hi rend="italic">Štátnik a národnohospodár Milan Hodža
                            1878</hi>–<hi rend="italic">1944.</hi> [Statesman and economist Milan
                        Hodža. 1878–1944] Bratislava: Veda, 2001. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Ďuriška, Zdenko. <hi rend="italic">Medzi mlynmi a bankami. Dejiny rodu
                            Makovickovcov.</hi> [Between mills and banks. The history of the
                        Makovický family] Martin: SGHS, 2007.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Ďuriška, Zdenko. <hi rend="italic">Pálkovci. Príbeh rodu garbiarských
                            podnikateľov z Liptova.</hi> [The Pálkos. History of a Liptov tanneries
                        family] Martin: SGHS, 2013.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Garver, Bruce M. <hi rend="italic">The Young Czech Party 1874</hi>–<hi
                            rend="italic">1901. The Emergence of a Multi-party System.</hi> New
                        Haven: Yale University Press, 1978. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Gregorová, Hana. <hi rend="italic">Spomienky.</hi> [Memories] Bratislava:
                        Tatran, 1979. </bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="italic">Historický časopis</hi>, 17 (1969). “Z korešpondencie
                        predsaviteľov českého a slovenského národného hnutia na prelome 19. a 20.
                        storočia:” [From the correspondence between Czech and Slovak national
                        movement at the turn of the 20<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> century]
                        270–84.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Holec, Roman.
                        <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Tatra banka v zrkadle dejín. </hi>[The
                        Tatra bank in the mirror of history] Bratislava: AEP, 2007.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Holec, Roman.  <hi rend="italic">Tragédia v Černovej a slovenská
                            spoločnosť.</hi> [The Tragedy of Černová Černová and Slovak society]
                        Martin: Matica slovenská, 1997.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Horváth, Štefan and Ján Valach, eds. <hi rend="italic">Peňažníctvo na
                            Slovensku do roku 1918.</hi> [Finances in Slovakia until 1918]
                        Bratislava: VTEL, 1975.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Hronský, Marián. “K politickému profilu generácie okolo časopisu Prúdy
                        (Prúdistov) (1910–1914).” [About the political profile of the generation
                        around the review Prúdy (1909–1914)] <hi rend="italic">Historický
                            časopis,</hi> 23 (1975): 509–31.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Hrušovský, Ján. <hi rend="italic">Starý Martin v živote a ľudoch.</hi>
                        [Old Martin in its life and people] Martin, 1947.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Janšák, Štefan. <hi rend="italic">Život Štefana Fajnora.</hi> [The Life of
                        Štefan Fajnor] Bratislava: Biblioteka, 1933.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Kořalka, Jiří. <hi rend="italic">Češi v habsburské říši a v Evropě
                            1815</hi>–<hi rend="italic">1914.</hi> [The Czechs in the Habsburg
                        Empire and in Europe] Prague: Argo, 1996.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Křen, Jan. <hi rend="italic">Konfliktní společenství. Češi a Němci
                            1780</hi>–<hi rend="italic">1918.</hi> [Conflicting Societies. Czechs
                        and Germans 1780–1918] Prague: Academia, 1990. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Lipták, Ľubomír, dir. <hi rend="italic">Politické strany na Slovensku
                            (1860</hi>–<hi rend="italic">1989).</hi> [The political Parties in
                        Slovakia (1860–1989)] Bratislava: Archa, 1992.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Markovič, Julius. <hi rend="italic">Nitrianský politický trestný proces:
                            politická úvaha.</hi> [The Nitra political trial: political reflexion]
                        Turč. Sv. Martin, 1903.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Pekník, Miroslav, ed. <hi rend="italic">Ferdinand Juriga. Ľudový smer
                            slovenskej politiky.</hi> [Ferdinand Juriga. The popular direction of
                        Slovak politics] Bratislava: Veda, 2009. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Podrimavský, Milan. “Organizácia Slovenskej národnej strany v rokoch
                        1900–1914.” [The organization of the SNS in the years 1900-1914] <hi
                            rend="italic">Historický časopis,</hi> 25 (1977): 193, 194.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Podrimavský, Milan. <hi rend="italic">Slovenská národná strana v druhej
                            polovici 19. storočia.</hi> [The Slovak National Party in the second
                        half of the 19<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> century] Bratislava: SAV,
                        1983.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Rychlík, Jan, ed. <hi rend="italic">Korespondence T. G. Masaryk
                            – slovenští veřejní činitelé.</hi> [Correspondence T. G. Masaryk
                        – Slovak public activists] Prague: Masarykův ústav AV ČR, 2007.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Sirinelli, Jean-François. “<hi rend="italic">Génération et histoire
                            politique.</hi>” [Generations and political history]
                        <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Vingtième Siècle, </hi>22
                        (1989).</bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Slovenské národné zhromaždenie v Turčianskom Sv. Martine 1861. </hi>[The
                        1861 Slovak national assembly of Turčianský Sväty Martin] T. S. Martin:
                        Matica slovenská, 1941.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Stehlík, Michal. <hi rend="italic">Češi a Slováci 1882</hi>–<hi
                            rend="italic">1914. Nezřetelnost společné cesty.</hi> [Czechs and
                        Slovaks 1882-1914. The indistinct nature of common paths] Prague: Togga,
                        2009. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Šenšel, Ľudovít. <hi rend="italic">Pätdesiat rokov Tranoscia.
                            1898</hi>–<hi rend="italic">1948.</hi> [50 years of Tranoscius]
                        Liptovský Mikuláš, 1948.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Šrobár, Vavro. “Počiatky slovenského obrodenia.” [The beginnings of the
                        Slovak awakening] In:
                        <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Sborník slovenskej mladeže </hi>[Slovak
                        youth collection], 1909.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Thurzo, Ivan. <hi rend="italic">Medzi vrchmi a na rovine.</hi> [Between
                        the hills and in the plains] Bratislava: Tatran, 1987. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Thurzo, Ivan and Alena Bartlová. <hi rend="italic">Slovenský
                            Perikles.</hi> [The Slovak Pericles] Bratislava: Vydavateľstvo Spolku
                        slovenských spisovateľov, 2008.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Zuberec, Vladimír. “<hi rend="italic">Formovanie slovenského národného
                            hnutia v rokoch 1900</hi>–<hi rend="italic">1918.</hi>” [The formation
                        of the Slovak national movement, 1900-1918] <hi rend="italic">Historický
                            časopis,</hi> 20 (1972): 205–46.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Winock, Michel.
                        <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">L’Effet de génération. Une brève histoire des intellectuels français. </hi>[The
                        generational effect. A brief history of French intellectuals] Paris: Thierry
                        Marchaisse, 2011.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
            <div type="summary">
                <docAuthor>Etienne Boisserie </docAuthor>
                <head>DRUŽINSKE VEZI IN »GENERACIJSKI KLJUČ« V PRENOVLJENIH PRISTOPIH K DRUŽBENEMU
                    VREDNOTENJU SLOVAŠKE ELITE NA ZAČETKU 20. STOLETJA</head>
                <head>POVZETEK</head>
                <p>Članek preučuje del evolucije, do katere je prišlo v slovaškem patriotskem okolju
                    ob koncu 19. in na začetku 20. stoletja. Opaziti je mogoče intelektualni
                    preobrat, ki po eni strani temelji na geografski razširitvi dejavnosti mladih
                    slovaških patriotov in po drugi strani na vplivu revije
                    <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Hlas </hi>(1898–1904), na katero so imeli
                    močan vpliv novinci, ki so študirali v avstrijskem delu Avstro-ogrske monarhije.
                    Ta proces je tik pred 20. stoletjem privedel do nove dinamike, a je bil na koncu
                    neuspešen predvsem zaradi trajnih vrzeli v slovaški družbeni politiki. </p>
                <p>Nova generacija, ki je bila pod velikim vplivom zapuščine revije <hi
                        rend="italic">Hlas</hi>, je skušala te vrzeli premostiti z novimi povezavami
                    med različnimi regijami, ki so bile vključene v patriotsko gibanje, in njihovimi
                    glavnimi člani, ter ustvariti orodja za oblikovanje prenovljene vizije družbenih
                    potreb na Slovaškem. Zdi se, da so bile ožja družina in prijateljske vezi enako
                    učinkovite kot v prejšnjih desetletjih, ko so prav tako krepile vezi med
                    aktivisti. Kljub temu se je tik pred 1. svetovno vojno slovaško patriotsko
                    okolje soočalo s težavami pri izvedbi družbenega in nacionalnega programa.</p>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
