<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Writing the Political History of the Republic of Slovenia</title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename>Jure</forename>
                        <surname>Gašparič</surname>
                        <roleName>senior researcher, PhD</roleName>
                        <affiliation>Institute of Contemporary History</affiliation>
                        <address>
                            <addrLine>Kongresni trg 1</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>1000 - Ljubljana, Slovenia</addrLine>
                        </address>
                        <email>jure.gasparic@inz.si</email>
                    </name>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>2016-10-06</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>
                    <orgName xml:lang="sl">Inštitut za novejšo zgodovino</orgName>
                    <orgName xml:lang="en">Institute of Contemporary History</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Kongresni trg 1</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>SI-1000 Ljubljana</addrLine>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>http://ojs.inz.si/pnz/article/view/182</pubPlace>
                <date>2016</date>
                <availability status="free">
                    <licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title xml:lang="sl">Prispevki za novejšo zgodovino</title>
                <title xml:lang="en">Contributions to Contemporary History</title>
                <biblScope unit="volume">56</biblScope>
                <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
                <idno type="ISSN">2463-7807</idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source, born digital.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc xml:lang="en">
                <p>Contributions to Contemporary History is one of the central Slovenian scientific
                    historiographic journals, dedicated to publishing articles from the field of
                    contemporary history (the 19th and 20th century).</p>
                <p>The journal is published three times per year in Slovenian and in the following
                    foreign languages: English, German, Serbian, Croatian, Bosnian, Italian, Slovak
                    and Czech. The articles are all published with abstracts in English and
                    Slovenian as well as summaries in English.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <projectDesc xml:lang="sl">
                <p>Prispevki za novejšo zgodovino je ena osrednjih slovenskih znanstvenih
                    zgodovinopisnih revij, ki objavlja teme s področja novejše zgodovine (19. in 20.
                    stoletje).</p>
                <p>Revija izide trikrat letno v slovenskem jeziku in v naslednjih tujih jezikih:
                    angleščina, nemščina, srbščina, hrvaščina, bosanščina, italijanščina, slovaščina
                    in češčina. Članki izhajajo z izvlečki v angleščini in slovenščini ter povzetki
                    v angleščini.</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="sl"/>
                <language ident="en"/>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords xml:lang="en">
                    <term>Political history</term>
                    <term>1991–2016</term>
                    <term>Slovenia</term>
                    <term>political parties</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords xml:lang="sl">
                    <term>politična zgodovina</term>
                    <term>1991–2016</term>
                    <term>Slovenija</term>
                    <term>politične stranke</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change>
                    <date>2016-10-18</date>
                    <name>Neja Blaj Hribar</name>
                    <desc>Pretvorba iz DOCX v TEI, dodatno kodiranje</desc>
                </change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <docAuthor>Jure Gašparič<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn1" n="*"><hi rend="bold">senior
                        researcher, PhD, Institute of Contemporary History, Kongresni trg 1, 1000 -
                        Ljubljana, Slovenia,<ref target="mailto:jure.gasparic@inz.si"
                            >jure.gasparic@inz.si</ref></hi></note></docAuthor>
            <docImprint>
                <idno type="cobissType">Cobiss tip: 1.01</idno>
                <idno type="UDC">UDK: </idno>
                <date>Prejeto 6. 10. 2016</date>
            </docImprint>
            <div type="abstract" xml:lang="sl">
                <head type="main">IZVLEČEK</head>
                <head>PISATI POLITIČNO ZGODOVINO REPUBLIKE SLOVENIJE</head>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Avtor v prispevku obravnava problematiko raziskovanja in
                        pisanja politične zgodovine Republike Slovenije po letu 1991. Po uvodni
                        ugotovitvi, da ljudje od vsega začetka niso zaupali politikom in strankam,
                        zastavi vprašanje, kako so ti ves čas ravnali, kako so se razvijale
                        politične institucije, kako so se prilagajale svetu in času, ki se je v
                        dvajsetih letih spremenil. Najprej predstavi številne dileme in metodološke
                        posebnosti problematike (problem historične distance, smiselnost početja,
                        neobvladljivost in specifičnost virov), nato pa oriše mogoče pristope in
                        načine spopadanja z izzivom. V drugem delu prispevka povzame ugotovitve
                        lastnega raziskovanja tega obdobja (o polarizaciji, personalizaciji,
                        medializaciji in informalizaciji politike), jih vpenja v širši evropski
                        okvir in poleg tega zariše še izziv za prihodnje raziskovanje.</hi></p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Ključne besede: politična zgodovina, 1991–2016, Slovenija,
                        politične stranke</hi></p>
            </div>
            <div type="abstract">
                <head>ABSTRACT</head>
                <p><hi rend="italic">The author focuses on the issue of researching and writing the
                        political history of the Republic of Slovenia after its independence in
                        1991. After his introductory assessment that ever since the beginning people
                        have not trusted politicians and political parties, he focuses on the
                        question of how people have acted throughout this time, how the political
                        institutions have been developing, and how they have been adapting to the
                        world and the times which have changed radically in the last twenty five
                        years. First the author presents numerous dilemmas and methodological
                        peculiarities of the issue at hand (the problem of historical distance, the
                        sensibility of the activity, the uncontrollable and specific sources), and
                        then he proceeds to describe the possible approaches and methods of meeting
                        this challenge. In the second part of the contribution the author sums up
                        the findings resulting from his own research of this period (about the
                        polarisation, personalisation, medialisation and informalisation of
                        politics), placing them into the wider European context. Furthermore, he
                        also outlines the challenges for future research.</hi></p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Keywords: Political history, 1991–2016, Slovenia, political
                        parties</hi></p>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div>
                <head>"A New Political Spectrum Is Being Created..."</head>
                <p>Attempting to write a paper about the development of the Slovenian politics of
                    the last quarter of a century represents a special challenge and a kind of an
                    adventure for historians. It is best illustrated by looking at the beginnings
                    and the final stages of the period – namely, extreme points help historiography
                    to correctly place and interpret the processes. Let us begin in 1993 and take a
                    look at the young National Assembly (Slovenian Parliament). That autumn it was
                    visited, in the middle of an intense budgetary discussion, by the Czech
                    President Václav Havel, "Citizen Havel". The former dissident, dramatist and
                    author of political essays addressed the Slovenian MPs with a short speech in
                    accordance with his political thought about the "anti-political politics".<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn2" n="1"> Jiří Suk, "Od nezmožnosti politiky k
                        politice jako umění možného. Paradohní život občana Václava Havla v letech
                            1969<hi rend="italic">–</hi>1992," in: <hi rend="italic">Kapitoly z
                            dějin české demokracie po roce 1989</hi>, ed. Adéla Gjuričová and Michal
                        Kopeček (Praha and Litomyšl: Paseka, 2008), 16<hi rend="italic">–</hi>51.
                    </note> The popular Havel symbolised the romantic, "velvet" image of the
                    transition, which, however, was essentially quite a bit rougher than that in the
                    Czech Republic as well as in Slovenia.</p>
                <p>"One of the things we most definitely have in common is that we are both building
                    a parliamentary democracy," Havel said. "A new political spectrum is emerging,
                    with new political subjects who are seeking their own identity and their place.
                    These subjects are now searching for new avenues for cooperation, also with
                    regard to the ways of representation. To put it simply, we are building a
                    political system... However, many dangers lurk in this dramatic, interesting and
                    exciting situation, and we should pay special attention to them. In my opinion,
                    one of such dangers is that the parties in our territory could obtain an
                    overrated role. It seems as if the state suddenly belonged to the political
                    parties. As if the parties were not supposed to serve their country, but rather
                    that the country should serve the parties... I wholeheartedly wish that your
                    Parliament as well as ours were safe from these dangers, which have been preying
                    on us in this difficult period."<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn3" n="2">
                        Dokumentacijsko-knjižnični oddelek Državnega zbora Republike Slovenije,
                        Dobesedni zapis 13. seje I. mandata DZ z dne 9. 11. 1993 [Verbatim Record of
                        13th Session of the first Mandate]. Available at: <hi rend="italic">Portal
                            DZ</hi>, <ref target="http://www.dz-rs.si"
                        >http://www.dz-rs.si</ref>.</note>
                </p>
                <p>As the most recent research of our Czech colleagues emphasises, in Havel’s
                    opinion the Czech Parliament was "not safe" from danger. As President, Havel
                    constantly criticised it for being hesitant and slow. Havel’s attitude was quite
                    openly anti-parliamentary (which has until now been overlooked by those who have
                    studied his work), and this stance of his was widely supported by the Czech
                        people.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn4" n="3"> Adéla Gjuričová,
                        "Anti-politics and anti-parliamentarism. Václav Havel and the Czechoslovak
                        parliament in the 1990s." Conference Paper (European Information and
                        Research Network on Parliamentary History: <hi rend="italic"
                            >Parlamentarismuskritik und Antiparlamentarismus in Europa</hi>. Berlin,
                        7 and 8 May 2015).</note> However, Havel was not only supported by his own
                    compatriots, but also by the citizens of Slovenia. Already in the time when the
                    Slovenian political system was being formed – when there was a lot of optimism
                    in the country – people did not trust the political institutions, parties and
                        politicians.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn5" n="4"> Niko Toš, ed., <hi
                            rend="italic">Vrednote v prehodu VIII. Slovenija v srednje in
                            vzhodnoevropskih primerjavah 1991–2011</hi> (Ljubljana and Wien:
                        Univerza v Ljubljani, Fakulteta za družbene vede, IDV-CJMMK and Edition
                        Echoraum, 2014), 302. Jure Gašparič, "O samoumevnosti uvajanja parlamentarne
                        demokracije v vzhodni Evropi po letu 1989." Conference Paper (<hi
                            rend="italic">Regionalni vidiki tranzicije</hi>. Nova Gorica, 15 October
                        2015).</note> According to the former politician and Constitutional Court
                    Judge Ciril Ribičič, people were supposedly convinced that the Parliament was a
                    "gang of lazy spendthrifts".<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn6" n="5"> Ciril
                        Ribičič, <hi rend="italic">Siva tipka 074</hi> (Ljubljana: Enotnost, 1995),
                        124.</note> In the following years Slovenia became the absolute champion in
                    almost all of the statistical categories used by Brussels to compare the
                    countries of the European East.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn7" n="6"> At the
                        tenth anniversary of the independent Slovenia, the Government Office for
                        Communication presented the Slovenian achievements in the following manner:
                        »In these past ten years Slovenia dismantled the old economy and set up a
                        new one. It has a national shipbuilding industry and its own airline, a
                        stock exchange, its World Trade Center and other institutions. With 892,000
                        people in employment, it boasts a per capita GDP of US$ 9,150 and an
                        inflation rate of 8.9 per cent. It introduced its own currency, the Slovene
                        tolar, it has strong foreign exchange reserves, and a tax system that is
                        increasingly in tune with that of Western Europe. The former socially-owned
                        companies have been (almost) entirely privatised. Business activities are
                        increasingly liberal, the exchange rate is favourable, the interest rate is
                        high in real terms and fiscal policy envisages minimal budget deficits.
                        Slovenia is rapidly becoming a transport hub, with the shortest route
                        connecting France and Italy with Hungary (Milan-Ljubljana-Budapest), and the
                        Balkans with Central Europe (Zagreb- Ljubljana-Munich). In the political
                        arena it has become established as a partner and adviser on the margin of
                        the turbulent Balkans. From its acceptance into the United Nations up to its
                        membership of the Security Council, the Council of Europe, the Organisation
                        for Security and Cooperation in Europe (OSCE), the World Trade Organisation
                        (WTO), the International Monetary Fund (IMF) and other international
                        institutions and also to becoming the most serious candidate country for
                        membership of Nato and the European Union, it is mapping out the path of a
                        recognised and established state in the modern world. It is an up-to-date,
                        progressive democracy, while at the same time it has retained the unique
                        image of a small nation that has not just survived millennia of foreign
                        influence and rule, but has also entered into the new order as a winner.« –
                            <hi rend="italic">Slovenia - 10 Years of Independence,</hi> 30 May 2016,
                            <ref target="http://www.slovenija2001.gov.si/10years/independence/"
                            >http://www.slovenija2001.gov.si/10years/independence/</ref>.</note> The
                    slogan about the Story of Success spread, but the standpoint with regard to
                    politics and political parties did not change. Quite the opposite: if we look at
                    the end of "our period", at the year 2013, we can establish that this opinion of
                    the people has only strengthened. </p>
                <p>In 2013 the dissatisfaction resulting from the economic crisis kept getting
                    increasingly profound and more and more obviously oriented against the political
                        elites.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn8" n="7"> The description of 2013 is
                        based on my text about the sixth term of the National Assembly. See: Jure
                        Gašparič,
                        <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Slovenski parlament. Politično-zgodovinski pregled od začetka prvega do konca šestega mandata (1992–2014) - Elektronska izdaja 1.0 </hi>(Ljubljana:
                        Inštitut za novejšo zgodovino, 2014). Available at: Zgodovina Slovenije –
                        SIstory, <ref target="http://www.sistory.si/SISTORY:ID:26950"
                            >http://www.sistory.si/SISTORY:ID:26950</ref>.</note> The general
                    disgruntlement, disappointment, resentment and mistrust due to – according to
                    the people's conviction – inappropriate responses of the state gradually
                    escalated into direct protests. The events started in the socially sensitive
                    environment: in the city of Maribor, from where the spark of the "people's
                    uprisings" also spread to other cities, including Ljubljana, where protesters
                    would frequently gather in front of the Parliament en masse. Mottoes about the
                    wrongfulness of the political system as well as appeals for the introduction of
                    direct democracy started appearing... Politics once again became similar to the
                    oldest trade, and this was expressed by one of the protesters in a brutally
                    direct, vulgar, but politically exceedingly meaningful banner: "A fuck or a
                    refund!"</p>
                <p>The beginning and the end of "our period" are thus, at the first glance, quite
                    closely connected in terms of the issue at hand. The cause-and-effect
                    relationship looks like this: a quarter of a century ago we started building a
                    political system, but ever since the beginning we have been finding that it did
                    not work very well and that it should not be trusted. Towards the end of our
                    period we have shown this through protests. The interpretation is simple, but
                    lacking a vital part: <hi rend="italic">politics itself.</hi> What have the
                    actions of the politicians been, how have the political institutions developed,
                    and how have they adapted to the world and the times that have changed in the
                    last twenty years? Obviously completely differently from what the people
                    expected. Does this mean that politicians are irrational? Are the voters, who
                    keep electing supposedly unsuitable politicians all the time, those who are
                    irrational? How can we explain and describe politics in the modern world? Vaclav
                    Havel once said: "We live in a postmodern world where everything is possible and
                    nothing is certain."<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn9" n="8"> Quoted after:
                        Andreas Rödder, <hi rend="italic">21.0. Eine kurze Geschichte der
                            Gegenwart</hi> (München: C.H.Beck, 2016), 11.</note> In the opinion of
                    many historians, the period after the Cold War is unclear and chaotic,
                        "unlesbar",<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn10" n="9"> Ibid.</note> and the
                    same goes for politics. Despite many similarities with the political history of
                    the older periods, delving into the more recent past is a true adventure, which
                    at the very beginning poses a few important methodological questions, brings on
                    challenges, reveals dilemmas, but at the same time already offers some answers
                    in advance.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>About the Distinctiveness of the Topic and About the Dilemmas</head>
                <p>The first answer, which can often be noted in the media and in a part of the
                    expert public, is that the research of the Slovenian politics after 1991 may be
                    an interesting and relevant topic, but that nothing truly new can be written
                    about it – at least not anything that has not already been written by those who
                    wrote about it and deliberated on it as it was happening.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn11" n="10"> When the biography of the former President Milan
                        Kučan was published, a journalist of the Delo newspaper brought the
                        attention to this issue as well when he asked the author the following:
                        "I've mentioned to a few of my colleagues that I'm reading your book. Every
                        one of them asked me the same question: 'Is there anything new in it?' What
                        they meant was whether the book revealed anything to refute all of the
                        previous interpretations..." – Matija Grah, "Vem za pričakovanja, da bom
                        odkril skrivnosti murgelske kleti," <hi rend="italic">Delo</hi>, 30 October
                        2015.</note> This sort of history would therefore only make sense if the
                    researcher stumbled upon reliable documents about one of the unknown or
                    unexplained political scandals from the last quarter of the century.</p>
                <p>Another preliminary answer, which is actually already a dilemma, concerns the
                    question of the general sensibility of researching processes that have not yet
                    come to their conclusion or we at least do not know that they have concluded. As
                    it is, a quarter of a century of the Slovenian state is a period of a
                    multi-layered transition, which is not yet complete in all of its aspects and
                    surges (of course, it is questionable how to define the conclusions of
                    processes). At the same time this period has been co-created by the elites that
                    are still at least partly publicly active (and which, of course, interpret these
                    processes in their own way). Hence it is supposedly too soon for historians to
                    take a look at this period of time. Things which may seem very significant today
                    and which the historians might focus on in their research could look completely
                    insignificant in time (and vice versa).<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn12" n="11">
                        Rödder, <hi rend="italic">21.0. Eine kurze Geschichte der Gegenwart</hi>,
                        13.</note> The history of the present, as George Kennan referred to it, is
                    thus allegedly not truly possible.</p>
                <p>The following dilemma, which is simultaneously a challenge, is related to the
                    temporal component. What is a methodologically suitable manner at all in which
                    historians could explore the recent politics and the phenomenon of the
                    political? As it happens, the available materials are inexhaustible in all
                    aspects, with regard to quantity as well as in terms of substantive and
                    scientific breadth. Besides the enormous quantities of materials produced by the
                    media – from newspapers to television, radio and internet sites – it is also
                    possible to collect the oral sources from the participants of the political
                    developments and make use of the vast quantity of the materials produced on a
                    daily basis and published by the state or its institutions (reports on the work
                    of the governments, handover files, studies, legislative materials, verbatim
                    records of parliamentary sessions, etc.). On the one hand these materials are
                    more diverse as, for example, the materials from the period of the first
                    Yugoslav state (Kingdom of SHS/Yugoslavia), but simultaneously also more
                    extensive and more comprehensive (non-evaluated, unfiltered, preserved in their
                    totality). Especially the audio-visual materials, which influence the world view
                    of the today's generations most significantly, represent a special challenge and
                    make the century-old historiographic rule <hi rend="italic">Quod non est in
                        actis non est in mundo</hi> quite problematic.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn13" n="12"> To find out more about the challenges that the
                        audiovisual media represent for the researchers of the present see: Thomas
                        Lindenberger, "Vergangenes Hören und Sehen. Zeitgeschichte und ihre
                        Herausforderung durch die audiovisuellen Medien," in: <hi rend="italic"
                            >Zeithistorische Forschungen/Studies in Contemporary History</hi>,
                        Online-Ausgabe, 1 (2004), H. 1, URL: <ref
                            target="http://www.zeithistorische-forschungen.de/1-2004/id=4586"
                            >http://www.zeithistorische-forschungen.de/1-2004/id=4586</ref>,
                        Druckausgabe: 72<hi rend="italic">–</hi>85.</note> Furthermore, a truly vast
                    quantity of online and other digital contents is being produced today: tweets,
                    Facebook posts, text messages... Quite a few resounding public stories have been
                    triggered precisely by this sort of media, but nevertheless nobody archives
                    these sorts of contents systematically.</p>
                <p>At the same time the historians of the most contemporary period have numerous
                    studies and analyses at their disposal as well as rough data produced by other
                    sciences that focus on modernity. In order to research the period of the
                    independent Republic of Slovenia it is critical to acquire the materials and
                    analyses from the Social Science Data Archives<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn14"
                        n="13"> See: <hi rend="italic">O Arhivu družboslovnih podatkov</hi>,
                        http://www.adp.fdv.uni-lj.si/o_arhivu/.</note> – especially the surveys
                    produced in the context of the Slovenian Public Opinion research (these have
                    been carried out continuously ever since the 1960s), studies of the political
                    analysis centre, and other studies from the field of politology, sociology, and
                    social sciences. Political economy researchers have the materials of economic
                    institutes at their disposal, while almost all sciences contribute their
                    viewpoint with regard to, for example, research policy.</p>
                <p>The (un)manageable amount of materials on the one hand is closely connected with
                    its research usefulness on the other hand. Naturally, all kinds of materials are
                    useful for researchers. It is only a question of what the researchers focus on
                    and how. However, the materials for the most recent period are largely permeated
                    by the prejudice that they only represent the surface of the events – in
                    accordance with the aforementioned answer or conviction that we already know
                    everything about "our" period, and what we do not know has been concealed and
                    will remain hidden. (Of course, I do not know according to what logic it will
                    then be revealed to our descendants.)</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>On the Approaches to the Topic and About the Dilemmas</head>
                <p>Quite a few challenges and dilemmas undoubtedly exist; we only have to ask
                    ourselves how to deal with them. The first dilemma (or rather a preconception)
                    for the researchers who claim that nothing new can be written about this period
                    of time is actually the easiest to handle. We can look at it from a purely
                    philosophical and theoretical as well as from the practical point of view.
                    Namely, when we undertake any serious and methodologically sound research we
                    cannot theoretically know what sort of interpretative conclusions we will reach.
                    Any evaluation in advance can turn out as erroneous (for example, years ago I
                    myself was convinced that from its very beginning King Alexander's Dictatorship
                    in the Kingdom of Yugoslavia in 1930s kept generating new political problems
                    instead of solving them, but later I kept discovering more and more that
                    initially its image as well as its perception were completely different). </p>
                <p>In the same vein the questions that we asked yesterday were perhaps completely
                    different and non-essential in comparison with the issues that we are interested
                    in today. Not long ago it was important which politician used to be a member of
                    the League of Communists, while today we are already interested in other things.
                    After all, this kind of questioning represents the essence and the general
                    characteristic of historiography, which concerns all the historic periods. The
                    present and the environment we live in always dictate the research questions.
                    For example, in Germany the 2008 financial crisis resulted in a notably
                    increased interest in the economic history in general.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn15" n="14"> Frank Bösch and Jürgen Danyel, "Die
                        Zeitgeschichtsforschung und ihre Methoden," in: <hi rend="italic"
                            >Zeitgeschichte – Konzepte und Methoden</hi>, ed. Frank Bösch and Jürgen
                        Danyel (Göttingen: Vandenhoeck &amp; Ruprecht, 2012), 9<hi rend="italic"
                            >–</hi>21, here 13. Rödder, <hi rend="italic">21.0. Eine kurze
                            Geschichte der Gegenwart</hi>, 13.</note> Simultaneously it is
                    completely practical to claim that research in historiography, which does not
                    lead to any new or original interpretations, is neither meaningless nor flawed.
                    In a sense this is just another way of accumulating knowledge and bringing the
                    attention to the topics and aspects of the historiographic science. However, in
                    so far as research is integral and synthetically-oriented, it is especially
                    meaningful and well-founded – after all, historiography is oriented towards
                    writing complete interpretations. </p>
                <p> Another dilemma – that the contemporary time is too young for historians,
                    because historical distance is required for serious research – is justified up
                    to a point. It is certainly simpler to research a remote and concluded process,
                    unlike the today's seemingly chaotic times. Things are easier to interpret if we
                    see them whole, including their beginning and end. However, the advantage
                    represented by distance hides quite a dangerous inherent trap: the knowledge of
                    the end. If we are familiar with the conclusion of a certain process, we are in
                    danger of adapting the whole interpretation of the developments to this ending.
                    We are in danger of looking for reasons in the actions of people, logical in
                    view of the familiar ending (consequence), while forgetting that in history
                    things happen even when nobody is planning them.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn16" n="15"> The historian of ideas and concepts Quentin Skinner
                        refers to this mistake as the myth of prolepsis. One of the researchers of
                        the process of the dissolution of Yugoslavia Dejan Jović underlines the
                        frequency of this mistake in the explanations of the end of the Socialist
                        Federal Republic of Yugoslavia. – Dejan Jović, "Razlozi za raspad
                        socijalističke Jugoslavije: kritička analiza postojećih interpretacija," <hi
                            rend="italic">Reč</hi> 62, No. 8 (June 2001), 91<hi rend="italic"
                        >–</hi>157, here 142<hi rend="italic">–</hi>52. </note> The historians
                    focusing on the present do not know the end, and therefore the relationship
                    between the purpose and the supposed result cannot compromise their
                        analyses.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn17" n="16"> The German historian
                        Andreas Wirsching, author of the book about the history of Europe in our
                        time, also states that the advantage of researching the present lies in the
                        "erzwungene Verzicht auf jegliche Teleologie." Namely, historians are not
                        exposed to the danger of the teleological search for the purpose and goal of
                        history. – Andreas Wirsching, <hi rend="italic">Der Preis der Freiheit.
                            Geschichte Europas in unserer Zeit</hi> (München: C.H.Beck, 2012), 14<hi
                            rend="italic">–</hi>15.</note>
                </p>
                <p>On the other hand, however, we should be aware that the history of the present
                    can have rather direct effects on the formation of the self-image of the state
                    and its citizens, as it studies a recent period and thus addresses the memories
                    of the living or their direct descendants. The history of the present explains
                    "our time", which is why people do care how it is described (this is not only an
                    issue with the history of the present, but rather with all of contemporary
                    history – perhaps in Slovenia this especially concerns the World War II
                    historians). Historiography can contribute to the formation of a "suitable"
                    self-image, just like it happened in Germany after World War II when the myth
                    about the so-called "Erfolgsgeschichte" formed, as well as in Great Britain,
                    where this period was for a long time characterised as the "post-war
                        consensus".<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn18" n="17"> The British
                        historiography has characterised the post-war "consensus" as a myth. <hi
                            rend="italic">–</hi> Gabriele Metzler, "Zeitgeschichte: Begriff –
                        Disziplin – Problem, Version: 1.0," in: <hi rend="italic"
                            >Docupedia-Zeitgeschichte</hi>, 7 April 2014, <ref
                            target="https://docupedia.de/zg/Zeitgeschichte"
                            >https://docupedia.de/zg/Zeitgeschichte</ref>.</note> Addressing living
                    contemporaries can therefore represent a specific trap for historians, but it is
                    still much more manageable than what is probably the biggest research problem:
                    the amount and variety of materials.</p>
                <p> If only a few decades ago historians kept finding that the history of the most
                    recent period was not possible since the thirty-year restriction on the access
                    to materials was enforced, as a matter of principle, in all the archives, today
                    the situation is quite the opposite. The ocean of sources is endless, and,
                    moreover, these sources are <hi rend="italic">different</hi> in many aspects
                    from, for example, the sources for studying the history of the First Yugoslavia.
                    In both cases we can outline the developments in politics on the basis of
                    newspaper articles; in both cases we can resort to documents that have been
                    preserved (it seems interesting that historians do not have either the complete
                    archives of the pre-war political parties nor the archives of the today's
                    parties at their disposal);<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn19" n="18"> Currently
                        only the materials of three parties – the socialists, the Greens and the
                        Liberal Democracy of Slovenia – are in the Archives of the Republic of
                        Slovenia. Of these the LDS was the most influential and has, to date, taken
                        part in the various governments the longest (SI AS 366, Socialistična
                        stranka Slovenije (1990-1993), SI AS 2117, Zeleni Slovenije (1990-1993), SI
                        AS 2111 Liberalna demokracija Slovenije (1976-2011)).</note> and in both
                    cases we can also make use of political memoirs<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn20"
                        n="19"> Quite a few memorial records by the politicians of our period exist,
                        but they focus either on the time of the Slovenian emancipation or represent
                        merely a collection of thoughts and notes about a certain period of time
                        (which may also be very interesting and useful in terms of research).
                        However, only a few of these texts are systematic and chronologically
                        ordered, focusing on concrete political developments. See for example Ivo
                        Hvalica, <hi rend="italic">Zadnja replika</hi> (Ljubljana: Promag, 2002).
                        Ciril Ribičič, <hi rend="italic">Siva tipka 074</hi> (Ljubljana: Enotnost,
                        1995). Miran Potrč, <hi rend="italic">Klic k razumu. Spomini</hi>
                        (Ljubljana: Modrijan, 2014). </note> and verbatim records of parliamentary
                    sessions. However, here the similarities end. Of course, it is questionable to
                    what a degree the dissimilarity of sources hinders the political historians in
                    their research. In principle this should not represent an obstacle, but it is
                    certainly a kind of a challenge. First we have to be aware that every period has
                    its own sources with their own particular characteristics. The materials about
                    the Theresian reforms of the 18<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> century are
                    certainly different from those about the history of the Communist Party after
                    1945, and these again differ from the materials about the contemporaneous
                    politics. Today the world is different and individuals operate and work in
                    accordance with other guidelines. In the past a large amount of meeting-minutes
                    was available, and the archives also frequently contained personal notes,
                    letters, and so on. Today these materials are virtually non-existent and
                    unavailable for historians; but we do have television, the internet, living
                    participants of the events, etc. These sources appear less reliable than
                    archival documents, at least at the first glance, even though they can be much
                    more telling. This is especially true of the oral sources – witnesses, once upon
                    a time seen as the "enemies of historians",<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn21"
                        n="20"> The collocation was coined by Wolfgang Kraushaar when he
                        problematised the German historiography about the 1968 movement. – Metzler,
                        "Zeitgeschichte: Begriff – Disziplin – Problem."</note> can also enrich the
                    available historiographic material considerably, if only we gather and
                    methodologically process their testimonies in a suitable manner.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn22" n="21"> See: Zdenko Čepič et al., <hi
                            rend="italic">Prikrita modra mreža. Organi za notranje zadeve Republike
                            Slovenije v projektu MSNZ leta 1990</hi> (Ljubljana: Inštitut za novejšo
                        zgodovino and Zveza policijskih veteranskih društev Sever, 2010).</note>
                </p>
                <p> All of the sources of our time – the classic ones, known already from the
                    previous periods (especially newspapers, verbatim records of parliamentary
                    sessions and legislative materials), as well as the newer (digital) sources –
                    can be thoroughly analysed and evaluated only if we apply the following two
                    approaches: <hi rend="italic">interdisciplinarity</hi> and the tools provided by
                    the today's <hi rend="italic">digital humanities.</hi> The latter enables us to
                    focus on new research questions and process extraordinary amounts of materials
                    (we can easily analyse the characteristics of the parliamentary discussions in
                    the period of fifty years, which used to be physically impossible before), while
                    interdisciplinarity ensures a more thorough and focused approach. As it is,
                    research into modernity focuses more and more on the topics and problems, while
                    the distinctions between the individual disciplines are being blurred.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn23" n="22"> Metzler, "Zeitgeschichte: Begriff –
                        Disziplin – Problem."</note> Thus nowadays politologists, lawyers,
                    linguists, anthropologists and historians cooperate (or have done so) in
                        practice.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn24" n="23"> See Conference Program:
                            <hi rend="italic">Parliaments and Methodology. Anthropological,
                            Discourse-Oriented and Digital Approaches to Parliamentary History</hi>.
                        Helsinki and Jyväskylä, Finland 12–14 June 2014, 1 June 2016, <ref
                            target="https://www.jyu.fi/en/congress/parliaments-and-methodology/program/EuParl_Programme.pdf"
                            >https://www.jyu.fi/en/congress/parliaments-and-methodology/program/EuParl_Programme.pdf</ref>.</note>
                </p>
                <p>Finally, what about the prejudice that the available materials do not reveal all
                    the secrets? The situation is similar as it used to be. Also in the Habsburg
                    Monarchy and in the First Yugoslavia everyone was convinced that the political
                    decisions were adopted behind the doors of smoky cabinets and coffee houses,
                    which is what the notes (sometimes different from one another) of various
                    political actors attest to.</p>
                <p>In principle the digression about the materials of our period could be much
                    longer than what I have just written, and all the concrete problems that the
                    researchers may stumble upon cannot be predicted at all. Therefore I would just
                    like to underline one more issue that I have faced myself, closely connected
                    with the sheer amount of the materials and density of the political
                    developments. In so far as a researcher's ambition is to comprehensively
                    describe a certain political period at least to a certain degree, the massive
                    amount of the materials at the initial stages dictates a <hi rend="italic"
                        >descriptive</hi> approach. Thus the wish to control and encompass <hi
                        rend="italic">everything</hi> in itself impedes any methodological
                        creativity.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn25" n="24"> Bösch and Danyel, "Die
                        Zeitgeschichtsforschung und ihre Methoden," 9–10.</note> However, if
                    researchers only have a limited amount of materials at their disposal, they are
                    forced to resort to different approaches and can at the same time be more daring
                    in the thesis they propose.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Topic Presentation</head>
                <p>Regardless of all the dilemmas and methodological challenges I will now take the
                    first step into the adventure and give a short description of the political
                    history of the independent Slovenia, on the basis of which it will be possible
                    to ask new questions and open new research dilemmas. In the book about the
                    history of the Slovenian Parliament I have outlined the basic sequence of events
                    with the main chapters of the post-independence development. Here I will sum up
                    its main points.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn26" n="25"> Jure Gašparič, <hi
                            rend="italic">Državni zbor 1992–2012. O slovenskem parlamentarizmu</hi>
                        (Ljubljana: Inštitut za novejšo zgodovino, 2012).</note> It seems that the
                    events in the last twenty years can be most logically broken down by the
                    parliamentary terms of office.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn27" n="26"> This may
                        seem self-evident, but the questions of the periodisation and (non)linearity
                        of the development are not always easy. The Czech colleagues have decided
                        for a similar division as well. See: Jan Wintr, <hi rend="italic">Česká
                            parlamentní kultura</hi> (Praha: Auditorium, 2010).</note>
                </p>
                <div>
                    <head>In the shadow of the transition (the 1992–1996 term)</head>
                    <p> At the first National Assembly elections in 1992, party-based democracy was
                        still in its infancy and the political arena, in which the parties had not
                        yet introduced clear and coherent programmes, was as a result somewhat vague
                        and unclear. In the elections, each party had their own electoral tactics,
                        and the campaign was not lacking low blows and brutal confrontations.
                        Numerous transitional characteristics could be seen in the campaign. It was
                        something new and it did not only shake up political life, but society in
                        general, it drew the attention of many citizens and included many scandalous
                        stories, happily gloated over by journalists and citizens alike. In those
                        days, as well as later, party leaders found themselves being exposed. At the
                        same time as parliamentary elections, presidential elections were also held;
                        the first President of the Republic of Slovenia was Milan Kučan.<note
                            place="foot" xml:id="ftn28" n="27"> Milan Kučan is the first among the
                            most visible politicians of our time about whom a serious
                            historiographical political biography has been written. See: Božo Repe,
                                <hi rend="italic">Milan Kučan, prvi predsednik</hi> (Ljubljana:
                            Modrijan, 2015).</note></p>
                    <p>The National Assembly's first line-up was rather fragmented, eight parties
                        gained seats and the majority of votes went to LDS (Liberal Democratic
                        Party), with the remaining parties far behind. The political leader Janez
                        Drnovšek formed a diverse coalition dubbed the "small political miracle" –
                        it was composed of LDS, Christian Democrats, United List (Združena lista)
                        and SDSS (<hi rend="color(252525)">Social Democratic Party of
                            Slovenia</hi><hi rend="bold color(252525)">)</hi>. Once the
                        relationships between coalition and opposition were established, the
                        Parliament and the Government began addressing its vast agenda. First and
                        foremost, the agenda dealt with urgent legislative activities, as the former
                        federal legislation had to be replaced on the one hand, and fundamental
                        documents of numerous state subsystems had to be adopted on the other – from
                        education, judiciary administration, tax system, ownership transformation,
                        and the formation of a new economic system, to national security, political
                        parties, and corruption. In addition to fundamental legislative activities,
                        the common thread of the first National Assembly term was economic issues.
                        Throughout the term, Drnovšek's coalition gradually dissolved, with only the
                        LDS and SKD (Slovenian Christian
                        Democrats<hi rend="apple-converted-space" xml:space="preserve">) </hi>remaining
                        in the end.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn29" n="28"> Gašparič, <hi
                                rend="italic">Državni zbor 1992–2012</hi>, 53–70.</note></p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>The weakness of the great coalition (the 1996–2000 term)</head>
                    <p> After elections, the second convocation of the National Assembly found
                        itself in a stalemate position. The parties of the so-called transition
                        right wing (new parties, formed in the late 1980s and early 1990s)
                        aggregately received 45 votes and all others (mainly parties, based on
                        former socialist organisations), including the two members representing
                        minorities and supporting the actual Prime Minister Drnovšek (the president
                        of LDS, the party that was the relative winner in the elections), also
                        received 45 votes. The Parliament, a reflection of the society, found itself
                        in a predicament, divided equally in half ... The constitutive session
                        dragged on and on and opposing views were in evidence at each parliamentary
                        step. However, the politicians finally managed to reach an agreement
                        resulting in a large coalition between the largest parties, LDS and SLS
                        (Slovene People’s Party), joined by DeSUS.</p>
                    <p>The coalition that was finally formed after a difficult few months was very
                        diverse despite the small number of partners because LDS and SLS represented
                        a combination of two conceptually and socially completely different parties.
                        In practice, during the second term, this thesis was confirmed by
                        parliamentary practice to a large extent. Conditions and realities in the
                        National Assembly were often confusing; it seemed that SLS was more of an
                        opposition party than a coalition party. Furthermore, the opposition failed
                        to attack and control the government in a coordinated manner because it was
                        also divided itself on an ideological level. SDS and SKD were closer to SLS
                        and ZLSD was closer to Liberal Democratic Party. The dissolution of the
                        coalition often seemed inevitable. In November 1997, presidential elections
                        for a five-year term were once again held. Despite some reservations, Milan
                        Kučan ran again and won the election in a landslide (for the last time).</p>
                    <p>Despite all of its crises (which were quite frequent, especially those
                        related to personnel), the shaky coalition between LDS and SLS managed to
                        keep going until the eve of the end of its term. In the spring of 2000, only
                        six months before elections, the coalition-opposition relationships in the
                        Parliaments were blown apart. After many difficult meetings with ups and
                        downs, the related parties, SLS and SKD, finally managed to agree on merging
                        into one party that would not be a part of the coalition. The fall of the
                        "falling" government was impending. Drnovšek did not wait for things to
                        develop further; he was a step ahead of his partners and proposed the
                        replacement of SLS ministers with new ones. A vote of confidence was
                        connected with the replacement of ministers, but it was not passed. After
                        merging, SLS and SKD became the largest party in Parliament and shortly
                        after the demise of Drnovšek it proposed Andrej Bajuk as the new Prime
                        Minister. However, the new parliamentary coalition was not destined to last
                        for long, as the second term was about to end in less than six months. Also,
                        the coalition itself experienced a severe political crisis after only a
                            month.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn30" n="29"> Ibid<hi rend="italic"
                                >.</hi>, 71–91.</note></p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Leftist domination (the 2000–2004 term)</head>
                    <p> On Sunday, 15 October 2000, the third National Assembly elections took place
                        in Slovenia. Once again, there was an election campaign and many appearances
                        took place, mainly by well-known parties and faces ... The elections that
                        occurred at the turn of the decade, century, and millennium did not
                        represent a major milestone themselves, but they symbolically marked the
                        entry into a new era. The first decade after the fall of the Berlin Wall,
                        named the "Time of Freedom" by the British historian Timothy Garton Ash, was
                        coming to an end and a new "nameless decade" was beginning; this was an
                        elusive period without clear features.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn31"
                            n="30"> Timothy Garton Ash, <hi rend="italic">Jahrhundertwende.
                                Weltpolitische Betrachtungen 2000</hi>–<hi rend="italic">2010</hi>
                            (München: Carl Hanser Verlag München, 2010), 17–18.</note> A year
                        earlier a common European currency was introduced and NATO expanded into its
                        first three eastern European countries, thus giving special emphasis on
                        integration processes. The following year, on 5 October 2000, only ten days
                        prior to elections in Slovenia, the last Yugoslav tyrant was overthrown –
                        the Serbian leader Slobodan Milošević. All of this may seem like some
                        historical censorship of an epoch. Slovenia was a part of these global
                        currents and during its third National Assembly term also joined the
                        European Union and NATO, symbolically (maybe even in an illusory manner)
                        concluding the transition process in the country. On top of everything, the
                        third term was also the last term led by Drnovšek's great LDS, the strongest
                        party after 1992. The election results on 15 October 2000 were its swansong.
                        LDS received 36.21% votes, assuring it 34 seats in the Parliament. It formed
                        a coalition with ZLSD, SLS and DeSUS.</p>
                    <p>To a large extent, the third term and the forms of parliamentary work were
                        characterised by the weakness of the opposition, the core of which were SDS
                        (former SDSS, renamed in Slovenian Democratic Party) and NSi (new party
                        named New Slovenia). The coalition was soon nicknamed "voting steamroller"
                        and in such conditions the opposition had to remain firm. During the term,
                        in 2002, the government had a new Prime Minister (Tone Rop) following Janez
                        Drnovšek's election to President of the Republic.<note place="foot"
                            xml:id="ftn32" n="31"> Gašparič, <hi rend="italic">Državni zbor
                                1992–2012</hi>, 92–107.</note></p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Rightist domination (the 2004–2008 term)</head>
                    <p> On the one hand, the fourth National Assembly elections, which were called
                        by the President of the Republic to take place on 3 October 2004, gave the
                        impression of an entirely every-day democratic routine with a standard
                        election campaign, and yet on the other they continued to be stuck in
                        established ideological and political patterns. The "cultural fight" between
                        the "left wing" and the "right wing" continued, though its intensity
                        decreased. The election results were not entirely unexpected, but they
                        marked a major ideological turning point. The great LDS lost for the first
                        time after 1992. On that Sunday, the winner was SDS with its leader Janez
                        Janša, who gradually became the flag bearer of the opposition after 1996.
                        Janša then also formed a coalition and became the Prime Minister. If the
                        distinct supremacy of the coalition and the weakness of the opposition
                        marked the third term, one could conclude that the fourth term would be
                        completely different in this regard. The coalition was smaller, more
                        diverse, and two hard-bitten parties in the opposition preyed on it, not
                        allowing the Government to even have the traditional 100 days of peace.
                        Different conditions and practices in Parliament were to be expected.
                        However, no significant changes occurred and the initial (unrealistic)
                        expectations crumpled. At the beginning, the stability and support of the
                        coalition and the Government were high (also in public opinion), but on the
                        hand, the opposition succumbed to internal searching and splits. In
                        particular, LDS seemed to have been experiencing a crisis. Therefore, the
                        fourth term was similar to the third term, only a few roles changed.
                        European topics were the undeniable cohesive element of politics and
                        numerous other topics were divisive along the traditional left-right axis.
                        During this time, in 2007, new presidential elections were held, but Janez
                        Drnovšek did not run again due to illness. The winner was Danilo Türk.<note
                            place="foot" xml:id="ftn33" n="32"> Ibid., 108–23.</note>
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>In the shadow of the crisis (the 2008–2011 term)</head>
                    <p> On the eve of the fifth National Assembly elections in September 2008, the
                        Slovene political arena seemed quite clear and predictable. The common
                        thread of all parties was "welfare", but the plans in their programmes to
                        achieve welfare were increasingly less specific and noticeably increasingly
                        more alike. Contrary to expectations, the relative victory went to the party
                        SD (Social Democrats) formerly known as ZLSD whose leader, Borut Pahor,
                        became the Prime Minister.</p>
                    <p>On the eve of the elections, it was already clear that a debt and financial
                        crisis is spreading around the world and that it might grow into a wider
                        economic crisis affecting Slovenia as well. Pahor's team gave the impression
                        that it was aware of the situation, but in the following few months, it
                        acted slowly and indecisively as per the Prime Minister's consensual
                        approach. The first bundle of anti-crisis measures reached the Parliament at
                        the end of the year. It was adopted by Members of Parliament on their last
                        sitting in 2008, thus symbolically foreshadowing the main focus of the fifth
                        term – overcoming the crisis which finally grew from a financial crisis into
                        a political one.</p>
                    <p>Throughout the term, there was division on all important topics (or at least
                        those that were stressed as such). When the Government finally managed to
                        agree on a solution for the border issue with the neighbouring Croatia,
                        which must undoubtedly be counted as one of its major successes, it
                        immediately encountered firm objections from the opposition and a portion of
                        prominent intellectuals (however, a large portion of intellectuals in the
                        public eye supported the agreement). During the third year of the term, the
                        trust in the Government and the Parliament was still low and dissatisfaction
                        grew. The political arena remained implacable and the coalition was
                        increasingly giving the impression that it was blocked from the outside and
                        from within and that it did not have any real "exit" ideas. The path into a
                        political crisis was thus set. The coalition gradually dissolved, ultimately
                        consisting only of SD and LDS. </p>
                    <p>The fifth term ended by a vote of no confidence given to the Government and,
                        with no new candidate for a Prime Minister, the President dissolved the
                        National Assembly on 21 October 2011. For the first time in (nearly) twenty
                        years of the Slovenian Parliament, early elections were to take place,
                        planned for 4 December 2011. The trust in a significant portion of
                        parliamentary parties was shaken and a significant restructuring of the
                        political arena was to be expected.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn34" n="33">
                            Ibid., 124–43.</note></p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>The time of disappointment and weariness (the 2011–2014 term)</head>
                    <p> Between the President's announcement that he would dissolve the National
                        Assembly and the elections, there was not much time. In such circumstances,
                        it was not surprising that the campaign lacked truly innovative approaches,
                        convincing and insightful solutions and compelling addresses to the voters.
                        The elections were quite peaceful (but not without scandals) and, for the
                        first time in twenty years, divisive ideological topics were more evidently
                        pushed into the background. In early October, the political atmosphere was
                        still predictable. However, shortly afterwards, the political arena began to
                        change drastically as new political faces and new parties appeared one after
                        another. Less than two months prior to elections, two new parties with an
                        extremely high rating appeared, as they climbed to the top of election
                        polls. The first one was founded by the Mayor or Ljubljana, Zoran Jankovič
                        (PS -Pozitivna Slovenija - Positive Slovenia), and the second by the former
                        minister Gregor Virant (Državljanska lista Gregorja Viranta - Gregor
                        Virant’s Civic List).</p>
                    <p>If the campaign warned of major political shifts in Slovenia, the election
                        results on Sunday, 4 December 2011, only confirmed them. The election was
                        won by Jankovič's PS, but its president – again, for the first time in
                        twenty years – did not become Prime Minister. The coalition was formed by
                        Janez Janša, the leader of SDS, which received the second highest number of
                        votes. The Parliament and the Government began fervently working and dealing
                        with the crisis and the fiscal consolidation of the country.</p>
                    <p>The dissatisfaction of people due to the economic crisis gradually increased
                        in the second half of 2012 and was directed specifically at political
                        elites. Numerous "people's uprisings" erupted. In such circumstances, the
                        coalition collapsed and in March 2013 a new Slovenian Government was formed
                        under the leadership of Alenka Bratušek of PS (first woman Prime Minister).
                        After the new Government was elected, the political storm calmed down for
                        one year despite numerous troubles in the Cabinet and unsuccessful staff
                        choices, until Bratušek resigned. This automatically ended the term for the
                        entire Cabinet. No one proposed a new political figure to form a government
                        and the new President, Borut Pahor, elected in 2012, dissolved the
                        Parliament on 2 June and called for elections to be held on 13 July 2014
                        (with harsh criticism due to the summer holiday period).<note place="foot"
                            xml:id="ftn35" n="34"> Gašparič, <hi rend="italic">Slovenski
                                parlament</hi>, 81–96.</note></p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>(The 2014– term)</head>
                    <p> It was expected that the elections would, as in 2011, significantly change
                        the political and personnel structure of the Parliament. There were several
                        reasons for this. Following the demise of Janša's Government, the momentum
                        of people's uprisings began to decline. However, the dissatisfaction with
                        politics and political elites remained and the results of public opinion
                        polls continued to be unforgiving. Therefore, a few uprising groups, such as
                        the All-Slovene People's Uprising, decided to use the potential of the
                        uprisings to actively enter into politics. In December 2013, the party
                        Solidarnost (Solidarity) was formed. The next year, on 1 March 2014, the
                        party United Left (<hi rend="italic">Združena levica</hi>) was formed
                        following the example of the then still attractive and convincing Syriza in
                        Greece. Just prior to the elections, additional three parties entered the
                        political arena: the party Verjamem (<hi rend="italic">I Believe</hi>) led
                        by Igor Šoltes, Alliance of Alenka Bratušek, and the Party of Miro Cerar.
                        The latter (later renamed into the Modern Centre Party) ultimately won with
                        the largest percentage of votes after 1992 and subsequently formed the
                        current Slovenian Government together with SD and DeSUS.<note place="foot"
                            xml:id="ftn36" n="35"> Ibid.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>The political situation has calmed down and it seems that politics has
                        retreated to the background somewhat... </p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Findings and Challenges</head>
                <p> What conclusions can we draw on the basis of this short insight in the political
                    history of the last quarter of a century? Firstly, the introductory finding that
                    out period is very <hi rend="italic">dynamic</hi>, riddled with events and <hi
                        rend="italic">"unreadable"</hi> can certainly be confirmed. Despite the
                    relative political stability of the Slovenian governments (in comparison with
                    the Czech Republic, for example), the party space has been unstable and ever
                    changing, in a continuous state of restructuring. Its most notable constant was
                    the <hi rend="italic">polarisation</hi> – the division of the political actors
                    into the Slovenian left and right. Furthermore, certain characteristics already
                    noted in the broader European space can also be ascribed to the Slovenian
                    development: the <hi rend="italic">personalisation</hi> of politics, <hi
                        rend="italic">medialisation</hi>, and <hi rend="italic"
                        >informalisation</hi>.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn37" n="36"> Wirsching,
                            <hi rend="italic">Der Preis der Freiheit</hi>, 308–18.</note></p>
                <p>Let us first look at the phenomenon of the left-right <hi rend="italic"
                        >polarisation.</hi> Where does it originate from and what is its perception
                    based on? At list partly the dividing line was (and still is) the attitude of
                    the political parties to the past, especially to World War II and the post-war
                    socialist period. In this regard certain parties see Yugoslavia and its society
                    in an exceedingly binary manner. Their interpretative pattern is
                    totalitarian‑historical, reducing the past merely to good and evil.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn38" n="37"> See: Michal Pullmann, <hi rend="italic"
                            >Konec experimentu. Přestavba a pád komunismu v Československu</hi>
                        (Praha: Scriptorium, 2011), 15–16.</note> The adherents of this pattern only
                    look at this state in order to find arguments for and against their views.
                    According to them an "evil" regime reigned in Yugoslavia, which was an
                    "artificial creation" that repressed the good of the society. Some of them may
                    acknowledge, though, that Yugoslavia also had some advantages. Such a
                    generalised claim is disputable already in the very analytical sense, since it
                    presupposes that people were nothing but indoctrinated masses, incapable of
                    taking care of themselves and simply persisting quietly in the Yugoslav
                    framework. However, as soon as these masses became capable of thought, they
                    immediately wanted to break free of the Titoist chains and seek safe haven in
                    their own democratic national states. This pattern is clearly understandable and
                    politically useful, but it overlooks the actual disposition of the people.</p>
                <p>The attitude towards the past can be associated with the issues of <hi
                        rend="italic">continuity and discontinuity</hi> in the historical
                    development. Despite the various convictions of individual political parties, in
                    the development after 1990 and 1991 we can notice many elements of continuity
                    from the previous period as well as radical turning points and transformations,
                    which is characteristic for the whole of the eastern Central Europe.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn39" n="38"> Gašparič, "O samoumevnosti uvajanja
                        parlamentarne demokracije v vzhodni Evropi."</note> We can also discern that
                    the parties with their emphasised interest in history and their opinions about
                    it frequently introduce additional confusion into the political space or
                    contribute to the mythisation of the past. There are ample examples: for
                    instance, in the last twenty-five years two parties from opposing sides appealed
                    to the heritage of the social democratic party from Austria, established in
                    1896. The president of the Slovenian People's Party stated that he was extremely
                    proud to be the successor of Anton Korošec, the most eminent Slovenian
                    politician in the First Yugoslavia, even though the today's Slovenian People's
                    Party has nothing to do with Korošec (except fictitiously).<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn40" n="39"> Cf. Mateja Ratej, "Začetki politične pluralizacije v
                        pojugoslovanski Sloveniji. Vprašanje političnega nasledstva Koroščeve SLS,"
                            <hi rend="italic">Zgodovinski časopis</hi> 67, No. 3–4 (2013),
                        472–92.</note> Later another party referred to Korošec's party as well... </p>
                <p>The <hi rend="italic">personalisation</hi> of politics is another characteristic
                    of the Slovenian politics as well as of the European politics of our time. This
                    may be nothing new, as we have known many examples of outstanding political
                    personae in the post-war Europe (e.g. Charles de Gaulle, Willy Brandt). However,
                    these were always personifications of concrete contents and standpoints. On the
                    other hand, after 1990 we find that in Europe political personalities <hi
                        rend="italic">per se</hi> have come to the forefront, frequently without any
                    contents (they have even been known to form their parties in an ad hoc
                        manner).<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn41" n="40"> Wirsching, <hi
                            rend="italic">Der Preis der Freiheit</hi>, 313–15.</note> Slovenia is no
                    exception in this regard. It seems that few parties are resilient enough to
                    survive the replacement of their main leaders, whom all the spotlights are aimed
                    at, without significant turmoil.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn42" n="41"> On the
                        other hand, the pre-election events in the neighbouring Croatia in the
                        summer of 2016 attest to the fact that the replacement of an unpopular
                        president of the party with a more likeable leader can swiftly restore the
                        trust of the voters in the party. As it happened, after the fall of the
                        Most-HDZ coalition government in June 2016 it seemed that the HDZ and its
                        President Tomislav Karamarko would certainly be defeated at the elections.
                        However, the sentiment of the electoral body changed in just a few months –
                        when the party was taken over by Andrej Plenković.</note> The latter
                    phenomenon is certainly closely connected with the <hi rend="italic"
                        >medialisation</hi> of politics, which is also a wider all-European
                        characteristic.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn43" n="42"> Wirsching, <hi
                            rend="italic">Der Preis der Freiheit</hi>, 312.</note> While jumbo
                    posters were a great novelty of the campaigns back in 1992, the political
                    actions of today are taking place on a variety of media platforms. The
                    Parliament may still be the central arena for political debates, but other
                    formats represent an increasingly serious competition. Furthermore it seems that
                    the Parliament in its essence is mostly and merely the following: the arena for
                    debates and not the space where politics is being formed. In the people's
                    opinion, serious political decisions are reached far away from the public gaze,
                    which means that politics is <hi rend="italic">informalised.</hi> This is also
                    nothing new: we have already underlined that even in the old Yugoslavia and old
                    Austria people were frequently convinced that politics is being made behind
                    closed doors, often in the absence of the Parliament (the only difference is
                    that once upon a time the cabinets and coffee houses were filled with smoke,
                    which is probably a thing of the past). However, back then the frustrated
                    Members of Parliament finally gave vent to their irritation by engaging in
                    severe obstructions. In our period, however, deputies are simply overburdened
                    with their functions in the working bodies and other activities, which may
                    consequently diminish the importance of the Parliament.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn44" n="43"> Ibid., 311.</note>
                </p>
                <p>In light of these findings it seems that the connection between the introductory
                    Havel's warning and the large-scale anti-political demonstrations is more
                    understandable. Nobody (or almost nobody) wanted to undermine the trust in the
                    parliamentary democracy intentionally. That simply happened due to the
                    aforementioned characteristics of politics. There is no cause-and-effect
                    relationship; and this, on the other hand, gives rise to other questions,
                    partially focused on the future. One of the first questions is whether we have
                    arrived to the end of the big and deeply-rooted parties with their traditional
                    electoral bases. This does not seem impossible. In 2005 a large-scale public
                    opinion research was carried out among the voters in the Western European
                    countries, who responded that political parties were necessary, but also
                    rejected the thesis that the existent parties were truly concerned with the
                    welfare of the people.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn45" n="44"> Ibid.,
                        347.</note> So what is the alternative, then? In parliamentary democracy the
                    alternative can only be another political party, but in the future such a party
                    will have to be very different from those established a quarter of a century
                    ago. The detailed exploration of party-political dynamics is thus certainly one
                    of the research challenges – not only external dynamics, but possibly also the
                    dynamics within the parties themselves, in so far as the researchers are enabled
                    to analyse that. Shedding some light on the party dynamics will finally allow us
                    to gain a better insight in the <hi rend="italic">decision-making process.</hi>
                    The aforementioned collaboration of anthropologists, linguists, politologists
                    and historians should be ensured, since the issue is multi-layered and the
                    answers are not necessarily rational. </p>
                <p>As it is, politics is not a game of chess, as the German historian Gerhard A.
                    Ritter wrote wittily.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn46" n="45"> Gerhard A.
                        Ritter, <hi rend="italic">Der Umbruch von 1989/91 und die
                            Geschichtswissenschaft</hi>. Bayerische Akademie der Wissenschaften.
                        Philosophisch-historische Klasse. Sitzungsberichte. Jahrgang 1995, Heft 5
                        (München, 1995), 23.</note> Nobody is forced to make their move once the
                    opponent has made one. Politicians are frequently lost. Time and again they do
                    not do anything, their actions are often irrational, and concrete results are
                    frequently unrelated to their actions. However, when the moment is right, some
                    of them know how to exploit it and are capable of doing it (after which they, of
                    course, present their actions as a result of a strategic consideration).<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn47" n="46"> The former German Vice-Chancellor and
                        Minister of Foreign Affairs Joschka Fischer admitted this freely in his
                        memoirs, as he wrote that without the financial scandal of the CDU party the
                        red-green coalition, created in 1998, would never have existed: "Luck and
                        chance are essential for politics, like the air we breathe. What is later
                        shown as a brilliant plan or a well thought-out strategy, or what the actors
                        later declare as such, is often a result of chance or simply luck, not so
                        much of the alleged genius of the people involved." – Joschka Fischer, <hi
                            rend="italic">Rdeče-zelena leta. Prelomni dogodki od vojne na Kosovu do
                            11. Septembra</hi> (Ljubljana: Didakta, 2011), 271.</note> The factor of
                    time – the context – thus remains an essential element of the analysis, and
                    without it we cannot truly understand politics.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="bibliography">
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Sources and Literature</head>

                    <bibl>Ash, Timothy Garton. <hi rend="italic">Jahrhundertwende. Weltpolitische
                            Betrachtungen 2000</hi>–<hi rend="italic">2010</hi>. München: Carl
                        Hanser Verlag München, 2010.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Bösch, Frank and Jürgen Danyel. "Die Zeitgeschichtsforschung und ihre
                        Methoden." In: <hi rend="italic">Zeitgeschichte – Konzepte und
                        Methoden</hi>, eds. Frank Bösch and Jürgen Danyel, 9–21. Göttingen:
                        Vandenhoeck &amp; Ruprecht, 2012.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Čepič, Zdenko, Filip Čuček, Jure Gašparič, Damijan Guštin, Božo Repe and
                        Uroš Svete. <hi rend="italic">Prikrita modra mreža. Organi za notranje
                            zadeve Republike Slovenije v projektu MSNZ leta 1990</hi>. Ljubljana:
                        Inštitut za novejšo zgodovino and Zveza policijskih veteranskih društev
                        Sever, 2010.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Dokumentacijsko-knjižnični oddelek Državnega zbora Republike Slovenije,
                        Dobesedni zapis 13. seje I. mandata DZ z dne 9. 11. 1993 [Verbatim Record of
                        13th Session of the 1st Mandate]. Available at: <hi rend="italic">Portal
                            DZ</hi>. <ref target="http://www.dz-rs.si"
                        >http://www.dz-rs.si</ref>.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Fischer, Joschka. <hi rend="italic">Rdeče-zelena leta. Prelomni dogodki od
                            vojne na Kosovu do 11. septembra</hi>. Ljubljana: Didakta, 2011 (Orig.
                            <hi rend="italic">Die rot-grünen Jahre. Deutsche Außenpolitik - vom
                            Kosovo bis zum 11. September</hi>).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Gašparič, Jure. "O samoumevnosti uvajanja parlamentarne demokracije v
                        vzhodni Evropi po letu 1989." Conference Paper (<hi rend="italic">Regionalni
                            vidiki tranzicije</hi>. Nova Gorica, 15 October 2015).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Gašparič, Jure. <hi rend="italic">Državni zbor 1992–2012. O slovenskem
                            parlamentarizmu</hi>. Ljubljana: Inštitut za novejšo zgodovino,
                        2012.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Gašparič, Jure. <hi rend="italic">Slovenski parlament.
                            Politično-zgodovinski pregled od začetka prvega do konca šestega
                            mandata (1992</hi>–<hi rend="italic">2014) - Elektronska izdaja
                        1.0</hi>. Ljubljana: Inštitut za novejšo zgodovino, 2014. Available at:
                        Zgodovina Slovenije – SIstory. <ref
                            target="http://www.sistory.si/SISTORY:ID:26950"
                            >http://www.sistory.si/SISTORY:ID:26950</ref><hi rend="Hyperlink"
                        >.</hi></bibl>
                    <bibl>Gjuričová, Adéla. "Anti-politics and anti-parliamentarism. Václav Havel
                        and the Czechoslovak parliament in the 1990s." Conference Paper (European
                        Information and Research Network on Parliamentary History: <hi rend="italic"
                            >Parlamentarismuskritik und Antiparlamentarismus in Europa</hi>. Berlin,
                        7. and 8 May 2015).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Grah, Matija. "Vem za pričakovanja, da bom odkril skrivnosti murgelske
                        kleti." <hi rend="italic">Delo</hi>, 30. October 2015.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Hvalica, Ivo. <hi rend="italic">Zadnja replika</hi>. Ljubljana: Promag,
                        2002.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Jović, Dejan. "Razlozi za raspad socijalističke Jugoslavije: kritička
                        analiza postojećih interpretacija." <hi rend="italic">Reč</hi> 62, No. 8
                        (June 2011): 91–157.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Lindenberger, Thomas. "Vergangenes Hören und Sehen. Zeitgeschichte und
                        ihre Herausforderung durch die audiovisuellen Medien." In: <hi rend="italic"
                            >Zeithistorische Forschungen/Studies in Contemporary History</hi>,
                        Online-Ausgabe, 1 (2004), H. 1. URL: <ref
                            target="http://www.zeithistorische-forschungen.de/1-2004/id=4586"
                            >http://www.zeithistorische-forschungen.de/1-2004/id=4586</ref>,
                        Druckausgabe: 72–85.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Metzler, Gabriele. "Zeitgeschichte: Begriff – Disziplin – Problem,
                        Version: 1.0." In: <hi rend="italic">Docupedia-Zeitgeschichte</hi>, 7. April
                        2014. <ref target="https://docupedia.de/zg/Zeitgeschichte"
                            >https://docupedia.de/zg/Zeitgeschichte</ref>.</bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="italic">O Arhivu družboslovnih podatkov</hi>. <ref
                            target="http://www.adp.fdv.uni-lj.si/o_arhivu/"
                            >http://www.adp.fdv.uni-lj.si/o_arhivu/</ref>.</bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="italic">Parliaments and Methodology: Anthropological,
                            Discourse-Oriented and Digital Approaches to Parliamentary History</hi>.
                        Helsinki and Jyväskylä, Finland 12–14 June 2014. <ref
                            target="https://www.jyu.fi/en/congress/parliaments-and-methodology/program/EuParl_Programme.pdf"
                            >https://www.jyu.fi/en/congress/parliaments-and-methodology/program/EuParl_Programme.pdf</ref>.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Potrč, Miran. <hi rend="italic">Klic k razumu. Spomini</hi>. Ljubljana:
                        Modrijan, 2014.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Pullmann, Michal. <hi rend="italic">Konec experimentu. Přestavba a pád
                            komunismu v Československu</hi>. Praha: Scriptorium, 2011.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Ratej, Mateja. "Začetki politične pluralizacije v pojugoslovanski
                        Sloveniji. Vprašanje političnega nasledstva Koroščeve SLS." <hi
                            rend="italic">Zgodovinski časopis</hi> 67, No. 3–4 (2013):
                        472–92.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Repe, Božo. <hi rend="italic">Milan Kučan, prvi predsednik</hi>.
                        Ljubljana: Modrijan, 2015.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Ribičič, Ciril. <hi rend="italic">Siva tipka 074</hi>. Ljubljana:
                        Enotnost, 1995. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Ritter, Gerhard A. <hi rend="italic">Der Umbruch von 1989/91 und die
                            Geschichtswissenschaft</hi>. Bayerische Akademie der Wissenschaften.
                        Philosophisch-historische Klasse. Sitzungsberichte. Jahrgang 1995, Heft 5.
                        München, 1995.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Rödder, Andreas. <hi rend="italic">21.0. Eine kurze Geschichte der
                            Gegenwart</hi>. München: C.H.Beck, 2016.</bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="italic">Slovenia - 10 Years of Independence,</hi> 30 May
                            2016,<ref target="http://www.slovenija2001.gov.si/10years/independence/"
                            >http://www.slovenija2001.gov.si/10years/independence/</ref>.</bibl>

                    <bibl>Suk, Jiří. "Od nezmožnosti politiky k politice jako umění možného.
                        Paradohní život občana Václava Havla v letech 1969–1992." In:
                        <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Kapitoly z dějin české demokracie po roce 1989, </hi>eds.
                        Adéla Gjuričová and Michal Kopeček, 16–51. Praha and Litomyšl: Paseka,
                        2008.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Toš, Niko, ed. <hi rend="italic">Vrednote v prehodu VIII. Slovenija v
                            srednje in vzhodnoevropskih primerjavah 1991-2011</hi>. Ljubljana and
                        Wien: Univerza v Ljubljani, Fakulteta za družbene vede, IDV-CJMMK and
                        Edition Echoraum, 2014.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Wintr, Jan. <hi rend="italic">Česká parlamentní kultura</hi>. Praha:
                        Auditorium, 2010.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Wirsching, Andreas. <hi rend="italic">Der Preis der Freiheit. Geschichte
                            Europas in unserer Zeit</hi>. München: C.H.Beck, 2012.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
            <div type="summary" xml:lang="sl">
                <p>Jure Gašparič</p>
                <p>PISATI POLITIČNO ZGODOVINO REPUBLIKE SLOVENIJE</p>
                <p>POVZETEK</p>
                <p>Poskus pisanja besedila o razvoju slovenske politike v zadnjega četrt stoletja je
                    za zgodovinarja poseben izziv in svojevrstna pustolovščina, ki že v začetku
                    odpira nekaj važnih metodoloških vprašanj, odstira nekaj dilem, a hkrati že
                    ponuja nekaj vnaprejšnjih odgovorov. Prvi odgovor, ki ga je pogosto zaslediti v
                    medijih in delu strokovne javnosti, je ta, da je raziskovanje slovenske politike
                    po letu 1991 že zanimiva in relevantna tema, a o njej ni mogoče napisati ničesar
                    zares novega, vsaj nič takega, kar ne bi sprotni kronisti dogajanja že zapisali.
                    Drugi vnaprejšnji odgovor, ki je pravzaprav že dilema, zadeva vprašanje obče
                    smiselnosti raziskovanja procesov, ki še niso zaključeni. Čas naj bi bil za
                    pogled zgodovinarja še premlad. S časovno komponento je povezano naslednja
                    dilema. Kako sploh metodološko ustrezno kot zgodovinar raziskovati nedavno
                    politiko in fenomen političnega? Gradivo, ki je na voljo, je namreč brezbrežno v
                    vseh ozirih – tako po količini kot po problemski in znanstveni širini.</p>
                <p>Izzivov in dilem je nedvomno precej, vprašanje je, kako temu streči. Prva dilema,
                    ki pravi, da ni mogoče o tem času napisati ničesar novega, je še najlažje
                    obvladljiva. Pri vsakršnem resnem in metodološko osmišljenem raziskovanju namreč
                    že teoretično ne moremo vedeti, do kakšnih interpretativnih ugotovitev bomo
                    prišli. Ravno tako so vprašanja, ki smo si jih zastavili včeraj, morda čisto
                    drugačna in nebistvena v primerjavi z vprašanji, ki nas zanimajo danes. Druga
                    dilema, ki pravi, da je sodobni čas za zgodovinarja premlad, je do neke mere
                    upravičena. Gotovo je enostavneje raziskovati oddaljen in zaključen proces,
                    kakor današnji, na videz kaotičen čas. Toda prednost, ki jo predstavlja
                    distanca, v sebi skriva nemajhno past – vedenje o koncu. Znanemu koncu
                    (posledici) bomo iskali logične vzroke v ravnanjih ljudi in pri tem pozabili, da
                    se v zgodovini stvari dogajajo tudi takrat, ko jih nihče ne načrtuje.
                    Problematika virov je še najlažje obvladljiva. Vse vire naše dobe – tako
                    klasične, znane že iz preteklih dob, kakor novejše (digitalne) - lahko temeljito
                    analiziramo in pretehtamo le ob pritegnitvi dveh načinov pristopa – z <hi
                        rend="italic">interdisciplinarnostjo</hi> in s pomočjo orodij, ki jih danes
                    ponuja <hi rend="italic">digitalna humanistika</hi>. Raziskovanje sodobnosti se
                    namreč bolj in bolj osredotoča na teme in probleme, pri čemer padajo meje med
                    posameznimi disciplinami.</p>
                <p>In kaj lahko po opravljenem raziskovanju sklepamo o politični zgodovini zadnjega
                    četrt stoletja? Najprej se gotovo potrjuje ugotovitev, da je naša doba zelo <hi
                        rend="italic">dinamična</hi>, dogodkovno gosta in <hi rend="italic"
                        >»neberljiva«</hi>. Navkljub relativni politični stabilnosti vlad je bil
                    strankarski prostor nestabilen in spreminjajoč, v neprekinjenem
                    prestrukturiranju. Med večjimi konstantami je bila <hi rend="italic"
                        >polarizacija</hi> - delitev političnih akterjev na slovensko levico in
                    desnico. Poleg tega lahko slovenskemu razvoju pripišemo tudi nekatere od
                    značilnosti, ki so jih zaznali v širšem evropskem prostoru – <hi rend="italic"
                        >personalizacijo</hi> politike, <hi rend="italic">medializacijo</hi> in <hi
                        rend="italic">informalizacijo</hi>. Eden raziskovalnih izzivov za prihodnost
                    je podrobno proučevanje strankarsko-politične dinamike – ne le navzven, po
                    možnosti tudi znotraj strank, v kolikor bi bilo raziskovalcu to omogočeno.
                    Interdisciplinarno sodelovanje pri tem ne sme izostati, saj je problematika
                    večplastna, odgovori pa ne nujno racionalni.</p>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
