<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Defence of the Republic of Slovenia 1991–2004</title>
                <title>From Individual to Collective Defence</title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename>Damijan</forename>
                        <surname>Guštin</surname>
                        <roleName>Research Associate</roleName>
                        <roleName>PhD</roleName>
                        <affiliation>Institute of Contemporary History</affiliation>
                        <address>
                            <addrLine>Kongresni trg 1</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>SI-1000 Ljubljana, Slovenia</addrLine>
                        </address>
                        <email>damijan.gustin@inz.si</email>
                    </name>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>2016-11-03</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>
                    <orgName xml:lang="sl">Inštitut za novejšo zgodovino</orgName>
                    <orgName xml:lang="en">Institute of Contemporary History</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Kongresni trg 1</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>SI-1000 Ljubljana</addrLine>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>http://ojs.inz.si/pnz/article/view/194</pubPlace>
                <date>2016</date>
                <availability status="free">
                    <licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title xml:lang="sl">Prispevki za novejšo zgodovino</title>
                <title xml:lang="en">Contributions to Contemporary History</title>
                <biblScope unit="volume">56</biblScope>
                <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
                <idno type="ISSN">2463-7807</idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source, born digital.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc xml:lang="en">
                <p>Contributions to Contemporary History is one of the central Slovenian scientific
                    historiographic journals, dedicated to publishing articles from the field of
                    contemporary history (the 19th and 20th century).</p>
                <p>The journal is published three times per year in Slovenian and in the following
                    foreign languages: English, German, Serbian, Croatian, Bosnian, Italian, Slovak
                    and Czech. The articles are all published with abstracts in English and
                    Slovenian as well as summaries in English.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <projectDesc xml:lang="sl">
                <p>Prispevki za novejšo zgodovino je ena osrednjih slovenskih znanstvenih
                    zgodovinopisnih revij, ki objavlja teme s področja novejše zgodovine (19. in 20.
                    stoletje).</p>
                <p>Revija izide trikrat letno v slovenskem jeziku in v naslednjih tujih jezikih:
                    angleščina, nemščina, srbščina, hrvaščina, bosanščina, italijanščina, slovaščina
                    in češčina. Članki izhajajo z izvlečki v angleščini in slovenščini ter povzetki
                    v angleščini.</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="sl"/>
                <language ident="en"/>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords xml:lang="en">
                    <term>security</term>
                    <term>defence system</term>
                    <term>Territorial Defence of Republic of Slovenia</term>
                    <term>Slovenian Armed Forces</term>
                    <term>national security system</term>
                    <term>Republic of Slovenia</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords xml:lang="sl">
                    <term>varnost</term>
                    <term>Slovenija</term>
                    <term>obramba</term>
                    <term>TORS</term>
                    <term>Slovenska vojska</term>
                    <term>nacionalnovarnostni sistem RS</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change>
                    <date>2016-11-15</date>
                    <name>Neja Blaj Hribar</name>
                    <desc>Pretvorba iz DOCX v TEI, dodatno kodiranje</desc>
                </change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <docAuthor>Damijan Guštin<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn1" n="*">
                    <hi rend="bold" xml:space="preserve">Research Associate, PhD, Institute of Contemporary History, Kongresni trg 1, SI-1000 Ljubljana, Slovenia, </hi><ref target="file:///C:\Users\damijang\Downloads\damijan.gustin@inz.si"><hi rend="bold">damijan.gustin@inz.si</hi></ref></note></docAuthor>
            <docImprint>
                <idno type="cobissType">Cobiss type: 1.01</idno>
                <idno type="UDC">UDC: 355.02(497.4)"1991/2004"</idno>
            </docImprint>
            <div type="abstract">
                <head>ABSTRACT</head>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Following the successful defence of the country in June and
                        July 1991, the Republic of Slovenia developed its partly unestablished
                        defence system in the light of the instability of the country’s southern
                        neighbourhood that continued to be ravaged by war for the next five years.
                        As an independent country, Slovenia developed its system of national defence
                        in the context of armed neutrality, but with a desire to join Nato and thus
                        transition to a system of collective defence. The Territorial Defence was
                        developed into a regular army and renamed as the Slovenian Armed Forces in
                        1994. In the circumstances dictated both by restrictions imposed by the UN
                        (arms embargo) as well as the country’s own capacities and available
                        material resources, Slovenia developed a single-type army based on national
                        service and initial large numbers that were gradually reduced. In 1993, the
                        country decided to pursue collective defence as a strategic goal and
                        initiated efforts to join Nato. As Slovenia moved closer to Nato and as the
                        security of its immediate environment changed, numerous reforms of the Army
                        and of the defence sector loomed. During Slovenia's preparations to join
                        Nato from 2000 to 2004, the country abandoned its national service system in
                        2003 and reformed the Slovenian Armed Forces into a professional army
                        numbering about 7600 professional soldiers, NCOs and officers, as well as an
                        additional limited voluntary reserve force</hi>. </p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Key words: security, defence system, Territorial Defence of
                        Republic of Slovenia, Slovenian Armed Forces, national security system,
                        Republic of Slovenia</hi></p>
            </div>
            <div type="abstract" xml:lang="sl">
                <head type="main">IZVLEČEK</head>
                <head>OBRAMBA REPUBLIKE SLOVENIJE 1991-2004</head>
                <head>OD SAMOSTOJNE V KOLEKTIVNO OBRAMBO</head>
                <p><hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Republika Slovenija je svoj še ne docela vzpostavljen obrambni sistem po uspešni obrambi junija in julija 1991 oblikovala pod vplivom varnostne nestabilnosti južnega sosedstva, kjer je še pet let divjala vojna. Kot neodvisna država je razvijala svoj nacionalno-varnostni sistem v okolju oborožene nevtralnosti, a z željo, da se pridruži Natu in s tem preide v sistem kolektivne obrambe. Teritorialno obrambo je razvila v redno vojsko in jo 1994 preimenovala v Slovensko vojsko. V pogojih, ki so jih določale tako omejitve OZN (prepoved prodaje orožja) kot tudi lastne zmožnosti in razpoložljivi materialni resursi, je razvila enozvrstno vojsko, ki je temeljila na vojaški obvezi in veliki vojni sestavi, ki pa jo je postopoma zmanjševala. Leta 1993 je izbrala za strateški cilj kolektivno obrambo, in si prizadevala, da se vključi v Nato. Približevanje Natu in hkratne spremembe varnostnega okolja so narekovale številne reforme vojske in obrambnega sektorja. V procesu priprav na vključitev v Nato v letih od 2000 do 2004 je leta 2003 opustila naborniški sistem, Slovensko vojsko preuredila v poklicno vojsko s sestavom okoli 7600 poklicnih vojakov, podčastnikov in častnikov in maloštevilno prostovoljno rezervo kot dopolnilom. </hi></p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Ključne besede: varnost, obramba, TORS, Slovenska vojska,
                        nacionalnovarnostni sistem RS, Slovenija</hi></p>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div>
                <head>Defending the Independence and the Slovenian Defence System in 1991</head>
                <p>As early as on the second day of its existence as an independent country,
                    Slovenia was, on 26 June 1991, already forced to defend itself with force, as it
                    tried to preserve its independence. The state leadership described the
                    intervention of the Yugoslav People’s Army as an act of aggression. The armed
                    conflict with the Yugoslav People’s Army was limited, of low intensity and short
                    in duration. The Brijuni Agreement, signed a week after the cease-fire on 2
                    July 1991 that ended the conflict, codified the cease-fire as an institutional
                    armistice whose observance would be monitored by the European Community.
                    Following a decision by the Presidium of the Socialist Federal Republic of
                    Yugoslavia on the (temporary) retreat of the Yugoslav People’ Army from Slovenia
                    on 18 July 1991, the Republic of Slovenia became a de facto independent country,
                    despite a three-month moratorium.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn2" n="1"> Božo Repe, <hi rend="italic">Jutri je nov dan.
                                Slovenci in razpad Jugoslavije</hi> (Ljubljana: Modrijan, 2002).
                            Tomaž Kladnik,
                            ed.,<hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve"> Vojaška obramba Slovenije</hi>
                            1990–1991 (Ljubljana: Defensor, 2011). Tomaž Kladnik, <hi rend="italic">Slovenska vojska v službi domovine</hi> (Ljubljana: Defensor, 2006)
                            26–32. </note> By 26 October 1991, when the last remnants of the
                    Yugoslav People’s Army’s forces left the territory of the Republic of Slovenia,
                    Slovenia was an independent, sovereign country, although as yet unrecognised by
                    the majority of the world’s countries (i.e. only recognised by 4) and still
                    facing serious threats to its security. </p>
                <p>The defence system that Slovenia established in autumn 1990 successfully stood
                    the test of war in June 1991. However, the system of national security was
                    developed only to the degree allowed by the situation of Slovenian secession,
                    when the country was still intertwined with the Yugoslav system of national
                    security, which meant that the Slovenian defence system was only able to
                    separate itself from the unified Yugoslav system as much as the circumstances
                    allowed. The system was based on a creative adaptation of the Yugoslav defence
                    system and included those elements that were within the jurisdiction of the
                    republics, which, as Yugoslavia underwent a serious crisis, were able to claim
                    for themselves at least part of its (otherwise federal) powers. The defence
                    forces thus consisted of three elements, the Territorial Defence, the People’s
                    Militia and the Civil Protection Service.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn3" n="2"> Kladnik, ed., <hi rend="italic">Vojaška
                                obramba Slovenije</hi>, 14, 15.</note> To defend the country’s
                    independence, these forces were able to call upon 70,000 conscripts of the
                    Territorial Defence (just prior to the start of the war, the number available
                    was increased by a few thousand by transferring younger conscripts from the
                    Yugoslav People’s Army to the Territorial Defence), about 9,000 active and
                    reserve members of the Militia, and the Civil Protection Service. In actuality,
                    about 35,000 members of the Territorial Defence and 7100 members of the Militia
                    were mobilized.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn4" n="3">
                            Ibid., 15, 16.</note>
                </p>
                <p>After the cease-fire agreement was signed on 8 July 1991, armed forces were never
                    again used to defend the country, in spite of serious threats to its safety and
                    the outbreak of the war in neighbouring Croatia in the autumn of the same year.
                    While the three-month moratorium on Slovenian independence which was included in
                    the peace treaty did represent an obstacle, it did not prevent the coordination
                    of urgent defence matters. After the Federal Presidium of the Socialist Federal
                    Republic of Yugoslavia decided on 18 July to temporarily recall the Yugoslav
                    People’s Army’s units and institutions from Slovenia, the Slovenian defence
                    system was able to act more freely. The further development of the defence and
                    security system of Slovenia thus proceeded in peace, even though Slovenia
                    remained positioned at the edge of the warring Western Balkans and subject to
                    measures of the international community pertaining to the area of the former
                    Yugoslavia, most notably an embargo on the purchase of arms.</p>
                <p>The first order of business was thus to build up the defence system. The strategy
                    for the development of the Slovenian defence system oscillated between the only
                    system possible at the time – a defence by means of own armed forces and other
                    unarmed entities – and the emerging wishes for Slovenia to join the collective
                    defence system represented by the North Atlantic Treaty Organization (Nato). On
                    6 October 1991, after more than three months, the retreat of the Yugoslav
                    People’s Army forces was finally over. By gaining its independence, the Republic
                    of Slovenia became a rather small country, both in terms of the standard
                    quantitative criteria as well as in terms of recognising that it could ensure
                    its own safety only by relying on other countries and international
                    organizations and institutions.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn5" n="4"> See: Špela Kranjc, »Članstvo v NATO. Študija
                            primerov Slovenije in Estonije« (diplomsko delo, Fakulteta za družbene
                            vede, 2009), 9.</note></p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>“The Time of Enthusiasm”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn6" n="5">Alojz Šteiner,
                            <hi rend="italic">Slovenska vojska med tranzicijo in transformacijo</hi>
                        (Ljubljana: Slovenian Armed Forces, Military Schools Centre, 2015),
                        53.</note>– Development of the Security and Defence System in
                    1991–1993</head>
                <p>In autumn 1991, senior officials of the Slovenian defence structures prompted the
                    continuation of the development of the defence system. In terms of the internal
                    development of the Slovenian security and defence structures, this period had
                    started as early as prior to the country’s declaration of independence on 25
                    June 1991.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn7" n="6"> The
                            Defence and Protection Act (Zakon o obrambi in zaščiti) was passed on 29
                            March 1991 and the Military Service Act (Zakon o vojaški dolžnosti) on 6
                            April 1991; the symbolic first contingent of recruits was also
                            conscripted before the declaration of independence, on 15 May 1991. See:
                            Kladnik, ed., <hi rend="italic">Vojaška obramba Slovenije</hi>,
                        87.</note>
                </p>
                <p>Security threats to the country remained high, as war raged across neighbouring
                    Croatia, with battles being fought immediately across the south-eastern
                    Slovenian border until at least January 1992. In terms of Slovenian security and
                    defence policy, the fact that the Republic of Croatia was the weaker side in its
                    conflict with the Yugoslav People’s Army and the Serbian population (of the
                    Republic of Serbian Krajina) and at the same time a partner (ally) that
                    irrevocably lost the trust of the Slovenian state authorities on 26 June 1991
                    was troubling, as it precluded any future alliances. For a while it seemed quite
                    possible that the forces of the Yugoslav Army would reappear at the southern
                    border. A part of Slovenian armed forces was thus assigned to protect it. This
                    was one of the reasons why Slovenia, under an arms embargo that applied to the
                    whole area of former Yugoslavia, began helping Croatia and later Bosnia by
                    supplying them with arms. However, this turned into an arms trade managed by the
                    Slovenian Ministry of Defence by summer 1991. Eventually, the competent state
                    authorities became the immediate sellers, dealers and sometimes brokers of
                    material, including not just what had been captured from the Yugoslav People’s
                    Army or contained in their or the Territorial Defence stockpiles, but also arms
                    purchased on the grey market.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn8" n="7"> Matej
                            Šurc, <hi rend="italic">Prevarana Slovenija. Domoljubje, zapisano z
                                ničlami</hi> (Ljubljana: Sanje, 2016). Matej Šurc and Blaž Zgaga,
                                <hi rend="italic">V imenu države. Trilogija: book 1: Odprodaja</hi>
                            (Ljubljana: Sanje, 2011). Matej Šurc and Blaž Zgaga, <hi rend="italic">V
                                imenu države. Trilogija: book 2: Preprodaja</hi> (Ljubljana: Sanje,
                            2011).</note> However, in doing so, Slovenia generally proceeded
                    with awareness of its own arms requirements, which the country was able to
                    largely cover using confiscated or relinquished materiel previously used by the
                    Yugoslav People’s Army. </p>
                <p>Using the Constitution of the Republic of Slovenia, adopted in December 1991, the
                    country defined its defence system at the highest level, while leaving the
                    determination of the detailed structure of its armed forces to further
                    legislation. The Constitution expressly limited the use of force to the defence
                    of state sovereignty and territorial integrity. The Constitution legislated
                    parliamentary control over the Slovenian armed forces and the possibility of
                    conscientious objection to military service. The only remaining mention of the
                    previously well-supported demilitarized national defence was the following
                    non-binding comment: “In the provision of security the state proceeds
                    principally from a policy of peace, and an ethic of peace and
                        non-aggression.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn9" n="8">
                            <hi rend="italic">Official Gazette of the Republic of Slovenia</hi>, No.
                            33/1991, 28 December 1991, Constitution of the Republic of Slovenia,
                            Article 124. The alternative pacifist idea of guaranteeing safety
                            without an army, which was the subject of a political clash in the
                            spring of 1991, was thus abandoned. See Anton Grizold, “Obrambni sistem
                            republike Slovenije. Stanje in perspektive nadaljnjega razvoja,“ in:
                            <hi rend="italic">Zbornik strokovno znanstvenih razprav</hi> (Ljubljana: Ministry of the
                            Interior of the Republic of Slovenia, December 1991),
                        161–181.</note> Slovenia legislated defence using armed forces and thus
                    provided a basis for its concept of armed neutrality. However, both the
                    political elite and the public were already talking about initiatives to join
                    Nato, which was believed to be necessary to guarantee Slovenia’s sovereignty in
                    light of the wars raging nearby.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn10" n="9">
                            Anton, Bebler, “Pot Slovenije v Nato = Slovenia's road to Nato,” <hi rend="italic">Bilten Slovenske vojske</hi> 11, No. 3 (November
                            2009): 107.</note></p>
                <p>The structure of the Territorial Defence of the Republic of Slovenia, which
                    retained its original name in spite of efforts to change it to Slovenian Army,
                    remained unchanged, as the Defence Act was not amended for a while either. The
                    formation of the army initially remained the same as during the war, i.e. with 7
                    regional headquarters and 26 subordinate area headquarters of the Territorial
                    Defence. The Slovenian army remained primarily territorial, but, inasmuch as it
                    was possible under the embargo and with limited financial resources, it
                    continued to develop branches and services it was lacking; i.e. artillery,
                    armoured unites, the air force. Arms left in Slovenia by the Yugoslav People’s
                    Army, including about 140 tanks, were of great help in this regard. The systems
                    and doctrines of General People’s Defence and Social Self-Protection were
                    abandoned. The creation of a new military tradition based on the new foundation
                    of the “War for Slovenia” and the part played by Slovenian forces in the State
                    of Slovenes, Croats and Serbs was also well under way.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn11" n="10"> Cf. Vladimir Prebilič and Jelena Juvan,
                            “(Ne)obstoj slovenske vojaške identitete,” <hi rend="italic">Sodobni
                                vojaški izzivi</hi> 14, No. 1 (2012): 55–67.</note></p>
                <p>The Army was manned through general compulsory military service.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn12" n="11"> At the time, the
                            Army had at its disposal slightly over 15,000 conscripts every year. Cf.
                            Andrej Lovšin, “Obrambni sistem in kadri od leta 1991 do 2003, 2,” <hi rend="italic">Slovenska vojska</hi> 12, No. 1, 16 January 2004.
                        </note> Conscription resumed in 1992. That year, 8151 conscripts
                    finished their training in the Territorial Defence of the Republic of Slovenia,
                    followed by 10,000 to 12,000 annually, as those who had not served their
                    military duty in the years when Slovenia was gaining independence were
                    conscripted as well. The Defence Act from April 1991 already gave conscripts the
                    right to conscientious objection and thus to serve their duty in non-military
                    contexts. 7 conscripts exercised this right in 1992; in the following years,
                    their numbers increased and truly balooned only after 1997.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn13" n="12"> Ibid.</note> The
                    seven-month training (which actually only lasted six months) during military
                    service was of a dual nature, with one part taking place at education centres
                    and the other in peace-time units of the Territorial Defence. The army was
                    professionally reinforced with commissioned and non-commissioned officers of the
                    Yugoslav People’s Army, as the Territorial Defence employed virtually every
                    officer who heeded the appeal of the Presidium of the Republic of Slovenia and
                    defected to the Territorial Defence by 1 July 1991. Of the 1893 employees of
                    the Territorial Defence at the end on 1991, 1278 had previously served in the
                    Yugoslav People’s Army.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn14" n="13"> Marijan Kranjc, <hi rend="italic">Slovenska
                                vojaška inteligenca</hi> (Grosuplje: Grafis Trade, 2005),
                        408.</note>
                </p>
                <p>Another objective of the development was to increase the professional core of the
                    armed forces and establish a professional military unit, the so-called 1
                    Special Brigade MORiS, established in October 1992, that was not a part of the
                    Territorial Defence but rather answered directly to the Ministry of Defence. The
                    armed forces of the Territorial Defence of the Republic of Slovenia numbered
                    77,000, but only 5 % of these were regular peacetime forces.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn15" n="14"> Šteiner, <hi rend="italic">Slovenska vojska med tranzicijo in transformacijo</hi>, 53. Grizold
                            claims 87,000 members of the armed forces and 3000 regular
                            employees.</note>
                </p>
                <p>Political parties were banned from the armed forces, and professional employees –
                    primarily commissioned and non-commissioned officers – were not allowed to be
                    party members or to partake in any party-related activities while in uniform.
                    However, this does not mean that political influences and opinions could not be
                    felt in the functioning of the defence system. Following the example of the
                    countries of Western Europe, the army came under civilian control, specifically
                    under control of the Parliament. </p>
                <p>The army, which had won the 1991 war, enjoyed a high level of public trust, with
                    state authorities further deliberately developing its positive public image.
                    Citizens saw the armed forces of their country as an important and
                    non-problematic part of the state structure and expressed a higher than average
                    level of trust in it.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn16" n="15"> Tomaž Repnik,
                            “Odnos civilne družbe do Slovenske vojske v obdobju 1991–2006”
                            (diplomsko delo, Fakulteta za družbene vede, 2006).</note></p>
                <p>On 3 February 1992, the Presidium of the Republic of Slovenia approved the
                    proposed General Plan for the Organization, Outfitting, Arming and Training
                    within the Territorial Defence of the Republic of Slovenia. According to the
                    Plan, the Territorial Defence would have 45,000 members, 18,000 of whom would be
                    in the manoeuvre forces, i.e. the special brigade, the missile and helicopter
                    brigade, seven infantry brigades, four armoured and mechanized battalions, an
                    anti-tank division and a support artillery division. The professional part of
                    the army would consist of 1350 commissioned officers, 1550 non-commissioned
                    officers and 1700 privates. The special brigade would be wholly
                        professional.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn17" n="16"> Kladnik, ed., <hi rend="italic">Vojaška obramba
                                Slovenije</hi>, 18–19. “Pomembnejši utrinki iz zgodovine Slovenske
                            vojske od prevzema popolne suverenosti nad slovenskim ozemljem do danes
                            – 20 let ponosni nase in v ponos Sloveniji,” retrieved on 7 June 2016,
                                <ref target="http://www.slovenskavojska.si/fileadmin/slovenska_vojska/pdf/sporocila/20let_zgod.pdf">http://www.slovenskavojska.si/fileadmin/slovenska_vojska/pdf/sporocila/20let_zgod.pdf</ref>.</note>
                    The Plan was the first complex programme that laid out a tangible strategy for
                    the development of the Slovenian army. In the following years, the Territorial
                    Defence attained the goals that had partly already been set and implemented when
                    the Plan was approved.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Transformation Into a Classic National Army</head>
                <p>The years from 1993 to 1995 were a time of normative efforts to transform the
                    Territorial Defence into a classic national army that would be able to defend
                    Slovenian sovereignty on its own, even though the state leadership
                    simultaneously already initiated the efforts to move closer to Nato and to
                    eventually join it. The Resolution on the Basis for the Concept of National
                    Security of the Republic of Slovenia was adopted in December 1993.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn18" n="17">
                            <hi rend="italic">Official Gazette of the Republic of Slovenia</hi>, No.
                            71/1993, 30 December 1993.</note> The Resolution emphasized that
                    “[f]or the Republic of Slovenia as part of a new international reality and a
                    country located in the immediate vicinity of the Balkans crisis area, provision
                    of national security is a matter of primary importance.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn19" n="18"> Ibid., item 11.</note>
                    The Slovenian army was defined as a defence force of the Republic of Slovenia
                    whose aim was to deter any attacks on the country and to coordinate and
                    implement military defence in the event of outside aggression or other forceful
                    interventions of foreign military forces against Slovenia. The Resolution
                    defined three primary ways in which Slovenia could be threatened: through a
                    military attack by an outside force, through internal threats including possible
                    attempts of a violent transformation of the social order, and through threats to
                    the environment. Slovenian Armed Forced were in charge of military defence
                    against a potential outside attack, while civil defence was tasked with civilian
                    defence. Security was supposed to be ensured by a security system whose main
                    parts were the Ministry of the Interior and two intelligence and security
                    services. On the other hand, a system of protection and rescue was set up to
                    protect against environmental dangers.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn20" n="19"> Ibid. Cf. Anton Grizold, “Nejasen namen. Resoluciji o izhodiščih
                            zasnove nacionalne varnosti Republike Slovenije na rob,” <hi rend="italic">Primorski dnevnik</hi> 49, No. 88, 1993.</note>
                </p>
                <p>Joining Nato, i.e. transitioning to collective defence, was first set as a
                    national policy goal a year before, when it was also approved by the General
                    Assembly. In January 1994, Nato published a call for participation in a
                    pre-joining preliminary programme called Partnership for Peace (Partnerstvo za
                        mir).<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn21" n="20">
                            <hi rend="italic">NATO, Official texts: Partnership for Peace Invitation
                                Document, 10–11 January 1994</hi>, retrieved on 7 October 2016, <ref target="http://www.nato.int/cps/en/natohq/official_texts_24468.htm?mode=pressrelease">http://www.nato.int/cps/en/natohq/official_texts_24468.htm?mode=pressrelease</ref>.</note>
                    At the same time, with a resolution amendment passed in January 1994, joining
                    Nato was defined as an important objective of Slovenian national defence, even
                    though the resolution focused primarily on political and diplomatic cooperation
                    and only secondarily on military cooperation.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn22" n="21">
                            <hi rend="italic">Official Gazette of the Republic of Slovenia</hi>, No.
                            2/1994. David Humar, Ivan Mikuž, Samo Zanoškar, Dean Groff and Leon
                            Holc, “Integration of the Slovenian armed forces into NATO and EU
                            military structures,” <hi rend="italic">Bilten Slovenske vojske</hi> 11,
                            No. 2 (2009): 60.</note> Slovenia joined the
                    <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Partnership for Peace </hi>programme as
                    early as 30 March 1994. Next year saw the creation of the first <hi rend="italic">Individual Partnership Programme</hi>, which both determined
                    Slovenia’s political objectives and stated the military and other capacities
                    Slovenia could offer to Nato.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn23" n="22"> Ibid., 61. Šteiner, <hi rend="italic">Slovenska
                                vojska med tranzicijo in transformacijo</hi>, 78.</note> This
                    period is also characterized by high internal tensions between the security
                    services of the Ministry of the Interior and the Ministry of Defence, with
                    suspicions of a planned coup and with the removal from office of the Minister of
                    Defence in March 1994.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn24" n="23"> Cf. Janez
                            Janša, <hi rend="italic">Okopi. Pot slovenske države 1991–1994</hi>
                            (Ljubljana: Mladinska knjiga, 2014).</note>
                </p>
                <p>New defence legislation was passed on 20 December 1994, after more than a year of
                    discussion and coordination.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn25" n="24">
                            <hi rend="italic">Official Gazette of the Republic of Slovenia</hi>, No.
                            82/94, Defence Act. Cf. Božo Repe, <hi rend="italic">Milan Kučan: prvi
                                predsednik</hi> (Ljubljana: Modrijan, 2015), 404–06.</note> “The
                    Defence Act provided a comprehensive framework for the defence system, primarily
                    in terms of organization, structure, tasks and other issues pertaining to the
                    Slovenian Armed Forces as a classic military organization as well as in terms of
                    civil defence. The Act also settled matters significant for the organization and
                    planning of defence, which came under the sole authority of the state. The
                    Defence Act separated the defence system from the system of protection against
                    natural and other disasters, except in cases where the systems complemented each
                        other.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn26" n="25">
                            “Defence Act: draft from 13 April 2016, EVA 2016-1911-0001,” retrieved
                            on 10 October 2016, <ref target="http://www.mo.gov.si/fileadmin/mo.gov.si/pageuploads/pdf/predpisi/obramba/v_pripravi/ZObrMedresorsko_20160413.pdf">http://www.mo.gov.si/fileadmin/mo.gov.si/pageuploads/pdf/predpisi/obramba/v_pripravi/ZObrMedresorsko_20160413.pdf</ref>.</note>
                    Pursuant to the Act, the Territorial Defence of the Republic of Slovenia was
                    renamed as the Slovenian Armed Forces the following year. </p>
                <p>After the adoption of an amendment to the Military Service Act, an important
                    change was implemented in regard to the training of conscripts.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn27" n="26">
                            <hi rend="italic">Official Gazette of the Republic of Slovenia</hi>, No.
                            94/95, Military Service Act – official consolidated text.</note> In
                    September 1996, education centres were abolished and the conscripted recruits
                    trained within military units. That way, the Slovenian Armed Forces were able to
                    increase the numbers of their peacetime units. This was also the first time that
                    additional funds were envisioned for arms purchases, while the so-called Basic
                    Development Programmes were used to define the armament and equipment
                    requirements in detail.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn28" n="27">
                            <hi rend="italic">Official Gazette of the Republic of Slovenia</hi>, No.
                            13/94, Act Providing Funds for the Realization of Basic Development
                            Programmes of the Armed Forces of the Republic of Slovenia in
                            1994–2007.</note></p>
                <p>In August 1995, Croatia achieved military victory with Operation Storm, thus
                    stabilizing Slovenia’s southern neighbourhood and greatly decreasing the
                    security and military threats faced by Slovenia.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn29" n="28"> Jože Pirjevec, <hi rend="italic">Jugoslovanske
                                vojne: 1991–2001</hi> (Ljubljana: Cankarjeva založba, 2003). Ozren
                        Žunec, “Operacije <hi rend="italic">Bljesak</hi> i <hi rend="italic">Oluja</hi>,” in: <hi rend="italic">Rat u Hrvatskoj i Bosni i Hercegovini: 1991–1995</hi>, eds. Branka Magaš and Ivo Žanić (Zagreb:
                            Jesenski i Turk and Sarajevo: Dani, 1999), 93–110. </note></p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Hoping for NATO</head>
                <p>In late 1990s, the direction and forms of development of the national security
                    system of the Republic of Slovenia were mostly determined by strategies for the
                    accession of Slovenia to the European and Euro-Atlantic institutional
                    frameworks, i.e. the European Union and Nato. In addition to Slovenia, all
                    former members of the Warsaw Pact and the newly formed Baltic states wanted to
                    join Nato as well; they expected the organization to involve them in its system
                    of collective security and thus solve all their security problems, from issues
                    regarding doctrine and development to structural matters. However, unlike the
                    Slovenian political elite, the population continued to show significant support
                    for the concept of armed neutrality, and the idea that the country should join
                    Nato’s system of collective defence was met with some doubts and
                        resistance.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn30" n="29">
                            Cf. Bebler, ”Pot Slovenie v NATO = Slovenia’s road to NATO,” 111,
                            112.</note>
                </p>
                <p>In 1996, the so-called <hi rend="italic">individual dialogue</hi> was used to
                    prepare the involvement of Slovenian Armed Forces in the process of planning and
                    assessment in which reforms and reorganizations of the defence system were being
                    determined. Particular attention was paid to the issue of compatibility with old
                    member states.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn31" n="30">
                            Šteiner,
                            <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Slovenska vojska med tranzicijo in transformacijo, </hi>78.
                            Š. Kranjc, „Članstvo v NATO,“ 29, 30.</note></p>
                <p>Among the results of the process of joining the collective defence system was the
                    decision for Slovenia to participate in peacekeeping operations in various
                    crisis areas all over the world. The first such intervention began in 1997, when
                    the first 25 members of the Slovenian Armed Forces and two members of the Police
                    were sent to participate in the ALBA peacekeeping operation in Albania.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn32" n="31"> Jelena Juvan, „Mirovne operacije kot
                            sredstvo zagotavljanja nacionalne varnosti?“ (Defence Research Centre of
                            the Faculty of Social Sciences of the University of Ljubljana),
                            retrieved on 2 July 2016, <ref target="http://www.fvv.um.si/DV2010/zbornik/nacionalna_varnost/juvan_doc.pdf">http://www.fvv.um.si/DV2010/zbornik/nacionalna_varnost/juvan_doc.pdf</ref>.
                        Jelena Juvan, „Slovenska vojska v mirovnih operacijah,” in: <hi rend="italic">Mirovne operacije in vloga Slovenije</hi>, ed. Ljubica
                            Jelušič (Ljubljana: Faculty of Social Sciences, 2005), 175–86. Klemen Grošelj,
                                <hi rend="italic">Slovenija v svetu mirovnih operacij</hi>
                            (Ljubljana: Založba FDV, 2007), 124–40.</note></p>
                <p>Slovenian request to join was turned down at the Madrid session of Nato in
                        1997.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn33" n="32">
                            Šteiner, <hi rend="italic">Slovenska vojska med tranzicijo in
                                transformacijo</hi>, 83.</note> The following period of
                    operation of the Slovenian defence system was wholly dedicated to continuing the
                    process of accession to Nato. As the reason behind the rejection was the fact
                    that the Slovenian army hadn't implemented the necessary reforms, the country,
                    in order to finally and surely attain the membership, resumed political efforts
                    and undertook a number of military reorganizations. In 1998, the country
                    developed the National Strategy for the Accession of Slovenia to Nato. The
                    effects of joining Nato were stated as follows: “Accession of Slovenia to Nato
                    would improve the security of the Republic of Slovenia and contribute to the
                    country’s long-term development.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn34" n="33"> “National Strategy for the Accession of the
                            Republic of Slovenia to Nato,” (February 1998), retrieved on 4 June
                            2016,
                        http://nato.gov.si/slo/dokumenti/nacionalna-strategija.pdf.</note></p>
                <p>As part of the accession process, Slovenia effected or had to implement a number
                    of structural reforms of its military and the defence system in general. The
                    main principles of the reforms were determined by the <hi rend="italic">Strategy
                        of Military Defence of the Republic of Slovenia</hi> drafted in 1998. The
                    strategy proposed a re-ordering of the armed forces into rapid reaction forces,
                    main defence forces and auxiliary defence forces. The strategy also anticipated
                    an increased permanent force bolstered by professional soldiers. </p>
                <p>Another important aspect of the strategy was cooperation with allied forces. In
                    1998, Slovenia was also the first candidate country to host the <hi rend="italic">Cooperative Adventure Exchange-98</hi> military exercise which
                    was also used to assess the candidate state’s logistical and support capacities. </p>
                <p>In 1999, Nato adopted the <hi rend="italic">Membership Action Plan</hi>, which
                    included Slovenia.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn35" n="34"> Šteiner, <hi rend="italic">Slovenska vojska med
                                tranzicijo in transformacijo</hi>, 83.</note> This formed the
                    basis on which Slovenia, starting in 2000, developed its annual national
                    programme for the attainment of membership in Nato. National programmes
                    encompassed matters of politics and the economy, defence and the military, and
                    of security, as well as legal and financial issues, which means that the reforms
                    carried out in order to join the military alliance were extremely complex and
                    also extended to areas other than defence. The reforms were carried out in
                    dialogue with Nato’s structures. The four-year period that preceded Slovenia’s
                    accession to Nato, with its four annual national programmes, was the main period
                    of adjustment for the Slovenian Armed Forces.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn36" n="35"> “Slovenija in NATO: kronologija slovenskega vključevanja v NATO,”
                                <hi rend="italic">Kronologija včlanjevanja</hi>, retrieved on 12
                            June 2016, <ref target="http://nato.gov.si/slo/slovenija-nato/">http://nato.gov.si/slo/slovenija-nato/</ref>. </note> In
                    February 2000, the <hi rend="italic">General Long-Term Plan for the Development
                        and Outfitting of the Slovenian Armed Forces</hi> (Splošni dolgoročni
                    program razvoja in opremljanja Slovenske vojske – SDPRO SV) was adopted, further
                    determining the organizational and technical aspects of outfitting the Slovenian
                    Armed Forces in a ten-year period.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn37" n="36">
                            <hi rend="italic">Official Gazette of the Republic of Slovenia</hi>, No.
                            32/2000, 1483, 13 April 2000.</note></p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Adapting to NATO</head>
                <p>At the beginning of the new millennium, the issues of Slovenian security and
                    defence became less acute. The conflict in the immediate Yugoslav neighbourhood
                    had settled, and after the Croatian victory in Operation Storm and the Dayton
                    Peace Agreement regarding Bosnia and Herzegovina, peace returned to the Western
                    Balkans, with the exception of Kosovo. National defence became a function
                    without a tangible goal, and security threats were minimal.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn38" n="37"> According to a representative
                            public opinion survey carried out by the Defence Research Centre in
                            2003, only 14 % of respondents felt threatened in any way. 42.5 % of
                            those surveyed believed that it was unlikely for Slovenia ever to need
                            an army again. In a similar study carried out in 2001, this belief was
                            only shared by 31 %. – “Slovenci se počutimo varne,” <hi rend="italic">Slovenska vojska</hi> 12, No. 1, 16 January 2004.</note> This
                    resulted in a diminishing focus on security and defence and in dwindling care
                    for the defence of the country. This change of circumstances coincided with
                    processes of modernization within Nato that were being implemented since the end
                    of the Cold War. The central aspect of these changes was the shift of security
                    threats from military to non-military and the resulting need to transform armed
                    forces from high-manpower militaries to professional forces with smaller
                    numbers. Mass armies of citizens were unsuited for new security threats, so
                    almost all Nato member countries transitioned to professional armed forces.</p>
                <p>From 2000 onward, Slovenia carried out the second cycle of adaptations to the
                    Western armies in Nato. The adaptations or reforms extended to three important
                    areas:</p>
                <list type="ordered">
                    <item>organizational changes to forces, differentiation between mobile and
                        immobile forces;</item>
                    <item>separation of operational command and strategic command (including
                        physical separation: Force Command in Vrhnika and General Staff in
                        Ljubljana); </item>
                    <item>discontinuation of the system of conscription and establishment of a
                        professional army. </item>
                </list>
                <p rend="List Paragraph">In 2002 Slovenia was finally invited to begin accession
                    negotiations for Nato membership. This signalled the beginning of rapid changes
                    for the Slovenian Armed Forces: decrease of reserves to less than 50 % of the
                    previous numbers, gradual discontinuation of conscription and creation of a
                    professional army, development of forces that could participate in the allied
                    contingent. After a decade of decreases, the defence budget again increased to
                    almost two percent of the GDP.</p>
                <p rend="List Paragraph">Among the most visible aspects of the reform of the
                    Slovenian Armed Forces was the suspension of manning the forces through
                    conscription and the establishment of a professional army. Slovenia abolished
                    compulsory military service in 2003, a year before the country had planned to do
                    so and a mere two years after the idea was first proposed. The last generation
                    of conscripts to serve military duty left their barracks on 15 October
                        2003.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn39" n="38">
                            Lovšin, “Obrambni sistem in kadri od leta 1991 do 2003,
                    2.”</note></p>
                <p>However, adapting to Nato’s standards didn't only encompass military policy
                    documents but was also reflected in frequent military reforms that pertained to
                    either certain segments of armed forces or to the whole military – beginning
                    with amendments to the Defence Act that regulated the participation of the
                    country in the system of collective defence at a normative level, stating that
                    national defence “is also being realized through the joining and active
                    involvement of the country in international security associations based on
                    international treaties”. The structure of forces within the army and the
                    military intelligence and security activities were changed as well. The
                    amendment also instituted voluntary service in the contractual reserve
                    formation. With regard to professional soldiers, provisions regulating military
                    service were improved and special working conditions were regulated as
                        well.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn40" n="39">
                            <hi rend="italic">Official Gazette of the Republic of Slovenia</hi>, No.
                            47/2002, Act Amending the Defence Act.</note>
                </p>
                <p>Pursuant to these amendments, the manpower of the Slovenian Armed Forces was
                    decreased from 47,000 to 30,000 people. District territorial headquarters and
                    some of the operational commands were abolished. The Force Command was
                    established in 2003. Units of rapid response forces were given priority to be
                    manned by professional soldiers. </p>
                <p>The rapid and constant changes to the Slovenian Armed Forces had a negative
                    impact as well, as various reform measures had unwanted effects. Numerous
                    solutions were barely given a chance before being reformed again. Changes to
                    various units and especially commands were sometimes left unfinished, be it due
                    to material limitations or rapidly changing circumstances. </p>
                <p>As the professional part of the armed forces had too many commissioned and
                    non-commissioned officers and too few privates, the military mostly offered
                    employment to the latter. Gradually the numbers of the Slovenian Armed Forces
                    increased towards the target of 8000. By the end of 2001, there were 5043 of
                    them, but by the end of 2005, the number already increased to 7316. In the same
                    period, the number of professional soldiers increased from 707 to 2918.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn41" n="40"> “Letno poročilo Ministrstva za
                            obrambo za leto 2005. Mors, 27 May 2014,” retrieved on 5 May 2016, <ref target="http://www.mo.gov.si/fileadmin/mo.gov.si/pageuploads/pdf/ministrstvo/letno_porocilo_2005.pdf">http://www.mo.gov.si/fileadmin/mo.gov.si/pageuploads/pdf/ministrstvo/letno_porocilo_2005.pdf</ref>.</note>
                    The status of soldiers as public employees was problematic as well, as it was
                    often unsuitable for professional soldiers. </p>
                <p>After the initial increase, when the numbers of the voluntary contractual
                    reserves reached about 1400, replenishment of forces stagnated. In 2005, the
                    reserves consisted of 7917 conscripts. Service in the military was voluntary and
                    possible for both men and women, and a couple hundred volunteers took advantage
                    of this each year.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn42" n="41"> Ibid., 15, 16, 31. “Prvih sto prostovoljcev,” <hi rend="italic">Slovenska vojska</hi>, 12, No. 1, 1.</note></p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Slovenian Armed Forces Outside Slovenia</head>
                <p rend="List Paragraph">One of the most visible forms of operation of the Slovenian
                    Armed Forces was their participation in so-called “crisis response operations”,
                    i.e. in missions in crisis areas. From the first such case in 1997 onward, the
                    presence of Slovenian Armed Forces abroad as part of missions led by the UN, the
                    European Union or Nato increased, and such cooperation became a mainstay of the
                    army’s operation. Another important part of the army’s activities was its
                    participation in missions in the area of former Yugoslavia, particularly in
                    Bosnia and Herzegovina. In 2005, members of Slovenian Armed Forces were thus
                    involved in six such operations, with their participation being most numerous in
                    Bosnia, Kosovo and Afghanistan.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn43" n="42"> “Letno poročilo MORS za leto 2005,”
                        16–18.</note> As members of the Slovenian Armed Forces left for various
                    crisis areas, their numbers increased, so did the intensity of their
                    assignments. However, in all peacekeeping missions, members of Slovenian Armed
                    Forces were integrated with larger units under foreign command.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn44" n="43"> Juvan, Mirovne
                            operacije kot sredstvo zagotavljanja nacionalne varnosti?, 175–86.
                            Grošelj, <hi rend="italic">Slovenija v svetu mirovnih operacij</hi>,
                            124–40.</note></p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Joining Collective Defence – Objective Attained and the Beginning of a New
                    Period</head>
                <p>The voices that were critical of the idea of joining Nato led the national
                    political elite to call a referendum on this issue while simultaneously
                    campaigning in its support. Slovenia was only the second country to decide for
                    such a procedure. At the referendum held on 23 March 2003, joining Nato was
                    supported by 66.08 % of those who voted, and this result provided the political
                    elite with enough support to implement the final steps of the process.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn45" n="44"> “Poročilo o
                            izidu glasovanja o izidu referenduma o pristopu Republike Slovenije k
                            Organizaciji Severnoatlantske pogodbe (NATO), ki je bil 23. marca 2003,”
                                <hi rend="italic">Referendumski rezultati</hi>, retrieved on 8
                            October 2016, <ref target="http://nato.gov.si/slo/slovenija-nato/referendum/rezultati/">http://nato.gov.si/slo/slovenija-nato/referendum/rezultati/</ref>.
                        </note> Six days later, on 29 March 2004, Slovenia ratified the
                    accession agreement and became a member of Nato.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn46" n="45"> “Protocol to the North
                            Atlantic Treaty on the accession of the Republic of Slovenia,” <hi rend="italic">NATO - Official text: Protocol to the North Atlantic
                                Treaty on the accession of the Republic of Slovenia,
                                26-Mar.-2003</hi>, available at: <ref target="http://www.nato.int/cps/en/natohq/official_texts_20315.htm">http://www.nato.int/cps/en/natohq/official_texts_20315.htm</ref>.</note>
                    For the Slovenian defence system, this signalled the end of a difficult and
                    sometimes contradictory journey towards becoming a part of the European
                    defensive alliance – though on its margin – as well as a part of the ring around
                    the crisis area of former Yugoslavia (Croatia, Bosnia and Herzegovina, Serbia,
                    Kosovo, Montenegro, Macedonia and Albania) that now consisted of Slovenia,
                    Hungary, Romania, Bulgaria and Greece, along with Italy across the Adriatic Sea.
                    The security configuration in the area was thus greatly improved, although not
                    yet completely in place, as there were already signs that the countries that
                    were at the time still isolated would eventually be included as well.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="bibliography">
                <head>Sources and Literature</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl>“Defence Act: draft from 13 April 2016, EVA 2016-1911-0001.” Retrieved on
                        10 October 2016. <ref target="http://www.mo.gov.si/fileadmin/mo.gov.si/pageuploads/pdf/predpisi/obramba/v_pripravi/ZObrMedresorsko_20160413.pdf">http://www.mo.gov.si/fileadmin/mo.gov.si/pageuploads/pdf/predpisi/obramba/v_pripravi/ZObrMedresorsko_20160413.pdf</ref>.</bibl>
                    <bibl>“Letno poročilo Ministrstva za obrambo za leto 2005.” Mors, 27 May 2014.
                        Retrieved on 5 May 2016. <ref target="http://www.mo.gov.si/fileadmin/mo.gov.si/pageuploads/pdf/ministrstvo/letno_porocilo_2005.pdf">http://www.mo.gov.si/fileadmin/mo.gov.si/pageuploads/pdf/ministrstvo/letno_porocilo_2005.pdf</ref>.</bibl>
                    <bibl>“National Strategy for the Accession of the Republic of Slovenia to Nato.”
                        February 1998. Retrieved on 4 June 2016. <ref target="http://nato.gov.si/slo/dokumenti/nacionalna-strategija.pdf">http://nato.gov.si/slo/dokumenti/nacionalna-strategija.pdf</ref>. </bibl>
                    <bibl>“Pomembnejši utrinki iz zgodovine Slovenske vojske od prevzema popolne
                        suverenosti nad slovenskim ozemljem do danes – 20 let ponosni nase in v
                        ponos Sloveniji.” Retrieved on 7 June 2016. <ref target="http://www.slovenskavojska.si/fileadmin/slovenska_vojska/pdf/sporocila/20let_zgod.pdf">http://www.slovenskavojska.si/fileadmin/slovenska_vojska/pdf/sporocila/20let_zgod.pdf</ref>.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Bebler, Anton. “Pot Slovenije v Nato = Slovenia's road to Nato.” <ref target="http://cobiss6.izum.si/scripts/cobiss?ukaz=DISP&amp;id=1441189963927040&amp;rec=-104491008&amp;sid=2&amp;fmt=11"><hi rend="italic">Bilten Slovenske vojske</hi> 11, No. 3 (November
                            2009): 105–16</ref>.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Grizold, Anton. “Nejasen namen. Resoluciji o izhodiščih zasnove nacionalne
                        varnosti Republike Slovenije na rob.” <hi rend="italic">Primorski
                            dnevnik</hi> 49, No. 88, 1993.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Grizold, Anton. “Obrambni sistem republike Slovenije. Stanje in
                        perspektive nadaljnjega razvoja.“ In: <hi rend="italic">Zbornik strokovno
                            znanstvenih razprav,</hi> 161–81. Ljubljana: Ministry of the Interior of
                        the Republic of Slovenia, December 1991. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Grošelj, Klemen. <hi rend="italic">Slovenija v svetu mirovnih
                            operacij</hi>. Ljubljana, Založba FDV, 2007.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Humar, David, Ivan Mikuž, Samo Zanoškar, Dean Groff and Leon Holc.
                        “Integration of the Slovenian armed forces into NATO and EU military
                        structures.” <hi rend="italic">Bilten Slovenske vojske</hi> 11, No. 2
                        (2009): 59–81.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Janša, Janez. <hi rend="italic">Okopi. Pot slovenske države
                        1991–1994</hi>. Ljubljana: Mladinska knjiga, 2014.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Juvan, Jelena. “Mirovne operacije kot sredstvo zagotavljanja nacionalne
                        varnosti?.” Defence Research Centre of the Faculty of Social Sciences of the
                        University of Ljubljana. Retrieved on 2 July 2016. <ref target="http://www.fvv.um.si/DV2010/zbornik/nacionalna_varnost/juvan_doc.pdf">http://www.fvv.um.si/DV2010/zbornik/nacionalna_varnost/juvan_doc.pdf</ref>.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Juvan, Jelena. “Slovenska vojska v mirovnih operacijah.” In: <hi rend="italic">Mirovne operacije in vloga Slovenije</hi>, ed. Ljubica
                        Jelušič, 175–186. Ljubljana: Faculty of Social Sciences, 2005.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Kladnik, Tomaž, ed. <hi rend="italic">Vojaška obramba Slovenije
                            1990–1991</hi>. Ljubljana: Defensor, 2011.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Kladnik, Tomaž. <hi rend="italic">Slovenska vojska v službi domovine</hi>.
                        Ljubljana: Defensor, 2006.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Kranjc, Marijan. <hi rend="italic">Slovenska vojaška inteligenca</hi>.
                        Grosuplje: Grafis Trade, 2005.</bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="italic">Kronologija včlanjevanja</hi>. “Slovenija in NATO:
                        kronologija slovenskega vključevanja v NATO.” Retrieved on 25 June 2016.
                            <ref target="http://nato.gov.si/slo/slovenija-nato/kronologija/">http://nato.gov.si/slo/slovenija-nato/kronologija/</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>Lovšin, Andrej. “Obrambni sistem in kadri od leta 1991 do 2003, 2.” <hi rend="italic">Slovenska vojska</hi> 12, No. 1, 16 January 2004.</bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="italic">NATO, Official texts: Partnership for Peace Invitation
                            Document, 10–11 January 1994</hi>. Retrieved on 7 October 2016. <ref target="http://www.nato.int/cps/en/natohq/official_texts_24468.htm?mode=pressrelease">http://www.nato.int/cps/en/natohq/official_texts_24468.htm?mode=pressrelease</ref>.</bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Official Gazette of the Republic of Slovenia. </hi>Ljubljana:
                        Uradni list Republike Slovenije.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Pirjevec, Jože. <hi rend="italic">Jugoslovanske vojne: 1991–2001</hi>.
                        Ljubljana: Cankarjeva založba, 2003.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Prebilič, Vladimir and Jelena Juvan. “(Ne)obstoj slovenske vojaške
                        identitete.” <hi rend="italic">Sodobni vojaški izzivi</hi> 14, No. 1 (2012):
                        55–67.</bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="italic">Referendumski rezultati.</hi> “Poročilo o izidu
                        glasovanja o izidu referenduma o pristopu Republike Slovenije k Organizaciji
                        Severnoatlantske pogodbe (NATO), ki je bil 23. marca 2003.” Retrieved on 8
                        October 2016. <ref target="http://nato.gov.si/slo/slovenija-nato/referendum/rezultati/">http://nato.gov.si/slo/slovenija-nato/referendum/rezultati/</ref>.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Repe, Božo. <hi rend="italic">Jutri je nov dan. Slovenci in razpad
                            Jugoslavije.</hi> Ljubljana: Modrijan, 2002.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Repe, Božo. <hi rend="italic">Milan Kučan: prvi predsednik</hi>.
                        Ljubljana: Modrijan, 2015.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Repnik, Tomaž. “Odnos civilne družbe do Slovenske vojske v obdobju
                        1991–2006.” Diplomsko delo, Fakulteta za družbene vede, 2006.</bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="italic">Slovenska vojska</hi> 12, No. 1, 1. “Prvih sto
                        prostovoljcev.” </bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="italic">Slovenska vojska</hi> 12, No. 1, 16 January 2004.
                        “Slovenci se počutimo varne.” </bibl>
                    <bibl>Špela Kranjc, “Članstvo v NATO. Študija primerov Slovenije in Estonije.”
                        Diplomsko delo, Fakulteta za družbene vede, 2009.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Šteiner, Alojz. <hi rend="italic">Slovenska vojska med tranzicijo in
                            transformacijo</hi>. Ljubljana: Slovenian Armed Forces, Military Schools
                        Centre, 2015.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Šurc, Matej and Blaž Zgaga. <hi rend="italic">V imenu države. Trilogija:
                            book. 1: Odprodaja</hi>. Ljubljana: Sanje, 2011.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Šurc, Matej and Blaž Zgaga. <hi rend="italic">V imenu države. Trilogija:
                            book. 2: Preprodaja</hi>. Ljubljana: Sanje, 2011.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Šurc, Matej. <hi rend="italic">Prevarana Slovenija. Domoljubje, zapisano z
                            ničlami</hi>. Ljubljana: Sanje, 2016.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Žunec, Ozren. “Operacije Bljesak i Oluja.” In: <hi rend="italic">Rat u Hrvatskoj i Bosni i Hercegovini:
                        1991–1995</hi>, eds. Branka Magaš and Ivo
                        Žanić, 93–110. Zagreb: Jesenski i Turk and Sarajevo: Dani,
                        1999.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
            <div type="summary" xml:lang="sl">
                <head type="main">OBRAMBA REPUBLIKE SLOVENIJE 1991–2004</head>
                <head>OD SAMOSTOJNE V KOLEKTIVNO OBRAMBO</head>
                <head>POVZETEK</head>
                <docAuthor>Damijan Guštin</docAuthor>
                <p>Republika Slovenija je svoj obrambni sistem začela oblikovati še v okviru
                    jugoslovanske federativne države in še pred tem, ko je najavila svojo
                    osamosvojitev. Takoj po razglasitvi neodvisnosti je ta še ne docela vzpostavljen
                    obrambni sistem uspešno prestal preizkušnjo, ko je bila 26. junija 1991
                    prisiljena v obrambo z oboroženo silo. Nadaljnji razvoj obrambno-varnostnega
                    sistema Slovenije je po premirju in umiku sil JLA iz Slovenije potekal v
                    mirnodobnih razmerah, čeprav je bila Slovenija še dolgo na robu bojujočega se
                    zahodnobalkanskega prostora. Dogradnja obrambnega sistema je sledila edini možni
                    smeri, obrambi s svojo oboroženo silo in z drugimi neoboroženimi strukturami, a
                    željo, da bi se Slovenija vključila v kolektivno obrambo Severnoatlantskega
                    pakta (Nato), saj je bila tipična majhna država, ki je svojo obrambo lahko
                    zagotavljala le deloma. Razvoj je sledil dvema dolgima in obsežnima razvojnima
                    procesoma: obrambno-varnostni sistem Slovenije je bilo treba dokončati in
                    oblikovati glede na novo dejstvo neodvisne države; prevladujoča želja slovenske
                    državne elite, da Slovenija preide na kolektivno obrambo, ki jo je predstavljala
                    edina še delujoča vojaška zveza, Severnoatlantski pakt, pa ji je določila
                    poglavitno smer, saj se je že od leta 1993 prizadevala za sprejem v NATO. Med
                    tema procesoma pa so se vojske drugih evropskih držav temeljito spremenile;
                    prilagodile so se spremenjenim varnostnim grožnjam, postale so manjše,
                    fleksibilne, poklicne vojske, čemur se je poskušala prilagoditi tudi Slovenska
                    vojska. Slovenski obrambni sistem se je v devetdesetih razvil tako po
                    opremljenosti kot po organiziranosti, vendar pa so številne reforme obrambnega
                    sistema in vojske sledila šele po letu 1997, ko Slovenija ni uspela s svojo
                    prošnjo za sprejem v Natovo kolektivno obrambo, in zlasti po letu 1999, ko je
                    Nato sprejel Akcijski načrt za članstvo, ki je vključeval tudi Slovenijo.
                    Najbolj vidne reforme so zadevale njen obseg in strukturo. V začetku novega
                    tisočletja je začel slabeti varnostni in obrambni imperativ Slovenije, saj se je
                    sosednji zahodnobalkanski prostor umiril. Posledica tega sta bili opuščanje
                    skrbi za obrambo in zmanjšanje pomena varnosti in obrambe. Slovenija je od leta
                    2000 do končnega sprejetja v Nato leta 2004 izvedla drugi ciklus prilagajanja
                    zahodnim armadam. Prilagajanje je zajelo tri pomembna področja, prilagoditev
                    organizacije sil, ločitev med premakljivimi in nepremakljivimi silami; ločitev
                    operativne ravni poveljevanja od strateške (poveljstvo sil na Vrhniki,
                    generalštab v Ljubljani) in opustitev naborniškega sistema in uvedba poklicne
                    vojske. </p>
                <p>Leta 2002 je Slovenija končno dobila povabilo k pristopnim pogajanjem za članstvo
                    v Natu. S tem so se začele hitre spremembe: zmanjšanje rezervne sestave na manj
                    kot 50 odstotkov prejšnjega sestava, odpravljanje naborniškega sistema, odprava
                    obveznega služenja vojaškega roka, ki je bilo izvedeno 2003, eno leto pred
                    predvidenim rokom, in uvajanje poklicne vojske, snovanje sil, ki bi sodelovale v
                    zavezniškem kontingentu. Delež izdatkov za obrambo se je po desetletju upada
                    spet približal dvema odstotkoma BDP. Uvedena je bila zgolj poklicna vojska z
                    okoli 7600 poklicnimi vojaki, podčastniki in častniki, ter dopolnilna pogodbena
                    rezerva, ki pa je ostala maloštevilna.</p>
                <p>Vzporedno s spremembami je referendum o vstopu v Nato s 66,08 odstotka
                    glasovalcev za vstop dal politično-državni eliti dovolj veliko podporo za
                    sklepne poteze vključevanja. Slovenija je 29. marca 2004 z ratifikacijo
                    pristopnega sporazuma postala članica Nata in s tem dosegla zastavljeni cilj,
                    prešla v kolektivno obrambo.</p>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>