<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Campaigning Europe.<lb/>The Czech Parliamentary Elections of 2002<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn2" n="*">The text was created with support for the
                        long-term conceptual development of the research organization, <hi rend="italic">RVO</hi> No.
                        68378114.</note></title>
                <author>
                    <forename>Adéla</forename>
                    <surname>Gjuričová</surname>
                    <roleName>PhD</roleName>PhD., at the Institute of Contemporary History of the
                    Czech Academy of Sciences, gjuricova@usd.cas.cz <roleName>Senior
                        researcher</roleName>
                    <affiliation>Institut of Contemporary History of the Czech Academy of
                        Sciences</affiliation>
                    <email>gjuricova@usd.cas.cz</email></author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>2023-09-21</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>
                    <orgName xml:lang="sl">Inštitut za novejšo zgodovino</orgName>
                    <orgName xml:lang="en">Institute of Contemporary History</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Privoz 11</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>SI-1000 Ljubljana</addrLine>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>http://ojs.inz.si/pnz/article/view/4168</pubPlace>
                <date>2023</date>
                <availability status="free">
                    <licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title xml:lang="sl">Prispevki za novejšo zgodovino</title>
                <title xml:lang="en">Contributions to Contemporary History</title>
                <biblScope unit="volume">63</biblScope>
                <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
                <idno type="ISSN">2463-7807</idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source, born digital.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc xml:lang="en">
                <p>Contributions to Contemporary History is one of the central Slovenian scientific
                    historiographic journals, dedicated to publishing articles from the field of
                    contemporary history (the 19th and 20th century).</p>
                <p>The journal is published three times per year in Slovenian and in the following
                    foreign languages: English, German, Serbian, Croatian, Bosnian, Italian, Slovak
                    and Czech. The articles are all published with abstracts in English and
                    Slovenian as well as summaries in English.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <projectDesc xml:lang="sl">
                <p>Prispevki za novejšo zgodovino je ena osrednjih slovenskih znanstvenih
                    zgodovinopisnih revij, ki objavlja teme s področja novejše zgodovine (19. in 20.
                    stoletje).</p>
                <p>Revija izide trikrat letno v slovenskem jeziku in v naslednjih tujih jezikih:
                    angleščina, nemščina, srbščina, hrvaščina, bosanščina, italijanščina, slovaščina
                    in češčina. Članki izhajajo z izvlečki v angleščini in slovenščini ter povzetki
                    v angleščini.</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="sl"/>
                <language ident="en"/>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords xml:lang="en">
                    <term>Czech Republic 1996–2004</term>
                    <term>EU enlargement</term>
                    <term>Czech parliamentary elections of 2002</term>
                    <term>Europeanization</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords xml:lang="sl">
                    <term>Češka republika 1996–2004</term>
                    <term>širitev EU</term>
                    <term>češke parlamentarne volitve 2002</term>
                    <term>evropeizacija</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change><date>2023-09-26T07:18:35Z</date>
                    <name>Mihael Ojsteršek</name>
                    <desc>Pretvorba iz DOCX v TEI, dodatno kodiranje</desc></change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <docAuthor>Adéla Gjuričová<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn1" n="**"><hi rend="bold">PhD.,
                        Senior Research Fellow at the Institute of Contemporary History of the Czech
                        Academy of Sciences, <ref target="mailto:gjuricova@usd.cas.cz">gjuricova@usd.cas.cz</ref></hi></note></docAuthor>
            <docImprint>
                <idno type="cobissType">Cobiss tip: 1.01</idno>
                <idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.51663/pnz.63.2.03</idno>
            </docImprint>
            <div type="abstract">
                <head>IZVLEČEK</head>
                <head>KAMPANJA ZA EVROPO. ČEŠKE PARLAMENTARNE VOLITVE 2002</head>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Avtorica v prispevku obravnava kampanjo pred češkimi
                        parlamentarnimi volitvami leta 2002 in se osredotoča na predstave, povezane
                        z Evropsko unijo in pričakovanim članstvom Češke. Pojasnjuje radikalizacijo
                        domačega in mednarodnega političnega konteksta ter pokaže, da je bil pristop
                        k EU v kampanji sicer vseprisoten, vendar je bil zreduciran na dve temi, ki
                        nista bili povezani z dejanskim vstopom v Unijo, in sicer elektrarno Temelin
                        in tako imenovane Beneševe dekrete. V zaključnem delu prispevka poskuša
                        institucionalni vidik razvoja povezati z razpravo o evropeizaciji.</hi>
                </p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Ključne besede: Češka republika 1996–2004, širitev EU, češke
                        parlamentarne volitve 2002, evropeizacija</hi></p>
            </div>
            <div type="abstract" xml:lang="en">
                <head>ABSTRACT</head>
                <p><hi rend="italic">The article deals with the campaign before the Czech
                        parliamentary elections in 2002, focusing on the imagery concerning the
                        European Union and the expected Czech membership. It explains the
                        radicalizing domestic and international political context, demonstrating
                        that while the EU accession was omnipresent in the campaign, it was reduced
                        to two topics unrelated to actual entry into the Union, namely Temelín power
                        plant and the so called Beneš decrees. The concluding part seeks to relate
                        the institutional aspect of the development to the debate on
                        Europeanization. </hi></p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Keywords: Czech Republic 1996–2004 – EU enlargement – Czech
                        parliamentary elections of 2002 – Europeanization</hi></p>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div>
                <head>Introduction</head>
                <p>The Czech government negotiated accession to the European Union for more than
                    three years, before the EU and the Czech entry became the centre of electoral
                    debate for the first time. “The election is also about the country’s relation to
                    the EU,” <hi rend="italic"> The Financial Times </hi>wrote on electoral day,
                    trying to sum up the positions of the main parties running in the parliamentary
                    elections of June 2002.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn3" n="1">Quoted in “Média:
                        volby v ČR jsou o vstupu do Unie,” <hi rend="italic">Právo</hi>, June 15,
                        2002, 8.</note></p>
                <p>The accession process was expected to be completed by the end of that year. In
                    the words of the government’s chief negotiator Pavel Telička, it was
                    “characterized by high expectations and hopes, but was also full of anxieties
                    and frustrations.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn4" n="2">Pavel Telička and Karel
                        Barták, “The Accession of the Czech Republic to the EU,” in <hi
                            rend="italic">The Accession Story: The EU from Fifteen to Twenty-Five
                            Countries</hi>, ed. George Vassiliou (Oxford and New York: Oxford UP
                        2007), 144–56, quote 144.</note> At this phase, the – fairly advanced –
                    adoption and implementation of the Union acquis was less of an issue than two
                    discriminatory proposals by the EU negotiators, including an intention to
                    temporarily restrict free movement of workers for new members and to limit EU
                    subsidies available to new members. In addition, due to the excessive state
                    share in the banking sector, the Czech Republic also had a problem meeting the
                    criteria of free competition.</p>
                <p>No matter how substantial the above issues were, European integration featured in
                    the campaign in an unexpected manner and through topics only vaguely related to
                    EU membership. The following text seeks to characterize the general political
                    setting before the elections. It tracks the highlights and main turning points
                    in the campaign, while relating the respective party strategies and public
                    rhetoric to the election outcomes. Then it applies the concept of
                    Europeanization in an unorthodox way. The earliest definitions perceived as a
                    process through which EU political and economic dynamics become part of the
                    organisational logic of national politics and policy-making.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn5" n="3">Robert Ladrech, “Europeanization of Domestic Politics
                        and Institutions: The Case of France,” <hi rend="italic">Journal of Common
                            Market Studies</hi> 32, No. 1 (1994): 69–88.</note> Political
                    scientists who most frequently employed the concept tended to focus on the
                    effects on political parties, other institutional actors or specific national
                    policies <hi rend="italic">following</hi> EU entry. This remained the case even
                    with procedures dealing with the process in East-Central Europe.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn6" n="4">See e.g., Ladislav Cabada and Alenka
                        Krašovec, <hi rend="italic">Europeanization of National Political
                            Parties</hi> (Dobrá Voda: Vydavatelství a nakladatelství Aleš Čeněk,
                        2004). Petr Fiala, Vít Hloušek, Markéta Pitrová, Pavel Pšeja and Petr Suchý,
                        “Evropeizace politických stran a zájmových skupin: základní problémy a směry
                        analýzy,” <hi rend="italic">Politologický časopis</hi> 13, No. 1 (2006):
                        3–26. Lukáš Linek and Štěpán Pecháček, “Vliv evropské integrace na politické
                        strany, stranický systém a volební chování v České republice,” in <hi
                            rend="italic">Proměny reprezentace zájmů po vstupu do Evropské
                        unie</hi>, eds. Zdenka Mansfeldová and Aleš Kroupa (Praha: Sociologické
                        nakladatelství, 2008), 53–78.</note> The present study, on the contrary,
                    opts to employ the concept in a non-normative, historical description of the
                    adaptation process before 2004, which has until now been rare.</p>
                <p>The following text is intended as a contribution to understanding how the
                    national institutions of EU membership-seekers transformed during the accession
                    process and what range of sentiments towards the West and the EU arose during
                    that period. A historicisation of various positions within political
                    institutions, exemplified in one election campaign, can reveal how the
                    relationship between the nation states and the EU was imagined, constructed and
                    performed. Besides this, it may also prove helpful to consider some of the
                    latest trends in the Europeanization debate in that context, especially those
                    dealing with the Europeanization of political institutions, their transformation
                    and the shifts in their mutual balance within political systems. The concept of
                    de-parliamentarization, introduced in the concluding part of the article, might
                    clarify some of the institutional contradictions connected with the accession
                    process as well as its aftermath in Czech politics after 2004. Therefore,
                    reflection on Europeanization may offer an explanation for the long-term
                    presence of a contradiction between a generally shared support for EU membership
                    in the country on the one hand and the mutually exclusive views on what the
                    accession would, should and must not involve on the other.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>An Explosive Year</head>
                <p>It is difficult to forget Central European politics which were in place at the
                    beginning of 2002. In Austria, a petition against the completion of the Temelín
                    nuclear power plant in South Bohemia gained mass support. It implied that a
                    former Communist country could not run safe nuclear technology. While the issue
                    of Temelín's safety was ventilated in the European Union, historical topics
                    gained prominence, especially the so-called Beneš decrees. They were a special
                    part of legislation issued by Czechoslovak President Edvard Beneš during WWII
                    and in 1945 that deprived Czechoslovak German and Hungarian speaking citizens of
                    their citizenship and civil rights, took away all their property and ordered
                    their deportation. The abolition of these decrees became associated with, or
                    rather to condition, the Czech Republic's EU accession. This was first
                    articulated by the nationalist-populist Freedom Party of Austria (at that time,
                    a fresh member of the government coalition) and by some German and Austrian
                    expellee organisations. Yet after Czech Prime Minister Miloš Zeman, in an
                    interview with the Austrian weekly <hi rend="italic">Profil</hi> in January
                    2002, described the German population of Czechoslovakia as the fifth column of
                    the Nazis, as “traitors who would otherwise have qualified for the death
                    penalty” and the Austrians as Hitler's first allies,<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn7" n="5">Quoted in Adam Drda, “Strategie provokatéra,” <hi
                            rend="italic">BBC Česká redakce</hi>, January 25, 2002,
                        https://www.bbc.co.uk/czech/koment/020125.shtml.</note> leading Austrian and
                    German politicians joined the protest. At the end of January, the Austrian
                    parliament passed a resolution by the votes of the coalition People's Party and
                    the Freedom Party calling on the Austrian government to have the decrees
                        repealed.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn8" n="6">Adéla Gjuričová, “Obhajoba
                        národních zájmů v čase východního rozšíření EU: 2002 – ‘nacionální epizoda’
                        ODS?,” in <hi rend="italic">Kapitoly z dějin české demokracie po roce
                            1989</hi>, eds. Adéla Gjuričová and Michal Kopeček (Praha and
                        Litomyšl: Paseka, 2007), 116–31.</note></p>
                <p>In mid-February, when questioned about the Beneš decrees, Hungarian Prime
                    Minister Viktor Orbán stated in the European Parliament that he found it "very
                    difficult to imagine a country becoming a member of the European Union, while
                    retaining in its legislation norms that are in stark contradiction with the
                    legal principles of the Union."<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn9" n="7">Ibidem,
                        116.</note> Slovakia, the Czech Republic and then Poland cancelled their
                    participation at the Visegrad summit in Budapest.</p>
                <p>On a visit to Israel in February, Prime Minister Zeman managed to compare not
                    only Jörg Haider, the leader of the Austrian Freedom Party, but also Yasser
                    Arafat, to Hitler, and recommended the expulsion of Palestinians from Israel
                    should they not accede to Israeli demands for a peace settlement. Czech
                    diplomacy desperately extinguished the resulting interstate disputes and
                    uncertainties about the Czech Republic's foreign policy positions. Meanwhile,
                    NOVA, private television, reported that there were regions where "people were
                    afraid of the revocation of the decrees."<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn10" n="8"
                        >Ibid., 117.</note> One of the few harmonious moments on the Czech political
                    scene was on 24 April 2002, when the Czech Chamber of Deputies, with votes by
                    all parties approved a resolution on the presidential decrees of 1940 to 1946,
                    and claimed the legal and property relations resulting from them to be
                    "unquestionable, inviolable and unchangeable".<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn11"
                        n="9">
                        <hi rend="italic">Společná česko-slovenská digitální parlamentní knihovna
                        </hi>[Common Digital Czecho-Slovak Parliamentary Library], Chamber of
                        Deputies 1998–2002, Resolution No. 2235, Usnesení Poslanecké sněmovny ze 49.
                        schůze 24. dubna 2002 k dekretům prezidenta republiky,
                        https://www.psp.cz/sqw/text/text2.sqw?idd=35824.</note> Several MPs from
                    various parties spent the day in the Chamber wearing T-shirts with the words <hi
                        rend="italic">To je naše vlast, to je naše chalupa</hi> (This is our
                    homeland, this is our cottage).</p>
                <p>What started as calls from former refugee organisations and local Bavarian
                    politics, developed into a political agenda watched by national media in
                    Germany, Austria, Hungary, Slovakia and the Czech Republic. Yet this escalation
                    of conflicts and a general radicalisation of all Central European politics was
                    only one of the effects. The other important consequence was expressed by an
                    article in <hi rend="italic">The Guardian</hi> titled “Sudeten ghosts
                    threaten[ed] Czechs' EU aims.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn12" n="10">“Sudeten
                        ghosts threaten Czechs' EU aims,” <hi rend="italic">The Guardian</hi>,
                        February 26, 2002,
                        <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2002/feb/26/johnhooper">https://www.theguardian.com/world/2002/feb/26/johnhooper</ref>.</note> The novelty
                    was that the complex phenomenon of EU accession conditionality was transferred
                    to bilateral relations. Accession conditionality referred to specific financial,
                    legal, anti-discriminatory and other criteria set collectively by the EU that
                    membership seekers had to meet. Yet there were individual members who declared
                    not to agree with some of the potential members’ adoption in the Union, unless
                    they fulfilled a condition set by the member. For example, Austria demanded that
                    the Czech Republic should not be allowed membership, before it discontinued the
                    construction of another bloc of Temelín and unless it explicitly struck the
                    Beneš decrees from Czech law. Even Michael Leigh, the European Commission’s
                    chief negotiator with the Czechs, wrote in a cool-headed ex post report that the
                    Czech Republic had some really serious problems standing in the way of
                    accession, such as institutional reform or market distortions. “While Temelín
                    was not one of them, Austria was one.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn13" n="11"
                        >Michael Leigh, “The Czech Republic as an EU candidate: Strengths and
                        weaknesses,” in <hi rend="italic">The road to the European Union. Volume 1:
                            The Czech and Slovak Republics</hi>, eds. Jacques Rupnik and Jan
                        Zielonka (Manchester and New York: Manchester University Press, 2003),
                    87–97.</note></p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Well-reasoned Radicalism</head>
                <p>No matter how little connection the above topics, especially the Beneš decrees,
                    had with the accession criteria and how absent they were from the formal
                    membership negotiations, it was exactly these issues that were presented as
                    European Union accession requirements in the forthcoming election campaign. The
                    paradox of the pre-election combat was that while all potential parliamentary
                    parties supported EU entry, the campaign was more aggressive and dividing over
                    the issue than ever before. Yet in this respect, internal politics were to
                        blame.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn14" n="12">Cf. Pavel Šaradín et al., <hi
                            rend="italic">Volby 2002. Analýza programů a výsledků ve volbách do
                            Poslanecké sněmovny</hi> (Olomouc: Periplum, 2002), 15–20.</note> In the
                    previous term the country had been controlled by a hidden grand coalition of two
                    proclaimed archenemies. The Social Democrats (ČSSD) formed a minority
                    government, while the right-wing Civic Democrats (ODS) were bound by the
                    so-called <hi rend="italic">Opposition Agreement</hi> to support the government
                    in exchange for guaranteed positions in parliament and key public stakeholder
                    organizations. Later, in what they called <hi rend="italic">Patent of
                        Toleration</hi>, the two parties even stipulated legal and constitutional
                    steps that they would jointly adopt, including an amendment of the electoral law
                    that strengthened the winners in translating election outcomes into mandates and
                    made electoral contest much less accessible for coalitions.</p>
                <p>All this implied that the two allies needed to find differentiating positions in
                    the campaign, but so had their common opponents, the Coalition (a centre-right
                    alliance of former partners of the ODS, an alignment based on opposing the
                    opposition-agreement system) and the Communists. Radicalism of both the rhetoric
                    and the creative aspect of the campaign was the only possible outcome.</p>
                <p>The governmental Social Democrats showed a double-faced performance. On the one
                    hand, the party congress elected a new, more liberal chairman who would replace
                    the offensive, gender-blind and troublesome Miloš Zeman, and a party expert team
                    conceived the <hi rend="italic"> ČSSD Euromanifesto</hi>, a document which
                    seriously considered the benefits and costs of EU membership. Yet on the other,
                    even the new progressive leader Vladimír Špidla, who had opposed the previous
                    deal with the right-wing Civic Democrats, was forced by PR advisors to kick off
                    the campaign by an “address to the nation” delivered from the peak of Říp hill
                    in Northern Bohemia, the centre of a Czech nationalist foundation myth. He
                    emphasised it was both a human and a national interest to preserve “the existing
                    post-war establishment and property setting.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn15"
                        n="13">Silvie Blechová, “Do boje za národní zájmy jdou i socialisté,” <hi
                            rend="italic">Lidové noviny</hi>, April 8, 2002, 1.</note> This
                    undertone and the focus on celebrities starring in the social democratic
                        “megaparties”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn16" n="14">Institut politického
                        marketing, “Kampaň k volbám do poslanecké sněmovny,” in <hi rend="italic"
                            >Glossary</hi>,
                            <ref target="https://politickymarketing.com/glossary/kampan-volby-poslanecka-snemovna-2002">https://politickymarketing.com/glossary/kampan-volby-poslanecka-snemovna-2002</ref></note>
                    overshadowed all their social-policy proposals as well as substantial comments
                    on the Union administration based on findings and experience in the negotiation
                    process.</p>
                <p>The <hi rend="italic">ČSSD Euromanifesto</hi> combined integration optimism with
                    a pragmatic attitude required by the public. It advocated the social-policy
                    aspects of European integration, which “make it a dynamic and powerful project
                    outmatching a mere free-trade zone.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn17" n="15"
                        >ÚSD, Contemporary Documentation collection (hereafter SD), fond Volby do
                        Parlamentu ČR 2002 [Elections to Parliament of the Czech Republic, 2002], PV
                        02/8, carton 2, folder 9, Euromanifest ČSSD, 4.</note> It called the entry
                    “an unrepeatable opportunity” which would extend to Czech nationals the same
                    rights as those of EU citizens and “help the country solve problems beyond its
                    power or capability.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn18" n="16">Ibid., 7.</note>
                    It also analysed the costs – the fees, limitation of sovereignty in some areas,
                    increased competition from stronger economies, even expected rising prices of
                    some products,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn19" n="17">Ibid., 10–12.</note> but
                    concluded that the benefits outweighed the costs. Being this reasonable and
                    substantive, the document remained unnoticed in the campaign itself and did not
                    leave any deeper mark in the political memory or the history of political
                    marketing.</p>
                <p>In both the above aspects, i.e., the rationality and visibility of the argument,
                    the opposite was true for the campaign of the opposition-agreement partner, and
                    the main contestant of the Social Democrats, the ODS. The Civic Democrats
                    countered with a kick-off rally in Liberec, once the Sudeten German capital, now
                    a regional centre bustling with the fear of a German comeback. In a campaign
                    opening address, party leader Václav Klaus depicted the ODS as the only party
                    for which “the defence of national interests is not an issue that was
                    purposefully discovered before the elections.” He made it clear they were opting
                    for a dramatic and warning tone: “We are facing pressure to change the post-war
                    establishment in Europe both symbolically and in property and legal terms, at
                    the expense of our country,” he stated, urging voters to keep a close eye on
                    “who is giving in to pressure from outside.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn20"
                        n="18">Jindřich Šídlo and David Steiner, “Začíná ‘národní’ týden české
                        politiky,” <hi rend="italic">Mladá fronta Dnes</hi>, April 6, 2002,
                        2.</note>
                </p>
                <p>The party had taken advantage of the time in opposition and the internal
                    ideological disputes. Now it came up with a clear programme and the most
                    professional campaign of all. The visuals and events revolved around a short
                    text consisting of ten chapters entitled <hi rend="italic">The Electoral
                        Decalogue</hi>. It suggested there were ten important topics in Czech
                    politics, in which the ODS “opted for” (in Czech the same word as “vote”) the
                    only correct choice, from “low taxes”, through “safety for the elderly” to
                    “fresh air into bureaucracy”.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn21" n="19">ÚSD, coll.
                        SD, f. Volby do Parlamentu ČR 2002, PV 02/8, carton 3, folder 17, Vstříc
                        novému osudu. Volební desatero ODS 2002.</note> Its structure and the
                    formulation of slogans were used throughout the campaign, which fully focused on
                    Václav Klaus and the concept of national interests, the party’s political
                    invention from many years ago, was adopted and responded to by all other
                    parties.</p>
                <p>Although the Civic Democrats had an influential Eurosceptic wing,<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn22" n="20">They composed the famous <hi
                            rend="italic">Manifesto of Czech Eurorealism</hi> in 1999–2000, in which
                        they combined the Czech prejudice against the EU with anti-German
                        sentiments. It depicted the Czech political thought as inherently close to
                        the Anglo-Saxon tradition and distant from provincial Central European
                        neighbours as well as from the prevailing West European left-wing, led by
                        the Germans. See Jan Zahradil, Petr Adrián, Miloslav Bednář and Petr
                        Plecitý, <hi rend="italic">10 let Manifestu českého eurorealismu </hi>[10
                        Years after the Manifest of Czech Eurorealism] (Brusel: Skupina Evropských
                        konzervativců a reformistů, 2011).</note> they tried to keep them in the
                    background and stick to the <hi rend="italic">Decalogue</hi>. Three of the ten
                    commandments dealt with foreign policy and relations, yet in practice brought
                    the European Union forward as the main motive. In the first of the ten chapters,
                    “ODS votes for the EU”, it called for a fast entry into the Union, yet endorsed
                    a pragmatic perspective, mentioning for example, how much the country had so far
                    invested into accession. Meanwhile, it dropped little notions of the European
                    “super-state” and “ruthless conflict of interest”.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn23" n="21">ÚSD, coll. SD, Vstříc novému osudu, 4.</note> Images
                    of the European Union also remained the central theme in the chapter “ODS votes
                    for national interests,” in which the programme called for “not letting
                    ourselves be shouted down”, refuse to “give in to pressure” and “eat humble
                    pie”. The Czechs should achieve EU entry “with a straight back, not on their
                        knees”.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn24" n="22">Ibid., 14, 15.</note>
                    Following up on the EU note, the statement of self-confidence was extended as
                    far as the topic of the Beneš decrees and the expulsion of Germans: “The past
                    must not be changed. A public defence of legitimate Czech interests is not
                        nationalism.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn25" n="23">Ibid., 15.</note> In a
                    smartly composed mix of economic and political pragmatism on the one hand, and
                    Eurosceptic stereotypes and aggressive rhetoric on the other, the national
                    interests included “our history, way of life, customs, traditions, culture,
                    economic and political interests, property and legal stability and security,
                    everything that our children will inherit from us.”<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn26" n="24">Ibid., 14.</note>
                </p>
                <p>In the Civic Democrats campaign, the national interests completely overshadowed
                    other agendas, and as a result, some of the party's traditional themes were not
                    addressed at all. The authors of the campaign were right in that this
                    structuring allowed the concentration on – previously problematic leader –
                    Václav Klaus and his simplistic identification of who/what is right and who/what
                    is evil. As one of the leaflets inserted in the <hi rend="italic">Právo</hi>
                    daily shortly before the elections, “ODS stands here as the only bastion of
                    defence, as a line of resistance against the future made by Špidla [the chairman
                    of the Social Democrats], made by Grebeníček [the Communist leader]. It is the
                    only hope for those who don't want to live the next generation in some kind of
                    Špidloland, full of old socialist junk that is already being thrown away in the
                    rest of developed Europe where it belongs: in the garbage dump."<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn27" n="25">
                        <hi rend="italic">Právo</hi>, June 13, 2002.</note></p>
                <p>And yet, rather than bringing electoral gains, this strategy changed the general
                    dynamics of the campaign. The liberal Coalition took a radical stance in favour
                    of EU entry. In a booklet published by one of the members of the alliance, the
                    Freedom Union, and titled <hi rend="italic">With the Union to the Union</hi>,
                    the party depicted integration into the EU as a guarantee of modernization and
                    labelled its critics “Euronegativists and Euroignorants, two mutually feeding
                    sterile attitudes.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn28" n="26">ÚSD, coll. SD, f.
                        Volby do Parlamentu ČR 2002, PV 02/8, carton 5, folder 23, S Unií do Unie.
                        Evropská vize Unie svobody, 10, 19, 20.</note> The leaflet titled <hi
                        rend="italic">We live in Europe</hi> ended with a cartoon in which two men
                    wearing office suits and using a pickaxe and a jackhammer were knocking down a
                    wall blocking passage to an EU signboard. The slogan “ODS protects national
                    interests” was written on the broken wall.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn29"
                        n="27">Ibid., Žijeme v Evropě.</note>
                </p>
                <p>Generally, it is difficult for such an intellectual style to become visible in a
                    campaign, and all in all, the alliance failed to highlight EU issues completely.
                    Most representatives, frustrated by the previous years of the opposition
                    agreement, which deprived them of any influence in key institutions, focused on
                    internal political and legal issues.</p>
                <p>The last important contestant, the Communist Party of Bohemia and Moravia (KSČM),
                    represented an artful position of a different kind. It interpreted the current
                    EU as a capitalist, and in that respect an undesirable project, yet it did not
                    reject integration completely, saying it would wait for the negotiations to be
                    completed, and then make a decision and recommendation for a referendum. In <hi
                        rend="italic">Who We Are and What We Want</hi>, a booklet structured along
                    smartly formulated FAQs, it suppressed the questions of EU entry, and instead
                    referred to the ideals of full employment, fairer taxation and housing for
                    everybody. It suggested that the Communists knew the solutions to the most
                    pressing issues of ordinary people, while not trusting the social dimension of
                    EU policies: “KSČM is aware that integration processes can bring greater
                    economic efficiency and cultural enrichment. However, we do not overlook (…) the
                    EU's efforts to reduce social security, to increase bureaucracy and to increase
                    the profits of large multinational corporations at the expense of broad sections
                    of the population.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn30" n="28">ÚSD, coll. SD, f.
                        Volby do Parlamentu ČR 2002, PV 02/8, carton 6, folder 42, Kdo jsme a co
                        chceme. Odpovědi na nejčastěji kladené otázky, 59.</note> This means that
                    the Communist Party joined some of the notorious Eurosceptic themes usually
                    associated with the right wing – such as bureaucracy or the weakening of
                    national economic policies and a detrimental effect on local agriculture. Yet
                    their massive campaign around the slogan “With the people for the people”
                    focused on the traditional electorate, working-class people in small towns and
                    villages, which produced notions of traditional Czech industries and
                    agriculture, the need for “the development of the countryside” and also populist
                    anti-German rhetoric, rather than any mention of the EU.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn31" n="29">Ibid., carton 6, folder 50, S lidmi pro
                    lidi.</note></p>
                <p>In summary, the 2002 campaign saw the question of “national interests” and of
                    their position vis-à-vis the European integration prevail over any technical
                    debate on the gains and losses resulting from Czech membership. This was true
                    not only among party contestants but also for mainstream media and public
                    discourse in general. Shortly before the election, even the liberal daily <hi
                        rend="italic">Lidové noviny </hi>published an interview with the French
                    presidential candidate Jean-Marie Le Pen, titled “Czechs, EU is a trap!”<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn32" n="30">Quoted in Jakub Patočka, “Nové české
                        zájmy,” <hi rend="italic">Neviditelný pes</hi>, May 14, 2002,
                        https://neviditelnypes.cz/.</note> When the popular public-service radio
                    station <hi rend="italic">ČRo Radiožurnál </hi>invited two experts to discuss
                    nationalism and national interests, virtually all listeners, who were able to
                    ask questions via telephone in the live programme, did one thing in common. They
                    criticised the liberal critic of the national-interest campaign and sided with
                    the ethnocentric, Eurosceptic and anti-German statements by the other speaker, a
                    notorious radical commentator and advisor to the Chairman of the Chamber of
                    Deputies Václav Klaus.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn33" n="31">“Radiofórum:
                        Nacionalismus a národní zájmy (Jiří Pehe, Ladislav Jakl),” <hi rend="italic"
                            >ČRo Radiožurnál</hi>, May 15, 2002,
                        <ref target="https://radiozurnal.rozhlas.cz/zvukovy-archiv-poradu-radioforum-6327905">https://radiozurnal.rozhlas.cz/zvukovy-archiv-poradu-radioforum-6327905</ref>.</note>
                </p>
                <p>And yet, the election results showed the effects of the campaign as ambivalent.
                    All parliamentary parties lost mandates, except for the Communists who reached
                    their post-1989 maximum of 18.5 percent of the ballot. Although six months
                    before the election, the polls suggested a victory by the Civic Democrats, the
                    aggressive campaign led to their defeat (24.5 percent) by the Social Democrats
                    (30.2 percent). Political participation seemed to be the chief loser though,
                    with a turnout of 58 percent being the lowest ever at the time and representing
                    a dramatic fall in comparison with the previous two national elections (76.4
                    percent in 1996 and 74 percent in 1998).</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Europe Both Present and Absent</head>
                <p>Central Europe experienced a far-reaching radicalization of politics during this
                    period, including addressing a number of historical and ethnonational issues, a
                    process that George Mink described as “a revival of the symbolic past in the
                    context of EU enlargement”.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn34" n="32">Georges
                        Mink, “Revival of the symbolic past in the context of EU enlargement,” in
                            <hi rend="italic">Patters of Europeanisation in Central and Eastern
                            Europe</hi>, eds. Zdenka Mansfeldová, Vera Sparschuh and Agnieszka
                        Wenninger (Hamburg: Reinhold Krämer Verlag, 2005), 133–43.</note> The
                    material presented from the 2002 election campaign documented two contradictory
                    inclinations: The Czech political parties rejected the Austrian Europeanization
                    of Temelín, while at the same time Europeanizing any piece of the national
                    agenda. In other words, while EU accession was omnipresent, the campaign reduced
                    it to two topics that everybody in the country agreed on, namely Temelín and the
                    Beneš decrees, which were unrelated to actual entry into the Union. Yet it
                    completely omitted three issues that were essential for negotiation with the EU,
                    while consensus over them was missing and really difficult to reach.</p>
                <p>The free movement of workers, one of the fundamental principles of the EU, was
                    the first of the crucial issues fiercely negotiated before the Czech entry. The
                    reason was that Austria, Germany and Spain feared an inflow of cheap labourers
                    from East-Central Europe as a result of which the talks included real pressure
                    to keep West European labour markets temporarily closed for new members. The
                    compromise reached by the negotiators consisted of a transitory period on free
                    movement, while the Czechs succeeded in banning EU citizens from buying real
                    estate in the country during that time. Second, the state of competition as well
                    as institutional reform was the object of EU criticism. Insufficient protection
                    of fair competition was a leftover of the economic and institutional
                    transformation as carried out by the ODS in the 1990s, when its negative effects
                    were cushioned through state intervention and subsidised credit. And third,
                    there was a discriminatory financial proposal from the EU that in the first
                    year, new members would only receive a 25-percent fraction of the direct
                    subsidies they were entitled to, with the share slowly increasing until 2013.
                    The final deal saw the inequality offset by more funds being made available
                    through projects financed from structural funds.</p>
                <p>Bringing the whole episode within the context of Europeanization studies, it
                    naturally draws our attention to the period preceding actual accession, a phase
                    we earlier characterized as almost completely disregarded by literature on
                    Europeanization. Robert Ladrech’s <hi rend="italic">Europeanization and National
                        Politics </hi>is an exception in this respect. His was a solitary voice
                    trying to re-direct the discussion and included membership seekers as well.
                    Ladrech noted that “much of the domestic change occurred before actual
                    membership, so we are, strictly speaking, discussing Europeanization during the
                    pre-accession process.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn35" n="33">Robert Ladrech,
                            <hi rend="italic">Europeanization and National Politics</hi> (London:
                        Palgrave Macmillan, 2010), 38.</note> The cautious formulation of the
                    argument proves how unconventional such a perspective is within the approach.
                    Ladrech further argued that in the accession process, candidate states remained
                    to be, for the most part, only “downloaders” of themes, concepts or policies,
                    and were in no position of influence or power to “upload their preferences in a
                    meaningful way.” At the same time, widespread conditionality was exerted on
                    them: having applied for membership, they had to face the Union re-focusing on
                    the evaluation of the efforts made by the candidate’s government to meet the
                    conditions and rules of the acquis. Adoption in the EU was meant to “reflect a
                    sort of ‘official’ acknowledgement of success in transformation.”<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn36" n="34">Ibid., 38, 39.</note></p>
                <p>These views are relevant for a reflection on the agenda-setting within the 2002
                    election campaign. The documented shift in Czech public debate on the EU,
                    towards Temelín and the Beneš decrees, presumed its adaptation to a specific
                    bilateral conditionality set by the neighbouring countries, Austria and Germany
                    and dealing with equally specific, EU-unrelated issues.</p>
                <p>The fact that no party focused on the actual pressing issues of accession, namely
                    the prospect of not gaining free movement of workers or full EU subsidies,
                    manifests a different important trend in the debate as well as in changing the
                    institutional setting. There are occasional notions of “de-parliamentarization”
                    as resulting from Europeanization, in the sense of an erosion of parliamentary
                    control over executive office-holders and a broader impact on the constitutional
                    balance between executive and legislature.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn37"
                        n="35">John O’Brennan and Tapio Raunio, “Introduction. Deparliamentarization
                        and European integration,” in <hi rend="italic">National Parliaments within
                            the Enlarged European Union: From ‘Victims’ of Integration to
                            Competitive Actors?</hi> eds. John O’Brennan and Tapio Raunio
                        (London and New York: Routledge, 2007), 1–26. Cf. Ladrech, <hi rend="italic"
                            >Europeanization and National Politics</hi>, 71–74.</note> Yet the trend
                    was even more significant among candidates for membership. It was the national
                    governments that became the prime interlocutors between domestic interests and
                    policy-making on the one hand and the EU on the other. The candidate status
                    strengthened narrow government teams even further, making them responsible for
                    downloading the acquis communautaire. The states needed legislative ratification
                    of imported legislation by parliaments, but the details were “fast-tracked” to
                    the institutional benefit of the executive. Furthermore, most parliaments
                    themselves agreed to remove EU-related issues from normal partisan debate and
                    competition. They understood themselves to be weak because they could not
                    guarantee absolute party discipline in these issues of prime importance. Since
                    any domestic innovation on the adoption and implementation was very limited,
                    parliaments – as dominantly national institutions – lost a substantial degree of
                        sovereignty.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn38" n="36">Cf. Ladrech, <hi
                            rend="italic">Europeanization and National Politics</hi>, 87–89.</note>
                    Thus in a relatively short amount of time, Europeanization had a great impact on
                    the institutionalization of the entire political system.</p>
                <p>This proved perfectly true in the studied campaign: the parties were fighting
                    about what the previous government did and what would the following government
                    have to do, but nobody ever mentioned the role of the parliament nor did they
                    require a translation of party positions into the negotiations with the EU. John
                    O’Brennan and Tapio Raunio studied the question of institutional shifts in
                    detail in their book <hi rend="italic">National Parliaments within the Enlarged
                        European Union</hi>. They found that bringing EU policy issues into
                    parliamentary debate or electoral campaign is of no use, once we mean party
                    tactic or re-election. They also described parliaments’ strategies of turning
                    “from ‘victims’ of integration to competitive actors” <hi rend="italic"> –</hi>
                    one of them being the Europeanization of election campaigns, involving both
                    avoiding real EU politics and replacing it with subliminal Euroscepticism.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn39" n="37">John O’Brennan and Tapio Raunio,
                        “Conclusion: National parliaments gradually learning to play the European
                        game?” in <hi rend="italic">National Parliaments within the Enlarged
                            European Union</hi>, 272–86.</note></p>
                <p>And so, as the <hi rend="italic">Financial Times</hi> election day article<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn40" n="38">Quoted in “Média: volby v ČR jsou o
                        vstupu do Unie,” <hi rend="italic">Právo</hi>, June 15, 2002, 8.</note>
                    stated the Czechs had been offered two different visions of the EU, it was right
                    to stick to metaphors, rather than mentioning elaborated political positions.
                    According to the news article, the Social Democrats and the Coalition presented
                    it as the holy grail that the country had been searching for since the fall of
                    Communism, while the ODS described it as a bitter pill that has to be
                    swallowed.</p>
                <p>Ostensibly, the content of national politics became Europeanized, while the
                    positions towards the EU grew more national in the sense that actors were
                    reacting to one another, rather than relating to actual trends in the EU. The
                    dramatic, polarized and aggressive campaign of 2002 combined a wild
                    Europeanization of domestic politics with an equally unacceptable
                    bilateralization of the European Union.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="bibliography">
                <head>Sources and Literature</head>
                <list type="unordered">
                    <head>Archive sources</head>
                    <item>ÚSD – Institute of Contemporary History of the Czech Academy of
                            Sciences:<list type="unordered">
                            <item>Collection Contemporary Documentation (SD), fond Volby do
                                Parlamentu ČR 2002 [Elections to Parliament of the Czech Republic,
                                2002].</item>
                        </list></item>
                </list>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Literature</head>
                    <bibl>Cabada, Ladislav, and Alenka Krašovec. <hi rend="italic">Europeanization of
                            National Political Parties.</hi> Dobrá Voda: Vydavatelství a
                        nakladatelství Aleš Čeněk, 2004.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Fiala, Petr, Vít Hloušek, Markéta Pitrová, Pavel Pšeja, and Petr Suchý.
                        “Evropeizace politických stran a zájmových skupin: základní problémy a směry
                        analýzy.” <hi rend="italic">Politologický časopis</hi> 13, No. 1 (2006):
                        3–26.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Gjuričová, Adéla. “Obhajoba národních zájmů v čase východního rozšíření
                        EU: 2002 – ‘nacionální epizoda’ ODS?.” In <hi rend="italic">Kapitoly
                            z dějin české demokracie po roce 1989</hi>. Edited by Adéla Gjuričová,
                        and Michal Kopeček, 116–31. Praha and Litomyšl: Paseka, 2007.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Institut politického marketing. “Kampaň k volbám do poslanecké sněmovny.”
                        In <hi rend="italic">Glossary</hi>. <ref
                            target="https://politickymarketing.com/glossary/kampan-volby-poslanecka-snemovna-2002"
                            >https://politickymarketing.com/glossary/kampan-volby-poslanecka-snemovna-2002</ref>.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Ladrech, Robert. <hi rend="italic">Europeanization and National
                            Politics</hi>. London: Palgrave Macmillan, 2010.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Ladrech, Robert. “Europeanization of Domestic Politics and Institutions:
                        The Case of France.” <hi rend="italic">Journal of Common Market Studies</hi>
                        32, No. 1 (1994): 69–88.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Leigh, Michael. “The Czech Republic as an EU candidate: Strengths and
                        weaknesses.” In <hi rend="italic">The road to the European Union. Volume 1:
                            The Czech and Slovak Republics</hi>. Edited by Jacques Rupnik and Jan
                        Zielonka, 87–97. Manchester and Nwe York: Manchester University Press, 2003.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Linek, Lukáš, and Štěpán Pecháček. “Vliv evropské integrace na politické
                        strany, stranický systém a volební chování v České republice.” In <hi
                            rend="italic">Proměny reprezentace zájmů po vstupu do Evropské
                        unie</hi>. Edited by Zdenka Mansfeldová and Aleš Kroupa. Praha: Sociologické
                        nakladatelství, 2008.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Mink, Georges. “Revival of the symbolic past in the context of EU
                        enlargement.” In <hi rend="italic">Patters of Europeanisation in Central
                            and Eastern Europe</hi>. Edited by Zdenka Mansfeldová, Vera Sparschuh
                        and Agnieszka Wenninger, 133–43. Hamburg: Reinhold Krämer Verlag,
                        2005.</bibl>
                    <bibl>O’Brennan, John, and Tapio Raunio. “Conclusion: National parliaments
                        gradually learning to play the European game?.” In <hi rend="italic"
                            >National Parliaments within the Enlarged European Union: From ‘Victims’
                            of Integration to Competitive Actors?</hi>. Edited by John O’Brennan and
                        Tapio Raunio, 272–86. London and New York: Routledge, 2007.</bibl>
                    <bibl>O’Brennan, John, and Tapio Raunio. “Introduction. Deparliamentarization and
                        European integration.” In <hi rend="italic">National Parliaments within the
                            Enlarged European Union: From ‘Victims’ of Integration to Competitive
                            Actors?</hi>. Edited by John O’Brennan and Tapio Raunio, 1–26. London and
                        New York: Routledge, 2007.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Šaradín, Pavel et al. <hi rend="italic">Volby 2002. Analýza programů a
                            výsledků ve volbách do Poslanecké sněmovny</hi>. Olomouc: Periplum,
                        2002.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Telička, Pavel, and Karel Barták. “The Accession of the Czech Republic to
                        the EU.” In <hi rend="italic">The Accession Story: The EU from Fifteen to
                            Twenty-Five Countries</hi>. Edited by George Vassiliou. Oxford and New
                        York: Oxford UP 2007.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Zahradil, Jan, Petr Adrián, Miloslav Bednář, and Petr Plecitý. <hi
                            rend="italic">10 let Manifestu českého eurorealismu </hi>[10 Years after
                        the Manifest of Czech Eurorealism.]. Brusel: Skupina Evropských
                        konzervativců a reformistů, 2011.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Newspaper sources</head>
                    <bibl>Blechová, Silvie. “Do boje za národní zájmy jdou i socialisté.“ <hi
                            rend="italic">Lidové noviny</hi>, April 8, 2002, 1.</bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="italic">ČRo Radiožurnál.</hi> “Radiofórum: Nacionalismus a
                        národní zájmy (Jiří Pehe, Ladislav Jakl).” Accessed May 15, 2002. <ref
                            target="https://radiozurnal.rozhlas.cz/zvukovy-archiv-poradu-radioforum-6327905"
                            >https://radiozurnal.rozhlas.cz/zvukovy-archiv-poradu-radioforum-6327905</ref>.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Drda, Adam. „Strategie provokatéra.“ <hi rend="italic">BBC Česká
                            redakce</hi>. Accessed January 25, 2002, <ref
                            target="https://www.bbc.co.uk/czech/koment/020125.shtml"
                            >https://www.bbc.co.uk/czech/koment/020125.shtml</ref>.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Patočka, Jakub. “Nové české zájmy.” <hi rend="italic">Neviditelný
                        pes</hi>. Accessed May 14, 2002. <ref target="https://neviditelnypes.cz/"
                            >https://neviditelnypes.cz/</ref>.</bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="italic">Právo.</hi> “Média: volby v ČR jsou o vstupu do Unie,”
                        June 15, 2002, 8.</bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="italic">Právo</hi>. June 13, 2002.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Šídlo, Jindřich, and David Steiner. “Začíná ‘národní’ týden české
                        politiky.” <hi rend="italic">Mladá fronta Dnes</hi>, April 6, 2002,
                        2.</bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="italic">The Guardian.</hi> “Sudeten ghosts threaten Czechs' EU
                        aims,“ February 26, 2002.
                        <ref target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2002/feb/26/johnhooper">https://www.theguardian.com/world/2002/feb/26/johnhooper</ref>.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Other sources</head>
                    <bibl><hi rend="italic">Společná česko-slovenská digitální parlamentní knihovna
                        </hi>[Common Digital Czecho-Slovak Parliamentary Library], Chamber of
                        Deputies 1998–2002, Resolution No. 2235, Usnesení Poslanecké sněmovny ze 49.
                        schůze 24. dubna 2002 k dekretům prezidenta republiky.
                        <ref target="https://www.psp.cz/sqw/text/text2.sqw?idd=35824">https://www.psp.cz/sqw/text/text2.sqw?idd=35824</ref>.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
            <div type="summary">
                <docAuthor>Adéla Gjuričová</docAuthor>
                <head>KAMPANJA ZA EVROPO. ČEŠKE PARLAMENTARNE VOLITVE 2002</head>
                <head>POVZETEK</head>
                <p>Češka vlada se je več kot tri leta pogajala o pristopu države k Evropski uniji,
                    ko sta EU in vstop Češke postala središče volilne razprave pred parlamentarnimi
                    volitvami junija 2002. Čeprav je bilo pri pogajanjih več resnih ovir (namen EU,
                    da za nove članice začasno omeji prosto gibanje delavcev in omeji subvencije EU,
                    ki so jim na voljo), se je evropsko združevanje nepričakovano znašlo v središču
                    pozornosti kampanje s temami, ki so bile le bežno povezane s članstvom v EU.</p>
                <p>Srednja Evropa je v tem obdobju doživljala obsežno radikalizacijo politike, ki je
                    vključevala tudi številna zgodovinska in etnonacionalna vprašanja. Razprava o
                    dveh od teh vprašanj je potekala tudi v Evropski uniji, vključno z avstrijskim
                    protestom proti dokončanju jedrske elektrarne Temelin na južnem Češkem in tako
                    imenovanimi Beneševimi dekreti, zakonodajo, izdano ob koncu druge svetovne
                    vojne, ki je omogočila izgon nemško in madžarsko govorečih državljanov iz
                    države. Odprava teh dekretov se je začela povezovati s pristopom Češke republike
                    k EU.</p>
                <p>Paradoksalno je bilo, da je bila kampanja glede tega vprašanja bolj agresivna in
                    razdiralna kot kdaj koli prej, čeprav so vse stranke podpirale vstop v EU. Kriva
                    je bila notranja politika. V predhodnem mandatu je državo obvladovala prikrita
                    velika koalicija dveh zapriseženih sovražnikov – socialnih demokratov in
                    desničarskih državljanskih demokratov – ki sta zdaj morala najti stališča, v
                    katerih sta se razhajala. V kampanji je vprašanje “nacionalnih interesov” in
                    njihovega položaja v odnosu do evropskega združevanja prevladalo nad kakršno
                    koli strokovno razpravo o dobrih in slabih straneh članstva. Nazadnje so volilni
                    rezultati pokazali, da so bili učinki kampanje ambivalentni. Vse parlamentarne
                    stranke so izgubile mandate razen komunistov, ki so dosegli največji uspeh po
                    letu 1989. Največjo škodo pa je utrpelo politično udejstvovanje, saj je bila
                    58-odstotna volilna udeležba najnižja do tedaj.</p>
                <p>Predstavljeno gradivo iz volilne kampanje leta 2002 je izkazovalo dve
                    nasprotujoči si težnji: češke politične stranke so zavračale avstrijsko
                    evropeizacijo jedrske elektrarne Temelin, hkrati pa so evropeizirale vse dele
                    nacionalne agende. Povedano drugače, čeprav je bil pristop k EU vseprisoten, ga
                    je kampanja skrčila na dve temi, ki nista bili povezani z dejanskim vstopom v
                    Unijo, medtem ko je popolnoma izpustila vprašanja, ki so bila bistvena za
                    pogajanja z EU.</p>
                <p>Na koncu je prispevek ugotovitve povezal s tistim delom študij evropeizacije, ki
                    so upoštevale predpristopno obdobje. Po trditvah Roberta Ladrecha so držav
                    kandidatke ostale “odjemalke” tem, medtem ko se je nad njimi vršilo vsesplošno
                    pogojevanje. Ta stališča se zdijo koristna za razmislek o oblikovanju agende v
                    okviru volilne kampanje leta 2002. “Deparlamentarizacija” kot posledica
                    evropeizacije, kot jo na primer razumeta John O’Brennan in Tapio Raunio, se
                    nanaša na okrnitev parlamentarnega nadzora nad nosilci izvršilnih funkcij. V
                    preučevani kampanji se je to izkazalo za povsem resnično: stranke so se
                    prepirale o tem, kaj je storila prejšnja vlada in kaj bo morala storiti
                    naslednja, nihče pa ni omenjal vloge parlamenta ali zahteval prenosa
                    strankarskih stališč v pogajanja z EU.</p>
                <p>Na videz se je vsebina nacionalnih politik evropeizirala, stališča do EU pa so
                    postala bolj nacionalna v smislu, da so se akterji odzivali drug na drugega, ne
                    pa na dejanske trende v EU. Dramatična, polarizirana in agresivna kampanja leta
                    2002 je združevala divjo evropeizacijo domače politike z enako nesprejemljivo
                    bilateralizacijo Evropske unije.</p>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
