<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Central European border settlements and interwar Ireland: a
                    transnational study of the North-Eastern Boundary Bureau and the Boundary
                    Commission</title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename>Lili</forename>
                        <surname>Zách</surname>
                    </name>
                    <roleName>Full Professor</roleName>
                    <roleName>PhD</roleName>
                    <affiliation>National University of Ireland</affiliation>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Galway University Road</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>Galway, Ireland</addrLine>
                    </address>
                    <email>l.zach1@nuigalway.ie</email>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>2017-02-21</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>
                    <orgName xml:lang="sl">Inštitut za novejšo zgodovino</orgName>
                    <orgName xml:lang="en">Institute of Contemporary History</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Kongresni trg 1</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>SI-1000 Ljubljana</addrLine>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>http://ojs.inz.si/pnz/article/view/228</pubPlace>
                <date>2016</date>
                <availability status="free">
                    <licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title xml:lang="sl">Prispevki za novejšo zgodovino</title>
                <title xml:lang="en">Contributions to Contemporary History</title>
                <biblScope unit="volume">57</biblScope>
                <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
                <idno type="ISSN">2463-7807</idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source, born digital.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc xml:lang="en">
                <p>Contributions to Contemporary History is one of the central Slovenian scientific
                    historiographic journals, dedicated to publishing articles from the field of
                    contemporary history (the 19th and 20th century).</p>
                <p>The journal is published three times per year in Slovenian and in the following
                    foreign languages: English, German, Serbian, Croatian, Bosnian, Italian, Slovak
                    and Czech. The articles are all published with abstracts in English and
                    Slovenian as well as summaries in English.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <projectDesc xml:lang="sl">
                <p>Prispevki za novejšo zgodovino je ena osrednjih slovenskih znanstvenih
                    zgodovinopisnih revij, ki objavlja teme s področja novejše zgodovine (19. in 20.
                    stoletje).</p>
                <p>Revija izide trikrat letno v slovenskem jeziku in v naslednjih tujih jezikih:
                    angleščina, nemščina, srbščina, hrvaščina, bosanščina, italijanščina, slovaščina
                    in češčina. Članki izhajajo z izvlečki v angleščini in slovenščini ter povzetki
                    v angleščini.</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="sl"/>
                <language ident="en"/>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords xml:lang="en">
                    <term>Irish border</term>
                    <term>plebiscites</term>
                    <term>transnational history</term>
                    <term>Central Europe</term>
                    <term>Partition</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords xml:lang="sl">
                    <term>irska meja</term>
                    <term>plebisciti</term>
                    <term>transnacionalna zgodovina</term>
                    <term>Srednja Evropa</term>
                    <term>delitev</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change>
                    <date>2017-09-18</date>
                    <name>Neja Blaj Hribar</name>
                    <desc>Pretvorba iz DOCX v TEI, dodatno kodiranje</desc>
                </change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <docAuthor>Lili Zách<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn1" n="*"> PhD, National University of Ireland,
                Galway University Road, Galway, Ireland; <ref target="l.zach1@nuigalway.ie ">l.zach1@nuigalway.ie</ref></note></docAuthor>
            <docImprint>
                <idno type="cobissType">Cobiss type: 1.01</idno>
                <idno type="UDC">UDC: </idno>
            </docImprint>
            <div type="abstract" xml:lang="sl">
                <head>IZVLEČEK</head>
                <head>DOGOVORI O SREDNJEEVROPSKIH MEJAH IN IRSKA V OBDOBJU MED VOJNAMA:
                    TRANSNACIONALNA ŠTUDIJA URADA ZA SEVEROVZHODNO MEJO IN MEJNE KOMISIJE</head>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Po koncu prve svetovne vojne so irski nacionalistični krogi zaradi
                    možne delitve Irske zavzeto spremljali rojstvo novih malih neodvisnih držav v
                    vzhodni Srednji Evropi. Iz časopisnih uvodnikov in člankov ter diplomatskih
                    poročil je razvidno, da se je povojna Irska odkrito zanimala za urejanje meja v
                    celinski Evropi, saj je bil razpad Avstro-Ogrske podobno sporen. Namen tega
                    prispevka je raziskati, kako so takratni irski poročevalci dojemali vprašanje
                    urejanja mej v Srednji Evropi, s čimer omogoča vpogled v preoblikovanje
                    političnega prostora na Irskem in v Srednji Evropi. Po kratki predstavitvi
                    ozadja vprašanja irskih meja se prispevek dotakne najpomembnejših točk v
                    zgodovinopisju, povezanih z urejanjem meja v obdobju po prvi svetovni vojni.
                    Podrobno obravnava tudi zgodovino delitve Irske, pri čemer se osredotoča
                    predvsem na Urad za severovzhodno mejo (North-Eastern Boundary Bureau) in Mejno
                    komisijo (Boundary Commission) ter na pomen srednjeevropskih precedensov za
                    njuno delo. Prispevek omogoča tudi vpogled v irsko zanimanje za manjšinsko
                    problematiko v evropskih obmejnih regijah po letu 1925, da bi prikazal navzven
                    usmerjen odnos irskih nacionalistov, celo v zvezi z mejami in
                    manjšinami.</hi></p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Ključne besede: irska meja, plebisciti, transnacionalna zgodovina,
                    Srednja Evropa, delitev</hi></p>
            </div>
            <div type="abstract">
                <head>ABSTRACT</head>
                <p><hi rend="italic">In the aftermath of the Great War, the birth of new independent
                    small states in East-Central Europe was closely followed in Irish nationalist
                    circles due to the possibility of Partition in Ireland. Newspaper editorials,
                    journal articles and diplomatic accounts illustrate that post-war Ireland had an
                    open attitude toward the settlement of borders on the Continent as the
                    dissolution of the Austro-Hungarian Empire was similarly controversial. This
                    paper aims to investigate how contemporary Irish commentators perceived the
                    question of boundary settlements in Central Europe in order to provide an
                    insight into the transformation of political space in both Ireland and Central
                    Europe. After providing a brief background to the Irish boundary question, this
                    paper touches upon the most important points in historiography with regard to
                    border settlements in the post-World War I era.. It also discusses Irish
                    Partition history in detail, concentrating on the North-Eastern Boundary Bureau
                    (NEBB) and the Boundary Commission, and the importance of Central European
                    precedents in their work. Moreover, this paper also proposes to provide an
                    insight into the Irish interest in the minority problem in European borderland
                    regions after 1925 in order to illustrate the outward-looking attitude to Irish
                    nationalists, even in relation to borders and minorities.</hi></p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Keywords: Irish border, plebiscites, transnational history, Central
                    Europe, Partition</hi></p></div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div><head>Introduction</head>
            <p>The period from 1919 to 1922 saw the transformation of political order in Ireland,
                while the right to self-determination and independence remained in the centre of
                Irish political rhetoric. With the outbreak of the Irish War of Independence and the
                opening of the Fist Dáil Éireann in January 1919, the relationship between Ireland
                and Britain deteriorated. Political changes in Ireland were accompanied by personnel
                changes in the informal Irish diplomatic service; “roaming” Sinn Féin envoys were
                entrusted with disseminating propaganda on the Continent and gaining recognition for
                the independent Irish republic. After the signing of the Anglo-Irish Treaty in
                December 1921, due to opposition to the oath of allegiance required of Dáil members
                and provisions for ongoing links with Britain, a spilt occurred in the Irish
                republican movement. The Irish Free State, separate from Northern Ireland
                (established by the Government of Ireland Act, 1920), was a dominion within the
                British Empire, with legislative independence. The Treaty only provided a partial
                achievement and a full Republic was only declared decades later, gaining full formal
                sovereignty for twenty-six counties in 1949.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn2" n="1"> Robert Lynch, <hi rend="italic">Revolutionary
                            Ireland, 1912–25</hi> (London: Bloomsbury Academic, 2015), 1. Stephen
                        Howe, <hi rend="italic">Ireland and Empire: Colonial Legacies in Irish
                            History and Culture</hi> (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 2000),
                        41.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The creation of a Boundary Commission was decided in order to amend the border
                between the Free State and Northern Ireland, as part of Article 12 in the Treaty:
                the final border was to be determined “in accordance with the wishes of the
                inhabitants, so far as may be compatible with economic and geographic conditions
                    […].”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn3" n="2"> NAI DE
                        2/304/1, <hi rend="italic">Documents on Irish Foreign Policy</hi>
                        [henceforth:<hi rend="italic"> DIFP</hi>]<hi rend="italic"> vol. ii</hi>.
                        No. 214, Final text of the Articles of Agreement for a Treaty between Great
                        Britain and Ireland as signed, London, December 6, 1921.</note> As Paul
                Murray highlighted, the year the Government of Ireland Act partitioned Ireland,
                territories in other parts of Europe were also being partitioned. They were assigned
                to the states that laid claim to them as a result of the post-war treaties that
                radically redrew of the map of Europe.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn4" n="3"> Paul Murray, <hi rend="italic">The Irish Boundary
                            Commission and its Origins 1886–1925</hi> (Dublin: UCD Press, 2011),
                        146.</note> Therefore, this controversy in relation to boundaries
                prompted an open attitude toward similar precedents on the Continent as the
                dissolution of the Austro-Hungarian Empire also left border disputes.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn5" n="4"> The name of the state
                        had changed on three occasions; between 16 November 1918 and 21 March 1919
                        it was called ‘Hungarian People’s Republic’ under the leadership of Mihály
                        Károlyi; the ‘Hungarian Soviet Republic’ was in existence under Béla Kun
                        between 22 March and 2 August 1919; this was followed by the short-lived
                        ‘Hungarian People’s Republic’, August 1919-February 1920. Then in February
                        1920, the monarchy (Hungarian Kingdom) was restored, without electing a King
                        but with Admiral Miklós Horthy serving as Governor.</note> This paper
                aims to highlight the significance of Central European border settlements in Irish
                political discourse with the purpose of illustrating that looking beyond national
                borders was not irreconcilable with Irish nationalism; on the contrary. </p></div>
            <div><head>Irish perceptions of borders in East-Central Europe after
                1918</head>
            <p>The last few months of 1918 saw the complete transformation of the multi-cultural
                Habsburg Central Europe, from a Dual Monarchy into a number of independent small
                states. Stephen Howe has argued that the struggle for Irish independence was
                comparable to Czechoslovakia and Hungary “attaining independence from alien
                    rule”.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn6" n="5"> Howe, <hi rend="italic">Ireland and Empire</hi>, 232.</note> Furthermore, he
                has also claimed that comparing ‘experiences of conflict, secession and redrawing of
                boundaries across Europe and beyond” was worth investigating.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn7" n="6"> Ibid.<hi rend="italic">,</hi>
                        237.</note></p>
            <p>The socio-political changes that resulted from the redefined borders in Europe after
                the Great War were inseparable from the formulation of national identities across
                Europe. Although the circumstances were different in Ireland and in Central Europe,
                the question of border revisions in the Danube basin sparked the interest of Irish
                contemporaries. When historian Patrick Keatinge described Ireland as “a revisionist
                small state, both in respect of the constitutional relationship with Britain and of
                partition [that] gave added edge to the Irish attitude of anti-imperialism in the
                nineteen-twenties and thirties”, he identified common ground between Ireland and
                other small states in Central Europe based on the revision of treaties (the
                Anglo-Irish Treaty and the Versailles Peace Treaties, respectively).<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn8" n="7"> Patrick Keatinge, <hi rend="italic">A Place among the Nations: Issues of Irish Foreign
                            Policy</hi> (Dublin: Institute of Public Administration, 1978), 172.
                    </note> Correspondingly, in more recent historiography, Michael Kennedy has
                confirmed that interwar Ireland “was siding with the ‘revisionist states’”, urging
                the revision of the post-war Paris Peace Treaties and constructing Irish foreign
                policy as part of the post-Versailles world order.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn9" n="8"> Michael Kennedy, “Chicanery and Candour: The
                        Irish Free State and the Geneva Protocol, 1924-5,” <hi rend="italic">Irish
                            Historical Studies</hi> vol. xxix, No. 115 (May 1995), 377 and
                    383.</note></p>
            <p>From the end of October 1918, the Irish press provided much coverage of how the
                Austrian empire was broken up. The Irish dailies were aware of the fact that the now
                powerless Austrian Government could not stand in the way of Polish, Hungarian,
                Czechoslovak and Yugoslav independence.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn10" n="9"> “Austrian Empire Broken Up. Emperor’s Manifesto. Four
                        Separate States Decreed,” <hi rend="italic">Irish Independent</hi>, October
                        18, 1918. “Break-Up of Austria,” <hi rend="italic">Freeman’s Journal</hi>,
                        October 18, 1918.</note> By 2 November 1918, the <hi rend="italic">Irish
                    Independent</hi> announced: “the disintegration of the Austrian Empire [might]
                be said to be complete,”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn11" n="10"> “Austria’s Complete Break Up. Vienna-Budapest
                        Revolutions. Count Tisza Killed. Bosnia Joins Serbia: New Austro-German
                        State. Fleet Given to Jugo-Slavs,” <hi rend="italic">Irish Independent</hi>,
                        November 2, 1918.</note> granting the independence of northern and
                southern Slavic people was a touchy subject for Irish nationalists, as their pleas
                for the same goal were rejected by the great powers late 1918/early 1919. The
                establishment of an Austrian republic was also noticed in Irish journals and
                newspapers due to the state’s overwhelmingly Catholic traditions. In addition, Irish
                interest was apparent in articles regarding the political turmoil in independent
                Hungary as well.</p>
            <p>J. J. Lee, who has compared Irish socio-economic and political developments with the
                case of other small states in his book <hi rend="italic">Ireland 1912-1985</hi>
                (1990), has also pointed out the differences between post-war border disputes in
                Ireland and Central Europe. Lee has emphasised that after the Great War “borders
                were revised in central and eastern Europe in favour of smaller states. This was
                precisely what did not happen in Fermanagh and Tyrone.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn12" n="11"> J. J.
                        Lee,<hi rend="italic"> Ireland 1912–1985: Politics and Society </hi>(Cambridge:
                        Cambridge University Press, 1989), 46.</note> Interestingly, Lee has
                also argued that “the Free State enjoyed yet a further advantage. It was not the
                potential victim of irredentist or imperialist ambitions”, unlike East-Central
                European states.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn13" n="12">
                            Ibid.<hi rend="italic">,</hi> 78, 79.</note> And while the Irish
                Free State had no Banat, no Silesia, no Slovakia, and no Transylvania, Northern
                Ireland was still the object of irredentist nationalist claims.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn14" n="13"> Ibid. </note> Therefore,
                irredentism was a key factor in the context of border-related conflicts, both in
                Ireland and in the successor states. Joep Leerssen has explained this with the fact
                that irredentism seemed to be the “logical and almost unavoidable extension” of
                nationalism in post-war Europe.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn15" n="14"> Joep Leerssen, <hi rend="italic">National Thought in
                            Europe: A Cultural History</hi> (Amsterdam: Amsterdam University Press,
                        2008), 176.</note> Similarly, Paul Murray, in a major study of the Irish
                Boundary Commission, compared the claims of Irish nationalists and Central European
                irredentists. He concluded that since the 1801 Act of Union was still in effect, in
                partitioning Ireland, “… the British legislature was establishing a new boundary
                within part of the United Kingdom over which it exercised the same political control
                as it did over the other parts. The boundary settlements in Central and Eastern
                Europe, in contrast, were the result of external interference with the territorial
                integrity of states which found themselves on the losing side in the First World
                    War.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn16" n="15"> Paul
                        Murray, <hi rend="italic">The Irish Boundary Commission and its Origins
                            1886–1925</hi> (Dublin: UCD Press, 2011), 299.</note></p></div>
            <div><head>Partition history: the North-East Boundary Bureau and the Boundary
                    Commission</head>
            <p>As it has been established in the Introduction, the struggle between unionists and
                nationalists over the Home Rule question had been part of political debates before
                the Great War. However, it was the Government of Ireland Act of 1920 that eventually
                sought to create two states, Northern Ireland and Southern Ireland, and establish
                two parliaments (the southern parliament envisaged did not materialise and Home
                Rule, which was granted to both, took effect only in the north).<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn17" n="16"> Ged Martin, “The Origins of
                        Partition,” in: <hi rend="italic">The Irish Border: History, Politics,
                            Culture,</hi> eds. Malcolm Anderson and Eberhard Bort (Liverpool:
                        Liverpool University Press, 1999), 67.</note> The Anglo-Irish Treaty of
                1921 brought further legislation to settle the relationship, allowing the recently
                formed state of Northern Ireland to opt out of the Irish Free State. In the case of
                the latter, a Boundary Commission would be established to amend the (presently
                provisional) border between Northern Ireland (still part of the United Kingdom) and
                the Irish Free State (gained dominion status). The
                “Provisional-Government-sponsored” North-Eastern Boundary Bureau (NEBB - October
                1922) and then the Boundary Commission (first met in November 1924) were to make a
                decision “in accordance with the wishes of the inhabitants, so far as may be
                compatible with economic and geographic conditions.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn18" n="17"> Michael Kennedy, <hi rend="italic">Division and Consensus: The Politics of Cross-Border
                            Relations in Ireland 1925–1969</hi> (Dublin: Institute of Public
                        Administration, 2000), 9. Geoffrey J. Hand, “Introduction,” in: <hi rend="italic">Report of the Irish Boundary Commission 1925</hi>
                        (Shannon: Irish University Press, 1969), viii.</note> First and
                foremost, before discussing the cases of European boundary commissions, the
                Memorandum on the European Precedents for the NEBB declared that: “it must be
                remembered that in Ireland a boundary has already been drawn through the disputed
                areas, such as did not exist in Europe. It seems plain that the wishes of the
                inhabitants on both sides of it are to be taken into account.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn19" n="18"> UCDA P35b/132 (28), Patrick
                        McGilligan Papers, Memorandum on the European Precedents for the North
                        Eastern Boundary Bureau. </note></p>
            <p>In order to support their claim with successful precedents, the NEBB investigated
                similar boundary settlements in post-war Europe. Director Kevin O’Shiel, researcher
                Bolton C. Waller, secretary Edward Millington Stephens were those most involved in
                the process.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn20" n="19"> Eda
                        Sagarra, <hi rend="italic">Kevin O’Shiel: Tyrone Nationalist and Irish
                            State-Builder</hi> (Dublin: Irish Academic Press, 2013), 201-04.</note> O’Shiel requested Waller, an expert
                on European boundary disputes to advise him. Waller, who was in charge of
                researching international precedents full-time in London, argued that in Ireland a
                plebiscite was simply unnecessary due to the fact that the wishes of the inhabitants
                were well known as a result of the elections, stressing that “the expense and
                possible danger of a plebiscite are best avoided.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn21" n="20"> Ibid. UCDA P35b/133, North-Eastern Boundary
                        Bureau Final Report, 26 February 1926, by E. M. Stephens, Secretary. UCDA
                        LA1/H/83, Eoin MacNeill Papers, Confidential Memorandum by Kevin O’Shiel
                        entitled “Procedure at Boundary Commission”, 1922. UCDA LA1/H/95, Eoin
                        MacNeill Papers, Memorandum by Kevin O’Shiel with covering letter relating
                        to political relations between the Irish Free State and the Irish
                        North-Eastern minority, June 1923. UCDA LA1/H/83, Eoin MacNeill Papers,
                        Kevin O’Shiel – “Boundary Commission and its precedents”. UCDA LA1/H/89,
                        Eoin MacNeill Papers, Notes on Procedure of Boundary Commission.</note>
                E. M. Stephens, barrister and civil servant, was also required to study “recent
                European precedents for territorial transfer on the basis of local plebiscites”, and
                to collect data and to intermediate between the Dublin government and nationalist
                officials in the border areas.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn22" n="21"> NAI DT S4743,
                        <hi rend="italic">DIFP </hi>vol. ii, No. 380, Final
                        Report of the North-Eastern Boundary Bureau, E.M. Stephens to Kevin
                        O’Higgins (Dublin), 26 February 1926, accessed September 23, 2015, <ref target="http://www.difp.ie/docs/1926/Work-of-the-North-Eastern-Boundary-Bureau/716.htm">http://www.difp.ie/docs/1926/Work-of-the-North-Eastern-Boundary-Bureau/716.htm</ref>.
                        Andrew Carpenter and Lawrence William White, “Stephens, Edward Millington,”
                        <hi rend="italic">Dictionary of Irish Biography </hi>[henceforth:
                            <hi rend="italic">DIB</hi>], accessed August 7, 2015, <ref target="http://dib.cambridge.org/viewReadPage.do?articleId=a8276">http://dib.cambridge.org/viewReadPage.do?articleId=a8276</ref>.
                    </note> Moreover, the Irish trade representative in Berlin at the time,
                Charles Bewley (later minister to Germany 1933-1939), also furnished the Bureau
                “with certain particulars regarding Boundary Commissions on the Continent.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn23" n="22"> NAI FIN/1/2168,
                        National Archives of Ireland, Department of Finance Files, Letter from E. M.
                        Stephens, Secretary of the NEBB to the Secretary, Department of Finance, 26
                        January 1923.</note> In particular, Bewley sent reports on the Upper
                Silesian plebiscite conditions and the Schleswig Commission.</p>
            <p>Historian Paul Murray has highlighted the fact that the Bureau had found the
                plebiscites of the following territories noteworthy: Upper Silesia (March 1921)
                between Poland and Germany; Schleswig (February-March 1920) between Denmark and
                Germany, and Klagenfurt/Celovec in south-eastern Carinthia (October 1920) between
                Austria and the Kingdom of the Serbs, Croats and Slovenes, in addition to the
                general border question in Hungary.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn24" n="23"> Murray, <hi rend="italic">The Irish Boundary
                            Commission,</hi> 146, 241 and 247.</note> In these areas,
                plebiscites, impartially conducted and supervised, were employed as the means of
                ascertaining the wishes of inhabitants with a view to assigning them to the
                jurisdiction of their choice. </p>
            <p>As far as the border between Austria and Hungary was concerned, Austria successfully
                claimed Western Hungary (Burgenland, with the exception of Sopron/Oedenburg), and
                was permitted to occupy these territories on 7 August 1921. In the city of
                Sopron/Oedenburg a plebiscite (December 1921) decided in favour of staying under the
                Hungarian state. The plebiscite was attacked by many (non-Magyar) contemporaries,
                and was later questioned by historians. Throughout the conflict, the Irish press,
                relying on Reuters cablegrams from Berlin and telegrams from Vienna, echoed the
                Austrian opinion.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn25" n="24">
                        “Just another War Front. Hungarians Invade Austria,” <hi rend="italic">Irish
                            Independent</hi>, September 7, 1921. “Burgenland Plebiscite. Budapest
                        Claims Big Majority for Hungary in Oedenburg,” <hi rend="italic">Freeman’s
                            Journal</hi>, December 19, 1921. “Austrian Objections. Report that
                        Oedenburg is to Go to Hungary Brings Protest,” <hi rend="italic">Freeman’s
                            Journal</hi>, December 28, 1921. Jeremy King, “Austria vs. Hungary:
                        Nationhood, Statehood, and Violence since 1867,” in: <hi rend="italic">Nationalitätenkonflikte im 20. Jahrhundert: Ursachen von inter
                            ethnischer Gewalt im europäischen Vergleich</hi> [<hi rend="italic">Nationality Conflicts in the 20th Century: Causes of Inter-Ethnic
                            Violence in European Comparison</hi>], eds. Philipp Ther and Holm
                        Sundhaussen (Berlin: Harrassowitz, 2001), 174, 175.</note>
                Interestingly, there were no references to this particular precedent in the records
                of the NEBB or the Boundary Commission, despite the large publicity the events
                attracted in the Irish papers.</p>
            <p>In the registry of NEBB documents, there was only one reference to Hungarian borders
                in this context. The file compiled in relation to the northern Hungarian border and
                the question of the Ruthenian minority was actually a copy of the Czechoslovak
                memorandum presented at the Paris Peace Conference. Therefore, it reflected the
                arguments of the Czechoslovak Republic, claiming the territory inhabited by
                Ruthenians in the north-eastern part of the former Dual Monarchy. The Czechoslovak
                memorandum stressed that: “the Ruthenians of Hungary, a nation closely related to
                the Slovaks, live under the same conditions as the Slovaks, that they are in very
                intimate relation with them, that their union to the Czecho-Slovak Republic would
                cause no difficulty whatever. 2. This solution would best respond to the political
                reality and to the principles of justice.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn26" n="25"> NAI NEBB/2/1/13, Peace Conference. Czecho-Slovak
                        Delegation, memo No. 6. Problem of the Ruthenians of Hungary. Peace
                        Conference Documents. Czecho-Slovak Delegation.</note></p>
            <p>Similarly, other NEBB documents regarding continental precedents such as territorial
                disputes about the Carinthian Klagenfurt/Celovec area between Austria and Yugoslavia
                (in favour of Slovene claims as opposed to the demands of the German population),
                the case of the Bohemian Germans or the general territorial demands of
                Czechoslovakia were based on the Czech and Yugoslav memoranda, respectively, and
                presented at Versailles.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn27" n="26"> Ibid. NAI NEBB/2/1/12, Peace Conference Document.
                        Jugo-Slav Delegation. The Problem of Celovec (Klagenfurth). NAI NEBB/2/1/10,
                        Peace Conference Documents. Czecho-Slovak Delegation. Problem Touching the
                        Germans in Bohemia. NAI NEBB/2/1/11, The Territorial Claims of the
                        Czecho-Slovak Republic. Peace Conference Document. Czecho-Slovak Delegation.
                        Memoire No. 2. UCDA P35b/132(28), Patrick McGilligan Papers, Memorandum on
                        the European Precedents for the North Eastern Boundary Bureau. </note>
                In consequence, when it came to Irish claims in relation to the north-eastern
                boundary, there were very few references to Austrian or Hungarian examples, despite
                the high number of incidents (including the occasional plebiscites) there.
                Nevertheless, Eda Sagarra has pointed out that the phrasing of Article 12 of the
                Anglo-Irish Treaty and its interpretation by the Free State is “to be understood in
                the context of the plebiscitary politics of post-war Central Europe, notably as laid
                down in the Treaties of Versailles and Trianon”, referring to Upper Silesia,
                Klagenfurt, Burgenland, North Schleswig, and East Prussia.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn28" n="27"> Sagarra, <hi rend="italic">Kevin O’Shiel</hi>,
                        205.</note> As the Austro-Hungarian Empire was defeated in the Great
                War, their successors’ claims were treated differently by the great powers at and
                after Versailles than the victorious, newly independent small nations in the region.
                Therefore, when the Irish commission was looking for a precedent to support Irish
                nationalist demands, they rather examined the appeals of previously successful small
                states. Altogether, the very fact that the question of boundaries was in dispute
                created a greater Irish interest in territorial settlements in Europe.</p>
            <p>In post-war Europe, there was no guarantee that the political boundaries were about
                to reflect ethnic boundaries; indeed, when it came to the boundary issue in Ireland,
                eventually, no plebiscite was held, despite the research done by the NEBB and the
                personal experience of, for instance, F. B. Bourdillon, Secretary of Irish Boundary
                Commission, former member of the Upper Silesian Commission (1920-22).<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn29" n="28"> NAI NEBB/4/5/2, Copy
                        of Letter from Hugh A. McCartan to Stephens, 15 October 1924.</note>
                Bourdillon’s interest in the boundary situation on the Continent was well
                documented; in his letter to E. M. Stephens, dated 15 October 1924, the Irish
                publicity agent of the Bureau, Hugh A. McCartan, emphasised that Bourdillon “was
                much interested in the Upper Silesian precedent.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn30" n="29"> Ibid.</note></p>
            <p>During the interwar years, the possibility of treaty revisions was a frequently
                discussed topic across Europe, including in Ireland. It was visible that “the Treaty
                of Versailles was not a heaven-sent document, to be regarded forever as rigid and
                inviolable. On the contrary,” argued
                the<hi rend="italic"> Irish Press;</hi> “it was – like the
                ‘Treaty’ forced on us – a settlement based on compulsion and an attempt to
                perpetuate the spoils system in its delimitation of frontiers.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn31" n="30"> “Europe’s Problems,” <hi rend="italic">Irish Press</hi>, September 26, 1935.</note> Echoing
                de Valera’s agenda and ideas about “peaceful revision”, placing the Irish question
                in parallel with other European small nations, the paper claimed: “…We in Ireland
                have more than an academic interest in this question. Ireland is one of the small
                nations which for centuries has endured oppression at the hands of powerful
                neighbouring State. […] Revision and readjustment must come, if there is to be
                lasting peace in the world […]. There must be provision for changing international
                treaties or conditions that bear within themselves the seeds of future wars .”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn32" n="31"> Ibid.</note></p>
            <p>Therefore, Irish newspapers regularly pointed to the Versailles treaties when
                discussing the prevailing “minorities question” in Central Europe, in parallel with
                the legacy of the Irish border settlement. The Free State’s disappointment with
                regards the Boundary Commission was undeniable; eventually the existing borders were
                confirmed on December 3, 1925, after the British Conservative <hi rend="italic">Morning Post</hi> leaked the planned transfers on November 7, 1925. The report
                of the Boundary Commission was suppressed and not published until 1969.</p></div>
            <div><head>Irish interest in the minority problem in borderland regions after
                    1925</head>
            <p>The Irish dissatisfaction with the borders in the early 1920s resulted in an active
                participation in the League of Nations, which was expected to see to the protection
                of, among others, the northern Irish Catholic minority. This was crucial for the
                Free State under both <hi rend="italic">Cumann na nGaedheal</hi>’s William T.
                Cosgrave and <hi rend="italic">Fianna Fáil</hi>’s Eamon de Valera (after 1932).
                Interestingly, although during the interwar years the Irish External Affairs took a
                close interest in minority problems at Geneva, at the same time, the Department was
                also keen on adhering to a non-partitionist attitude in relation to Ireland.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn33" n="32"> Gerard Keown,
                        “Creating an Irish Foreign Policy in the 1930s,” in: <hi rend="italic">Irish
                            Foreign Policy 1919–1966: From Independence to Internationalism,</hi>
                        eds. Michael Kennedy and Joseph Morrison Skelly (Dublin: Four Courts Press,
                        2000), 38. </note>
            </p>
            <p>Rogers Brubaker has noted that borderland conflicts in Central Europe after the Great
                War became “internationalised”.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn34" n="33"> Rogers Brubaker, <hi rend="italic">Nationalist
                            Politics and Everyday Ethnicity in a Transylvanian Town</hi> (Princeton:
                        Princeton University Press, 2006)<hi rend="italic">,</hi> 49.</note> For
                small states, like the Irish Free State, a crucial aspect of League of Nations
                membership was the organisation’s declared role as protecting ethnic and religious
                minorities. Therefore, when expecting the support of other small nations, it was not
                surprising when diplomats like the Irish High Commissioner in London (5 February
                1929-14 December 1930), Timothy Smiddy, articulated the view that the Irish Free
                State could be regarded as “a champion of the national interests of small States, as
                also of minorities”.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn35" n="34"> Michael Kennedy, “Smiddy, Timothy Anthony,” <hi rend="italic">DIB,</hi>
                        accessed December 16, 2014, <ref target="http://dib.cambridge.org/viewReadPage.do?articleId=a8130">http://dib.cambridge.org/viewReadPage.do?articleId=a8130</ref>. Aengus
                        Nolan, <hi rend="italic">Joseph Walshe: Irish Foreign Policy 1922–1946</hi>
                        (Cork: Mercier Press, 2008), 38. </note>
            </p>
            <p>Between the two world wars, the problematic nature of the boundary question was also
                highlighted by the aforementioned Bolton C. Waller. In addition to his role as
                researcher in the NEBB, Waller was also involved in the application procedure of the
                Free State’s admission to the League. He took note of the fact that simultaneous
                requests were made by Iceland, Latvia, Finland, Lithuania and Hungary as well.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn36" n="35"> UCDA LA1/H/61, Eoin
                        MacNeill Papers, Typescript report by B.C. Waller on the application of the
                        Irish Free State for admission to the League of Nations. Bolton C. Waller,
                            <hi rend="italic">Ireland and the League of Nations</hi> (Dublin: Talbot
                        Press, 1925). Bolton C. Waller, <hi rend="italic">Paths to World Peace</hi>
                        (London: G. Allen &amp; Unwin, 1926). Bolton C. Waller, <hi rend="italic">Hibernia, or, The Future of Ireland</hi> (London: Dutton,
                    1928).</note> Later he became the President of the League of Nations Society
                of Ireland.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn37" n="36"> Michael
                        Kennedy, <hi rend="italic">Ireland and the League of Nations 1919–1946.
                            International Relations, Diplomacy and Politics</hi> (Dublin: Irish
                        Academic Press, 1996), 28.</note> In his writings, Waller focused on the
                role of the League in keeping up peace and suggested, among others, to implement
                “improved safeguards for minorities.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn38" n="37"> “European Peace. Irishman’s Prize Essay,” <hi rend="italic">Irish Independent</hi>, September 16, 1924. NAI DT S4084,
                            <hi rend="italic">DIFP</hi> vol. ii, No. 272, Kevin O’Higgins to each
                        member of the Executive Council, enclosing a memorandum on the Boundary
                        Question (C.1987/24) (Confidential), Dublin, 25 September 1924, accessed
                        September 23, 2015, <ref target="http://www.difp.ie/docs/1924/Boundary-Commission:-possible-offer-to-Northern-Ireland/608.htm">http://www.difp.ie/docs/1924/Boundary-Commission:-possible-offer-to-Northern-Ireland/608.htm</ref>.</note>
                As early as 1922-1923, he claimed that certain segments of the Versailles treaties
                that redrew boundaries across Europe could be adopted in relation to the Irish
                boundary as well.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn39" n="38">
                        UCDA LA1/H/89, Eoin MacNeill Papers, Typescript memorandum by B.C. Waller on
                        “European precedents for the North-Eastern Boundary Bureau,” 1922-1923.</note> Writing in 1925, he argued that it
                was unworthy of Ireland as a small nation and “out of accord with our traditions and
                temperament, being as we are a roaming and restless people,” to avoid “all
                entanglements with the rest of the world.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn40" n="39"> Waller, <hi rend="italic">Ireland and the League
                            of Nations</hi>, 18.</note> He explained this with the fact that
                “throughout our history we have been concerned with the spread of ideas, and have
                had an influence out of all proportion to our size or strength.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn41" n="40"> Ibid.</note> Therefore,
                argued Waller, the League provided the best opportunity for small nations like
                Ireland to play a part in the world.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn42" n="41"> Ibid., 66. </note>
            </p>
            <p>One of the main tasks of the League, Waller found, was to supervise the protection of
                minority rights.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn43" n="42">
                        Ibid., 37.</note> This proved to be problematic, as demonstrated by his
                article of March 1929 in the <hi rend="italic">Irish Independent</hi>, where Waller
                declared that the Council faced its “least successful” challenge up to date; dealing
                with the “complaints and petitions” of certain “aggrieved minorities” including
                Finland, Romania, Hungary, and the German minority in Upper Silesia.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn44" n="43"> “Dangers that
                        Threaten World Peace,” <hi rend="italic">Irish Independent</hi>, March 6,
                        1929.</note> “The problem of minorities in Europe is real and
                threatening”, emphasised Waller, most likely leading to war.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn45" n="44"> Ibid.</note> The <hi rend="italic">Cork Examiner</hi> named a possible reason for the negligence of
                the question to be the fact that “very few older members of the League could
                honestly declare that they themselves invariably treated their minorities in
                accordance with the spirit of the guaranteeing Treaty.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn46" n="45"> “Protection of Minorities,” <hi rend="italic">Cork Examiner</hi>, July 3, 1930.</note> Indeed, the
                ethno-linguistic and religious divisions, such as the cases observed by the <hi rend="italic">Cork Examiner</hi>, were so deeply embedded in certain societies
                that the presence of the League of could not remedy the situation.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn47" n="46"> Zara Steiner, <hi rend="italic">The Lights That Failed. European International History 1919–1933</hi>
                        (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 2007), 364.</note></p>
            <p>Irish perceptions of the regional minorities in the borderlands,
                    “<hi rend="italic">outside</hi> the imagined” newly independent nation-states,
                illustrate the complexity of Central European identities in the face of extreme
                political changes.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn48" n="47">
                        Brubaker, <hi rend="italic">Nationalist Politics</hi>, 46.</note> The
                troubling nature of minority issues was frequently discussed in the Irish press in
                the interwar years. This was visible, among others, in Irish comments on the Sudeten
                Germans in the Czechoslovak State; the formerly Austrian Catholics in the South
                Tyrol; and Hungarians along the frontiers of Czechoslovakia, Romania and Yugoslavia. </p></div>
            <div><head>Conclusion</head>
            <p>The importance of Central European precedents within the context of
                Irish partition and boundary settlement sheds light on a lesser discussed part of
                Irish nationalist discourse, namely, the outward looking attitude Irish nationalists
                had in relation to Partition. Therefore, this paper hoped to highlight the
                significance of the wider international context when investigating the Irish border
                question in the early interwar years. It aimed to illustrate Irish awareness of the
                political transformation of Central Europe and territorial settlements after the
                Great War, with special attention the plebiscites in Upper Silesia and Klagenfurt,
                also emphasising the significance the League of Nations, particularly after the
                failure of the Boundary Commission. Consequently, even though the Boundary
                Commission failed to alter the Irish border, the history of its work should be
                viewed as part of a larger European narrative.</p></div>
            
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="bibliography">
                <head>Sources and literature</head>
            <list type="unordered">
                <head>Archive sources:</head>
                <item>NAI, National Archives of Ireland:<list>
                <item>Department of Finance Files
                    - FIN/1/2168.</item>
                    <item>North-Eastern Boundary Bureau Files, NEBB/2/1/10, NEBB/2/1/11, NEBB/2/1/12, NEBB/2/1/13, NEBB/4/5/2.</item></list></item>
                <item>UCDA, University College Dublin Archives:<list>
                <item>Eoin MacNeill Papers, LA1/H/61, LA1/H/83, LA1/H/89,
                    LA1/H/95.</item>
                <item>Patrick McGilligan Papers, P35b/132 (28),
                    P35b/133.</item></list></item>
            </list>
            <listBibl>
                <head>Archive sources (Online):</head>
                <bibl>NAI DE 2/304/1, National Archives of Ireland, Dáil Éireann Files, <hi rend="italic">Documents on Irish Foreign Policy</hi> [<hi rend="italic">DIFP</hi>] vol. ii. No. 214, Final text of the Articles of Agreement for a
                    Treaty between Great Britain and Ireland as signed (London), December 6, 1921.
                    Accessed September 23, 2015. <ref target="http://www.difp.ie/docs/1921/Anglo-Irish-Treaty/214.htm">http://www.difp.ie/docs/1921/Anglo-Irish-Treaty/214.htm</ref>. </bibl>
                <bibl>NAI DT S4084, National Archives of Ireland, Department of the Taoiseach Files, <hi rend="italic">Documents on Irish Foreign Policy</hi> [<hi rend="italic">DIFP</hi>] vol. ii, No. 272, Kevin O’Higgins to each member of the Executive Council, enclosing a memorandum on the Boundary Question (C.1987/24) (Confidential), Dublin, 25 September 1924. Accessed September 23, 2015.<ref target="http://www.difp.ie/docs/1924/Boundary-Commission:-possible-offer-to-Northern-Ireland/608.htm">http://www.difp.ie/docs/1924/Boundary-Commission:-possible-offer-to-Northern-Ireland/608.htm</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl>NAI DT S4743, National Archives of Ireland, Department of the Taoiseach Files,
                    <hi rend="italic">Documents on Irish Foreign Policy</hi> [<hi rend="italic">DIFP</hi>] vol. ii, No. 380, Final Report of the North-Eastern Boundary
                    Bureau, E.M. Stephens to Kevin O’Higgins (Dublin), 26 February 1926. Accessed
                    September 23, 2015. <ref target="http://www.difp.ie/docs/1926/Work-of-the-North-Eastern-Boundary-Bureau/716.htm">http://www.difp.ie/docs/1926/Work-of-the-North-Eastern-Boundary-Bureau/716.htm</ref>.
                </bibl>
            </listBibl>
            <listBibl>
                <head>Literature:</head>
                <bibl>Brubaker, Rogers. <hi rend="italic">Nationalist Politics and Everyday
                    Ethnicity in a Transylvanian Town.</hi> Princeton: Princeton University
                    Press, 2006.</bibl>
                <bibl>Hand, Geoffrey J. “Introduction.” In: <hi rend="italic">Report of the Irish
                    Boundary Commission 1925.</hi> Shannon: Irish University Press, 1969.</bibl>
                <bibl>Howe, Stephen. Ireland and Empire: Colonial Legacies in Irish
                    History and
                    Culture. Oxford: Oxford University Press, 2000.</bibl>
                <bibl>Keatinge, Patrick. <hi rend="italic">A Place among the Nations: Issues of
                    Irish Foreign Policy.</hi> Dublin: Institute of Public Administration,
                    1978.</bibl>
                <bibl>Kennedy, Michael. “Chicanery and Candour: The Irish Free State and the Geneva
                    Protocol, 1924-5.” <hi rend="italic">Irish Historical
                        Studies</hi> vol. xxix, No. 115 (May 1995): 371-84.</bibl>
                <bibl>Kennedy, Michael. <hi rend="italic">Division and Consensus: The Politics of
                    Cross-Border Relations in Ireland 1925–1969.</hi> Dublin: Institute of
                    Public Administration, 2000.</bibl>
                <bibl>Kennedy, Michael. <hi rend="italic">Ireland and the League of Nations
                    1919–1946. International Relations, Diplomacy and Politics.</hi> Dublin:
                    Irish Academic Press, 1996. </bibl>
                <bibl>Keown, Gerard. “Creating an Irish Foreign Policy in the 1930s.” In: <hi rend="italic">Irish Foreign Policy 1919–1966: From Independence to
                    Internationalism,</hi> edited by Michael Kennedy and Joseph Morrison Skelly,
                    25-43. Dublin: Four Courts Press, 2000. </bibl>
                <bibl>King, Jeremy. “Austria vs. Hungary: Nationhood, Statehood, and Violence since
                    1867.” In: <hi rend="italic">Nationalitätenkonflikte im 20. Jahrhundert:
                        Ursachen von inter ethnischer Gewalt im europäischen Vergleich</hi> [<hi rend="italic">Nationality Conflicts in the 20th Century: Causes of
                            Inter-Ethnic Violence in European Comparison</hi>], edited by Philipp Ther
                    and Holm Sundhaussen, 163-82. Berlin: Harrassowitz,
                    2001.</bibl>
                <bibl>Lee, J. J.
                    <hi rend="italic">Ireland 1912–1985: Politics and Society. </hi>Cambridge:
                    Cambridge University Press, 1989.</bibl>
                <bibl>Leerssen,
                    Joep.<hi rend="italic"> National Thought in Europe: A Cultural History.</hi>
                    Amsterdam: Amsterdam University Press, 2008.</bibl>
                <bibl>Lynch, Robert. Revolutionary Ireland, 1912-25. London: Bloomsbury Academic, 2015.</bibl>
                <bibl>Martin, Ged. “The Origins of Partition.” In: <hi rend="italic">The Irish
                    Border: History, Politics, Culture,</hi> edited by Malcolm Anderson and
                    Eberhard Bort, 57-112. Liverpool: Liverpool University
                    Press, 1999.</bibl>
                <bibl>Murray, Paul. <hi rend="italic">The Irish Boundary Commission and its Origins
                    1886–1925.</hi> Dublin: UCD Press, 2011.</bibl>
                <bibl>Nolan, Aengus. <hi rend="italic">Joseph Walshe: Irish Foreign Policy
                    1922–1946.</hi> Cork: Mercier Press, 2008.</bibl>
                <bibl>Sagarra, Eda. <hi rend="italic">Kevin O’Shiel: Tyrone Nationalist and Irish
                    State-Builder.</hi> Dublin: Irish Academic Press, 2013.</bibl>
                <bibl>Sharp, Alan. “Reflections on the Remaking of Europe 1815, 1919, 1945,
                    post-1989: Some Comparative Reflections.” <hi rend="italic">Irish Studies in
                        International Affairs</hi> vol. viii (1997): 5-20.</bibl>
                <bibl>Steiner, Zara. <hi rend="italic">The Lights That Failed. European
                    International History 1919–1933.</hi> Oxford: Oxford University Press,
                    2007.</bibl>
            </listBibl>
            <listBibl>
                <head>Newspaper sources:</head>
                <bibl>Cork Examiner July 3, 1930. “Protection of Minorities.” </bibl>
                <bibl>Freeman’s Journal October 18, 1918. “Break-Up of Austria.” </bibl>
                <bibl><hi rend="italic">Freeman’s Journal</hi>, December 19, 1921. “Burgenland
                    Plebiscite. Budapest Claims Big Majority for Hungary in Oedenburg.” </bibl>
                <bibl><hi rend="italic">Freeman’s Journal</hi>, December 28, 1921. “Austrian
                    Objections. Report that Oedenburg is to Go to Hungary Brings Protest.” </bibl>
                <bibl>Irish Independent October 18, 1918. “Austrian Empire Broken Up. Emperor’s Manifesto. Four Separate States Decreed.” </bibl>
                <bibl>Irish Independent November 2, 1918. “Austria’s Complete Break Up. Vienna-Budapest Revolutions. Count Tisza Killed. Bosnia Joins Serbia: New Austro-German State. Fleet Given to Jugo-Slavs.” </bibl>
                <bibl><hi rend="italic">Irish Independent</hi>, September 7, 1921. “Just another War
                    Front. Hungarians Invade Austria.” </bibl>
                <bibl><hi rend="italic">Irish Independent</hi>, September 16, 1924. “European Peace.
                    Irishman’s Prize Essay.” </bibl>
                <bibl><hi rend="italic">Irish Independent</hi>, March 6, 1929. “Dangers that
                    Threaten World Peace.” </bibl>
                <bibl><hi rend="italic">Irish Press</hi>, September 26, 1935. “Europe’s Problems.”
                </bibl>
            </listBibl>
            <listBibl>
                <head>Online sources:</head>
                <bibl>Carpenter, Andrew and Lawrence William White. “Stephens, Edward Millington.”
                    <hi rend="italic">Dictionary of Irish Biography</hi>. Accessed August 7,
                    2015. <ref target="http://dib.cambridge.org/viewReadPage.do?articleId=a8276">http://dib.cambridge.org/viewReadPage.do?articleId=a8276</ref>. </bibl>
                <bibl>Kennedy, Michael. “Smiddy, Timothy Anthony.” <hi rend="italic">Dictionary of
                    Irish Biography.</hi> Accessed December 16, 2014. <ref target="http://dib.cambridge.org/viewReadPage.do?articleId=a8130">http://dib.cambridge.org/viewReadPage.do?articleId=a8130</ref>. </bibl>
            </listBibl>
            <listBibl>
                <head>Other sources:</head>
                <bibl>Waller, Bolton C. <hi rend="italic">Hibernia, or, The Future of Ireland.</hi>
                    London: Dutton, 1928.</bibl>
                <bibl>Waller, Bolton C. <hi rend="italic">Ireland and the League of Nations.</hi>
                    Dublin: Talbot Press, 1925.</bibl>
                <bibl>Waller, Bolton C. <hi rend="italic">Paths to World Peace.</hi> London: G.
                    Allen &amp; Unwin, 1926.</bibl>
            </listBibl></div>
           <div type="summary" xml:lang="sl">
               <docAuthor>Lili Zách</docAuthor>
            <head>DOGOVORI O SREDNJEEVROPSKIH MEJAH IN IRSKA V OBDOBJU MED VOJNAMA: TRANSNACIONALNA
                ŠTUDIJA URADA ZA SEVEROVZHODNO MEJO IN MEJNE KOMISIJE</head>
            <head>POVZETEK</head>
            <p>Glede na dokumentirano irsko zanimanje za urejanje evropskih meja je namen tega
                prispevka osvetliti pomen precedensov z ozemlja nekdanje Avstro-Ogrske in njihov
                vpliv na irsko mejno vprašanje v letih po prvi svetovni vojni. Po podpisu versajskih mirovnih pogodb so bile novozačrtane
                    meje v Srednji Evropi deležne precej pozornosti tudi v irski javnosti in
                    časopisju, ne samo v tamkajšnjih političnih krogih. Prelomni točki v irskem
                    mejnem vprašanju sta predstavljala zakon o vladi Irske (Government of Ireland
                    Act) iz leta 1920, v skladu s katerim naj bi na irskem otoku nastali dve državi,
                    in angleško-irski sporazum (Anglo-Irish Treaty), ki je omogočil novoustanovljeni
                    državi Severni Irski ločitev od Svobodne države Irske. Sčasoma sta bila
                    ustanovljena Urad za severovzhodno mejo (NEBB – oktobra 1922) in pozneje še
                    Mejna komisija (novembra 1924), da bi popravila (prvo začasno) mejo med Severno
                    Irsko in Svobodno državo Irsko v skladu z "željami prebivalcev".</p>
            <p>Za utemeljitev zahtev je Urad za severovzhodno mejo preučil podobne dogovore o mejah v povojni Evropi. Direktor Kevin O’Shiel, raziskovalec Bolton C. Waller in sekretar Edward Millington Stephens so bili ključni akterji pri raziskovanju in odločanju. Poleg tega so bile zelo pomembne tudi osebne izkušnje F. B. Bourdillona, sektretarja Mejne komisije za Irsko, nekdanjega člana Komisije za Gornjo Šlezijo (1920–22), saj je lahko primerjal celinske dogovore z irskimi okoliščinami. Urad za severovzhodno mejo in Mejna komisija sta posvetila precej pozornosti plebiscitom zaradi poudarjenega pomena "želj prebivalcev" tudi v irskem primeru. Zato so se Uradu zdeli pomembni plebisciti na naslednjih ozemljih: v Gornji Šleziji (marec 1921); v Schleswigu (februar-marec 1920); in v Celovcu na jugovzhodu avstrijske Koroške (oktober 1920). Kljub temu pa na Irskem ni bilo plebiscita in tudi meja med Severno Irsko in Svobodno državo Irsko se ni spremenila, saj so bile obstoječe meje potrjene 3. decembra 1925, potem ko je britanski časopis <hi rend="italic">Morning
                Post</hi> 7. novembra 1925 razkril načrtovane premike meja. Kljub neuspehu Mejne komisije pa je mogoče ugotoviti, da se vprašanje meja na Irskem ni obravnavalo osamljeno, ampak je bilo del širše evropske zgodbe.</p>
            <p>Najpomembnejša posledica Mejne komisije za Irsko je bilo
                okrepljeno irsko sodelovanje v Društvu narodov glede na vlogo, ki jo je ta
                organizacija imela v zaščiti etničnih in verskih manjših. Irski nacionalisti so
                si torej tudi za razpravo o ozemeljskih zahtevah, reviziji in pravicah manjših
                izbrali širši mednarodni oder, kjer so predstavili svoje zahteve in pogosto
                razpravljali o drugih dogovorih glede meja na celini. Na splošno je cilj tega
                prispevka prikazati, kako se je zgolj zaradi dejstva, da je bilo vprašanje meja
                sporno, povečalo irsko zanimanje za ozemeljske dogovore v Evropi, kar pomeni, da
                neodvisna Irska ni bila vase zagledana država, za kakršno je veljala pred
                tem.</p></div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>