<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Evaluation Remarks About Slovenian Parliamentary Democracy at Its
                    Twenty-Fifth Anniversary</title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename>Simona</forename>
                        <surname>Kustec Lipicer</surname>
                        <roleName>Full Professor</roleName>
                        <roleName>PhD</roleName>
                        <affiliation>Faculty of Social Sciences, University of
                            Ljubljana</affiliation>
                        <address>
                            <addrLine>Kardeljeva ploščad 5</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>SI-1000 Ljubljana</addrLine>
                        </address>
                        <email>simona.kustec-lipicer@fdv.uni-lj.si</email>
                    </name>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>2016-10-27</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>
                    <orgName xml:lang="sl">Inštitut za novejšo zgodovino</orgName>
                    <orgName xml:lang="en">Institute of Contemporary History</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Kongresni trg 1</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>SI-1000 Ljubljana</addrLine>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>http://ojs.inz.si/pnz/article/view/191</pubPlace>
                <date>2016</date>
                <availability status="free">
                    <licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title xml:lang="sl">Prispevki za novejšo zgodovino</title>
                <title xml:lang="en">Contributions to Contemporary History</title>
                <biblScope unit="volume">56</biblScope>
                <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
                <idno type="ISSN">2463-7807</idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source, born digital.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc xml:lang="en">
                <p>Contributions to Contemporary History is one of the central Slovenian scientific
                    historiographic journals, dedicated to publishing articles from the field of
                    contemporary history (the 19th and 20th century).</p>
                <p>The journal is published three times per year in Slovenian and in the following
                    foreign languages: English, German, Serbian, Croatian, Bosnian, Italian, Slovak
                    and Czech. The articles are all published with abstracts in English and
                    Slovenian as well as summaries in English.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <projectDesc xml:lang="sl">
                <p>Prispevki za novejšo zgodovino je ena osrednjih slovenskih znanstvenih
                    zgodovinopisnih revij, ki objavlja teme s področja novejše zgodovine (19. in 20.
                    stoletje).</p>
                <p>Revija izide trikrat letno v slovenskem jeziku in v naslednjih tujih jezikih:
                    angleščina, nemščina, srbščina, hrvaščina, bosanščina, italijanščina, slovaščina
                    in češčina. Članki izhajajo z izvlečki v angleščini in slovenščini ter povzetki
                    v angleščini.</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="sl"/>
                <language ident="en"/>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords xml:lang="en">
                    <term>Yugoslavia</term>
                    <term>history</term>
                    <term>historiography</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords xml:lang="sl">
                    <term>Državni zbor Republike Slovenije</term>
                    <term>demokracija</term>
                    <term>volivci</term>
                    <term>vlada</term>
                    <term>spremembe</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change>
                    <date>2016-10-06</date>
                    <name>Neja Blaj Hribar</name>
                    <desc>Pretvorba iz DOCX v TEI, dodatno kodiranje</desc>
                </change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <docAuthor>Simona Kustec Lipicer<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn1" n="*">Full Professor,
                    PhD, Faculty of Social Sciences, University of Ljubljana, Kardeljeva ploščad 5,
                    SI-1000 Ljubljana, <ref
                        target="file:///C:\Users\filipc\Downloads\simona.kustec-lipicer@fdv.uni-lj.si"
                        >simona.kustec-lipicer@fdv.uni-lj.si</ref></note></docAuthor>
            <docImprint>
                <idno type="cobissType">Cobiss type: 1.01</idno>
                <idno type="UDC">UDC: 328(497.4)"2014/2016"</idno>
            </docImprint>
            <div type="abstract" xml:lang="sl">
                <head type="main">IZVLEČEK</head>
                <head>OCENA SLOVENSKE PARLAMENTARNE DEMOKRACIJE OB NJENI PETINDVAJSETLETNICI</head>
                <p><hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">V članku je z namenom podati oceno dosedanjih praks slovenske parlamentarne demokracije podan kronološki pregled sprememb in prevladujočih demokratičnih vzorcev v državi od prvih parlamentarnih volitev po sprejemu ustave do aktualnega časa. Osrednjo mesto analize, ki je v prvem delu članka utemeljena prvenstveno na statističnih podatkih v drugem delu pa na sekundarnih virih, med njimi spoznanjih že izvedenih raziskovalnih študij ter medijskih zapisov, je namenjeno parlamentarnemu in vladnemu vedenju političnih strank v posameznem volilnem obdobju. Analiza pokaže, da je bila slovenska parlamentarna demokracija v prvem, poosamosvojitvenem obdobju pretežno predvidljivo osredotočena v temeljni demokratični razvoj in ni beležila pomembnejših sprememb skozi čas. Na drugi strani pa predvsem zadnja tri volilna obdobja (t.i. drugo obdobje demokracije) kažejo na bistvene spremembe od prvotno zastavljenega delovanja in jih zaznamuje prevlada notranjih strankarskih interesov ter konfliktov, kar ima učinek na celotni demokratični prostor v državi. Na podlagi vsega prikazanega je eno od ključnih spoznanj članka, da politične stranke v Sloveniji ohranjajo temeljno vlogo gradnika parlamentarne demokracije, vendar pa izvajanje njihovih vlog in aktivnosti tako znotraj parlamentarne kot vladne arene v zadnjih obdobjih pospešeno opozarja na premislek o osrednjem poslanstvu ter demokratičnih funkcijah političnih strank. Prav tako je zlasti v zadnjem obdobju možno zaznati, da se možnosti nezanesljivega in nepredvidljivega volilnega rezultata za stranke povečujejo sorazmerno z njihovimi notranjimi ter medstrankarskimi konflikti, ki na parlamentarno demokracijo države mečejo izrazito negativno podobo. </hi></p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Ključne besede: Državni zbor Republike Slovenije, demokracija,
                        volivci, vlada, spremembe</hi></p>
            </div>
            <div type="abstract">
                <head>ABSTRACT</head>
                <p><hi rend="italic">In order to evaluate the existing practices of the Slovenian
                        parliamentary democracy, the author conducted a chronological overview of
                        the shifts in prevailing democratic patterns, starting with the first
                        parliamentary elections after the country gained independence onwards.
                        Parliamentary and governmental political party behaviour was central to the
                        analysis and, thus, was analysed using both statistical data and secondary
                        sources, which primarily consisted of academic and research papers and media
                        records. The analysis revealed that Slovenian parliamentary democracy in the
                        initial (first) decade was according to the electoral data predictable and
                        by programme orientation oriented towards democratic development. However,
                        over the past three election cycles (second decade), the situation began to
                        change quickly, indicating a predominance of internal party interests and
                        conflicts that affect the country’s entire democratic arena. One of the main
                        findings of the article suggests that political parties in Slovenia remain a
                        fundamentally important pillar of parliamentary democracy, but their roles
                        and activities within the parliamentary, governmental and other arenas
                        increasingly warn of their central mission and democratic system functions.
                        It can be detected that the potentials for electoral uncertainties increase
                        with the intensities of internal and inter-parties’ conflicts which all give
                        distinctly negative connotation to the country’s parliamentary democracy.
                    </hi></p>
                <p><hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve"> Key words: National Assembly of the Republic of Slovenia, Democracy, Voters, Government, Changes</hi></p>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div>
                <head>The Place of the Political Parties in the Parliamentary Democracy</head>
                <p> In Europe, political parties are an essential aspect of parliamentary-party
                        democracy,<hi rend="Footnote_Anchor"><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn2" n="1">
                            Alan Ware, <hi rend="italic">Citizens, parties, and the state. A
                                reappraisal</hi> (Princeton, N. J.: Princeton University Press,
                            1988).</note></hi> as they allow the parliamentary arena to function
                    normally. Because of this, political parties represent the core of modern
                    politics. </p>
                <p> With the advent of mass democracy in the late-nineteenth and early-twentieth
                    centuries, the existence of a direct link between the state and individuals
                    became more and more unrealistic; this shift has contributed to the
                    legitimisation of political parties as intermediaries between individual
                    citizens and the state.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn3" n="2"> Ingrid van Biezen
                        and Richard S. Katz, <hi rend="italic">Democracy and Political Parties</hi>.
                        Paper, prepared for the workshop ‘Democracy and Political Parties’, ECPR
                        Joint Sessions, 2005 (Granada, April 2005), 1, available at URL: <ref
                            target="https://ecpr.eu/Filestore/PaperProposal/3402a19c-2e82-4b30-bf30-6a423927d5b0.pdf"
                            >https://ecpr.eu/Filestore/PaperProposal/3402a19c-2e82-4b30-bf30-6a423927d5b0.pdf</ref>.</note>
                    As a result, political parties have taken on the role of an interface, or a  connecting point between the citizens and state institutions. Parties
                    have begun to function as a key element of the integration of the people’s will
                    and the respective governing authorities. In this regard, the implementation of
                    universal and free voting has led to an assertion of power by the political
                    parties. </p>
                <p> Despite their relatively recent appearance on the political stage, parties have
                    made such a strong mark on contemporary politics and democracy that
                    twentieth-century democracy could be best described as a ‘party democracy’.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn4" n="3"> Note 2.</note> Parties not only became an
                    indispensable part of the democratic society’s existence; they also became a
                    fundamental factor for changes in democratic societies.<hi
                        rend="Footnote_Anchor"><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn5" n="4"> Richard S.
                            Katz, "Party in Democratic Theory," in:
                                <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Handbook of Party Politics, </hi>eds<hi
                                rend="italic">.</hi> Richard S Katz and Daniel Crotty (London: Sage,
                            2006), 44.</note></hi></p>
                <p> Up until this point, democratic theorists did not consider the role of political parties to be an important factor in the changing patterns of democracy.
                    Numerous studies on the institutional and procedural functions of political
                    parties exist,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn6" n="5"> Peter Mair, "Party System
                        Change," in:
                        <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Handbook of Party Politics, </hi>eds.
                        Katz and Crotty, 63–75.</note> including some that explore the relationship
                    between citizens and the state,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn7" n="6"> Arendt
                        Ljiphart, <hi rend="italic">Patterns of Democracy</hi> (Yale: Yale
                        University Press, 2012). </note> but few have focused on political parties
                    as the third fundamental constitutive pillar of democracy. </p>
                <p> With regard to a system-wide democracy, political parties exist and work on two
                    levels: </p>
                <list type="ordered">
                    <item>Level 1 refers to the platform political parties create for themselves in
                        the external environment; this includes their attitudes and their making
                        related to their voters, to their work in political institutions etc.</item>
                    <item>Level 2 refers to internal party dynamics, which are reflected in their
                        internal political processes, how they perceive their own mission and
                        jurisdictions in the system and, consequently, any adequate cadre,
                        financial, intellectual and other operational resources allocated to
                            them.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn8" n="7">
                                Andre Krouwel, "Party Models," in:
                                <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Handbook of Party Politics, </hi>eds.
                                Katz and Crotty, 249–70. Peter Mair and Ingrid van Biezen,
                                "Partymembership in twenty European democracies, 1980–2000," <hi
                                    rend="italic">Party Politics</hi>, No. 7 (2011): 5–21. See also
                                Note 5.</note></item>
                </list>
                <p> The most recent research has found that parties are losing relevance as vehicles
                    of representation, mobilisation and channels for interest articulation and
                    aggregation. All of this together makes parties increasingly incapable of
                    carrying out their essential function and, consequently, have had an indirect
                    impact on citizens’ decreasing trust and confidence in political institutions
                    and politics in general.<note place="foot"
                            xml:id="ftn9" n="8"> Michael Gallagher, Michael Laver and Peter Mair,
                                <hi rend="italic">Representative Government in Western Europe</hi>
                            (New York: McGraw-Hill, 2005). Russell J. Dalton, David M. Farrell and
                            Ian McAllister,<hi rend="apple-converted-space"> </hi><hi rend="italic"
                                >Political parties and democratic linkage. How parties organize
                                democracy</hi> (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 2011).</note></p>
                <p> The primary aim of this article is to recognise and assess the patterns of
                    Slovenian parliamentary democracy; these patterns are identified using electoral
                    experiences from the independence of the state onwards. The behaviour of the
                    parliamentary and governmental political parties are at the centre of the
                    analysis. In order to structure the chronological overview, the analysis focuses
                    on each electoral term as an individual unit in which the prevailing frameworks
                    represent the wider political context, upgraded with the political party arenas’
                    main specifics of the analysed time periods. The analysis uses statistical data
                    and other secondary sources – which consist primarily of academic research
                    papers and media records – to explore these themes. </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>The Slovenian Experience as an Example: The Broader Political Context of
                    Parliamentary Democracy from Independence Until Today <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn10" n="9"> Chapter based on the following data and
                        other sources' webpages: <hi rend="italic">National Electoral Commission</hi>,
                        accesed 15 September 2016, URL:
                        http://www.dvk-rs.si/index.php/en.<hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve"> Official Gazette of the Republic of Slovenia</hi>,
                        accesed 15 September 2016, URL: <ref target="https://www.uradni-list.si/"
                            >https://www.uradni-list.si/</ref>. <hi rend="italic">Government of the
                                Republic of Slovenia</hi>, accesed 15 September 2016, URL: <ref
                                    target="http://www.vlada.si/en/about_the_government/governments_of_the_republic_of_slovenia/"
                                    >http://www.vlada.si/en/about_the_government/governments_of_the_republic_of_slovenia/</ref>.
                        <hi rend="outputtext"><seg rend="italic">Reports on National Assembly's work
                            in the parliamentary terms</seg>, accesed 15 September 2016, </hi>URL:
                        <ref
                            target="http://www.dz-rs.si/wps/portal/Home/deloDZ/raziskovalnaDejavnost/Knjige"
                            >
                            http://www.dz-rs.si/wps/portal/Home/deloDZ/raziskovalnaDejavnost/Knjige</ref>.<hi rend="outputtext" xml:space="preserve"> </hi>
                        "Freedom House,"
                        <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Nations in Transit. Slovenia, 2016, </hi>accesed
                        20 June 2016, URL: <ref
                            target="https://freedomhouse.org/report/nations-transit/2016/slovenia"
                            >https://freedomhouse.org/report/nations-transit/2016/slovenia</ref>. "<hi
                                rend="st1">European Journal of Political Research,"</hi>
                        <seg rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Political Data Yearbook. </seg>Slovenia,
                        2016, accesed 20 June 2016, URL: <ref
                            target="http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/journal/10.1111/(ISSN)2047-8852/homepage/slovenia.htm"
                            >
                            http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/journal/10.1111/(ISSN)2047-8852/homepage/slovenia.htm</ref>.<hi rend="outputtext" xml:space="preserve"> For </hi>more
                        details about the statistical data and in-depth analysis see also Simona Kustec
                        Lipicer and Andrija Henjak, "<hi rend="st1">Changing dynamics of democratic
                            parliamentary arena in Slovenia. Voters, parties, elections,</hi>"<hi
                                rend="st1">
                                <seg rend="italic">Prispevki za novejšo zgodovino</seg>
                            </hi>55, No. 3 (<hi rend="st1">2015</hi>).</note></head>
                <p> After gaining independence in 1991, the first election of representatives to the
                    National Assembly of the Republic of Slovenia took place in 1992. There have
                    since been an additional seven election cycles, and ten governments have been
                    elected to the National Assembly.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn11" n="10"> The
                        1990 elections may be mentioned as a forerunner of the first
                        after–independence elections to the National Assembly in 1990. In the 1990
                        elections, 80 members were elected in each of the three assembly chambers,
                        which were the Socio–Political Chamber, the Chamber of Associated Labour and
                        the Chamber of Communities. Government was formed based on the outcome of
                        the Sociopolitical Chamber elections, and this was conducted by the
                        coalition of the Demos <hi rend="short_text">in the period of 1990 to 1992.
                            D</hi>ue to disagreements in the Demos coalition, the government was led
                        by the left Liberal Democracy of Slovenia, LDS
                        <hi rend="short_text" xml:space="preserve">just </hi>before the first
                        parliamentary elections (from May 1992 till the end of February
                        1993).</note></p>
                <p> Basic electoral indicators<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn12" n="11"> More details
                        about the statistical data and in-depth analysis are in Kustec Lipicer and
                        Henjak, "<hi rend="st1">Changing dynamics of democratic parliamentary arena
                            in Slovenia.</hi>"</note> show that on average, 20 political parties
                    participate in parliamentary elections. At least 17 political parties
                    participated in the 2008 and 2014 elections. In contrast, 26 parties
                    participated in the 1992 elections. Bigger variations in the number of competing
                    political parties between the two consecutive elections were not recorded. </p>
                <table rend="rules">
                    <head>Table 1: Data regarding the number of parties in the parliamentary
                        elections in Slovenia, 1990-2014</head>
                    <row role="label">
                            <cell/>
                            <cell>1992</cell>
                            <cell>1996</cell>
                            <cell>2000</cell>
                            <cell>2004</cell>
                            <cell>2008</cell>
                            <cell>2011</cell>
                            <cell>2014</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell role="label">No. of candidates</cell>
                            <cell>1475</cell>
                            <cell>1300</cell>
                            <cell>1007</cell>
                            <cell>1395</cell>
                            <cell>1182</cell>
                            <cell>1300</cell>
                            <cell>1246</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell role="label">No. of competing parties</cell>
                            <cell>26</cell>
                            <cell>22</cell>
                            <cell>23</cell>
                            <cell>23</cell>
                            <cell>17</cell>
                            <cell>20</cell>
                            <cell>17</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell role="label">No. of elected parties</cell>
                            <cell>8</cell>
                            <cell>7</cell>
                            <cell>8</cell>
                            <cell>7</cell>
                            <cell>7</cell>
                            <cell>7</cell>
                            <cell>7</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell role="label">No. of newly elected parties</cell>
                            <cell/>
                            <cell>1</cell>
                            <cell>3</cell>
                            <cell>1</cell>
                            <cell>2</cell>
                            <cell>2</cell>
                            <cell>3</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell role="label">No. of unelected parties</cell>
                            <cell/>
                            <cell>2</cell>
                            <cell>2</cell>
                            <cell>2</cell>
                            <cell>2</cell>
                            <cell>3</cell>
                            <cell>3</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell role="label">No. of coalition parties</cell>
                            <cell><p>4, later </p><p>3 and then 2</p></cell>
                            <cell>3 dropping to 2 </cell>
                            <cell>5 dropping to 4</cell>
                            <cell>4</cell>
                            <cell>4</cell>
                            <cell><p>5 (SDS term) / </p><p>4 (PS term) </p></cell>
                            <cell>3</cell>
                        </row>
                    </table>
                <p>Source: Adapted from the Official Gazette of the Republic of Slovenia (2016), National Electoral Commission (2016) and Government of the Republic of Slovenia (2016)</p>
                <p> The number of elected, re-elected and unelected parties remains stable. On
                    average, two new parties are elected in each election, whereas two parties fail
                    re-election. This data supports the volatility phenomena, which suggests that
                    political party electoral support changes according to their past electoral
                    success. Based on statistical data, since Slovenia’s 2004 elections (and even
                    more so from 2008 onwards), the volatility rates have reflected the electoral
                    success and after that immediate and complete failure of new political parties
                    to enter the parliament.</p>

                <figure>
                    <head>Figure 1: Volatility and vote share of new parties in the parliamentary
                        elections in Slovenia, 1992– 2014</head>
                    <graphic url="figure1.jpg" height="400px"/>
                    <p>Source: Adapted from Kustec Lipicer and Henjak (2015)</p>
                </figure>
                <p> On average, the government coalition consists of four parties. On average,
                    within one government office term, two shifts occur in coalition partners,
                    whether due to their resignation or to their replacement by the prime minister.
                    The only exception was the coalition in the 2004–2008 term, the only one in
                    Slovenian parliamentary history to sustain a complete electoral period term in
                    the initial composition.<note place="foot"
                            xml:id="ftn13" n="12"> Drago Zajc, Samo Kropivnik and Simona Kustec
                            Lipicer, <hi rend="Emphasis"><seg rend="italic normalweight">Od volilnih
                                    programov</seg></hi><hi rend="st1"
                                ><seg rend="italic" xml:space="preserve"> do koalicijskih pogodb. Analiza politične kongruence</seg>
                                (Ljubljana: Fakulteta za družbene vede, 2012).</hi></note></p>
                <p> These circumstances have resulted in a significant decrease in trust in the
                    government and the National Assembly generally and in the political parties
                    specifically. Over the past two electoral periods, the level of trust in
                    political parties has fallen below 5 %.<note
                            place="foot" xml:id="ftn14" n="13"> Niko Toš, ed., <hi rend="italic"
                                >Vrednote v prehodu VIII. Slovenija v srednje in vzhodnoevropskih
                                primerjavah 1991–2011</hi> (Ljubljana and Wien: Univerza v
                            Ljubljani, Fakulteta za družbene vede and IDV-CJMMK – Edition Echoraum,
                            2014).</note> However, the average electoral participation is still
                    slightly higher than 70 %. After 2004, the turnout rate dropped to the
                    aforementioned average, with participation in the last elections in 2014 barely
                    exceeding 50 %, all of which points to a decrease in the legitimacy of electoral
                    participation, something that needs to be taken into consideration in the
                    democratic political system. </p>
                <figure>
                    <head>Figure 2: Election turnout in Slovenia, 1992–2014</head>
                    <graphic url="figure2.jpg" height="400px"/>
                    <p>Source: National Electoral Commission (2016)</p>
                </figure>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Parliament 1992–1996</head>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="color(222222)">Slovenia’s first National Assembly of the Republic
                        election in 1992 was influenced by the early period of democracy. Based on
                        constitutional norms, internal visions of action and fundamental political
                        visions regarding how to model and develop a democratic state and market
                        system, political parties – together with the parliament and the government,
                        which function as fundamental pillars of democracy – began to build up their
                        democratic experience.</hi><hi rend="Footnote_Anchor"><note place="foot"
                            xml:id="ftn15" n="14"> Aleksander Lorenčič, <hi rend="naslov"
                                ><seg rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Prelom s starim in začetek novega. Tranzicija slovenskega gospodarstva iz socializma v kapitalizem (1990–2004) </seg>(Ljubljana:
                                Inštitut za novejšo zgodovino, 2012). </hi>Jure Gašparič, <hi
                                rend="italic">Slovenski parlament. Politično-zgodovinski pregled od
                                začetka prvega do konca šestega mandata (1992–2014) – 1.0</hi>
                            (Ljubljana: Inštitut za novejšo zgodovino, 2014), accesed 29 June
                            2016, URL: <ref target="http://www.sistory.si/SISTORY:ID:26950"
                                >http://www.sistory.si/SISTORY:ID:26950</ref>. Janko Prunk and Tomaž
                            Deželan, eds., <hi rend="italic">Dvajset let slovenske države</hi>
                            (Maribor: Aristej and Ljubljana: Fakulteta za družbene vede, Center za
                            politološke raziskave, 2012).
                        </note></hi> Internal party conflicts that related to new social movements’ internal democratic processes were prevalent and ultimately resulted in their separation or integration of social movements into political parties formations which consequently indicated a farewell of the former from the political system.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn16" n="15"> Danica Fink
                            - Hafner, <seg rend="italic normalweight">Nova
                                    družbena gibanja</seg><seg rend="italic" xml:space="preserve"> – subjekti politične inovacije</seg>
                                (Ljubljana: Fakulteta za družbene vede, 1992).
                    </note> In the shadow of these processes, the first coalition was very diverse. Consisting of parties from both the left and the right, this new coalition was led by the relative winner of the elections, the left-centred liberal democracy of Slovenia (LDS), and its president, Janez Drnovšek,
                       became the prime minister.</p>
                <p>In March 1994, the
                        affair ‘Depala vas’ was revealed. Though it was the only one, it induced a
                        huge polemic of the aforementioned office term. This affair also directly
                        affected the governmental coalition’s internal instability. The coalition
                        leading, the left-winged LDS, was primarily a reason for deposing the then
                        Minister of Defence, which led to the resignation of the right positioned
                        social democratic party SDSS, whose members included said Minister of
                        Defence, from the governmental coalition. Further, in 1994, the then Foreign
                        Minister from the quota of another, also in the right political pole
                        positioned partner Slovenian Christian Democrats, SKD, also resigned from
                        the Government. However, despite this, the SKD remained in the coalition.
                        Six months before the 1996 general elections, the left-wing social
                        democrats, ZLSD, the second of the four coalition partners, resigned from
                        the coalition.<note place="foot"
                            xml:id="ftn17" n="16"> Marko Pečauer, "Skoraj vsak mandat se konča s
                            krizo," <hi rend="italic">Delo</hi>, 19 September 2008, accesed 22 May
                            2016, URL: <ref target="https://m.delo.si/clanek/174052"><hi
                                    rend="Internet_Link"
                            >https://m.delo.si/clanek/174052</hi></ref>.</note></p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Parliament 1996–2000</head>
                <p> The second term of the National Assembly was again marked by the relative
                    victory of the LDS party. The party’s president, Janez Drnovšek, formed a new
                    governmental coalition, this time with the newly elected, interest-driven
                    Democratic Party of Retired Persons of Slovenia, DeSUS, and the center–right
                    agrarian party of Slovenian People’s Party, SLS.</p>
                <p> The coalition, despite its constant internal tensions, endured until six months
                    before the next election, where the National Assembly, on the recommendation of
                    the Prime Minister, called for a vote of no confidence in the government. The
                    coalition did not pass. This was the first time in history that the National
                    Assembly voted that they had no trust in the government.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn18" n="17"> The merger
                            of the coalition party SLS with the opposition, SKD, led to the
                            resignation of all of the ministers of SLS from the government. The
                            ministers of SLS constituted almost half of the government. Furthermore,
                            the appointment of new ministers was tied to a vote of no confidence in
                            the new government, but was not elected. </note> Instead of calling
                    early elections for a six month period, the government was taken over from the
                    (already) united former right coalition party SLS and the right-wing opposition
                    parties SKD (SLS + SKD), as well as the Slovenian Democratic Party SDS (formerly
                    the SDSS). The coalition was lead by the prime minister, Andrej Bajuk from SLS +
                    SKD. The main characteristic marking this half-year long right-wing coalition
                    was the numerous politically driven personal replacements.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn19" n="18"> One of the
                            key people of the ruling coalition parties became Telekom's CEO; the
                            director of the Tax Administration was illegally deposed with more than
                            a hundred government officials. More in <hi rend="italic">STA</hi>
                            (Arhiv novic), accesed 30 June 2016, URL: <ref target="http://sta.si/"
                                    >http://sta.si</ref>. </note></p>
                <p> Aside from another round of internal coalition tensions and other
                    parliamentary-party turbulences, the second parliamentary term remained
                    influenced by the further development of the market-economic model, as well as
                    the starting processes of integrating the country into the international arena.
                    After the Depala vas affair, another similar military-police political affair
                    emerged (Vič Holmec) during the same term, together with the already mentioned
                    affairs connecting the political cadre replacements in this period’s last
                    months. </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Parliament 2000–2004</head>
                <p> The third parliamentary elections were again won by the left-positioned LDS,
                    this time with the vast majority of 36,26 of the votes. LDS President, Janez
                    Drnovšek, assembled a governmental coalition for the third time. This third
                    coalition was described as a ‘large heterogeneous coalition’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn20" n="19">Alenka Krašovec and Ladislav Cabada L., "Kako smo si
                                različni. Značilnosti vladnih koalicij v
                                Sloveniji, Češki republiki in na
                                Slovaškem,"<seg rend="italic normalweight">Teorija in
                                    praksa</seg> 50, No. 5/6 (2013): 717–35.</note>
                    In the beginning of the mandate, the coalition was composed of five parties, all
                    of which had already cooperated with the mandatary back when he had been leading
                    the two previous governments.<note place="foot"
                            xml:id="ftn21" n="20">The SDS was the only party that the coalition had
                            already cooperated with in the past, but was also not invited into the
                            current large coalition. The SLS, which was responsible for the
                            governmental crisis before the end of the previous mandate, also
                            participated in the coalition.</note> In 2002, Prime Minister
                    Drnovšek ran and was subsequently elected for the President of the Republic. The
                    new prime minister within the same coalition became Drnovšek’s former party
                        colleague.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn22"
                            n="21"> The party membership of Janez Drnovšek was frozen when he was
                            elected for the President of the Republic. In 2006, Drnovšek resigned
                            from the LDS. </note> Tone Rop, the former minister of finances,
                    became the ruling party’s new president. </p>
                <p> Strong disagreements emerging in the coalition almost a year before the new
                    parliamentary elections led to the resignation of the right SLS ministers. In
                    this parliamentary term, an active opposition action was recognised. Also, a
                    vote of no confidence in the government, which did not pass, was proposed by the
                    right leading opposition parties SDS and Nsi.<note
                            place="foot" xml:id="ftn23" n="22"> Immediately after the 2000 elections
                            and subsequent internal party disagreements, the NSi were formed out of
                            the resigned members and deputies from before the election merged the
                            SLS + SKD. After the formation of the NSi, the party SLS + SKD was again
                            renamed the SLS.</note> A programme interested governmental report
                    on Slovenia’s 2000–2004 development<note place="foot"
                            xml:id="ftn24" n="23"> More
                            details<hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve"> Arhiv glavnih novic; Vlada Republike Slovenije</hi>,
                            2016, accesed 5 July 2016, URL: <ref
                                target="http://www.vlada.si/medijsko_sredisce/glavne_novice/"
                                >http://www.vlada.si/medijsko_sredisce/glavne_novice/</ref>.</note>
                    was prepared for this occasion, and it served as a valuable written side-effect
                    remark of this political act.</p>
                <p> This period was positively influenced by external politics, namely, formal
                    membership in the EU and NATO. External factors, along with the encouraging
                    economic indicators and, consequently, social indicators,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn25" n="24"> Lorenčič,
                                <seg rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Prelom s starim in začetek novega. </seg></note>
                    showed the successful realisation of the country’s development model that was
                    set a decade ago, which was focused on the economic and international
                    consolidation and stabilisation of the country.</p>
                <p> In contrast to the increasingly numerous internal political affairs and party conflicts, decreased trust in the fundamental political institutions and lower electoral participation were notable in this period and thus influenced the processes of democratic political institution consolidation. Most
                    notably, in 2003, Udba.net media archive was released by the right-wing parties,
                    which referred to the list of previous employees in the communist times.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn26" n="25"> Ali H.
                            Žerdin, "Udba.net,"<hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Udba.net | MLADINA.si, </hi>available
                            at: <ref
                                target="http://www.mladina.si/61653/18-04-2003-udba_net/?utm_source=dnevnik%2F18-04-2003-udba_net%2F&amp;utm_medium=web&amp;utm_campaign=oldLink"
                                >http://www.mladina.si/61653/18-04-2003-udba_net/?utm_source=dnevnik%2F18-04-2003-udba_net%2F&amp;utm_medium=web&amp;utm_campaign=oldLink</ref>.</note>
                    Parallel to this, some other examples of pre-election and election allegations
                    of appointing political staffing<note place="foot"
                            xml:id="ftn27" n="26"> More details in <hi rend="italic">STA</hi> (Arhiv
                            novic), accesed 30 June 2016, URL: <ref target="https://www.sta.si/"
                                >https://www.sta.si/</ref>.</note> were present. From the stated internal and mutual party
                    relation perspective, the <hi rend="background(white)">Slovenian political
                        development first showed bigger democratic wounds and prevented a smooth
                        continuation of democratic growth.</hi>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Parliament 2004–2008</head>
                <p> After the fourth elections in 2004, the mandate to form the government was taken
                    over by the centre-right coalition for the first time. The governmental
                    coalition included the election winner, SDS, the right parties, NSi and SLS, and
                    the centrist DeSUS party. All parties had already had prior experience in the
                    previous coalitions. </p>
                <p> The country had successfully completed the process of integration and entry into
                    the international arena during this term, which they did by adopting the
                    European currency, the Euro, presiding, as the first CEE member state, to the
                    Council of the EU in 2008 and implementing the so-called ‘borderline rules’ of
                    the Schengen area.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn28"
                            n="27"> Note 26.</note> The initial development model in the
                    economic, social and international segments was successfully completed.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn29" n="28"> Note
                            24.</note> However, the consolidation of the state and government
                    democratic structures, on the other hand, could not be confirmed. The mandate
                    was influenced by a number of internal and international high-profile affairs,
                    such as regulating the problems of the Roma people, the rights violations of the
                    so-called ‘erased’, the beginning of the Partia affair, the Piranski zaliv
                    affair and numerous personnel changes, which were thought to be linked with the
                    political parties.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn30"
                            n="29"> Note 26.</note> Despite the fact that all of the democratic
                    institutions had been established for over a decade and a half following the
                    country’s independence, their final consolidation and credibility was constantly
                    undermined by a number of internal scandals and affairs, conflicts, personnel
                    exchanges and, with that, logically related institutional instability. All of
                    this had the same common denominator: the parliamentary and, specifically, the
                    ruling government political parties’ uncertainties.</p>
                <p> In this term, internal coalition disagreements culminated again half a year
                    before the next elections, with the vote of confidence in the parliament. The
                    tensions of the coalition partners SLS and DeSUS complicated the internal
                    coalition relations, as did a new proposal by the prime minister to vote for the
                    future of this government. The government passed a vote of confidence and was
                    the only one in the country’s current government and parliamentary history to
                    endure over the same coalition structure until the end of the regular term.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Parliament 2008–2011</head>
                <p> The fifth parliamentary elections were marked by a tight election result. The
                    mandate to form a government was again assigned to the coalition of the leftist
                    parties. The coalition was included the leading Social Democratic party, SD,
                    which led the government for the first time; the barely elected LDS; the newly
                    established political party, Zares (although the majority of the Zares consisted
                    of members of the old LDS); and the permanent coalition partner, DeSUS. </p>
                <p> This period, despite the programme affinity and the manageable number of
                    coalition partners, was characterized by continuous internal issues, coalition
                    unrest and scandals. Furthermore, this period was also affected by the global
                    economic crisis, to which the country had responded with excessive borrowing,
                    thereby putting a growing burden on the national budget.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn31" n="30"> Boštjan Noč, <hi rend="italic">Kazalniki zadolženosti
                            Slovenije</hi>. Paper, prepared for the Conference Statistični dnevi,
                        2011, accesed 20 May 2016, URL: <ref
                            target="http://www.stat.si/StatisticniDnevi/Docs/Radenci2011/Noc-Kazalniki_zadolzenosti-prispevek.pdf"
                            >http://www.stat.si/StatisticniDnevi/Docs/Radenci2011/Noc-Kazalniki_zadolzenosti-prispevek.pdf</ref>.</note></p>
                <p> Initial personnel moves by Prime Minister Borut Pahor led to the coalition
                    partners’ request to convene an extraordinary session of the coalition summit in
                    2009. A wave of resignations from ministers and other high officials followed in
                    2010. Almost one-third of the ministers were replaced. Resignations continued in
                    2011, following the resignation of the Minister of Higher Education, Science and
                    Technology and the president of the Zares party. Interpellations were actively
                    filled, and all governmental reform proposals were obstructed by the opposition;
                    later, proposals were also obstructed by the voters on the
                    referenda.<hi rend="highlight" xml:space="preserve"> Six referendums were tendered during this parliamentary term, namely, arbitration, reform referendums on the mini jobs, a pension reform referendum and a referendum on the </hi>Law
                    on the Prevention of Labour and Employment in the black, <hi rend="highlight">as
                        well as a referendum on the RTV contribution and archives.</hi><note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn32" n="31">Simona Kustec Lipicer and Niko Toš,
                        "Analiza volilnega vedenja in izbir na prvih predčasnih volitvah v Državni
                        zbor," <hi rend="italic">Teorija in praksa</hi> 50, No. 3-4 (May-August
                        2013): 503–29, 685.</note></p>
                <p> This mandate was also marked by a number of internal political scandals in
                    addition to the aforementioned personnel affairs – for example, the unsuccessful
                    rehabilitation of the banking system; the construction of the sixth block of the
                    Šoštanj Thermal Power Plant; the insolvency of once successful companies, such
                    as Vegrad, Istrabenz, Mura; and government Falcon aircraft. Other corruption
                    scandals included the bullmastiffs affair, the Ultra affair, the rental of the
                    National Bureau of Investigation premises and the
                    <hi rend="highlight" xml:space="preserve">Dimic affair. </hi></p>
                <p> In terms of Slovenia’s international activities, this mandate was marked by the
                    agreement of the Republic of Slovenia’s and the Republic of Croatia’s prime
                    ministers in November 2009, which stated that open border conflict issues would
                    be resolved through international arbitration. Besides this, the appearance of
                    the top Slovenian politicians in the international arena visibly faded in all
                    other topics. Civil servants were often involved in political decision-making
                    processes on behalf of the state, or the state was not represented in
                    aforementioned processes.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn33" n="32"> Damjan Lajh
                        and Zdravko Petak, eds., <hi rend="italic">EU Public Policies Seen from a
                            National Perspective. Slovenia and Croatia in the European Union</hi>
                        (Ljubljana: Fakulteta za družbene vede, 2015).</note> The situation above
                    was expressed when first DeSUS and later Zares resigned from the coalition a
                    year before the new election was called. The National Assembly requested for a
                    vote of confidence on the Prime Minister’s proposal and, for the second time in
                    history, the government did not pass the vote. Therefore, the President of the
                    Republic convened the first early elections for autumn 2011. </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Parliament 2011–2014</head>
                <p> The results of the 2011 autumn elections brought a major twist to the
                    parliamentary political arena. Competition for votes between old and successful
                    new political parties became a pure fact, with the new ones gaining more and
                    more electorate trust. </p>
                <p> Despite the very real prospect of early parliamentary elections, political
                    parties were not as sufficiently prepared, either financially or
                    organisationally, as the political parties in the previous National Assembly
                    elections. The role of the two new political parties established just before the
                    elections – left-positive Slovenia (PS) and centre-right Civic List (DL)<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn34" n="33"> The Movement for Sustainable Development
                        of Slovenia (TRS) was established as an alternative to the party system in
                        October 2011. The Party for Sustainable Development of Slovenia was then
                        formed from the political wing of the movement. The mentioned political
                        party participated in the parliamentary elections in 2011, but, despite
                        initial good opinion polls and prognoses, did not exceed the threshold for
                        entry into parliament. However, it did achieve a comparable election result
                        as the old, once successful parties SNS and LDS and a half higher result
                        than the former parliamentary coalition party Zares. The TRS members were
                        mostly recognisable personalities from public life and value – oriented
                        intellectuals left.</note> – was one of the key innovations of the
                    pre-electoral, the electoral and, subsequently, the post-election period from
                    the party perspective. Both parties personalised their leaders, who were both
                    politically recognisable figures, namely, Zoran Janković, the second-time
                    elected mayor of the capital city of Ljubljana (PS), and Gregor Virant, one of
                    the hitherto most prominent members of the SDS party and the Minister of Public
                    Administration from 2004 to 2008 (DL). These two parties occupied 41 % of all
                    parliamentary seats. For the first time since 1992, after 12 years as the
                    country’s leading government party, the LDS did not pass the electoral
                    threshold. The party received only 1.48 % of the votes. The only national party
                    in Slovenia, the SNS, received only 1.80 % of the votes in the 2011 elections and
                    so did not enter the parliament. Zares, which had been elected into the
                    parliament immediately after its establishment before the 2008 parliamentary
                    elections, also failed to pass the electoral threshold. However, after a
                    three-year break between 2008 and 2011, the NSi reached the electoral threshold
                    and re-entered the parliament. </p>
                <p> The existing old political parties, shocked by the election results but still
                    more politically experienced, formed the government coalition, after the newly
                    established left-wing party PS together with the future members of a coalition
                    failed to nominate the Speaker of the Parliament and afterwards the government.
                    Hence PS left the mandate to the second best party, the experienced right-wing
                    SDS.</p>
                <p> The SDS composed a short-term government with a five-member coalition that was,
                    despite its size, quite close ideologically. The SDS coalition partners were
                    also a new political party, DL, two old right-wing coalition partners SLS and
                    Nsi and a constant in all coalitions present party DeSUS. Soon after the
                    government’s formation, Prime Minister Janez Janša (SDS) was first (and again)
                    accused of direct political intervention in replacements and nomination of
                    staffing since the beginning of the term,<note
                            place="foot" xml:id="ftn35" n="34">
                            <hi rend="italic">Kadrovski blitzkrieg – Mladina.si </hi>, 2012, accesed
                            30 June 2016, URL: <ref
                                target="http://www.mladina.si/109350/kadrovski-blitzkrieg/"
                                >http://www.mladina.si/109350/kadrovski-blitzkrieg/</ref>.</note>
                    and afterwards the Commission for the Prevention of Corruption released a report
                    pointing to the financial accusations against the prime minister and, a few
                    weeks later, the president of PS, the largest parliamentary party,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn36" n="35"> "KPK,"<hi
                                rend="italic">Odločitve in mnenja komisije ǀ Komisija za preprečevanje korupcije</hi>,
                            2012, accesed 20 June 2016, URL: <ref
                                target="https://www.kpk-rs.si/sl/nadzor-in-preiskave/odlocitve-in-mnenja-komisije"
                                >https://www.kpk-rs.si/sl/nadzor-in-preiskave/odlocitve-in-mnenja-komisije</ref><hi rend="Internet_Link" xml:space="preserve">. </hi><hi
                                rend="italic">STA</hi> (Arhiv novic), accesed 30 June 2016, URL:
                            URL: <ref target="https://www.sta.si/">https://www.sta.si/</ref><hi
                                rend="Internet_Link">.</hi></note> which resulted in the
                    resignation of both politicians from their senior positions. Janša resigned as
                    prime minister after the National Assembly rejected the vote of confidence,
                    while Janković temporarily resigned as the PS party president. Leadership of the
                    PS party was temporarily and ‘as a last resort’ left to Alenka Bratušek after
                    the aforementioned incident. Alenka Bratušek became a mandatary and, in March
                    2013, she took over the leadership of the ninth Slovenian government, which was
                    composed of the left-social democratic party SD and former coalition partners DL
                    and DeSUS. However, internal conflicts in the PS, along with the new success of
                    the PS founding president at the party electoral congress, led to the
                    resignation of Prime Minister Bratušek just one year after she took over the
                    government. The President of the Republic called for early elections for the
                    second time in a row in late spring 2013.<note
                            place="foot" xml:id="ftn37" n="36">
                            <hi rend="italic">STA</hi> (Arhiv novic), accesed 30 June 2016, URL:
                                <ref target="https://www.sta.si/">https://www.sta.si/</ref>.</note>
                </p>
                <p> This term was marked by the disability of both governments, which were facing
                    many of their internal and between political parties’ pressures, divisions and
                    ambitions, despite their attempts to solve the economic and financial crisis and
                    their work to return the country to the international arena. However, the
                    biggest international slip at the end of mandate was Bratušek’s self-nomination
                    for the European Commissioner.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn38" n="37"> Note
                        36.</note></p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Parliament 2014 -</head>
                <p> The seventh parliamentary election, which was also the second preliminary
                    election in Slovenia, was implemented at the beginning of summer vacation on
                    July 13, 2014. The election results again followed a similar parliamentary arena
                    patterns as the previous elections. </p>
                <p> The biggest winner of the 2014 elections was the newly established centre Party
                    of Miro Cerar, or the SMC. Once again, this party had been established just
                    before the elections and had one main driving figure: the publicly well-known
                    and respectful constitutional lawyer Miro Cerar. The party gained 40 % of the
                    votes and was renamed the Modern Centre Party in early 2015;it formed a
                    left-centred government coalition in September 2014 together with the left-wing
                    social democrats, SD and DeSUS. </p>
                <p> Insights into the parliamentary arena show that in addition to the SMC, the
                    threshold was as well achieved by two new left-wing parties, the United Left
                    (ZL) and nearly passed the electoral threshold new party of the former prime
                    minister, ZaAB. In contrast to the past elections, these three political parties
                    did not enter the parliamentary arena. Two of them were successful new parties
                    at the former elections and members of the governmental coalition. The third
                    unsuccessful party was the right-positioned SLS, the historically oldest party,
                    as well as a frequent, but generally conflictual, member of many former
                    governmental coalitions. </p>
                <p> Similar to the recent terms of office coalition, work so far has been marked by
                    internal party accusations and tensions, as well as remarks on the lack of
                    leadership capacities. A set of opposition activities has been well activated
                    against the work of the coalition.<note place="foot"
                            xml:id="ftn39" n="38"> Note 36.</note> During the current
                    government activity from autumn of 2014 until nowadays, the public-financial
                    conditions were stabilised, particularly the control over the allowed budget
                    deficit. Additionally, legally transparent frames for managing state assets were
                    accepted, economic growth increased importantly, while unemployment rate
                    decreased to the level before the crisis in 2008. A greater emphasis was placed
                    on the protection and management of natural resources. The government, however,
                    once again more actively cooperates in the international community, particularly
                    through participation in migration policy.<hi rend="Footnote_Anchor"><note
                            place="foot" xml:id="ftn40" n="39">
                            <hi rend="italic">STA</hi> (Arhiv novic), accesed 30 June 2016, URL:
                                <ref target="https://www.sta.si/">https://www.sta.si/</ref><hi
                                rend="Internet_Link">.</hi></note></hi>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Conclusion</head>
                <p> Slovenian’s 25 year-old parliamentary democracy has revealed some patterns
                    throughout its quite active and also turbulent development. These patterns can
                    be divided into two periods: 1) the implementation period for democratic state
                    model and its positioning in the international environment (1992–2008) and 2)
                    the period of internal political and party crises and the search for a new model
                    of growth (2008–present).</p>
                <p> The state democracy’s first period was characterised by a clear and distinct,
                    ideologically distant programme vision, as well as by a focus on the
                    international environment and the internal ability of the political parties and
                    elites to establish the democratic management foundations and the modes of
                    governing. In contrast, the second, still ongoing period is characterised by
                    political parties’ prevailing dominance throughout the political system (or
                    so-called partitocracy).<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn41" n="40"> Note 7.</note>
                    Political parties express tendencies for controlling all of the state
                    (sub)systems, which are not and should not depend on political parties’ policies
                    and influence (e.g. cartelisation patterns).<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn42"
                        n="41"> Note 41.</note> Therefore, political parties are also involved in
                    most of the state's affairs and political staffing. This means that parties do
                    not use their powers and functions to mediate and control the political system’s
                    conflictual issues and problems but are actively helping to shape them. As
                    political parties (as well as individuals in these parties) are still pursuing
                    their own interests, they are constantly causing disagreements and turbulences.
                    Not only does this not lead to forming successful coalition partnerships, it
                    also disables individual party functioning, as well as it also enables the
                    winning potentials of completely new and undefiled parties to enter the
                    parliament or even win the forthcoming elections.</p>
                <p> Effective management of the coalition so far corresponds to the great importance
                    of having individuals in politics whose knowledge and skills correspond to
                    transparent political leadership, as well as the importance of controlling party
                    speculations. These speculations include different kinds of pressure that
                    coalition partners put on a leading party, as well as how some parties
                    tactically chose to resign just before the specific term of government ran out.
                    In this regard, it is clear that political parties forming the governmental
                    coalition play a direct and decisive role in political stability. Hence, in
                    terms of government experience, we can see that the failure of all of the
                    previous coalition governments was directly related to the internal coalition
                    partners’ affairs and disagreements. However, they never directly related to the
                    success of opposition parties’ pressures to the coalition work.</p>
                <p> There are also not real differences possible to detect between left- and right-
                    positioned political parties, in addition to coalitions that<lb/>share the same
                    patterns over time in all of the three analysed arenas. Some differences in this
                    regard could potentially be noticed in the cases of new political parties, but
                    as they would be mostly Mayflys up until today, lacking the capacities and
                    experiences for implementing stable and sustainable democratic stability through
                    their parliamentary group and coalition work, their long-term effect on
                    democracy is mostly unseen. </p>
                <p> With the 1992 elections as a starting point, a total of 148 political parties
                    have competed at the elections, while 51 have constituted the country’s
                    parliamentary arena afterwards. 12 new political parties have been elected to
                    the National Assembly, though 14 of them have not been successful in re-entering
                    the parliament, and only one of the older parties has been voted back into
                    Parliament. Not a single one of the newly elected political parties has been
                    re-elected in the subsequent elections, though the old political parties are on
                    the whole losing their election success with each election cycle. Because of all
                    of the stated, the nature of the Slovenian parliamentary democracy is still
                    considered reasonable, although it signals clear warnings of the risks,
                    especially those of the practices and functions undertaken inside the party
                    arenas. Citizens still recognise political parties as the intermediators between
                    their will and the political institutions’ work. This is still reasonably
                    moderate, although on one hand political participation as seen through election
                    turnout data is constantly falling. On the other hand the share of effective
                    votes is very high, but the volatility rate shows that voters more and more give
                    voice for the political newcomers and activations from the civil society
                    initiatives in the last three terms. </p>
                <p> One of the main findings of the article suggests that political parties in
                    Slovenia remain a fundamentally important pillar of parliamentary democracy, but
                    their roles and activities within the parliamentary, governmental and other
                    arenas increasingly warn of their central mission and democratic system
                    functions. It can be detected that the potentials for electoral uncertainties
                    increase with the intensities of internal and inter-parties’ conflicts which all
                    give
                    <hi rend="short_text" xml:space="preserve">distinctly negative connotation to the country’s parliamentary democracy. </hi></p>
            </div>

        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="bibliography">
                <head>Sources and Literature</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Literature:</head>

                    <bibl>Dalton, Russell J., David M. Farrell and Ian McAllister.<hi rend="italic"
                            >Political parties and democratic linkage. How parties organize
                            democracy</hi>. Oxford: Oxford University Press, 2011.</bibl>
                    <bibl>"European Journal of Political Research."
                            <seg rend="italic">Political Data Yearbook. Slovenia</seg>, 2016.
                            Accesed 20 June 2016. URL: <ref
                            target="http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/journal/10.1111/(ISSN)2047-8852/homepage/slovenia.htm"
                            >http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/journal/10.1111/(ISSN)2047-8852/homepage/slovenia.htm</ref><hi
                            rend="st1">.</hi></bibl>
                    <bibl>Fink - Hafner, Danica. <seg rend="italic normalweight"
                                >Nova družbena gibanja – subjekti politične inovacije</seg>.
                            Ljubljana: Fakulteta za družbene vede, 1992.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Gallagher, Michael, Michael Laver and Peter Mair. <hi rend="italic"
                            >Representative Government in Western Europe</hi>. New York:
                        McGraw-Hill, 2005.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Gašparič, Jure. <hi rend="italic">Slovenski parlament.
                            Politično-zgodovinski pregled od začetka prvega do konca šestega
                            mandata (1992–2014) – 1.0</hi>.
                        Ljubljana: Inštitut za novejšo zgodovino, 2014. Accesed 29 June 2016.
                            URL: <ref target="http://www.sistory.si/SISTORY:ID:26950"
                            >http://www.sistory.si/SISTORY:ID:26950</ref>.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Katz, Richard S. "Party in Democratic Theory." In:
                        <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Handbook of Party Politics, </hi>eds.
                        Richard S. Katz and Daniel Crotty, 34–47. London: Sage, 2006.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Krašovec, Alenka and Ladislav Cabada L. "Kako smo si različni.
                        Značilnosti vladnih koalicij v Sloveniji, Češki republiki in na
                            Slovaškem."<seg rend="italic normalweight">Teorija in praksa</seg> 50,
                        No. 5/6 (2013): 717–35.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Krouwel, Andre. "Party Models." In:
                        <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Handbook of Party Politics, </hi>eds.
                        Richard S. Katz and Daniel Crotty, 249–270. London: Sage, 2006.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Kustec Lipicer, Simona and Andrija Henjak. "Changing dynamics of
                        democratic parliamentary arena in Slovenia. Voters, parties, elections."
                            <seg rend="italic">Prispevki za novejšo zgodovino</seg> 55, No. 3
                        (2015): 84–104.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Kustec Lipicer, Simona and Niko Toš. "Analiza volilnega vedenja in izbir
                        na prvih predčasnih volitvah v Državni zbor." <hi rend="italic">Teorija in
                            praksa</hi> 50, No. 3-4, (May-August 2013): 503–29, 685. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Lajh, Damjan and Zdravko Petak, eds. <hi rend="italic">EU Public Policies
                            Seen from a National Perspective. Slovenia and Croatia in the European
                            Union</hi>. Ljubljana: Fakulteta za družbene vede, 2015.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Ljiphart, Arendt. <hi rend="italic">Patterns of Democracy</hi>. Yale: Yale
                        University Press, 2012. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Lorenčič, Aleksander. <seg rend="italic">Prelom s starim in začetek
                            novega. Tranzicija slovenskega gospodarstva iz socializma v kapitalizem
                            (1990–2004).</seg> Ljubljana: Inštitut za novejšo zgodovino,
                        2012.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Mair, Peter and Ingrid van Biezen. "Partymembership in twenty European
                        democracies, 1980–2000." <hi rend="italic">Party Politics</hi>, No. 7
                        (2011): 5–21.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Mair, Peter. "Party System Change." In:
                        <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Handbook of Party Politics, </hi>eds.
                        Richard S. Katz and Daniel Crotty, 63–75. London: Sage, 2006.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Noč, Boštjan. <hi rend="italic">Kazalniki zadolženosti Slovenije</hi>.
                        Paper, prepared for the Conference Statistični dnevi, 2011. Accesed 20 May
                        2016. URL: <ref
                            target="http://www.stat.si/StatisticniDnevi/Docs/Radenci2011/Noc-Kazalniki_zadolzenosti-prispevek.pdf"
                            >http://www.stat.si/StatisticniDnevi/Docs/Radenci2011/Noc-Kazalniki_zadolzenosti-prispevek.pdf</ref>.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Pečauer, Marko. "Skoraj vsak mandat se konča s krizo." <hi rend="italic"
                            >Delo</hi>, 19 September 2008. Accesed 22 May 2016. URL: <ref
                            target="https://m.delo.si/clanek/174052">https://m.delo.si/clanek/174052</ref>.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Prunk, Janko and Tomaž Deželan, eds. <hi rend="italic">Dvajset let
                            slovenske države</hi>. Maribor: Aristej and Ljubljana: Fakulteta za
                        družbene vede, Center za politološke raziskave, 2012. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Toš, Niko, ed. <hi rend="italic">Vrednote v prehodu VIII. Slovenija v
                            srednje in vzhodnoevropskih primerjavah 1991–2011</hi>. Ljubljana and
                        Wien: Univerza v Ljubljani, Fakulteta za družbene vede and IDV-CJMMK –
                        Edition Echoraum, 2014.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Van Biezen, Ingrid and Richard S. Katz. <hi rend="italic">Democracy and
                            Political Parties</hi>. Paper, prepared for the workshop ‘Democracy and
                        Political Parties’, ECPR Joint Sessions, 2005, 14–19. Granada, April 2005.
                        Available at URL: <ref
                            target="https://ecpr.eu/Filestore/PaperProposal/3402a19c-2e82-4b30-bf30-6a423927d5b0.pdf"
                            >https://ecpr.eu/Filestore/PaperProposal/3402a19c-2e82-4b30-bf30-6a423927d5b0.pdf</ref>.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Ware, Alan. <hi rend="italic">Citizens, parties, and the state. A
                            reappraisal</hi>. Princeton, N. J.: Princeton University Press,
                        1988.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Zajc, Drago, Samo Kropivnik and Simona Kustec Lipicer. <seg rend="italic normalweight">Od volilnih programov do koalicijskih pogodb. Analiza politične
                                kongruence</seg>. Ljubljana: Fakulteta za družbene vede,
                        2012.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Other Sources:</head>
                    <bibl>"Freedom House." <hi rend="italic">Nations in Transit. Slovenia,
                            2016</hi>. Accesed 20 June 2016, URL: <ref
                            target="https://freedomhouse.org/report/nations-transit/2016/slovenia"
                            >https://freedomhouse.org/report/nations-transit/2016/slovenia</ref>.</bibl>
                    <bibl>"<seg rend="normalweight"
                            >KPK.</seg>"<hi
                            rend="italic">Odločitve in mnenja komisije ǀ Komisija za preprečevanje korupcije</hi>,
                        2012. Accesed 20 June 2016. URL: <ref
                            target="https://www.kpk-rs.si/sl/nadzor-in-preiskave/odlocitve-in-mnenja-komisije"
                            >https://www.kpk-rs.si/sl/nadzor-in-preiskave/odlocitve-in-mnenja-komisije</ref>.</bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="italic">Arhiv glavnih novic; Vlada Republike Slovenije</hi>,
                        2016. Accesed 5 July 2016. URL: <ref
                            target="http://www.vlada.si/medijsko_sredisce/glavne_novice/"
                            >http://www.vlada.si/medijsko_sredisce/glavne_novice/</ref>.</bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="italic">Government of the Republic of Slovenia</hi>. Accesed 15
                        September 2016. URL: <ref
                            target="http://www.vlada.si/en/about_the_government/governments_of_the_republic_of_slovenia/"
                            >http://www.vlada.si/en/about_the_government/governments_of_the_republic_of_slovenia/</ref>.</bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="italic">Kadrovski blitzkrieg</hi> – <hi rend="italic"
                            >Mladina.si, </hi>2012. Accesed 30 June 2016. URL: <ref
                            target="http://www.mladina.si/109350/kadrovski-blitzkrieg/"
                            >http://www.mladina.si/109350/kadrovski-blitzkrieg/</ref>.</bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="italic">National Electoral Commission</hi>. Accesed 15 September
                        2016. URL: <ref target="http://www.dvk-rs.si/index.php/en"
                            >http://www.dvk-rs.si/index.php/en</ref>.</bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="italic">Official Gazette of teh Republic of Slovenia</hi>.
                        Accesed 15 September 2016. URL: <ref target="https://www.uradni-list.si/"
                            >https://www.uradni-list.si/</ref>.</bibl>
                    <bibl><seg rend="italic">Reports on National Assembly's
                                work in the parliamentary terms</seg> Accesed 15 September 2016.
                        URL: <ref
                            target="http://www.dz-rs.si/wps/portal/Home/deloDZ/raziskovalnaDejavnost/Knjige"
                            >http://www.dz-rs.si/wps/portal/Home/deloDZ/raziskovalnaDejavnost/Knjige</ref>.<hi rend="outputtext" xml:space="preserve"> </hi>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="italic">STA</hi> (Arhiv novic). Accesed 30 June 2016. URL: <ref
                            target="https://www.sta.si/">https://www.sta.si/</ref>.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Žerdin, Ali H. "Udba.net." <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Udba.net | MLADINA.si. </hi>Accesed
                        21 July 2016. URL: <ref
                            target="http://www.mladina.si/61653/18-04-2003-udba_net/?utm_source=dnevnik%2F18-04-2003-udba_net%2F&amp;utm_medium=web&amp;utm_campaign=oldLink"
                            >http://www.mladina.si/61653/18-04-2003-udba_net/?utm_source=dnevnik%2F18-04-2003-udba_net%2F&amp;utm_medium=web&amp;utm_campaign=oldLink</ref>.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
            <div type="summary" xml:lang="sl">
                <head type="main">OCENA SLOVENSKE PARLAMENTARNE DEMOKRACIJE OB NJENI
                    PETINDVAJSETLETNICI</head>
                <head>POVZETEK</head>
                <docAuthor>Simona Kustec Lipicer</docAuthor>
                <p> Namen članka je oceniti dosedanje prakse slovenske parlamentarne demokracije.
                    Skozi kronološki pregled sprememb in prevladujočih demokratičnih vzorcev vedenja
                    političnih strank preučujemo parlamentarno in vladno delovanje, kot se kaže v
                    državi od prvih parlamentarnih volitev po sprejemu ustave do aktualnega
                    časa.</p>
                <p> Članek je razdeljen v dva večja sklopa, od katerega enega (po obsegu sicer
                    manjšega) predstavlja analiza temeljnih volilnih podatkov, drugega (po obsegu
                    prevladujočega dela besedila) pa prikaz ključnih lastnosti vladnega in s tem
                    posredno tudi parlamentarnega delovanja političnih strank v posameznem mandatnem
                    obdobju, kot jih prikazujejo sekundarna spoznanja že izvedenih raziskovalnih
                    študij ter medijskih zapisov.</p>
                <p> Od prvih demokratičnih volitev po sprejemu slovenske ustave leta 1991 je bilo do
                    danes izvedenih sedem parlamentarnih volitev, oblikovanih pa je bilo deset
                    različnih vlad. Skupaj je na volitvah v preučevanih obdobjih tekmovalo 148
                    političnih strank oziroma v povprečju 20 na posamezne volitve. Od volitev leta
                    1992 dalje je parlamentarni prag prestopilo 51 političnih strank, od njih 12
                    povsem na novo, medtem ko jih 14 na naslednjih volitvah ni bilo ponovno
                    izvoljenih. Stopnja izvoljivosti povsem novih političnih strank v obdobju
                    zadnjih treh volitev izjemno narašča, hkrati pa v tem istem času število
                    tekmujočih strank v primerjavi s prejšnjimi volitvami upade za blizu četrtino
                    (podoben upad beležimo tudi v številu tekmujočih strank med prvimi volitvami
                    leta 1992 in naslednjimi leta 1996). Značilnost parlamentarnega in strankarskega
                    prostora v obdobju zadnjih treh parlamentarnih volitev je tudi izjemen volilni
                    uspeh novih strank ter izraziti neuspeh na naslednjih volitvah, saj do sedaj
                    nobena od njih na naslednjih volitvah ponovno ne prestopi parlamentarnega praga.
                    Iz volitev v volitve prav tako upada volilni uspeh starih strank, ki pa v
                    nasprotju z novimi strankami praviloma presežejo volilni prag, a zasedejo vsakič
                    manj sedežev v parlamentu. Ponovna vrnitev v parlament po predhodnem volilnem
                    neuspehu je do sedaj uspela le politični stranki iz t.i. skupine starih strank
                    ter nobeni od novih. Nasploh je za slovenski parlamentarni prostor značilno, da
                    je stopnja volilne nestanovitnosti (t. i. <hi rend="italic">volatility</hi>) v
                    nasprotju s stabilnimi starejšimi demokracijami visoka. Vidno upada tudi stopnja
                    volilne udeležbe.</p>
                <p> V drugem delu članka del analize dinamike vladnega delovanja in vedenja v
                    posameznem volilnem obdobju, ki je utemeljen prvenstveno na pregledu spoznanj že
                    izvedenih raziskovalnih študij ter medijskih zapisov. V nasprotju s prikazanimi
                    temeljnimi volilnimi podatki, ki se skozi obdobja ne spreminjajo fundamentalno,
                    analiza v drugem delu članka pokaže na bolj živahno, a hkrati tudi vse bolj
                    negativno dinamiko razvoja slovenske strankarske in s tem povezano parlamentarne
                    demokracije. To je glede na vzorce dosedanjih praks in doseženih učinkov možno
                    razdeliti v dve prevladujoči obdobji, in sicer: 1. pozitivno obdobje (1992 –
                    2008), ki ga zaznamuje pretežno predvidljiva osredotočenost države v temeljni
                    demokratični razvoj in povzemanje dobrih demokratičnih praks, aktivno
                    sodelovanje v mednarodnem prostoru, vključno s polnopravnim vstopom države v EU
                    in NATO, poudarek na spoštovanju človekovih pravic ter tržnega liberalizma
                    starih razvitih demokracij; ter. 2. negativno obdobje (2008 - ), ki še vedno
                    traja in ga zaznamuje predvsem čas znotraj in medstrankarskih konfliktov in
                    ozkega zasledovanja lastnih strankarskih interesov, v katerem lastnosti prvega
                    obdobja povsem umanjkajo.</p>
                <p> Ključno spoznanje članka utrjuje spoznanje, da politične stranke v Sloveniji
                    ohranjajo temeljno vlogo gradnika, a tudi krvnika parlamentarne demokracije.
                    Izvajanje njihovih vlog in aktivnosti tako znotraj parlamentarne kot vladne
                    arene v zadnjih obdobjih namreč pospešeno opozarja na premislek o osrednjem
                    poslanstvu ter demokratičnih funkcijah političnih strank. Prav tako je zlasti v
                    zadnjem obdobju možno zaznati, da se možnosti nezanesljivega in nepredvidljivega
                    volilnega rezultata za stranke povečujejo sorazmerno z njihovimi notranjimi ter
                    medstrankarskimi konflikti, ki na parlamentarno demokracijo države mečejo
                    izrazito negativno podobo. </p>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
