<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Socialist Yugoslavia’s Efforts to Democratise International and Intercultural
                    Communication: A Reappraisal<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn1" n="*">This work was
                        financially supported by the Slovenian Research Agency, contract number
                        J5-1793.</note></title>
                <author>
                    <forename>Slavko</forename>
                    <surname>Splichal</surname>
                    <roleName>Dr.</roleName>
                    <roleName>Professor</roleName>
                    <affiliation>University of Ljubljana, Faculty of Social Sciences</affiliation>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Kardeljeva ploščad 5</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>SI-1000 Ljubljana</addrLine>
                    </address>
                    <email>slavko.splichal@fdv.uni-lj.si</email>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>2022-04-21</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>
                    <orgName xml:lang="sl">Inštitut za novejšo zgodovino</orgName>
                    <orgName xml:lang="en">Institute of Contemporary History</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Privoz 11</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>SI-1000 Ljubljana</addrLine>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>http://ojs.inz.si/pnz/article/view/3989</pubPlace>
                <date>2022</date>
                <availability status="free">
                    <licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title xml:lang="sl">Prispevki za novejšo zgodovino</title>
                <title xml:lang="en">Contributions to Contemporary History</title>
                <biblScope unit="volume">62</biblScope>
                <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
                <idno type="ISSN">2463-7807</idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source, born digital.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc xml:lang="en">
                <p>Contributions to Contemporary History is one of the central Slovenian scientific
                    historiographic journals, dedicated to publishing articles from the field of
                    contemporary history (the 19th and 20th century).</p>
                <p>The journal is published three times per year in Slovenian and in the following
                    foreign languages: English, German, Serbian, Croatian, Bosnian, Italian, Slovak
                    and Czech. The articles are all published with abstracts in English and
                    Slovenian as well as summaries in English.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <projectDesc xml:lang="sl">
                <p>Prispevki za novejšo zgodovino je ena osrednjih slovenskih znanstvenih
                    zgodovinopisnih revij, ki objavlja teme s področja novejše zgodovine (19. in 20.
                    stoletje).</p>
                <p>Revija izide trikrat letno v slovenskem jeziku in v naslednjih tujih jezikih:
                    angleščina, nemščina, srbščina, hrvaščina, bosanščina, italijanščina, slovaščina
                    in češčina. Članki izhajajo z izvlečki v angleščini in slovenščini ter povzetki
                    v angleščini.</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="sl"/>
                <language ident="en"/>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords xml:lang="en">
                    <term>Yugoslavia</term>
                    <term>intercultural communication</term>
                    <term>mass media</term>
                    <term>socialism</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords xml:lang="sl">
                    <term>Jugoslavija</term>
                    <term>medkulturno komuniciranje</term>
                    <term>množični mediji</term>
                    <term>socializem</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change>
                    <date>2022-04-28T08:05:34Z</date>
                    <name>Mihael Ojsteršek</name>
                    <desc>Pretvorba iz DOCX v TEI, dodatno kodiranje</desc>
                </change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <docAuthor>Slavko Splichal<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn2" n="**">Professor, Faculty of
                    Social Sciences, University of Ljubljana, Kardeljeva ploščad 5, SI-1000,
                    Ljubljana; <ref target="mailto:slavko.splichal@fdv.uni-lj.si"
                        >slavko.splichal@fdv.uni-lj.si</ref></note>
            </docAuthor>
            <docImprint>
                <idno type="cobissType">Cobiss tip: 1.01</idno>
                <idno type="DOI">doi: https://doi.org/10.51663/pnz.62.1.1</idno>
            </docImprint>
            <div type="abstract" xml:lang="sl">
                <head>IZVLEČEK</head>
                <head><hi rend="italic">PREMISLEK O PRISPEVKIH SOCIALISTIČNE JUGOSLAVIJE K
                        MEDNARODNEMU IN MEDKULTURNEMU KOMUNICIRANJU</hi></head>
                <p><hi rend="italic">V tem članku predstavljam (ponovno) branje nekaterih svojih
                        raziskav in razprav o množičnem komuniciranju in razvoju socialistične
                        demokracije v Jugoslaviji, objavljenih v zadnjih dveh desetletjih obstoja
                        večnacionalne federacije pred njenim nenadnim in nasilnim propadom. Članek
                        je zasnovan kot ponovna presoja ključnih idej in rezultatov nekaterih
                        empiričnih raziskav, ki sem jih zasnoval in izvajal v sedemdesetih in
                        osemdesetih letih prejšnjega stoletja do osamosvojitve Slovenije leta 1991.
                        Vključujejo več različnih tematik, kot so komuniciranje med republikami v
                        Jugoslaviji, tuja radijska propaganda in delovanje tiskovne agencije Tanjug,
                        zbiranje novic in redakcijsko odbiranje ter razvoj komunikologije kot
                        znanstvene discipline v Jugoslaviji.</hi></p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Ključne besede: Jugoslavija, medkulturno komuniciranje,
                        množični mediji, socializem</hi></p>
            </div>
            <div type="abstract" xml:lang="en">
                <head>ABSTRACT</head>
                <p><hi rend="italic">In this article, I present an annotated (re)reading of selected
                        research and writings on mass communication and the development of socialist
                        democracy in Yugoslavia that I published in the final 20 years of this
                        multinational federation’s existence prior to its sudden and violent
                        collapse. The article is conceived as a reappraisal of key ideas and results
                        of certain research I designed and conducted in the 1970s and 1980s up until
                        Slovenia attained its independence in 1991. They include a range of diverse
                        topics like communication among the republics in Yugoslavia, foreign radio
                        propaganda, news gathering and editorial gate-keeping, the performance of
                        the Tanjug news agency, as well as the development of communication science
                        as a scientific discipline in the federation.</hi></p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Keywords: Yugoslavia, intercultural communication, mass media,
                        socialism</hi></p>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div>
                <head>Introduction</head>
                <p>In this article, I present an annotated reading of selected research and writings
                    on mass communication and the development of socialist democracy in Yugoslavia
                    that I published during the final 20 years of this multinational federation’s
                    existence before its sudden and violent collapse. The article is conceived as a
                    reappraisal of key ideas and results of certain empirical research I designed
                    and conducted in the 1970s and 1980s up until Slovenia’s independence in 1991.
                    They include diverse topics like communication among the republics in
                    Yugoslavia, foreign radio propaganda, news gathering and editorial gate-keeping,
                    the performance of the Tanjug news agency, along with the development of
                    communication science as a scientific discipline in Yugoslavia. This reappraisal
                    is not meant to replace a systematic review and comprehensive analysis of the
                    topics and approaches, unity and differences in mass communication research
                    during socialist Yugoslavia and does not pretend to represent the entirety of
                    media research in the federation. However, a review of my personal research
                    efforts and publications over the last two decades of the former state can
                    reveal at least two things. It first indicates which topics were considered
                    relevant in scientific terms. In addition, given that most empirical research
                    was publicly funded, it also (at least partly) indicates which research topics
                    were then considered socially (and politically) legitimate.</p>
                <p>The Yugoslav communication system(s), like the political system of socialist
                    self-management, was born following the liberation and social revolution
                    completed after the Second World War and after the ideological and political
                    conflict with the Soviet Union and expulsion from the socialist bloc in 1948.
                    The early development of the press and radio in the new Yugoslavia unfolded in
                    the framework of state-party centralism and the revolutionary system of
                    agitation and propaganda, and was burdened by traditional revolutionary notions
                    of the transmission role of the press as part of the political avant-garde of
                    the working class. The steady transition from autocratic communication to forms
                    of socialisation and democratic communication intensified after the 1974
                    Yugoslav Constitution. Greater autonomy of the constituent federal units
                    (republics) and the self-management of state-owned enterprises and institutions
                    was introduced by the Constitution, yet they remained difficult and
                    controversial. The relationships among the republics were always marked by their
                    great economic and cultural differences. The differences resulting from the
                    different political interests of the republics, which were becoming stronger,
                    led to growing conflicts between them and made it hard to establish common
                    interests and benefits that everyone would recognise, with the ‘national
                    question’, and even the interethnic political conflicts that remained unresolved
                    until the federation’s demise.</p>
                <p>At the same time, ideologised notions of the unreserved and uncontroversial
                    self-governing development of communication, the uniqueness of the Yugoslav
                    socialist paradigm of the future and its incomparability with the development of
                    other social and communication systems in the world were gaining ground in
                    Yugoslavia’s development. The maintenance of a normative ‘understanding’ of
                    development and its planning, which did allow for new perspectives and
                    alternatives to development, was facilitated by the absence of critical
                    self-reflection, a forward-looking consideration of both the future and the
                    ‘outside’ world that we were in permanent – albeit often denied –
                    interdependence. The development of mass communication in Yugoslavia was also
                    challenged from the outside by the developed communication systems of societies
                    that had already moved into the new historical formation of the ‘information
                    society’ with modern information technology and information processes,
                    participatory communication, and a culture of political dialogue. While the
                    socialist authorities had invested in developing media from the very beginning,
                    the lack of economic development, technical infrastructure and skilled
                    journalists in the early stages hampered this development. Inter-republics
                    differences in development were also visible in the increase in communication
                    inequality, while the population’s national and linguistic diversity on the
                    other hand also spurred the development of media pluralism in federal units.
                    Apart from a short period of time in the 1940s, Yugoslavia did not have federal
                    media able to spread the same content across the country: the media, like
                    culture, education and research, was the sole responsibility of the republics
                    and their authorities. The only real exception was television news since the
                    republics gradually introduced new broadcasting technology and built production
                    facilities, and in the period before national television programmes were fully
                    established, the TV broadcasters of the republics retransmitted the news
                    produced by Serbian Television (TV Belgrade) in Serbo-Croatian, as the common
                    language of Croats, Montenegrins and Serbs was then called.</p>
                <p>When I entered the field of media studies as a young researcher, my international
                    experience was modest, yet very inspiring. As an undergraduate, I had an
                    opportunity to listen to lectures by foreign visiting professors, including
                    Dallas Smythe, and I assisted Professor Alex Edelstein in conducting surveys on
                    interpersonal communication and decision-making in Ljubljana. Soon after I
                    started to work for the University of Ljubljana in July 1971, I participated in
                    an international summer school on international journalism on the Croatian
                    island of Dugi otok in the Adriatic Sea, where most of the around 20
                    participants came from the USA, and one lecturer was Jim Halloran, president of
                    the IAMCR, who had made an important contribution to audience research and the
                    establishment of media studies as a research field. Generally, I can say that I
                    was brought up with a very liberal attitude to ‘bourgeois science’. I developed
                    my critical-Marxist orientation only after completing my master’s degree in
                    1974, when I started writing my doctoral dissertation on mass communication,
                    human freedom and alienation, defended in 1979 and published in Slovenian in
                        1981.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn3" n="1">Slavko Splichal, <hi
                            rend="italic">Množično in javno komuniciranje: od množičnega
                            komuniciranja kot negacije javnega v razvitem kapitalizmu do možnosti za
                            vzpostavitev njune enotnosti v samoupravni socialistični
                            demokraciji</hi>: <hi rend="italic">doktorska disertacija</hi>
                        (Ljubljana: Fakulteta za sociologijo, politične vede in novinarstvo; S.
                        Splichal, 1979). Slavko Splichal, <hi rend="italic">Množično komuniciranje
                            med svobodo in odtujitvijo</hi> (Maribor: Obzorja, 1981).</note></p>
                <p>Following my early liberal experiences in the early 1970s, my first live
                    encounter with an international conference – the 1974 IAMCR conference at Karl
                    Marx University in Leipzig, then German Democratic Republic – in which I
                    participated as an aspiring research assistant with a paper on international
                    radio propaganda, made me quite frustrated. On one hand, I acquired first-hand
                    experience of real ‘ideological imbalances’ as I listened to the ideologically
                    orchestrated presentations and discussions of the Eastern European and Russian
                    participants. Still, it was releasing to listen to prominent critical scholars
                    like Dallas Smythe and Herb Schiller in an open-stage dialogue criticising
                    representatives of conservative/administrative empirical research represented by
                    Elisabeth Noelle Neumann. <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn4" n="2"><hi
                            rend="italic">Anteil der Massenmedien bei der Herausbildung des
                            Bewußtseins in der sich wandelnden Welt,</hi> Internationale
                        wissenschaftliche Konferenz, IX. Generalversammlung der AIERI, Leipzig
                        (DDR), 17. 9. – 21. 9. 1974, 2 Bde. (Leipzig: Sektion Journalistik, VDJ der
                        DDR, AIERI, 1975). </note> This was undoubtedly a turning point in my
                    research career, later most clearly expressed in my doctoral dissertation.</p>
                <p>While my early research was largely empirically based, interest in theoretical
                    conceptualisations later prevailed, although I always remained in close contact
                    with methodology and empirical research. In fact, in socialism there was a
                    natural alliance between empirical and critical research, as opposed to
                    capitalism where empirical research is more often associated with administrative
                    research. In what follows, I look back at 20 years of communication research in
                    Yugoslavia, in which I was directly involved, to present selected findings that
                    shed light on the controversies surrounding media development in socialist
                    Yugoslavia. After briefly discussing the beginnings of media and communication
                    research in Yugoslavia and Slovenia, I review research projects on foreign
                    propaganda against Yugoslavia, news gathering and selection in both RTV
                    Ljubljana and Tanjug, and intercultural information and communication flows in
                    Yugoslavia, which I carried out in the 1970s and 1980s.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>The Pitfalls of Media Research in Socialist Yugoslavia</head>
                <p>While the development of society in most areas from the economy to education was
                    dominated by socialist ideas and regulated by the Communist Party (renamed the
                    League of Communists in 1952), media research that began in the 1960s has only
                    exceptionally been under such a strong influence. The development of the new
                    discipline or field of media and communication research in Yugoslavia was
                    largely marked by “productive inclusivism” or eclecticism, a kind of
                    ‘cohabitation’ of different communication schools and theoretical paradigms that
                    had contributed to its definition, development and institutionalisation at
                    universities. This was primarily due to the absence of original ‘Marxist
                    thought’ in (mass) communication theories on which the discipline’s development
                    could have been based or subordinated to, thereby making the new discipline
                    significantly different from many other disciplines like sociology, in which
                    such a ‘gold standard’ existed. In its early beginnings in Yugoslavia, for
                    example, sociology was often labelled a bourgeois science by the League of
                    Communists’ ideological authorities. To counter this view (with potentially
                    dangerous consequences) and to prove sociology's progressive or Marxist
                    character, sociological authors regularly cited Marx’s works. As reported by
                    Milić, out of 20 classical sociological theorists, including Durkheim, Habermas,
                    Lorenz, Mills, Parsons, Sorokin and Weber, 30% of all citations in Yugoslav
                    sociological articles between 1966 and 1985 referred to Marx. <note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn5" n="3">Vojin Milić, “Primena nekih bibliometrijskih i
                        prosopografskih postupaka u proučavanju istorije sociologije,” <hi
                            rend="italic">Sociološki pregled</hi> 12, No. 1–2 (1988): 73–98.</note>
                    In contrast, in a similar analysis of articles on media and communications
                    published in Yugoslav scientific journals between 1965 and 1986, just 4.6% of
                    citations referred to Marx, even though he still stood out as the most cited
                    author. <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn6" n="4">Slavko Splichal, “Indigenisation
                        vs. Ideologisation: Communication Science on the Periphery,” <hi
                            rend="italic">European Journal of Communication</hi> 4, No. 3 (1994):
                        329–59.</note> Contrary to sociology, it would be difficult to argue that
                    Marx(ist) theory – despite the significance of Marx’s early debates on freedom
                    of the press and his later writings on ideology and political economy – could
                    prevail over all other contributions to the field of communication, and thus
                    become the main or even only theoretical foundation for the new discipline's <hi
                        rend="italic">definition</hi>, <hi rend="italic">development</hi> and
                    academic <hi rend="italic">institutionalisation</hi>.</p>
                <p>Like other socialist countries of the twentieth century, political bureaucracies
                    in Slovenia and Yugoslavia were particularly suspicious of empirical research.
                    From the very beginning and for a long time, sociology was seen as a ‘bourgeois
                    science’ and restrictively integrated into academic life, as opposed to the
                    ideologically preferred political sciences. Later, this anti-Marxist ‘class
                    character’ was especially attributed to its empirical – considered <hi
                        rend="italic">administrative</hi> – research, notably surveys. Yet, in fact,
                    empirical research in the former socialist societies often acted as a critical
                    impulse against ideologised abstract social sciences, against formalism and
                    simplified generalisations, and was aimed at investigating differences in
                    interests and social contradictions in the processes of socialism's
                    development.</p>
                <p>It should thus come as no surprise that not only books but also the vast majority
                    of communication-related journal articles published in this period were not the
                    result of empirical research. Between 1964 and 1986, just 18.7% of 311 articles
                    related to (mass) communication, as published by 181 authors in 32 Yugoslav
                    social science journals, had an empirical character, a further 7.7% were both
                    theoretical and empirical, yet only 7.1% of them included statistical data
                        analysis.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn7" n="5">Ibidem.</note> The first
                    media-related empirical studies in Yugoslavia were published as late as in 1969,
                    and dominated the scene during the short period of democratisation until 1974
                    (particularly reporting social survey and audience research results), but after
                    1975 they almost disappeared for some time.</p>
                <p>During socialism in Yugoslavia, theoretical, often intuitive-speculative
                    approaches combined with normative idealism generally dominated in the scholarly
                    books and journal articles on communications. The prevalence of an
                    intuitive/speculative approach over robust theoretical approaches was reflected
                    in the fact that of all 311 articles included in a 23-year analysis between 1964
                    and 1986, a mere 2.9% comprised a critical assessment of the theory applied or
                    elaborated on. In total, almost 57% of the citations referred to original
                    publications (44.5%) or translations (12%) in Yugoslav languages. The most often
                    cited media and communication scholars in this period were members of diverse
                    schools of thought, such as Critical Theory (Adorno, Habermas, Enzensberger,
                    Bourdieu), Functionalism (Katz, Lasswell, Lazarsfeld, Merton, Schramm, Riley)
                    and “productive inclusivism” (McLuhan, McQuail, Kayser, Cazeneuve, Weiss).
                    Despite bureaucratic pressures, a kind of ‘cohabitation’ of communication
                    paradigms existed, although they were not equally widespread.</p>
                <p>Nevertheless, the authors most frequently referred to were ‘classical Marxists’
                    (Marx, Engels, Lenin) and top Yugoslav politicians (Tito, Kardelj, Šetinc,
                    Vlahović). Particularly in the late 1970s, citations reflecting the ‘arguments’
                    of authorities dominated: in addition to Marx, Edvard Kardelj, the leading
                    Yugoslav party ideologue, was the most often cited author during this period,
                    partly ‘explaining’ the absence of ‘the critical’ in theoretical essays. Papers
                    referring to Marx and Critical Theory could hardly be seen as a systematic
                    “critique of bourgeois mass communication research”, as conceptualised, for
                    example, by Lothar Bisky in the German Democratic Republic.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn8" n="6">Lothar Bisky, <hi rend="italic">Zur Kritik der
                            bürgerlichen Massenkommunikationsforschung</hi> (Berlin, DDR: VEB
                        Deutscher Verlag der Wissenschaften, 1974). </note> Citations of Marxist
                    authors gave no evidence of intellectual commitment to their works. They were
                    often quoted more to ‘legitimise’ their political correctness than
                    substantiating the theoretical relevance of a particular contribution.</p>
                <p>A similar pattern emerged in the organisation of scientific conferences, with
                    reference to the League of Communists' documents and doctrines serving as proof
                    of the social legitimacy (and political correctness) of research. For instance,
                    at the Yugoslav Conference on Inter-Republican Communication held in April 1975,
                    in his opening presentation Firdus Džinić discussed the “ideological basis of
                    inter-republican communication in the documents of the 10 <hi rend="superscript"
                        >th</hi> congress of the League of Communists of Yugoslavia”.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn9" n="7">Tomo Martelanc, “Jugoslovansko posvetovanje
                        o medrepubliškem komuniciranju,” <hi rend="italic">Teorija in praksa</hi>
                        12, No. 4–5 (1975): 527–30.</note> Džinić emphasised that the Yugoslav
                    information system should be built according to the attitudes approved by the
                    10th Congress of the Yugoslav League of Communists and on a unified ideological
                    basis as an integral part of the socialist, self-governing socio-political
                    system. It was supposed to enable the ‘free flow’ of information between
                    individual parts of Yugoslavia, which would practically mean that no “closed
                    communication areas” would exist.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn10" n="8"> Ibid.,
                        528.</note> Following this obligatory reference to party ideology, the
                    conference was conducted according to routine scientific standards. Despite the
                    widespread belief in the West at the time that research findings were
                    questionable because of Marxist influence and “an ideological imbalance toward
                    the left because of the political orientation” of Yugoslavia,<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn11" n="9">Stanley Smith, “Mass Media and International
                        Understanding by France Vreg,” <hi rend="italic">International and
                            Intercultural Communication Annual</hi>, Vol. 6, ed. Nemi C. Jain
                        (Annandale, Va.: Speech Communication Association, 1982), 116–19. </note>
                    this could not be proven in empirical research. On the contrary, and not always
                    without reason, bureaucratic party critics pointed to the “positivist and
                    functionalist methods” used in empirical research, along with “revisionist
                    theories”, “technocratic liberalism”, and “abstract humanism”. Western concerns
                    with “ideological imbalances toward the left”, whatever that may have meant,
                    were especially absurd in light of the administrative measures taken against the
                    social sciences in several Yugoslav republics. The official ideological critique
                    also endangered the university programme for journalism in Ljubljana, as it was
                    said to be impregnated with “positivism and bourgeois theories”. The Director of
                    the Yugoslav Institute of Journalism in Belgrade wrote a letter to Slovenian
                    authorities “denouncing Vreg’s communication theory as non-Marxist and proposing
                    that Slovenian journalists should be trained in Belgrade”. <note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn12" n="10">France Vreg, “Trideset let komunikacijske znanosti na
                        Slovenskem,” <hi rend="italic">Teorija in praksa</hi> 28, No. 8-9 (1991):
                        1018–24, 1021.</note> As I recall, he also denounced the UNESCO-funded study
                    of foreign radio propaganda in Yugoslavia<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn13"
                        n="11">Tomo Martelanc, Slavko Splichal, Breda Pavlič, Anuška Ferligoj, Vlado
                        Batagelj and Mojca Drčar Murko, <hi rend="italic">External Radio
                            Broadcasting and International Understanding: Broadcasting to
                            Yugoslavia</hi>. <hi rend="italic">Reports and papers in mass
                            communication</hi>, No. 81 (Paris: UNESCO, 1977).</note> conducted by
                    the Faculty of Sociology, Political Science and Journalism at that time as being
                    a threat to national security.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>News Gatekeeping Studies and the Role of the Tanjug News Agency</head>
                <p>Notwithstanding ideological and political obstacles, empirical research into the
                    media in Yugoslavia had advanced considerably since the late 1960s. I first
                    encountered empirical media research while completing my journalism studies in
                    the early 1970s as an associate in the Programme Studies Department (PSD) at the
                    Slovenian national public broadcaster Radio-Television Ljubljana. Lado Pohar, a
                    former journalist and correspondent from the USA, the first head of Television
                    Ljubljana, who was the initiator and first leader of the PSD and conducted some
                    audience research with external collaborators even before the department was
                    formally established, held a very ambitious vison of the newly established
                    research department: “Our goal is to help the institute achieve even greater
                    openness in communicating with the audience, and to enable the audience to have
                    an even more important impact on the programme. At the same time, we want to
                    complement if not replace the intuition in the daily programming and directing
                    the development of the policy of both media in our country with the findings of
                    communication research and other sciences” <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn14"
                        n="12">Vida Šrot, “Zgodovina raziskovanja RTV programov in občinstva: Služba
                        za študĳ programa in njeni nasledniki,” <hi rend="italic">Javnost – The
                            Public</hi> 15, supplement (2008): 133–50, 134. Lado Pohar, <hi
                            rend="italic">Problematika Službe za študij programa</hi> (mimeo)
                        (Ljubljana: Služba za študij programa, RTV Ljubljana, 1975). </note></p>
                <p>Similar research units performing audience and readers surveys and content
                    analysis of newspapers, radio, and television programmes were also set up by
                    public broadcast corporations and major newspapers in other Yugoslav
                        republics.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn15" n="13">Lado Pohar and Tilka
                        Jamnik, <hi rend="italic">Bibliografija raziskav radia in televizije,
                            opravljenih v raziskovalnih centrih jugoslovanskih RTV ustanov v letih
                            1952</hi>–<hi rend="italic">1977, Bilten SŠP</hi>, No. 7 (Ljubljana:
                        Služba za študij programa, RTV Ljubljana, 1978). </note> Yet, following the
                    initial orientation of these departments to enhance the quality of programmes,
                    their operations were more strongly focused on supporting advertising or were
                    discontinued altogether, as occurred with the PSD in Ljubljana.</p>
                <p>Although the research department at Radio and Television Ljubljana mostly
                    administered surveys on listening to and watching radio and television
                    programmes, it also completed more sophisticated empirical research.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn16" n="14">Slavko Splichal, <hi rend="italic"
                            >Socializacijske vsebine na televiziji, Bilten SŠP</hi>, No. 8
                        (Ljubljana: Služba za študij programa, RTV Ljubljana, 1974). Slavko
                        Splichal, <hi rend="italic">Pretok sporočil na radiu in televiziji, Bilten
                            SŠP</hi>, No. 17 (Ljubljana: Služba za študij programa, RTV Ljubljana,
                        1976). </note> In 1973, I designed a gatekeeping study that analysed 9,102
                    news items received by Ljubljana radio and television news programmes from news
                    agencies, Yugoslav RTV centres, journalists, and correspondents in the 2 weeks
                    between 24 September and 7 October. Following editorial decisions, 3,597 news
                    items (39.5%) were broadcast on radio and television news programmes. No
                    significant differences between radio and television news were found in the
                    editorial decision-making criteria, albeit almost twice as much news was used in
                    the radio newsroom (50.3% acceptance rate) than for the television programme
                    (28.5%). In a historical perspective, analysis of a selection of news in
                    retrospect reveals interesting peculiarities in the news values held by the
                    Slovenian (broadcast) media in the 1970s.</p>
                <p>In particular, the analysis shows quantitatively balanced reporting on the three
                    world political blocs of the time – the Western and Eastern blocs and the “Third
                    World” or non-aligned countries. While news input was strongly dominated by
                    reporting on the Western bloc, editorial selection sought to reduce this
                    dominance. Second, and not surprisingly, military conflicts were privileged,
                    followed by international relations, while reporting was the most selective when
                    covering science and culture. I would venture to argue that the priorities today
                    are hardly different. Third, the selection of news in RTV Ljubljana was
                    typically related to sources. At that time, Tanjug also sent its customers a
                    selection of news bulletins of major world press agencies (AFP, AP, UPI, TASS,
                    Reuters) as part of its regularly daily service (representing 30% of the total
                    news supply), which was the only official source for the media, even though they
                    also unofficially observed some foreign agencies. The news selection clearly
                    revealed preferences for AFP, which was a major news source for news from third
                    world countries (60.8% of news items used), followed by Reuters (42.6%), TASS
                    (39.8%), AP (36.9%) and UPI (27.6%). The frequency of selecting news reported by
                    Tanjug's own correspondents was slightly below average (36%). Tanjug was, of
                    course, the most common source of news from Yugoslavia, which relates to another
                    feature of news selection at the time. The news release rate was the lowest in
                    reporting on events from Yugoslavia (compared to Western, Eastern and
                    Third-World “blocs”) and the highest with respect to Slovenia: there was a
                    1.6-times higher probability that news from Slovenia would be selected than news
                    from elsewhere in Yugoslavia. The growing tendency of a relatively weak flow of
                    news and media content within Yugoslavia and people's only slight interest in
                    events in other Yugoslav republics during the 1970s and 1980s was also shown by
                    other analyses and surveys, as discussed later.</p>
                <table rend="rules">
                    <head><hi rend="bold">Table 1</hi>: Structure of incoming and outgoing news and
                        news publication rates in radio and television news broadcasts of RTV
                        Ljubljana (1973; in percent)</head>
                    <row>
                        <cell rend="both"/>
                        <cell rend="both">Input structure</cell>
                        <cell rend="both">Output structure</cell>
                        <cell rend="both">Acceptance rate</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell rend="both">International relations</cell>
                        <cell rend="both">43.3</cell>
                        <cell rend="both">50.6</cell>
                        <cell rend="both">46.1</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell rend="both">Armed conflicts</cell>
                        <cell rend="both"> 5.3</cell>
                        <cell rend="both"> 8.5</cell>
                        <cell rend="both">64.0</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell rend="both">Internal politics &amp; economics</cell>
                        <cell rend="both">25.4</cell>
                        <cell rend="both">25.0</cell>
                        <cell rend="both">38.9</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell rend="both">Culture &amp; science</cell>
                        <cell rend="both"> 8.2</cell>
                        <cell rend="both"> 5.4</cell>
                        <cell rend="both">26.3</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell rend="both">Crime, accidents</cell>
                        <cell rend="both"> 2.5</cell>
                        <cell rend="both"> 1.7</cell>
                        <cell rend="both">28.2</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell rend="both">Other</cell>
                        <cell rend="both">15.0</cell>
                        <cell rend="both">10.0</cell>
                        <cell rend="both">23.1</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="bold">Total news items = 100%</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="bold">9,102</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="bold">3,597</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="bold">39.5</hi></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell rend="both">West</cell>
                        <cell rend="both">39.3</cell>
                        <cell rend="both">39.8</cell>
                        <cell rend="both">40.0</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell rend="both">East</cell>
                        <cell rend="both">20.9</cell>
                        <cell rend="both">23.9</cell>
                        <cell rend="both">45.2</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell rend="both">Third World</cell>
                        <cell rend="both">25.9</cell>
                        <cell rend="both">29.7</cell>
                        <cell rend="both">45.4</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell rend="both">Yugoslavia</cell>
                        <cell rend="both">44.2</cell>
                        <cell rend="both">39.8</cell>
                        <cell rend="both">35.5</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell rend="both">Slovenia</cell>
                        <cell rend="both">13.0</cell>
                        <cell rend="both">18.6</cell>
                        <cell rend="both">56.5</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="bold">TOTAL</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="bold">143.4*</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="bold">151.8*</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="bold">39.5</hi></cell>
                    </row>
                    <note n="*">The total percentage exceeds 100 because each news item could
                        include more than one feature. <lb/>Source: Slavko Splichal, <hi
                            rend="italic">Pretok sporočil na radiu in televiziji</hi>. <hi
                            rend="italic">Bilten SŠP</hi>, No. 17 (Ljubljana: RTV Ljubljana, Služba
                        za študij programa, 1976)</note>
                </table>
                <lb/>
                <p>Immediately after completing the gatekeeping study at RTV Ljubljana, I had an
                    opportunity to design a new study focused on foreign news selection criteria at
                    Tanjug's headquarters. A research project on the Yugoslav news agency Tanjug and
                    the Non-Aligned News Agencies Pool (NANAP, established in 1975) was funded by
                    UNESCO as part of its international communication research programme. Already at
                    the outset, the project drew ideological attacks from Belgrade in particular,
                    claiming the research team was providing (ideological) adversaries with
                    confidential information about the work of both Tanjug and other non-aligned
                    news agencies. Although the criticism was disguised as ideological, it was in
                    fact more an expression of envy regarding the new research group in Ljubljana,
                    which was a threat to the monopoly held by the Belgrade-based Yugoslav Institute
                    of Journalism (JIN) in the area of international cooperation, especially as
                    concerns Tanjug and the non-aligned news pool.</p>
                <p>As the leading agency in the pool, Tanjug became a world-renowned news agency at
                    the time. Its national news services aimed at the Yugoslav media and other
                    (generally political) subscribers relied on three main types of sources in
                    foreign news coverage. In September 1977, the average input in Tanjug totalled
                    3,102 foreign news items per day, of which Tanjug selected 327 or 10.5% for its
                    Yugoslav subscribers. Accounting for 52% of all foreign news delivered, the most
                    important suppliers were the five big international news agencies, AFP, Reuters,
                    TASS, AP and UPI. Tanjug’s own staff of foreign correspondents, numbering 46 by
                    the autumn of 1977, provided 8.3% of the news inflow, while the remaining 34.5%
                    came from 70 national news agencies with which Tanjug was cooperating under a
                    contract.</p>
                <p>In 1963, AP, Reuters, AFP and TASS (UPI did not then exist) supplied Tanjug with
                    over 70% of all news, 5.5% was sent by Tanjug’s own correspondents, 2% was taken
                    from foreign newspapers and radio stations, and the remaining 20% came from all
                    other national agencies. After then, the relative share held by the four major
                    news agencies in Tanjug's structure of incoming foreign news was steadily
                    declining (by almost one-third in 15 years), yet rising in absolute terms. At
                    the same time, the share of national, especially non-aligned, agencies in
                    Tanjug’s news services almost doubled, notably after 1975, when the pool of
                    non-aligned news agencies began operating.</p>
                <p>The 1979 gatekeeping study in Tanjug found that universal selection criteria like
                    ethnocentrism, the economic power of actors reported on, personification or
                    crises and conflicts were not implemented by all agencies. The most significant
                    departure from such universal criteria was seen in the reports of Tanjug and the
                    news agencies of the non-aligned countries. Tanjug’s policy and the non-aligned
                    news agencies’ inclusion in the international news exchange held important
                    consequences for the Yugoslav media. An international comparative study of news
                    exchange conducted in 29 countries around the world <note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn17" n="15"><hi rend="italic">Foreign News in the Media:
                            International Reporting in 29 Countries</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Reports
                            and Papers on Mass Communication</hi>, No. 93 (Paris: UNESCO,
                        1985).</note> found that among all 29 countries Yugoslavia and Poland had
                    reported less news from within its own geopolitical sphere than from any other
                    region. While in most countries the focus was on regional events and news
                    breaking in other parts of the world received only secondary attention, Tanjug
                    supplied Yugoslav media with news on events in the global peripheries.</p>
                <table rend="rules">
                    <head><hi rend="bold">Table 2</hi>: Tanjug’s news sources and news selection by
                        regions (in percent)</head>
                    <row>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(59584D)">Region</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both" cols="9"><hi rend="color(5C5C4F)">Sources of Tanjug’s news
                                services</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(4E4E42)">TOTAL</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(545448)">Discarded news</hi></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell rend="both"/>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(59584E)">Reuters</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(646256)">AP</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(606053)">UPI</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both">AFP</cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(606152)">TASS</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both">POOL</cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(5C5B4E)">Tanjug</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(58584A)">Others East</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(5C5C4F)">Others West</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"/>
                        <cell rend="both"/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(59584D)">Western Europe</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(59584E)">33.1</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(646256)">29.2</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(606053)">34.4</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both">35.9</cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(606152)">19.9</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both">7.4</cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(5C5B4E)">23.9</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(58584A)">14.9</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(5C5C4F)">38.0</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(4E4E42)">25.2</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(545448)">89.0</hi></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(535246)">Eastern Europe</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(5E5C50)">11.1</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(615E53)">13.6</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(5C594F)">9.1</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(5E5E53)">8.9</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(5E5E53)">43.4</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(616153)">1.9</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(535249)">26.8</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(4E4E44)">39.1</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(525245)">2.5</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(504F41)">15.3</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(4F5045)">88.6</hi></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(525046)">Arab countries</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(59584D)">14.3</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(5C5C4E)">14.5</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(5C5C4E)">16.8</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(525046)">17.3</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both">9.5</cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(5B5B4F)">41.9</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(5B584E)">15.9</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(53564A)">6.4</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(535446)">19.4</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(545448)">19.1</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(4B4B40)">89.6</hi></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell rend="left"><hi rend="color(4F4F44)">Asia and Australia</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(585849)">11.9</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(4E4E41)">10.0</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(4E4E41)">7.6</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(4F4F44)">7.0</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(46463C)">7.3</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(525346)">19.3</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(56564A)">8.0</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(535248)">14.7</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both">4.5</cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(505245)">11.1</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(4A4B3F)">90.3</hi></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(4B4A40)">Africa</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(4A4D42)">7.6</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(4A4D42)">4.3</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(4A4D42)">6.5</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(4A4D42)">6.0</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(4A493D)">3.4</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(525246)">5.8</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(535348)">2.4</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(424538)">7.2</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(4E4E45)">3.4</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(46493D)">5.6</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(4A4B41)">91.1</hi></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(4F4F44)">North America</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(5C5C50)">10.8</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(535049)">17.4</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(505044)">19.3</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(545446)">13.9</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(535349)">12.8</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(525346)">6.0</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(56564A)">9.9</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(545345)">5.0</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(524F45)">10.7</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(525245)">11.5</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(4E4E42)">90.0</hi></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(535348)">Latin America</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(545345)">3.5</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(545345)">5.0</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(535348)">2.4</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(545448)">4.7</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(56564B)">1.5</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(525248)">8.3</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(535046)">8.5</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(545345)">3.8</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(4E4D40)">14.9</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(525248)">5.6</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(504F45)">86.0</hi></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(535348)">International
                            organisations</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(545345)">7.6</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(545345)">5.9</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(545345)">3.8</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(545448)">6.3</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(545345)">2.1</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(545345)">9.4</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(545345)">4.6</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(545345)">8.9</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(545345)">6.5</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(545345)">6.6</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(545345)">85.7</hi></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(535348)">N = 100%</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(545345)">12.8</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(545345)">12.3</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(545345)">14.2</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(545448)">12.7</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(545345)">5.3</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(545345)">17.1</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(545345)">8.3</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(545345)">5.9</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(545345)">11.5</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(545345)">100.0</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(545345)">89.0</hi></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(535348)">Discarded news</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(545345)">91.7</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(545345)">91.9</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(545345)">92.5</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(545448)">94.4</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(545345)">96.3</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(545345)">90.3</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(545345)">46.3</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(545345)">98.6</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(545345)">98.7</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both" cols="2"/>
                    </row>
                    <note n="">Source: Slavko Splichal, Mlini na eter: propaganda, reklama in
                        selekcija sporočil v množičnem komuniciranju (Ljubljana: Partizanska knjiga,
                        1984), 34. </note>
                </table>
                <lb/>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Yugoslavia as a Target of Foreign Radio Propaganda</head>
                <p>Despite newer tools of international propaganda emerging in the 1960s and 1970s,
                    international broadcasting more than doubled from 1950 to 1960 and again from
                    1960 to 1970, reaching a total of over 12,000 hours of external radio
                    programming per week. Throughout its existence, Yugoslavia was high on the
                    agenda of international propaganda due to the armed uprising against the German
                    and Italian occupiers and their allies, the socialist revolution and then the
                    conflict with the Soviet Union, and later because of its leading role in the
                    Non-Aligned Movement. After the Second World War and during the Cold War, radio
                    was the most important medium for international propaganda. All major actors in
                    international politics funded the operation of radio propaganda stations, many
                    of which also broadcast in Yugoslav languages.</p>
                <p>Comparative data on audiences and motives for listening to foreign radio stations
                    in Yugoslavia were not systematically collected while the results of surveys
                    conducted by major propaganda stations in Europe (especially the US Radio
                    Liberty broadcasting from the Federal Republic of Germany, and Deutsche Welle)
                    were of dubious value since they were often used for propaganda purposes.
                    Nevertheless, occasional estimates of the number of listeners reveal the
                    importance of international radio propaganda at the time.</p>
                <p>According to a survey conducted by the Belgrade Institute of Social Sciences on a
                    Yugoslav sample, listening to foreign stations halved between 1965 and 1968,
                    from 27% to 15% of the adult population (yet, it is unclear whether the 1968
                    figures were collected before or after the invasion of Czechoslovakia). <note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn18" n="16">Firdus Džinič and Ljiljana Bačević, <hi
                            rend="italic">Inostrana propaganda u Jugoslaviji</hi> (Beograd: Institut
                        društvenih nauka, 1968).</note> During that time, Voice of America, Radio
                    Moscow, Bucharest and Tirana – each from a different ideological grouping – had
                    the largest audiences in Yugoslavia. More than half the listeners of foreign
                    radio stations stated that they listened to more than one foreign station in
                    order to compare news and commentaries from various sources and thereby create a
                    more objective picture, as the vast majority (90%) of listeners believed that
                    foreign stations only sometimes or never reported objectively.</p>
                <figure>
                    <head><hi rend="bold">Table 3</hi>: Amount of external radio broadcasting to
                        Yugoslavia in 1973 (SC = Serbo-Croatian, Slov = Slovenian, Mac = Macedonian;
                        duration in minutes)<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn19" n="17">Martelanc et
                            al., <hi rend="italic">External Radio Broadcasting</hi>,
                        10.</note></head>
                    <graphic n="1001" width="16.002cm" height="9.948333333333334cm"
                        url="media/image1.png" rend="inline"/>
                </figure>
                <p>A postal survey conducted by Deutsche Welle among its listeners in Slovenia in
                    1973 showed a relatively large potential impact of radio propaganda programmes
                    because the number of listeners increased greatly during times of crisis. The
                    survey indicated average annual growth of 2%–5% of their listeners in Slovenia
                    (excluding the simultaneous dropout of listeners), but during periods of crisis
                    the level rose to 11%–16% (e.g. during the fall of Ranković in 1965, the Soviet
                    invasion of Czechoslovakia in 1968, or the Middle East war in 1970). <note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn20" n="18">Slavko Splichal, <hi rend="italic">Mlini
                            na eter: propaganda, reklama in selekcija sporočil v množičnem
                            komuniciranju</hi> (Ljubljana: Partizanska knjiga, 1984).</note> In this
                    light, the decline in listening to foreign radio stations from 41.6% of at least
                    occasional listeners among adult citizens in Slovenia in 1969 to just 19% in
                    1976 detected by the “Slovenian Public Opinion” survey<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn21" n="19">The longitudinal “Slovenian Public Opinion” survey was
                        established in 1968 at the School of Political Sciences in Ljubljana, later
                        transformed into the Faculty of Social Sciences at the University of
                        Ljubljana.</note> should be taken <hi rend="italic">cum grano salis</hi> as
                    it was the first measurement of listening carried out immediately after the
                    Czechoslovak crisis, and the second measurement in a relatively calm political
                    period.</p>
                <p>A critical attitude to the perceived reliability and objectivity of the news not
                    only applied to foreign radio stations, but also the Yugoslav media. In the
                    Slovenian Public Opinion surveys of 1968 and 1972, almost half the respondents
                    agreed that “in our country one must at least sometimes read foreign newspapers,
                    listen to foreign stations or watch foreign television programmes if one wants
                    to be well informed”. The fact that the four most listened to foreign radio
                    stations in Yugoslavia (Voice of America, Moscow, Bucharest, Tirana) came from
                    different ideological clusters suggests that listening to foreign propaganda
                    stations was motivated by the need to compare news and commentary from different
                    sources and not just by general distrust of the domestic media.</p>
                <p>In this context, an analysis of external radio broadcasting to Yugoslavia was
                    conducted. In 1971, UNESCO adopted an international programme for communication
                    research. Within that programme, research into international communication
                    structures was one of the most important themes. The first 3-year project of
                    this programme (1973–1976) was conducted in Slovenia, and I was in charge of
                    designing research to analyse 15 news programmes of foreign radio stations from
                    14 countries broadcast in the Yugoslav languages to different national audiences
                    in socialist Yugoslavia, aiming at identifying the common features and
                    differences in radio propaganda.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn22" n="20">The
                        study was completed in 1977 upon publication of the monograph <hi
                            rend="italic">External Radio Broadcasting and International
                            Understanding: Broadcasting to Yugoslavia</hi> in the “UNESCO Reports
                        and papers in mass communication.”</note> The 1-week analysis was repeated
                    in 1997 on a smaller sample of eight foreign broadcasts in Slovene.</p>
                <p>The analysis was focused on symbols as the most significant indicators of
                    ideological systems (re)presented by propaganda, on the evaluation of subjects
                    of international relations (states and international organisations), and
                    distribution of attention to such subjects’ actions. The main feature of the
                    analysed programmes in two different periods was no doubt the consistent and
                    mutually exclusive evaluative (ideological) orientations of various broadcasts.
                    In both periods of the analysis, external radio programmes for Yugoslavia were
                    clustered using different multivariate methods into two exclusive groups: those
                    of the western versus those of the eastern hemisphere. The temporal changes only
                    concerned differences in the distribution of attention, i.e. the fact that the
                    activity of several subjects in international relations, except of the
                    superpowers, varied between different periods.</p>
                <figure>
                    <head><hi rend="bold">Figure 1</hi>: Point plot of foreign radio stations
                        broadcasting Serbo-Croatian programmes to Yugoslavia in 1973 in the space of
                        the first two orthogonal factors defined by ideological orientation (factor
                        I) and attention to political, economic and cultural events (factor II)
                            <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn23" n="21">Ibid., 20.</note></head>
                    <graphic n="1002" width="10.703277777777778cm" height="10.326311111111112cm"
                        url="media/image2.png" rend="inline">
                        <desc>F:\Documents\001\pic1.png</desc>
                    </graphic>
                </figure>
                <figure>
                    <head><hi rend="bold">Figure 2</hi>: Point plot of radio stations broadcasting
                        Serbo-Croatian programmes to Yugoslavia in 1973 and Slovenian programmes in
                        1997 in the space of the first two orthogonal factors defined by ideological
                        orientation (factor I) and changes in attention to political, economic and
                        cultural events between the two periods (factor II) <note place="foot"
                            xml:id="ftn24" n="22">Slavko Splichal and Anuška Ferligoj, “Ideology in
                            International Propaganda,” in: <hi rend="italic">Sociometric Research:
                                Data Collection and Scaling</hi>, eds. Willem E. Saris and Irmtraud
                            N. Gallhofer (Houndmills: Macmillan Press, 1988), 69–89.</note></head>
                    <graphic url="media/image3.jpeg">
                        <desc>F:\Documents\001\pic2_LI (2).jpg</desc>
                    </graphic>
                </figure>
                <p>The findings of the analysis confirm the significance of propaganda’s ideological
                    dimension, i.e. its subordination to the ruling political and economic
                    interests. This dimension stood out in the sample of radio propaganda stations
                    in each single period as well as cross-time analysis as the factor with the
                    largest explanatory power in factor analysis and the most important
                    discriminatory dimension between clusters obtained by hierarchical agglomerative
                    and local optimisation procedures. The results not only indicated a competitive
                    but an exclusive relationship between the orientations of the capitalist and
                    socialist-oriented groups of propaganda stations. The ideological dimension,
                    while dominant in the programmes of all stations analysed, was more typically
                    discriminatory within the cluster of eastern stations than within the cluster of
                    western ones.</p>
                <p>While none of the analysed stations paid much (or any) attention to the events in
                    Yugoslavia, <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn25" n="23">The only exception was
                        Radio Madrid in 1973, which had a markedly negative assessment of Yugoslav
                        domestic politics and explicitly supported Yugoslav political
                        emigration.</note> they all clearly supplemented the Yugoslav media in terms
                    of their potential (dis)socialising impact on Yugoslav audiences. Foreign
                    programmes aimed at Yugoslav listeners reported on generally the same events as
                    the Yugoslav media did (represented in the sample by the External Service of
                    Radio Belgrade and Radio Ljubljana), without providing any deeper knowledge, yet
                    evaluating them differently and associating them with different values. The
                    distribution of attention to international events and associated actors changed
                    considerably over 4 years (1973–1977), but did not differ significantly between
                    eastern and western stations. Nevertheless, western stations (BBC, Voice of
                    America, Deutsche Welle) were more sensitive to changes over time; their
                    programmes were more focused on current events than on major symbolic or
                    ideological themes that were at the forefront of eastern radio stations
                    (Beijing, Moscow). In contrast, the evaluative/ideological orientations were
                    relatively constant over time in all programmes and varied significantly between
                    the western and eastern stations, thus promoting relatively stable
                    agenda-setting profiles over time. As radio stations sought to convince
                    listeners of what were the most important issues from their particular
                    ideological point of view, the dominant actors and values did not change much
                    over time. This led to relatively stable structural relationships between the
                    radio programmes: while they changed slightly between the two analysed periods,
                    their variability did not have a significant effect on the differences between
                    the programmes.</p>
                <p>The characteristics of the content of individual foreign radio programmes and
                    specific ideological clusters of radio stations differed significantly from the
                    characteristics of the Yugoslav stations (Belgrade and Ljubljana) in each
                    period, thus showing a certain incongruence with the prevalent Yugoslav ideology
                    and potential dissocialising effects upon Yugoslav listeners. The dissonance
                    between the content of the foreign radio broadcasts and the Yugoslav media
                    clearly had potentially negative effects on the target communication system.
                    Potentially negative effects increase along with the increase in development
                    level of the transmitting and receiving communication system. The relatively
                    high level of development and openness of the Yugoslav communication system
                    meant that this problem did not reach critical proportions in Yugoslavia. Still,
                    the consequences could be significantly more serious for less developed
                    countries, which was the main reason for the initiative for non-aligned
                    countries to collaborate in the communication field and on the creation of a new
                    global information and communication order in the 1970s.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Intercultural Communication in Yugoslavia</head>
                <p>While Yugoslavia had taken decisive action to improve the imbalanced flow of news
                    from around the world, it failed to effectively address the same problem at
                    home. Yugoslavia was not only very different in many respects, including
                    different religions, languages and alphabets, but was also very differently
                    developed economically. Among other things, Yugoslavia was characterised by an
                    “unbalanced flow of news” between the six republics and two autonomous
                    provinces, a problem resembling the challenge that the Yugoslav state, together
                    with the Non-Aligned Movement, sought to address by establishing a pool of
                    non-aligned news agencies. Like the fields of culture, art, education, science
                    and, in part, sports, the media was the domain of republican policies and
                    regulations. Following amendments to the Federal Constitution of 1971,
                    regulation of the media was transferred to the individual republics’ legislation
                    such that the federation only remained responsible for regulating international
                    communication and criminal law for communication offences. After many years of
                    discussions, the Federal Law on the Foundations of the Public Information System
                    was adopted in 1985, intended to bring about greater unity in the normative
                    regulation of relations in the communications sphere. The new law established
                    the basic principles of “public information” in Yugoslavia, the fundamental
                    rights, obligations and responsibilities of the media, its founders and sources
                    of information, and ways of pursuing “special social interests” in the media,
                    while the creation and operation of media organisations remained the republics'
                    exclusive responsibility. Internal political and economic decentralisation ran
                    parallel to the country’s opening up to the outside world in the 1970s. <note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn26" n="24">For more details, see e.g. Slavko
                        Splichal and France Vreg, <hi rend="italic">Množično komuniciranje in razvoj
                            demokracije</hi> (Ljubljana: Komunist, 1986). Slavko Splichal,
                        “Self-management and the Media,” in: <hi rend="italic">Censorship and Libel:
                            The Chilling Effect (Studies in Communications, Vol. 4)</hi>, ed. Thelma
                        McCormack (London: JAI Press, 1990), 1–20. </note></p>
                <p>Considerable differences existed between the communication systems of republics
                    and provinces in terms of media production and consumption, occasionally leading
                    to competition and even conflicts, e.g. over the development of television.
                    Interethnic communication and dissemination of information were supposed to play
                    an important role in eliminating ethnic stratification in Yugoslavia by
                    transforming vertical differences between nations and nationalities into
                    horizontal differences between them and developing cultural pluralism. However,
                    these efforts remained largely normative.</p>
                <p>In 1984, more than 3,000 newspapers (including 27 dailies) and over 1,500
                    journals with a total yearly circulation of 1,434 million copies were published
                    in Yugoslavia. More than two-thirds of them, with over 80% of the total Yugoslav
                    circulation, were published in Serbo-Croatian, the official language in four of
                    the six Yugoslav republics. The most important publishing centres were in
                    Belgrade (Serbia) and Zagreb (Croatia). Croatian and, particularly, Serbian
                    newspapers were largely dispatched to the other republics, yet no Yugoslav
                    newspaper covered the whole federation. The relative circulation of daily
                    newspapers on average was 95 copies per 1,000 inhabitants, but varied
                    considerably among individual republics.</p>
                <p>Radio and television broadcasting represented a further pluralistic dimension of
                    the Yugoslav communication system(s). In 1984, 202 radio stations produced over
                    418,000 hours of programming for about 5 million subscribers. One-third of all
                    radio broadcasting was transmitted by 8 central radio stations (1 in each
                    republic and autonomous province), 14% by regional and 5.3% by local radio
                    stations. While the central stations were founded by republican socialist
                    alliances, regional and, especially, local stations were also created by groups
                    in civil society like national minorities, students and cultural
                    organisations.</p>
                <p>Nine television stations transmitted 15 programmes, totalling over 50,000 hours
                    per year, to about 4 million Yugoslav households possessing TV sets in 1984. The
                    number of households with TV sets varied from nearly 80% in the more developed
                    parts of the federation (Slovenia, Croatia, Vojvodina) to less than 50% in
                    Montenegro and Kosovo. Four TV stations broadcast their programmes in
                    Serbo-Croatian (Belgrade, Zagreb, Sarajevo, Titograd), and one each in Slovenian
                    (Ljubljana) and Macedonian (Skopje). TV Koper broadcast programmes in Italian
                    intended for the Italian minorities in Slovenia and Croatia, but also viewed in
                    Italy. Programmes of Television Pristina and Television Novi Sad were broadcast
                    in several languages reflecting the population’s multinational structure
                    (Albanian, Roma and Turkish in Kosovo, and Hungarian, Romanian, Slovak and
                    Ruthenic in Vojvodina).</p>
                <p>The local production of television stations did not exceed one-quarter of the
                    total programming time, while the Yugoslav production combined accounted for
                    two-thirds of the total programming time, with the remaining time being filled
                    by foreign broadcasts. Audiences only had a limited choice in watching
                    television broadcasts that could only be received within the republic of one’s
                    origin and in parts of the neighbouring republics. Still, access to all
                    programmes would not have meant any considerable changes as the programmes were
                    largely the same. In 1987, only 20 cable systems existed in Yugoslavia with no
                    more than 50,000 home terminals, all exclusively being distribution systems
                    without local programming in the local head-ends. In the 1980s, own television
                    production gradually increased, while production from other republics began to
                    be replaced by imported Western programmes, chiefly the United States and the
                    United Kingdom (see Table 4).</p>
                <table rend="rules">
                    <head>Table 4: The amount of programming and its origin in Television Ljubljana,
                        1985–1989 </head>
                    <row>
                        <cell rend="both"/>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="bold">1985</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="bold">1986</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="bold">1987</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="bold">1988</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="bold">1989</hi></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell rend="both">Total programming (in thousand minutes)</cell>
                        <cell rend="both">356</cell>
                        <cell rend="both">388</cell>
                        <cell rend="both">383</cell>
                        <cell rend="both">404</cell>
                        <cell rend="both">417</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell rend="both">Own programming, in %</cell>
                        <cell rend="both">22</cell>
                        <cell rend="both">28</cell>
                        <cell rend="both">31</cell>
                        <cell rend="both">35</cell>
                        <cell rend="both">38</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell rend="both">- % of repeats</cell>
                        <cell rend="both">27</cell>
                        <cell rend="both">34</cell>
                        <cell rend="both">35</cell>
                        <cell rend="both">34</cell>
                        <cell rend="both">36</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell rend="both">Other Yugoslav TV, in %</cell>
                        <cell rend="both">46</cell>
                        <cell rend="both">39</cell>
                        <cell rend="both">37</cell>
                        <cell rend="both">28</cell>
                        <cell rend="both">22</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell rend="both">- % of repeats</cell>
                        <cell rend="both">22</cell>
                        <cell rend="both">19</cell>
                        <cell rend="both">14</cell>
                        <cell rend="both">13</cell>
                        <cell rend="both">9</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell rend="both">Foreign-made, in %</cell>
                        <cell rend="both">32</cell>
                        <cell rend="both">33</cell>
                        <cell rend="both">32</cell>
                        <cell rend="both">37</cell>
                        <cell rend="both">40</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell rend="both">- % of repeats</cell>
                        <cell rend="both">21</cell>
                        <cell rend="both">22</cell>
                        <cell rend="both">25</cell>
                        <cell rend="both">24</cell>
                        <cell rend="both">19</cell>
                    </row>
                    <note n="">Source: Breda Kostanjšek, Izveštaj o emitovanom televizijskom
                        programu u 1989. godini (Ljubljana: RTV Slovenija, 1990).</note>
                </table>
                <lb/>
                <p>Asymmetric relations among the republics became ever more apparent in both media
                    reporting and the exchange of television programmes, and were also reflected in
                    mutual (dis)information among citizens of different republics. There was a
                    relatively weak interethnic flow of economic, political and cultural information
                    between parts of Yugoslavia. A large share of the population was not informed
                    about past and current factors and events important for understanding the
                    situation and development of the other Yugoslav nations and nationalities. The
                    nations about which most information was available in Yugoslavia were the
                    biggest ones, i.e. Serbs and Croats, while the smaller nations were, on average,
                    significantly less visible in the media of other republics.</p>
                <p>According to a 1980 Yugoslav survey, the history of other nations arouses the
                    greatest interest of citizens in all republics and both provinces (26.3% of
                    respondents on average, from 20.0% in Macedonia to 36.6% in Kosovo), followed by
                    the economy (18.8%), political events (15.5%), culture and the arts (14.8%),
                    sports (11.0%) and entertainment (8.2%). Interest in economic information was
                    significantly stronger among citizens from the most developed republics
                    (Slovenia and Croatia), but also in the least developed province of Kosovo.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn27" n="25">Peter Klinar, Slavko Splichal and Niko
                        Toš, <hi rend="italic">Informiranost o republikama i pokrajinama, narodima i
                            narodnostima</hi> (Beograd: Institut društvenih nauka, 1980).</note> In
                    addition to the citizens of Montenegro and Serbia, political news was given
                    priority by respondents in Montenegro, Serbia and Kosovo. Despite the lack of
                    knowledge about other republics and provinces, in the late 1970s almost 50% of
                    respondents in the whole of Yugoslavia believed the amount of information in the
                    national media covering other republics and provinces was adequate and only
                    one-tenth of them were very disappointed with the amount of intercultural news
                    in the media. Only one-fifth of the Yugoslav population knew all eight central
                    national dailies: 79.5% knew <hi rend="italic">Politika</hi>, published in
                    Serbia, 70.0% <hi rend="italic">Vjesnik</hi> (Croatia), 48.1% <hi rend="italic"
                        >Rilindja</hi> (Kosovo; perhaps also because of the paper's non-Slavic title
                    without really knowing it), 46.7% <hi rend="italic">Delo</hi> (Slovenia), 43.0%
                        <hi rend="italic">Oslobodjenje</hi> (Bosnia and Herzegovina), 31.0% <hi
                        rend="italic">Pobjeda</hi> (Montenegro), 26 .4% <hi rend="italic">Večer</hi>
                    (Macedonia) and 24.0% <hi rend="italic">Dnevnik</hi> (Vojvodina). Similar or
                    less mutual knowledge (or ignorance) also existed about other historical,
                    economic, political and cultural characteristics of individual republics.</p>
                <p>The pattern of information exchange between the republics through print and
                    television media that was discerned in the 1980s could hence be expected. Only
                    the newspapers published in Belgrade and Zagreb successfully crossed each
                    republic’s borders. This was especially true for the sports dailies <hi
                        rend="italic">Sportske novosti</hi> (published in Zagreb) and <hi
                        rend="italic">Sport</hi> (Belgrade), which in 1984 sold 40% and 38% of their
                    circulation, respectively, in other republics. Five political dailies sold more
                    than 20% of their circulation outside the republics in which they were
                    published: the Croatian <hi rend="italic">Vjesnik</hi> and tabloid <hi
                        rend="italic">Večernji list</hi>, published in Zagreb, and the Serbian <hi
                        rend="italic">Politika</hi> and tabloids <hi rend="italic">Politika
                        ekspres</hi> and<hi rend="italic"> Večernje novosti</hi>, published in
                    Belgrade. The daily newspaper <hi rend="italic">Borba</hi> had special editions
                    in Cyrillic and Latin, thus covering the entire Serbo-Croatian language area;
                    most readers were in Serbia (61% of total circulation), followed by Croatia
                    (21%) and Bosnia and Herzegovina (10%). Some magazines had most of their readers
                    in other republics; again, the largest share of circulation sold outside the
                    republic of publication was held by the sports magazine <hi rend="italic"
                        >Tempo</hi> weekly from Belgrade, with two-thirds of its total circulation
                    sold in Croatia and Bosnia and Herzegovina in particular.</p>
                <p>A similar pattern emerged with the exchange of television programmes among the
                    broadcasting centres in the Yugoslav republics. The normatively declared
                    “interconnection and transmission of cultures” through television was often
                    one-way, primarily from the Serbo-Croatian language area to the smaller national
                    and linguistic communities (Macedonian, Slovenian, Albanian). Since this was a
                    period of terrestrial television, television broadcasts made by other republics
                    were not available to watch directly, except in the border regions of the
                    republics. In 11 of 14 programmes, most broadcasts were in the Serbo-Croatian
                    spoken language or were subtitled in Serbo-Croatian. The only exceptions were
                    Channel 1 in Ljubljana (in Slovenian) and Skopje Television (in Macedonian) and
                    the Pristina Television programme (in Albanian; see Table 5). As shown by the
                    arrows in Figure 3, the only important creators of external television
                    programmes were Television Belgrade (Serbia) and Television Zagreb (Croatia),
                    from which all four of the other republics imported over 10% of the programmes
                    they broadcast in 1984, whereas in the opposite direction the programme exchange
                    was close to zero.</p>
                <table rend="rules">
                    <head><hi rend="bold">Table 5</hi>: Television programmes in Yugoslavia by the
                        broadcasting language in 1984</head>
                    <row>
                        <cell rend="both">Television station</cell>
                        <cell rend="both">Total hours</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">Percent of own production</cell>
                        <cell rend="center" cols="5"><hi rend="color(131313)">Percent of programme
                                in</hi></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell rend="both"/>
                        <cell rend="both"/>
                        <cell rend="both"/>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(0E0E0E)">Serbo-Croatian</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(0F0F0F)">Slovenian</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both">Macedonian</cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(0D0D0D)">Albanian</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(131313)">Other</hi></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(0F0F0F)">Belgrade 1</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(080808)">4,003</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(0E0E0E)">33</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(0E0E0E)">95</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(0F0F0F)"> 0</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"> 1</cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(0D0D0D)"> 0</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(131313)"> 4</hi></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(0D0D0D)">Belgrade 2</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(0E0E0E)">2,617</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(0D0D0D)">37</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(0D0D0D)">89</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"> 1</cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(0F0F0F)"> 2</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(0D0D0D)"> 4</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(131313)"> 4</hi></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(0B0B0B)">Ljubljana 1</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(0E0E0E)">3,415</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(0A0A0A)">34</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(0A0A0A)">19</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(0F0F0F)">78</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(0F0F0F)"> 0</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(0D0D0D)"> 0</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"> 3</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(080808)">Ljubljana 2</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(0E0E0E)">2,299</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(0B0B0B)"> 4</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(0B0B0B)">83</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(0F0F0F)"> 9</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(0F0F0F)"> 2</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"> 1</cell>
                        <cell rend="both"> 5</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(090909)">Novi Sad</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(0F0F0F)">2,1185</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(131313)">47</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(131313)">53</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(0F0F0F)"> 0</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(0F0F0F)"> 0</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(0F0F0F)"> 0</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both">47</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(0F0F0F)">Prishtina</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(0B0B0B)">3,092</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(0B0B0B)">48</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(0B0B0B)"> 6</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(0F0F0F)"> 0</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(0F0F0F)"> 0</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both">71</cell>
                        <cell rend="both">23</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(0E0E0E)">Sarajevo 1</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(0D0D0D)">3,724</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(080808)">19</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(080808)">96</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(0F0F0F)"> 0</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"> 1</cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(0F0F0F)"> 0</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(0E0E0E)"> 3</hi></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(0D0D0D)">Sarajevo 2</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(070707)">2,116</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(0B0B0B)">15</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(0B0B0B)">88</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(0F0F0F)"> 2</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(121212)"> 2</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"> 1</cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(0E0E0E)"> 7</hi></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(0E0E0E)">Skopje 1</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(0B0B0B)">3,971</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(0D0D0D)">31</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(0D0D0D)">38</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(0F0F0F)"> 0</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(121212)">55</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(101010)"> 3</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(0E0E0E)"> 4</hi></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(0F0F0F)">Skopje 2</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(0B0B0B)">2,417</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(0A0A0A)">15</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(0A0A0A)">62</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"> 1</cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(121212)">33</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"> 1</cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(101010)"> 3</hi></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(0E0E0E)">Titograd 1</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(0A0A0A)">3,836</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(080808)"> 9</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(080808)">96</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"> 1</cell>
                        <cell rend="both"> 1</cell>
                        <cell rend="both"> 1</cell>
                        <cell rend="both"> 1</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(0E0E0E)">Titograd 2</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(0B0B0B)">2,529</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(0B0B0B)"> 2</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(0B0B0B)">88</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(101010)"> 2</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(171717)"> 2</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(0F0F0F)"> 4</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(121212)"> 4</hi></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(0D0D0D)">Zagreb 1</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(0F0F0F)">3,564</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(0D0D0D)">36</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(0D0D0D)">95</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(101010)"> 0</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"> 1</cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(0F0F0F)"> 0</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(121212)"> 4</hi></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(0D0D0D)">Zagreb 2</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(090909)">2,152</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(0D0D0D)">25</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(0D0D0D)">91</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"> 1</cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(101010)"> 2</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="both"> 1</cell>
                        <cell rend="both"><hi rend="color(121212)"> 5</hi></cell>
                    </row>
                    <note n="">Slavko Splichal in France Vreg, <hi rend="italic">Množično
                            komuniciranje in razvoj demokracije</hi> (Ljubljana: Komunist 1986),
                        105</note>
                </table>
                <figure>
                    <head><hi rend="bold">Figure 3</hi>: Graphic representation of the ‘importing’
                        of television programmes from other republics. Arrows in the graph show at
                        least 10% of the imports from the television station to which an arrow is
                        pointing.</head>
                    <graphic url="media/image4.png"/>
                    <lb/>
                    <note n="">Source: Slavko Splichal in France Vreg, <hi rend="italic">Množično
                            komuniciranje in razvoj demokracije</hi> (Ljubljana: Komunist 1986),
                        105.</note>
                </figure>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Conclusion</head>
                <p>In retrospect, the conclusion seems obvious: socialist Yugoslavia’s efforts to
                    democratise its international and intercultural communication were ambitious and
                    partly successful in the short term, but ultimately failed – as did the
                    Socialist Yugoslavia project itself. The results of research looking at the
                    characteristics of external radio broadcasting, news selection and newspaper and
                    television traffic in Yugoslavia during the 1970s and 1980s show that asymmetry,
                    bias, imbalance, and one-way traffic strongly marked both the external
                    (international) and internal (intercultural) communication of Yugoslavia. Of
                    course, the results of this research are more illustrative than a systematic
                    explanation of the internal and external communication processes in
                    Yugoslavia.</p>
                <p>In 1986, I concluded my essay in <hi rend="italic">Mass Communication and the
                        Development of Democracy</hi> by arguing, “Despite the many contradictions
                    with the establishment of social ownership and the development of
                    self-management in the field of mass communication, the potential of Yugoslav
                    society is far from being exploited”.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn28" n="26"
                        >Slavko Splichal and France Vreg, <hi rend="italic">Množično komuniciranje
                            in razvoj demokracije</hi> (Ljubljana: Komunist, 1984), 179.</note></p>
                <p>Even 35 years later, I find this assessment to be very accurate. Let me
                    illustrate this in three points.</p>
                <p>In the light of contemporary debates on the autonomy of public service media in
                    Slovenia and elsewhere across Europe (and beyond), I recall my dispute over the
                    draft law on public information in 1985.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn29" n="27"
                        > Slavko Splichal, “Razsežnosti svobode komuniciranja. Ob osnutku zakona o
                        javnem obveščanju,” <hi rend="italic">Naši razgledi</hi>, 25 January and 8
                        February 1985.</note> At that time, I was critical of the lack of powers
                    that media councils possessed under the (new) law, yet today I can say that
                    media councils were more democratically designed in the 1980s than, for example,
                    today’s RTV Slovenia Programme Council (under the 2005 law). These councils, as
                    key social governing bodies in the media, were made up of delegates of employees
                    of communication organisations and delegates of users in the proportion
                    determined by the founding act. It was essential, however, that the delegates be
                    appointed directly by the relevant organisations and communities defined in the
                    founding act, without the interference of the founder, who was typically the
                    Socialist Alliance of Working People. One of my biggest criticisms <note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn30" n="28">Ibid.</note> was that the editor-in-chief
                    was not appointed by the council but directly by the founder. Still, compared to
                    the current ‘democratic’ regime dominated by (ruling) political parties directly
                    and indirectly represented in the Programme Council of Radio and Television
                    Slovenia, the councils in the 1980s enjoyed greater political autonomy.
                    According to modern standards of public service media autonomy, this remains the
                    most appropriate path to follow to ensure their autonomy.</p>
                <p>In the international comparative analysis of media reporting conducted in 1984
                    mentioned earlier, Slovenian newspapers proved to be the most
                    internationally-oriented among other media in 29 countries. The considerable
                    attention paid to international events outside the world’s centres was largely
                    due to Yugoslavia’s foreign policy of non-alignment. Tanjug, with its extensive
                    correspondent network and cooperation with the press agencies of non-aligned
                    countries, provided the Yugoslav media with news about events that had attracted
                    the attention of peripheral areas. In general, at that time, daily newspapers
                    and radio and television news programmes devoted more space, time and resources,
                    including their own correspondents, to international news than they do today,
                    which also had a significant impact on people’s international orientation. Such
                    media policy was principally in line with the ideas of a new world information
                    and communication order (NWICO) <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn31" n="29"><hi
                            rend="italic">Communication and Society Today and Tomorrow: Many Voices
                            One World. Towards a New More Just and More Efficient World Information
                            and Communication Order</hi> (<hi rend="italic">MacBride Report)</hi>
                        (Paris: UNESCO, 1980).</note> reaffirmed today in discussions on global
                    Internet governance, but was abandoned after Slovenia’s independence, transition
                    to capitalism, and growing nationalism.</p>
                <p>On the other hand, ethnocentric interests prevailed in the intercultural
                    communication in Yugoslavia even before the federation’s final disintegration.
                    Mutual interest among the republics was quite low, limited in the media to
                    protocol political news, which correlated with people in individual republics'
                    general disinterest in news from other republics and ethnic groups with a
                    different linguistic, religious and cultural heritage. The news values
                    proclaimed and applied to the international flow of news were not applied in
                    intercultural communication within Yugoslavia. What Schöpflin described as “a
                    semi-authoritarian system by consent” that is supposed to characterise all <hi
                        rend="italic">post-communist</hi> systems, which were “democratic in form
                    and nationalist in content”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn32" n="30">George
                        Schöpflin, “Post-Communism: A Profile,” <hi rend="italic">Javnost-The
                            Public</hi> 2, No. 1 (1995): 63-73, 63, 66.</note> and consisted of “an
                    evident element of consent for semi-democratic practices” and “legitimated
                    either by nationalism or by etatism, or by a subtle combination of the two”,
                    already emerged in late socialist or <hi rend="italic">pre-capitalist</hi>
                    Yugoslavia. Ethnonationalism first erupted in Yugoslavia in the early 1970s and
                    was never really curbed later. Ethnocentric news media contributed to the rising
                    political and economic nationalisms that eventually shattered the country to
                    pieces. They may have missed the opportunity to contribute to a rationally
                    guided separation, as occurred in Czechoslovakia, which was founded in the same
                    year as the first Yugoslavia (1918) and peacefully dissolved in 1993, 2 years
                    after Slovenia and Croatia declared independence.</p>
                <p>In my 1994 book <hi rend="italic">Media Beyond Socialism</hi>, I challenged the
                    view that the burial of authoritarian practices in socialist countries had been
                    followed by a smooth transition to democracy. Instead, I argued that the
                    post-communist media had mimicked Western economic and political practices and
                    was often exposed to the negative influences of authoritarianism, commercialism
                    and nationalism. Many countries have suffered enormously not only from a lack of
                    civic participation and control, but also from the erosion of the indigenous
                    intellectual foundations of social transformation that were lost after the
                    sudden takeover of political and economic power. Although political changes have
                    significantly broadened the horizons of human freedom, today I unfortunately
                    conclude that not only was my assessment of the new threats quite accurate at
                    the time, but the situation in several countries, including Slovenia, has even
                    worsened following the rise of authoritarian governments.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="bibliography">
                <head>Sources and Literature</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl>Bisky, Lothar. <hi rend="italic">Zur Kritik der bürgerlichen
                            Massenkommunikationsforschung</hi>. Berlin, DDR: VEB Deutscher Verlag
                        der Wissenschaften, 1974.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Džinič, Firdus and Ljiljana Bačević. <hi rend="italic">Inostrana
                            propaganda u Jugoslaviji</hi>. Beograd: Institut društvenih nauka,
                        1958.</bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="italic">Foreign News in the Media: International Reporting in 29
                            Countries</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Reports and papers on mass
                            communication,</hi> No. 93. Paris: UNESCO, 1985.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Klinar, Peter, Slavko Splichal and Niko Toš. <hi rend="italic"
                            >Informiranost o republikama i pokrajinama, narodima i
                        narodnostima</hi>. Beograd: Institut društvenih nauka, 1980.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Kostanjšek, Breda. Izveštaj o emitovanom televizijskom programu u 1989.
                        godini. Interno gradivo. Ljubljana: RTV Slovenija, 1990.</bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="italic">MacBride Report</hi>. <hi rend="italic">Communication
                            and Society Today and Tomorrow: Many Voices One World. Towards a New
                            More Just and More Efficient World Information and Communication
                            Order</hi>. Paris: Unesco, 1980. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Milić, Vojin. “Primena nekih bibliometrijskih i prosopografskih postupaka
                        u proučavanju istorije sociologije.” <hi rend="italic">Sociološki
                            pregled</hi> 12, No. 1-2 (1988): 73–98.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Martelanc, Tomo, “Jugoslovansko posvetovanje o medrepubliškem
                        komuniciranju.” <hi rend="italic">Teorija in praksa</hi> 12, No. 4-5 (1975):
                        527–30.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Martelanc, Tomo, Slavko Splichal, Breda Pavlič, Anuška Ferligoj, Vlado
                        Batagelj and Mojca Drčar Murko. <hi rend="italic">External Radio
                            Broadcasting and International Understanding: Broadcasting to
                            Yugoslavia</hi>. <hi rend="italic">Reports and papers in mass
                            communication</hi>, No. 81. Paris: UNESCO, 1977.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Pohar, Lado. <hi rend="italic">Problematika Službe za študij programa</hi>
                        (mimeo). Ljubljana: Služba za študij programa, RTV Ljubljana, 1975. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Pohar, Lado and Tilka Jamnik. <hi rend="italic">Bibliografija raziskav
                            radia in televizije, opravljenih v raziskovalnih centrih jugoslovanskih
                            RTV ustanov v letih 1952</hi>–<hi rend="italic">1977, Bilten SŠP</hi>,
                        No. 7. Ljubljana: Služba za študij programa, RTV Ljubljana, 1978.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Schöpflin, George. “Post-Communism: A Profile.” <hi rend="italic"
                            >Javnost-The Public</hi> 2, No. 1, (1995): 63–73.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Smith, Stanley. “Mass Media and International Understanding by France
                        Vreg.” In: <hi rend="italic">International and Intercultural Communication
                            Annual</hi>, Vol. 6. Ed. Nemi C. Jain, 116–19. Annandale, Va.: Speech
                        Communication Association, 1982. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Splichal, Slavko. <hi rend="italic">Socializacijske vsebine na televiziji,
                            Bilten SŠP</hi>, No. 8. Ljubljana: Služba za študij programa, RTV
                        Ljubljana, 1974.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Splichal, Slavko. <hi rend="italic">Pretok sporočil na radiu in
                            televiziji, Bilten SŠP</hi>, No. 17. Ljubljana: Služba za študij
                        programa, RTV Ljubljana, 1976. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Splichal, Slavko. <hi rend="italic">Množično komuniciranje med svobodo in
                            odtujitvijo</hi>. Maribor: Obzorja, 1981.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Splichal, Slavko. “Razsežnosti svobode komuniciranja. Ob osnutku zakona o
                        javnem obveščanju.” <hi rend="italic">Naši razgledi</hi>, January 25 and
                        February 8. 1985.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Splichal, Slavko. <hi rend="italic">Mlini na eter: propaganda, reklama in
                            selekcija sporočil v množičnem komuniciranju</hi>. Ljubljana:
                        Partizanska knjiga, 1984.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Splichal, Slavko. “Self-management and the Media.” In: <hi rend="italic"
                            >Censorship and Libel: The Chilling Effect (Studies in Communications,
                            Vol. 4)</hi>. Ed. Thelma McCormack, 1–20. London: JAI Press,
                        1990.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Splichal, Slavko. “Indigenisation vs. Ideologisation: Communication
                        Science on the Periphery.” <hi rend="italic">European Journal of
                            Communication</hi> 4, No. 3 (1994): 329–59. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Splichal, Slavko. <hi rend="italic">Media Beyond Socialism</hi>. Boulder:
                        Westview, 1994.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Splichal, Slavko and Anuška Ferligoj. “Ideology in International
                        Propaganda.” In <hi rend="italic">Sociometric research: Data Collection and
                            Scaling</hi>. Eds. Willem E. Saris and Irmtraud N. Gallhofer, 69–89.
                        Houndmills: Macmillan Press, 1988. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Splichal, Slavko and France Vreg, <hi rend="italic">Množično komuniciranje
                            in razvoj demokracije</hi>. Ljubljana: Komunist, 1986.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Šrot, Vida. “Zgodovina raziskovanja RTV programov in občinstva: Služba za
                        študĳ programa in njeni nasledniki.” <hi rend="italic">Javnost – The
                            Public</hi> 15, supplement (2008):133–50. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Vreg, France. “Trideset let komunikacijske znanosti na Slovenskem.” <hi
                            rend="italic">Teorija in praksa</hi> 28 (1991): 8–9, 1018–24.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
            <div type="summary" xml:lang="sl">
                <docAuthor>Slavko Splichal</docAuthor>
                <head>PREMISLEK O PRISPEVKIH SOCIALISTIČNE JUGOSLAVIJE K MEDNARODNEMU IN
                    MEDKULTURNEMU KOMUNICIRANJU</head>
                <head>POVZETEK</head>
                <p>V tem članku predstavljam (ponovno) branje nekaterih svojih raziskav in razprav o
                    množičnem komuniciranju in razvoju socialistične demokracije v Jugoslaviji,
                    objavljenih v zadnjih dveh desetletjih obstoja večnacionalne federacije pred
                    njenim nenadnim in nasilnim propadom. Članek je zasnovan kot ponovna presoja
                    ključnih idej in rezultatov nekaterih empiričnih raziskav, ki sem jih zasnoval
                    in izvajal v sedemdesetih in osemdesetih letih prejšnjega stoletja do
                    osamosvojitve Slovenije leta 1991. Vključujejo več različnih tematik, kot so
                    komuniciranje med republikami v Jugoslaviji, tuja radijska propaganda in
                    delovanje tiskovne agencije Tanjug, zbiranje novic in redakcijsko odbiranje ter
                    razvoj komunikologije kot znanstvene discipline v Jugoslaviji.</p>
                <p>V mednarodni primerjalni analizi poročanja medijev v 29 državah iz leta 1984 so
                    se slovenski časopisi izkazali za najbolj mednarodno usmerjene. Precej je k
                    pozornosti, ki je bila posvečena mednarodnim dogajanjem izven svetovnih središč,
                    prispevala jugoslovanska zunanja politika neuvrščenosti. Tiskovna agencija
                    Tanjug je s svojo razvejano dopisniško mrežo in sodelovanjem s tiskovnimi
                    agencijami neuvrščenih držav jugoslovanskim medijem posredovala novice o
                    dogodkih, ki so pritegovali pozornost območij zunaj svetovnih političnih in
                    ekonomskih središč. Na splošno so takrat slovenski dnevni časopisi ter radijske
                    in televizijske informativne oddaje mednarodnim novicam namenjali več prostora,
                    časa in sredstev, skupaj z lastnimi dopisniki, kot danes, kar je pomembno
                    vplivalo tudi na mednarodno usmerjenost ljudi. Takšna medijska politika je bila
                    v skladu z idejami o novem svetovnem informacijsko-komunikacijskem redu (NWICO),
                    ki se danes ponovno uveljavljajo v razpravah o globalnem upravljanju interneta,
                    vendar so se ji slovenski mediji po osamosvojitvi Slovenije, prehodu v
                    kapitalizem in z naraščajočim nacionalizmom odrekli.</p>
                <p>Po drugi strani pa so v medkulturnem komuniciranju v Jugoslaviji prevladovali
                    etnocentrični interesi že pred dokončnim razpadom federacije. Vzajemni interes
                    med republikami je bil precej šibek, v medijih je bil omejen na protokolarne
                    politične novice, kar je bilo v korelaciji s splošnim nezanimanjem ljudi v
                    posameznih republikah za novice iz drugih republik in etničnih skupin z drugačno
                    jezikovno, versko in kulturno dediščino. Novičarske vrednote, ki so bile
                    uveljavljene v mednarodnem poročanju, niso prevladovale tudi v medkulturnem
                    komuniciranju znotraj Jugoslavije. Etnonacionalizem je v Jugoslaviji prvič
                    izbruhnil v zgodnjih sedemdesetih letih prejšnjega stoletja in ga pozneje nikoli
                    niso zares zajezili. Etnocentrični mediji so prispevali k naraščajočemu
                    političnemu in gospodarskemu nacionalizmu, ki je sčasoma pripeljal do razpada
                    države. Morda so tudi mediji prispevali k zamujeni priložnosti, da bi omogočili
                    racionalno razpravo in ločitev republik po mirni poti, kot se je to zgodilo na
                    Češkoslovaškem, ki je bila ustanovljena istega leta kot prva Jugoslavija (1918)
                    in mirno razpuščena leta 1993, dve leti po razglasitvi neodvisnosti Slovenije in
                    Hrvaške.</p>
                <p>V začetku devetdesetih let preteklega stoletja sem oporekal prepričanju, da je
                    pokopu avtoritarnih praks v socialističnih državah sledil gladek prehod v
                    demokracijo. Spremembe po letu 1990 so nakazovale, da so postkomunistični mediji
                    posnemali zahodne gospodarske in politične prakse in bili pogosto izpostavljeni
                    negativnim vplivom avtoritarnosti, komercializacije in nacionalizmov. Očitno ni
                    šlo le za demokratični primanjkljaj, odsotnost državljanske udeležbe in nadzora,
                    temveč tudi za erozijo avtohtonih intelektualnih temeljev družbene preobrazbe,
                    ki so se izgubili po nenadnem prevzemu politične in gospodarske oblasti. Čeprav
                    so politične spremembe tistega časa bistveno razširile obzorja človekove
                    svobode, danes žal ugotavljam, da je bila moja takratna ocena novih groženj
                    precej natančna in da so se razmere v marsikateri državi, tudi v Sloveniji, z
                    vzponom avtoritarnih strank celo poslabšale.</p>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
