<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Remembering Tanjug: Analysing the Re-Articulation of Journalistic Roles at
                    the National News Agency of Socialist Yugoslavia<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn4"
                        n="*">This work was financially supported by the Slovenian Research Agency,
                        contract numbers J5-1793 and P5-0051.</note></title>
                <author>
                    <forename>Igor</forename>
                    <surname>Vobič</surname>
                    <roleName>Associate Professor</roleName>
                    <affiliation>University of Ljubljana, Faculty of Social Sciences</affiliation>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Kardeljeva ploščad 5</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>SI-1000 Ljubljana</addrLine>
                    </address>
                    <email>igor.vobic@fdv.uni-lj.si</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <forename>Kristina</forename>
                    <surname>Milić</surname>
                    <roleName>Researcher Associate</roleName>
                    <affiliation>University of Belgrade, Faculty of Political Science</affiliation>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Jove Ilića</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>RS-11000 Beograd</addrLine>
                    </address>
                    <email>kristina.malesevic@fpn.bg.ac.rs</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename>Ana</forename>
                        <surname>Milojević</surname>
                        <roleName>Postdoctoral Researcher</roleName>
                        <roleName>Assistant Professor</roleName>
                        <affiliation>University of Bergen, Department of Information Science and
                            Media Studies</affiliation>
                        <address>
                            <addrLine>Fosswinckels gate 6</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>N-5007 Bergen</addrLine>
                        </address>
                        <email>ana.milojevic@uib.no</email>
                        <affiliation>University of Belgrade, Faculty of Political
                            Science</affiliation>
                        <address>
                            <addrLine>Jove Ilića</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>RS-11000 Beograd</addrLine>
                        </address>
                        <email>ana.milojevic@fpn.bg.ac.rs</email>
                    </name>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>2022-04-21</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>
                    <orgName xml:lang="sl">Inštitut za novejšo zgodovino</orgName>
                    <orgName xml:lang="en">Institute of Contemporary History</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Privoz 11</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>SI-1000 Ljubljana</addrLine>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>http://ojs.inz.si/pnz/article/view/3979</pubPlace>
                <date>2021</date>
                <availability status="free">
                    <licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title xml:lang="sl">Prispevki za novejšo zgodovino</title>
                <title xml:lang="en">Contributions to Contemporary History</title>
                <biblScope unit="volume">62</biblScope>
                <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
                <idno type="ISSN">2463-7807</idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source, born digital.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc xml:lang="en">
                <p>Contributions to Contemporary History is one of the central Slovenian scientific
                    historiographic journals, dedicated to publishing articles from the field of
                    contemporary history (the 19th and 20th century).</p>
                <p>The journal is published three times per year in Slovenian and in the following
                    foreign languages: English, German, Serbian, Croatian, Bosnian, Italian, Slovak
                    and Czech. The articles are all published with abstracts in English and
                    Slovenian as well as summaries in English.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <projectDesc xml:lang="sl">
                <p>Prispevki za novejšo zgodovino je ena osrednjih slovenskih znanstvenih
                    zgodovinopisnih revij, ki objavlja teme s področja novejše zgodovine (19. in 20.
                    stoletje).</p>
                <p>Revija izide trikrat letno v slovenskem jeziku in v naslednjih tujih jezikih:
                    angleščina, nemščina, srbščina, hrvaščina, bosanščina, italijanščina, slovaščina
                    in češčina. Članki izhajajo z izvlečki v angleščini in slovenščini ter povzetki
                    v angleščini.</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en"/>
                <language ident="sl"/>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords xml:lang="en">
                    <term>journalistic roles</term>
                    <term>occupational life histories</term>
                    <term>interviews</term>
                    <term>Tanjug</term>
                    <term>Yugoslavia</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords xml:lang="sl">
                    <term>novinarske vloge</term>
                    <term>zgodovine poklicnega življenja</term>
                    <term>intervjuji</term>
                    <term>Tanjug</term>
                    <term>Jugoslavija</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change><date>2022-05-04T07:21:04Z</date>
                    <name>Mihael Ojsteršek</name>
                    <desc>Pretvorba iz DOCX v TEI, dodatno kodiranje</desc></change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <docAuthor>Igor Vobič<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn1" n="**"><hi rend="bold">Associate
                        Professor, University of Ljubljana, Faculty of Social Sciences, Kardeljeva
                        ploščad 5, SI-1000 Ljubljana; </hi><ref
                        target="mailto:igor.vobic@fdv.uni-lj.si"><hi rend="bold"
                            >igor.vobic@fdv.uni-lj.si</hi></ref>
                </note></docAuthor>
            <docAuthor>Kristina Milić<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn2" n="***"><hi rend="bold"
                        >Researcher Associate, University of Belgrade, Faculty of Political Science,
                        Jove Ilića, RS-11000 Beograd; </hi><ref
                        target="mailto:kristina.malesevic@fpn.bg.ac.rs"><hi rend="bold"
                            >kristina.malesevic@fpn.bg.ac.rs</hi></ref>
                </note></docAuthor>
            <docAuthor>Ana Milojević<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn3" n="****"><hi rend="bold"
                        >Postdoctoral Researcher, University of Bergen, Department of Information
                        Science and Media Studies, Fosswinckels gate 6, N-5007 Bergen; </hi><ref
                        target="mailto:ana.milojevic@uib.no"><hi rend="bold"
                            >ana.milojevic@uib.no</hi></ref><hi rend="bold">; Assistant Professor,
                        University of Belgrade, Faculty of Political Science, Jove Ilića, RS-11000
                        Beograd; </hi><ref target="mailto:ana.milojevic@fpn.bg.ac.rs"><hi
                            rend="bold">ana.milojevic@fpn.bg.ac.rs</hi></ref>
                </note></docAuthor>
            <docImprint>
                <idno type="cobissType">Cobiss tip: 1.01</idno>
                <idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.51663/pnz.62.1.5</idno>
            </docImprint>
            <div type="abstract">
                <head>IZVLEČEK</head>
                <head><hi rend="italic">SPOMINJANJE TANJUGA: ANALIZA REARTIKULACIJ NOVINARSKIH VLOG
                        NACIONALNE TISKOVNE AGENCIJE V SOCIALISTIČNI JUGOSLAVIJI</hi></head>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Vloga novinarstva v družbi je zgodovinsko vezana na
                        prevladujočo konceptualizacijo svobode tiska ter specifične družbene,
                        institucionalne in materialne pogoje produkcije novic. Študija proučuje
                        samopercepcije novinarjev, ki so delovali v obdobju socialistične
                        Jugoslavije, in sintetizira njihove spomine na novinarske usmeritve in
                        delovanje z vidika položaja novinarstva v družbi. Študija temelji na ustnih
                        zgodovinskih intervjujih z nekdanjimi novinarji, ki so od poznih petdesetih
                        do devetdesetih let prejšnjega stoletja tudi kot uredniki in tuji dopisniki
                        delali pri tiskovni agenciji Tanjug, ki je veljala za informacijsko
                        hrbtenico zveznega medijskega sistema v Jugoslaviji in agencijo z mednarodno
                        veljavo. Z združevanjem študij »novinarskih vlog« in raziskav »zgodovin
                        poklicnega življenja« ima študija dvojni prispevek. Prvič, opredeljuje
                        prilagodljive strategije spominjanja, ki jih intervjuvani novinarji
                        uporabljajo, da se legitimirajo kot profesionalci in relevantni interpreti
                        novinarstva v SFRJ. Drugič, razkriva več odtenkov znotraj običajnega,
                        pogosto poenostavljenega razumevanja novinarjev kot sodelavcev oblasti v
                        času socializma in prepoznava tri novinarske vloge: privilegiranih
                        posredovalcev, nadzornih analitikov in razsvetljevalcev, ki so specifične
                        manifestacije sodelovalne funkcije novinarstva.</hi></p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Ključne besede: novinarske vloge, zgodovine poklicnega
                        življenja, intervjuji, Tanjug, Jugoslavija</hi></p>
            </div>
            <div type="abstract">
                <head>ABSTRACT</head>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Historically, the role held by journalism in society is linked
                        to the dominant views on freedom of the press as well as the specific
                        societal, institutional and material conditions of news production. This
                        study explores self-perceptions of journalists working in the period of
                        socialist Yugoslavia and synthesises their recollections of journalistic
                        orientations and performances with respect to journalism’s place in society.
                        Methodologically, it is based on oral history interviews with former
                        journalists, who also worked as editors and foreign correspondents from the
                        late 1950s to 1990s, at the Tanjug news agency, considered to be the federal
                        media system’s information backbone in Yugoslavia. By combining
                        ‘journalistic roles’ studies and ‘occupational life history’ research, this
                        study makes two contributions. First, it identifies the adaptive strategies
                        of remembering used by the interviewed journalists to legitimise themselves
                        as professionals and relevant interpreters of SFRY journalism. Second, it
                        reveals nuances within the common, often simplified understandings of
                        journalists as collaborators with power during socialism, and highlights the
                        roles of privileged disseminator, monitoring analyst, and educator as
                        particular manifestations of the collaborative function.</hi></p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Keywords: journalistic roles, occupational life histories,
                        interviews, Tanjug, Yugoslavia</hi>
                </p>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <p style="text-align:right">
                <cit>
                    <quote>The League of Communists of Yugoslavia has always paid great attention to
                        journalism,<lb/>knowing how important the social and political role of
                        journalists is in a democratic and free self-<lb/>managing society.
                        Journalists have never been asked to be blindly obedient, but we have
                        always<lb/> reacted in those cases when there was not enough objectivity in
                        presenting the socio-political<lb/> situation in our country and when
                        journalistic articles could have a detrimental effect on our<lb/>
                        development or Yugoslavia's reputation in the world.</quote>
                    <lb/>
                    <bibl>President Tito, November 1970, <hi rend="italic">Naša Štampa</hi></bibl>
                </cit>
            </p>
            <p>This is how President of the Socialist Federal Republic of Yugoslavia Josip Broz Tito
                (1970/1980) addressed journalists upon the 25<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>
                anniversary of the Federation of Journalists of Yugoslavia (SNJ).<note place="foot"
                    xml:id="ftn5" n="1">Josip Broz Tito, “Od novinara se nikada nije tražila slijepa
                    poslušnost,” in: <hi rend="italic">Tito o informisanju</hi>, ed. Miroslav
                    Đorđević (Beograd: RTB. 1970/1980), 179, 180.</note> His address not only shows
                how political power defined the place of journalism in society, but the boundaries
                of journalists’ institutional position in the political arena. Tito regularly
                interpreted the normative foundations of journalism, reflected on media
                representations of society, and gave moral lessons to journalists. For instance, in
                the aftermath of the ‘Croatian Spring’ reform movement (1967–1971), Tito expressed
                his dissatisfaction with the work of the press, stating that it “discourages us from
                believing that we can go forward despite all the difficulties”.<note place="foot"
                    xml:id="ftn6" n="2">Josip Broz Tito, “Ne slažem se sa štampom kada dramatizira
                    pojedine slučajeve,” in: <hi rend="italic">Tito o informisanju, </hi>ed.
                    Miroslav Đorđević (Beograd: RTB. 1971/1980), 191.</note> Later on, after the 6th
                Summit of the Non-Aligned Movement in Cuba (1979), he praised journalists, “In a
                word, you did a great job. And the task was not easy, neither for you nor for us”.
                    <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn7" n="3">Josip Broz Tito, “Novinari odlično
                    obavili posao u Havani,” in: <hi rend="italic">Tito o informisanju, </hi>ed.
                    Miroslav Đorđević (Beograd: RTB. 1979/1980), 243.</note> Such public reflections
                by Tito shed light on complexities in the journalism–power–citizenry nexus, what was
                solidly in place and hat caused tension, along the continuous re-configuration of
                Yugoslav journalism.</p>
            <p>The place journalism held in socialist Yugoslavia was fluid and changed with the
                position of the media vis-à-vis the state and the Communist Party, fluctuating
                between liberalisation and coercion in different periods.<note place="foot"
                    xml:id="ftn8" n="4">Zrinjka Peruško, Dina Vozab and Antonija Čuvalo, <hi
                        rend="italic">Comparing Post-Socialist Media Systems</hi> (London, New York:
                    Routledge, 2021), 76–131. Melita Poler Kovačič, “Normative Role Orientations of
                    Yugoslav Journalists,” <hi rend="italic">Prispevki za novejšo zgodovino</hi> 62,
                    No. 1 (2022): 67-69.</note> Although journalism was normatively conceived
                through Marxism-Leninism, the discussions on journalistic orientations revealed that
                they not only stemmed from the official ideology, but from various, even
                contradictory influences during the re-institutionalisation of the media in
                Yugoslavia. In the changing political, economic and cultural context, the notion of
                journalists as ‘socio-political workers’ was continuously re-negotiated against the
                normative foundations, professional and political ideal(isation)s, media practices
                and journalistic (self-)perceptions in the multi-national society,<note place="foot"
                    xml:id="ftn9" n="5">Gertrude J. Robinson, <hi rend="italic">Tito’s Maverick
                        Media</hi> (Chicago: University of Illinois Press, 1977), 124–27. Mitja
                    Gorjup, “Ponuditi moramo svetu nov tip informiranja,” in: Mitja Gorjup, <hi
                        rend="italic">Samoupravno novinarstvo (Izbor govorov in člankov)</hi>, ed.
                    Vlado Jarc (Ljubljana: Delavska enotnost, 1975/1978), 59–66. France Vreg,
                    “Jugoslovanska šola novinarstva,” in: France Vreg, <hi rend="italic"
                        >Demokratično komuniciranje, izbrana dela</hi>, eds. Slavko Splichal and
                    Igor Vobič (Ljubljana: Založba FDV, 1983/2020), 111–24.</note> and even
                contested in the later years of SFRY.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn10" n="6"
                    >“Slovenski novinarji nočejo biti družbenopolitični delavci: iz razprave na
                    posvetovanju DNS,” <hi rend="italic">Teorija in praksa</hi> 25, No. 5 (Maj,
                    1988): 627.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Against this backdrop, the main goal of this study is to explore journalistic role
                orientations and performances in socialist Yugoslavia based on occupational life
                histories of Tanjug news agency journalists. Combining theoretical, methodological
                and analytical approaches to ‘journalistic roles’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn11"
                    n="7">Thomas Hanitzsch and Tim P. Vos, “Journalism Beyond Democracy,” <hi
                        rend="italic">Journalism</hi> 19, No. 2 (February 2018): 146–64.</note> and
                ‘occupational life history’ research<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn12" n="8">Oren
                    Meyers and Roei Davidson, “Interviewing Interviewers”, <hi rend="italic">The
                        Communication Review</hi> 20, No. 4 (October 2017): 277–95, <ref
                        target="https://doi.org/10.1080/10714421.2017.1377952"
                        >https://doi.org/10.1080/10714421.2017.1377952</ref>.</note> permitted us to
                examine complex historical dynamics within journalism and reconsider its place in
                society. Namely, the occupational life history approach allowed us to not simply
                study journalistic “narrated roles”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn13" n="9">Thomas
                    Hanitzsch, “Journalistic Roles,” in: <hi rend="italic">The International
                        Encyclopedia of Journalism Studies</hi>, eds. Tim P. Vos and Folker Hanusch
                    (Hoboken: John Wiley &amp; Sons, 2019): 4, <ref
                        target="https://doi.org/10.1002/9781118841570.iejs0029"
                        >https://doi.org/10.1002/9781118841570.iejs0029</ref>.</note> in the
                    fore<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn14" n="10">Hanno Hardt, “Newsworkers,
                    Technology, and Journalism History,” <hi rend="italic">Cultural Studies in Mass
                        Communication</hi> 7, No. 4, (1990): 346–65. </note>, but also to consider
                journalistic roles as both “referential” (i.e., telling a story about the past) and
                “evaluative” (i.e., linking these stories to the present moment in which the story
                is narrated)<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn15" n="11">Meyers and Davidson,
                    “Interviewing Interviewers,” 281.</note> regarding the place of both journalism
                and Tanjug in socialist society. The national news agency Tanjug (established in
                1943) was the information backbone of the federal media system in Yugoslavia<note
                    place="foot" xml:id="ftn16" n="12">Peruško, Vozab and Čuvalo, <hi rend="italic"
                        >Comparing Post-Socialist Media Systems</hi>, 111.</note> and the
                coordinating agency of the Non-Aligned News Agency Pool (NANAP) (established in
                1974) with considerable international relevance in the global news system.<note
                    place="foot" xml:id="ftn17" n="13">Christian Vukasovich and Oliver Boyd-Barrett,
                    “Whatever Happened to Tanjug?,” <hi rend="italic">International Communication
                        </hi><hi rend="italic">Gazzette</hi> 74, No. 8 (October 2012), 693–710.
                </note> Tanjug held a central position in the institutional framework of journalism,
                thus making it a relevant case for a historical study of journalistic roles. For
                that purpose, the authors adopted the method of oral history interviews to conduct
                semi-structured conversations with former senior journalists, who had also worked as
                editors and foreign correspondents at the news agency from the late 1950s to
                1990s.</p>
            <div>
                <head>Theoretical Framework and Historical Context</head>
                <head>Journalistic roles in socialist Yugoslavia</head>
                <p>Journalistic roles refer “to the way journalists perceive, articulate, and enact
                    generalized expectations as to how journalism is serving society, both in
                    normative and descriptive terms”,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn18" n="14">
                        Hanitzsch, “Journalistic Roles,” 1.</note> while their remembering entails
                    additional referential and evaluative dimension.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn19" n="15">Meyers and Davidson, “Interviewing Interviewers,” 281.
                    </note> We therefore understand remembered journalistic roles as forms of
                    ‘present’ personal perceptions and articulations of the roles that journalists
                    performed in ‘past’ practice. In other words, they are narrated as
                    reinterpretations against, to paraphrase Hanitzsch (2019), what journalists <hi
                        rend="italic">should have done</hi> (normative role orientations), what they
                        <hi rend="italic">(cl)aimed they did</hi> (cognitive role orientations),
                    what journalists <hi rend="italic">actually did</hi> (practised role
                    performance), and what they <hi rend="italic">thought they did</hi> (narrated
                    role performance).<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn20" n="16">Hanitzsch,
                        “Journalistic Roles,” 1–9. </note> Journalistic roles thus, as a
                    “retrospective mechanism” (ibid.), become a more complex reflection of changes
                    in norms and ideals as well as journalistic practices and (self-)perceptions.
                    Understood in this way, journalistic roles are connected to the historical
                    conditions and journalism’s place in society, here socialist Yugoslavia.</p>
                <p>In the post-war years in early socialist Yugoslavia, journalists were normatively
                    conceived as collective agitators, propagandists and mobilisers according to the
                    mystified Marxist-Leninist understanding of the role of the press. <note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn21" n="17">France Vreg, <hi rend="italic"
                            >Demokratično komuniciranje</hi> (Maribor: Obzorja, 1990), 205–16.
                        Robinson, <hi rend="italic">Tito’s Maverick </hi><hi rend="italic"
                            >Media</hi>, 16–19.</note> Later on, following the introduction of
                    socialist self-management, journalists were re-institutionalised as
                    “socio-political workers” through inner normative contradictions, as an analysis
                    of the ethics codes indicated.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn22" n="18">Poler
                        Kovačič, “Normative Role Orientations of Yugoslav Journalists.”</note> The
                    normative foundations of Yugoslav journalism included the salient journalistic
                    roles of advocate of the proletariat and facilitator of the development of
                    socialist society defined by self-management, Yugoslav patriotism, and ideas of
                    non-alignment. At the same time, journalists aimed to provide ‘objective’
                    information, to be critical of the acts and ideas of technocratic bureaucracy,
                    liberalism, nationalism, and individualistic opportunism, as well as to
                    intervene in social life by contributing to education and development. As
                    previous research shows,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn23" n="19">Robinson, <hi
                            rend="italic">Tito’s Maverick Media</hi>, 118–27.</note> embedded within
                    the media that struggled to function as open socialist tribunes and drivers of
                    established societal goals, journalistic roles were (re)negotiated between what
                    appeared as informational-instructive and facilitative-collaborative roles.</p>
                <p>Over time, the normative eclecticism of the “Yugoslav school of journalism”<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn24" n="20">Gorjup, “Jugoslovanska “šola”
                        novinarstva,” in: Mitja Gorjup <hi rend="italic">, Samoupravno novinarstvo
                            (Izbor govorov in </hi><hi rend="italic">člankov)</hi>, ed. Vlado Jarc
                        (Ljubljana: Delavska enotnost, 1975/1978), 56, 57. Vreg, “Jugoslovanska šola
                        novinarstva,” 111–24.</note> was changing along with the media sphere’s
                    gradual liberalisation and journalism reorientation to critical openness,
                    undogmatic Marxist analysis of reality, professional ethics, and by refuting
                    state centralism in the information system and bureaucratic apologetics.
                    Journalism’s place in society was re-articulated with ideas arising from
                    different journalistic traditions, such as detached observation, promoting
                    deliberation, monitoring and criticising the holders of power, and being aligned
                    to commercial interests and alleged audience needs.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn25" n="21">Dina Vozab and Dunja Majstorović, “The Transformation
                        of Normative Approaches to Journalism in Croatian Academic Literature,” <hi
                            rend="italic">Croatian Political Science Review</hi> 58, No. 2 (2021),
                        17, 18. </note> The idea of the press as a political tribune with
                    journalists providing chronicles of the socialist reality, monitoring and
                    revealing social relations while heralding progressive tendencies among the
                    self-managing workers seemed pivotal in journalism’s idealisations. <note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn26" n="22">France Vreg, “Tisk in družba: Ali je
                        Leninova misel o vlogi tiska zastarela,” in: <hi rend="italic">France Vreg:
                            Demokratično</hi>
                        <hi rend="italic">komuniciranje, izbrana dela</hi>, eds. Slavko Splichal and
                        Igor Vobič (Ljubljana: Založba FDV, 1957/2020), 68. </note> Nevertheless, a
                    survey conducted by SNJ in 1969 showed that a large majority of journalists
                    answered a series of questions in line with the role of “apologists” in
                    political reporting, while only a small number aligned themselves with the role
                    of “critic”, indicating difficulties in independent journalistic conduct with
                    respect to the (in)formal political power.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn27"
                        n="23">Robinson, <hi rend="italic">Tito’s Maverick Media</hi>, 125, 126.
                    </note> While almost two-thirds of the journalists in SNJ were party members,
                    only about one- fifth were actively engaged in socio-political action beyond the
                        newsroom.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn28" n="24">Ibidem, 118–27.</note>
                    This was seen in journalistic conduct mostly reproducing the contradictions of
                    the one-party political system<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn29" n="25">Slavko
                        Splichal, <hi rend="italic">Media Beyond Socialism </hi>(Boulder: Westview,
                        1994), 27.</note>, in which “the political elites believed that the press
                    should be written by party officials rather than professional journalists, a
                    belief congruent with the dominant conception of the media as means of education
                    and propaganda”.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn30" n="26">Ibid., 69.</note>
                    During the decay of socialist self-management and the Yugoslav state in the
                    1980s, tensions in the political realm intensified, retrospectively showing that
                    journalists as socio-political workers were interpellated as “agents of
                    bureaucratic class struggle”.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn31" n="27">Rastko
                        Močnik, “V boj za svobodo javne beside – danes,” in: Karl Marx, <hi
                            rend="italic">Cenzura in svoboda tiska</hi>, ed. Rastko Močnik
                        (Ljubljana: KRT, 1986), 18.</note></p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>The Tanjug news agency in different information periods</head>
                <p>In this diverse socio-historical context, the Tanjug news agency belonged to a
                    small category of news agencies that were operating as ‘intermediaries’ between
                    world and national news agencies, “serving both a national but also a
                    significant international market, reporting the latter from a broader
                    perspective than that of domestic interest”.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn32"
                        n="28">Vukasovich and Boyd-Barrett, “Whatever happened to Tanjug?,”
                        695.</note> In her seminal work, Gertrude Robinson identified different
                    “information periods” related with the Tanjug’s growing organisational and
                    financial autonomy in its institutional history.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn33" n="29">Robinson, <hi rend="italic">Tito’s Maverick
                        Media</hi>, 81–85.</note> In the first post-war years, “all content was
                    censored” and Tanjug’s function as a government instrument – fully owned and
                    financed by it – was to “propagandize the socialist order”, while monopolising
                    all news flow to the fledgling press and radio in the country and developing its
                    international presence as importantly defined by the Cominform break in 1948.
                    With the beginnings of corporate autonomy and media re-institutionalisation in
                    Yugoslavia, official pre-censorship was abolished at Tanjug, now partially
                    financed by the media. Throughout the 1950s, it operated as a “transmission
                    belt” for official texts, namely, the word-for-word reproduction of plans,
                    reports and speeches, while the political news remained relatively undiversified
                    and served governmental needs for justifying the “Titoist self-management
                    philosophy” and its search for an independent political stance in international
                    relations. In the 1960s, the political filtering was moved from outside of the
                    agency to internal Tanjug councils, where the agency set its own filtering
                    criteria. Political news was subject to the limitations imposed by “internal
                    socialisation”, the government’s influence on Tanjug news production was
                    indirect through boards, while the importance of the party ‘aktiv’, an
                    institutionalised voice for the opinions and interests of both functionaries and
                    party members, was in decline at the agency. In the 1970s, the handling of
                    political information became once again much more sensitive after the League of
                    Communists’ return to centralism, following the ‘Croatian Spring’, among other
                    political, economic and cultural factors. Financed by the media, enterprises and
                    the government in almost equal shares, Tanjug strengthened its international
                    coverage and emphasised federal and inter-republic reporting with (again) more
                    carefully defined filtering criteria, also (re)affirming which subjects were
                    ‘taboo’, like nationalism and criticism of self-management.</p>
                <p>Besides the official celebratory self-portrayal of Tanjug (1983),<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn34" n="30">Tanjug, <hi rend="italic">Tanjug: Četiri
                            decenije</hi>. (Beograd: Tanjug, 1983).</note> little is known about its
                    organisation and function in the late period of socialist self-management when
                    the notion of journalists as socio-political workers was contested by
                    journalists themselves, eventually removed from the professional code of ethics,
                    while journalists started to see themselves as “public workers” who were “not
                    accountable to the working class or the League of Communists”. <note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn35" n="31">“Slovenski novinarji nočejo biti
                        družbenopolitični delavci: iz razprave na posvetovanju DNS,” <hi
                            rend="italic">Teorija in praksa</hi> 25, No. 5 (Maj, 1988): 627.</note>
                    Drawing on the theoretical reconsiderations of journalistic roles, the changing
                    socio-historical contexts of journalism’s place in society during socialist
                    Yugoslavia, and Tanjug’s complex relationship with power and the citizenry, we
                    address this research gap by posing the main research question: </p>
                <p style="text-align:center">How do former Tanjug journalists re-articulate their
                    roles as they remember their role orientations and performance during socialist
                    Yugoslavia?</p>
                <p>This historically and theoretically informed study has two aims. While it seeks
                    to analyse the correlation between “orientations” (norms and values) and
                    “performance” (practices and narratives)<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn36" n="32"
                        >Hanitzsch, “Journalistic Roles,” 1–9. </note> of former Tanjug journalists,
                    its primary focus is on the process of remembering not only to locate the
                    historical accounts of their occupational lives, but to unearth “how past
                    occurrences are remembered, shared or consciously or unconsciously interpreted
                    and reinterpreted over time by those who lived through them”.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn37" n="33">Miranda J. Banks, “Oral History and Media Industries,”
                            <hi rend="italic">Cultural Studies </hi>28, No. 4 (March, 2014),
                        547.</note></p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Methodology</head>
                <p>To address the main research question, the “collaborative (auto)biography
                        interview”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn38" n="34">Sharlene N. Hesse-Biber
                        and Patricia Leavy, <hi rend="italic">The Practice of Qualitative
                            Research</hi> (London: Sage, 2005).</note> method was adopted, which
                    allowed us to explore the dynamics between the personal, institutional and
                    societal in Tanjug’s history. By collecting and analysing “individual
                    histories”, potentially contaminated with faulty memories, opinions and
                    forgotten details,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn39" n="35">Banks, “Oral History
                        and Media Industries,” 545, 546.</note> this study goes through “a kind of
                    Rashomon” with various voices and versions of the ‘grand narrative’.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn40" n="36">Ibid.</note></p>
                <p>Sampling was established through a combination of snowballing and controlling for
                    different periods of Tanjug’s development (1950s–1990s) and news agency figures
                    holding experience not only as journalists, but also editors and foreign
                    correspondents to address the agency’s organisational structure and diversity.
                    Initial informants from academia and journalism were used to nominate
                    interviewees and each interviewee was then asked to suggest names of former
                    Tanjug journalists according to the control criteria. In the periods before,
                    between or after their foreign correspondent positions, all of the interviewees
                    were journalists and editors for Tanjug news services for Yugoslavia and for
                    other countries, economic information, and information publications and other
                    services. The interviewees’ educational background is in the social sciences and
                    humanities, with most holding a law degree and having been members of the League
                    of Communists of Yugoslavia. Some had reservations about having their full names
                    published and we thus decided to anonymise all interviewees.</p>
                <table rend="rules">
                    <head>Table 1: The interviewees</head>
                    <row>
                        <cell rend="left"/>
                        <cell rend="center"><hi rend="bold">Date</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="center"><hi rend="bold">Period with Tanjug</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="left"><hi rend="bold">Foreign Correspondent: Place and
                                Period</hi></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell rend="center">int1</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">14/03/2017</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">1975–2005</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">Cuba (Havana): 1975–1983</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell rend="center">int2</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">14/03/2017</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">1959–1997</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">GDR (Berlin): 1968–1972; Soviet Union/Russia (Moscow):
                            1978–1982; 1995–1996; Czechoslovakia (Prague): 1985–1989</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell rend="center">int3</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">15/03/2017</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">1966–1994</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">Sweden (Stockholm): 1984–1988</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell rend="center">int4</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">03/03/2017</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">1975–2005</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">Mexico (Mexico City): 1979–1983; Cuba (Havana):
                            1987–1991</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell rend="center">int5</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">08/03/2017</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">1975–1992</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">West Africa: 1982–1987</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell rend="center">int6</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">01/03/2017</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">1972–1992</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">Italy (Rome): 1985–1989</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell rend="center">int7</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">18/02/2017</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">1959–1980; 1981–1994</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">Soviet Union (Moscow): 1970–1974; China (Beijing):
                            1976–1980; 1991–1993</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell rend="center">int8</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">20/03/2017</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">1957–1996</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">Soviet Union/Russia (Moscow):1968–1970; 1992–1996;
                            Czechoslovakia (Prague): 1980–1984; GDR/Germany (Berlin):
                            1988–1991</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell rend="center">int9</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">04/03/2017</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">1965–1996</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">Kenya (Nairobi): 1972–1975; Italy (Rome): late 1970s;
                            United Nations (New York): 1986–1989; Belgium (Brussels): early
                            1990s</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell rend="center">int10</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">09/03/2017</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">1959–1996</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">United Kingdom (London): 1975–1980; France (Paris):
                            1984–1988; 1992–1996</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell rend="center">int11</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">22/02/2017</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">1978–1994</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">Romania (Bucharest): 1985–1988; 1991–1994</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell rend="center">int12</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">24/02/2017</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">1969–1995</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">Ghana (Akra): 1977–1981; Kenya (Nairobi): 1984–1989;
                            Italy (Rome): 1992; Switzerland (Geneva): 1994–1995</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell rend="center">int13</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">07/03/2017</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">1970–2006</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">Egypt (Cairo): 1982–1986; Israel: 1987–1991; Switzerland
                            (Geneva): 1995–1998; Belgium (Brussels): 2001–2005</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell rend="center">int14</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">06/03/2017</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">1969–2010</cell>
                        <cell rend="center">Sweden (Stockholm): 1981–1985; Greece (Athens):
                            1987–1991; Turkey (Istanbul): 1994–1997 </cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>Each interview conversation was both ‘structured’ with an interview guide
                    developed around the main problem-centred themes (biographical history,
                    journalistic roles, journalism–power relations) and ‘open’ by letting the
                    interviewees “set the course of the interview, within reason” and included
                    follow-up questions to interrogate the process of remembering.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn41" n="37">Mike Conway, “Oral History Interviews,” <hi
                            rend="italic">The International Encyclopedia of Media Studies</hi>
                        (December 2013): 155–78, <ref
                            target="https://doi.org/10.1002/9781444361506.wbiems177"
                            >https://doi.org/10.1002/9781444361506.wbiems177</ref>.</note> The
                    interviews were conducted in Belgrade in public places like cafés and
                    journalistic clubs, and in private spaces like interviewees’ offices and
                    apartments, had an average length of 1 h 52 min (shortest: 1 h 17 min; longest:
                    2 h 58 min). The interviews were conducted in-person in the Serbian language,
                    audio recorded, and transcribed verbatim. The anonymised transcripts are
                    available from the Social Sciences Data Archive in Ljubljana.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn42" n="38">Igor Vobič and Ana Milojević, <hi rend="italic"
                            >Novinarstvo novinske agencije Tanjug u periodu socialističke
                            Jugoslavije, 2017 [podatkovna datoteka]</hi> (Ljubljana: Faculty of Social Sciences, Social Science
                        Data Archives, 2022), <ref target="https://doi.org/10.17898/ADP_TANJUG17_V1">https://doi.org/10.17898/ADP_TANJUG17_V1</ref>.</note></p>
                <p>The exploration of remembering journalistic roles entailed three levels of
                    analysis. First, we used the qualitative data analysis software NVivo ‘to node’
                    the journalists’ statements according to the six elementary journalistic
                    functions identified by Hanitzsch: informational-instructive,
                    analytical-deliberative, critical-monitorial, advocative-radical,
                    developmental-educative, collaborative-facilitative.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn43" n="39">Hanitzsch, “Journalistic Roles,” 1–9.</note>
                </p>
                <p>Second, after we identified the collaborative-facilitative role as the most
                    prominent one, we focused on the referential (i.e., journalists’ accounts of the
                    Tanjug socialist past) and evaluative (i.e., interrogating those accounts of the
                    past with the present interview context) dimensions of a journalist’s
                        memory<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn44" n="40">Meyers and Davidson,
                        “Interviewing Interviewers,” 281.</note> to reveal their adaptive strategies
                    of remembering.</p>
                <p>This led us to the third level of analysis where we considered the collaborative
                    role in greater depth with respect to (in)consistencies noticed in the
                    journalistic narrated roles. The focus on adaptive strategies and ‘new’
                    negotiations of ‘old’ institutionalised orientations and practices meant three
                    distinctive articulations within the collaborative journalistic role could be
                    identified.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Results: Remembering Journalistic Roles at the Tanjug News Agency</head>
                <div>
                    <head>Collaborative journalists, but not socio-political workers</head>
                    <p>The interview analysis indicates a lack of correspondence between normative
                        foundations defining journalists as socio-political workers and the
                        interviewees’ remembering and making sense of journalistic ideals, practices
                        and perceptions during socialism. Most interviewees regarded the notion of
                        socio-political worker as “ridiculous” (int3, int5, int13) or “irrelevant”
                        (int2), presenting it as an idea imposed from the outside and characterising
                        it as the counter-notion of a “journalist” (int3, int4, int7) or
                        “professional” (int10), “It was going in one ear and out the other, it
                        didn't concern me much, simply because I didn't have my personal, internal
                        affinities to be a socio-political worker, and I didn't care” (int2). Some
                        interviewees discussed the notion as “a phrase” (int2), “a formula” (int9)
                        or “slogan” (int14) used by political power to define the place held by
                        journalism in the political realm, as a means of limiting and surveilling
                        journalism, particularly critical journalists, while stating that some
                        colleagues were willing to accept it. Only one journalist stressed that he
                        openly regarded himself as a socio-political worker, “I accepted that in the
                        sense that I did responsible social work, which influenced the formation of
                        public opinion, and with that work I informed the public in my country about
                        the circumstances and political processes, and about the economy, sports,
                        culture in the country where I lived. In that sense, I was a social and
                        public worker” (int8).</p>
                    <p>While the interviewed journalists generally refused to align themselves as a
                        socio-political worker, the interview narrations indicate the dominance of
                        the collaborative function in Tanjug journalists’ (re)assessments of their
                        roles during the SFRY period. Namely, the interview analysis reveals a
                        dominant understanding of Tanjug journalists as “political partners” (int5)
                        and their journalistic conduct as “supportive of the main political line”
                        (int7) of the SFRY government, involving their “integral” function in the
                        development not only of self-managed socialism as a social system, but as
                        “part of the general state policy with respect to national affairs and
                        international relations” (int8). These inconsistencies allowed us to outline
                        the adaptive strategies of remembering and different roles in collaborative
                        journalism.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Adaptive strategies of remembering collaborative journalism</head>
                    <p>As the interviewees remembered the collaborative function as having been
                        dominant, they re-articulated the thematic boundaries of their journalistic
                        conduct as the “untouchable values” (int5) and the “limits” (int2), which
                        were not imposed but informally identified within newsrooms by journalists
                        and editors (int8) or were “simply known” (int2). Subjects not to be
                        questioned and to be reported on with particular sensitivity were President
                        Josip Broz Tito, the National Liberation Struggle during the Second World
                        War, the idea of Brotherhood and Unity in Yugoslavia, Self-Management as a
                        social system and philosophy, and the idea and movement of the
                        Non-Aligned.</p>
                    <quote>Unbelievable … I mean, none of us ever slipped off that path. Nobody told
                        us anything, they didn't force us, they didn't punish us, but everything
                        went well. The policy of the state is like that, and in a way, I have no
                        idea, a special, inexplicable way we knew it was like that, and we all
                        behaved like that. I really can't even explain. (int11)</quote>
                    <p>However, the interviewees acknowledged that editors and journalists
                        identified these boundaries also through the socialisation of newcomers. In
                        one instance, an interviewee had written a commentary about the SFRY’s
                        decision to write off the debt of some Non-Aligned countries. The commentary
                        was accepted by the editor-in-chief and published without the author’s name.
                        When the chief of staff in the government cabinet read the commentary aimed
                        at a top state official, he called the managing director of Tanjug and
                        demanded that the author be “thrown out” (int13).</p>
                    <quote>Then the director (…) called the editor-in-chief and asked, “Who wrote
                        this?” He said: “This young man of ours”. And then he [the editor-in-chief]
                        called the chief of staff and said, “Listen, you will have to remove me,
                        because I take responsibility”. (…) Then, the next day, the secretary of the
                        editor-in-chief told me that he had rewarded me with 40,000 dinars because
                        of that comment. My salary, for example, was 120,000 dinars at the time. I
                        said, “Okay”. After half an hour, the secretary of the director called and
                        said: “The director has given you a 60,000 dinar fine”. I asked, “Why?”. She
                        said, “I'll put him on”. And he spoke through his nose. I said, “Comrade
                        Director, what is this?”. “Kid", he said, "let this be a lesson. You are
                        still at the level of ordinary news and you dare to write a commentary”.
                        (int13)</quote>
                    <p>Not only across the interviews, but also within them at least three adaptive
                        strategies of remembering were identified with respect to the thematic
                        boundaries Tanjug journalists acknowledged in news agency production. These
                        mechanisms were adopted by the interviewees not to normalise Tanjug’s
                        collaborative function so much as legitimise themselves as professional
                        journalists in SFRY and to validate themselves as present interpreters of
                        journalism during the socialist self-management. The first adaptive strategy
                        was ‘appropriating’ the notions of ‘truth’, ‘news’ and ‘accuracy’, mending
                        them with respect to the established journalism–power relationship in the
                        country at that time and the national interests of SFRY.</p>
                    <quote>Everything that was covered and everywhere Tanjug reported from
                        regularly, I must say, was true. With the following note: it was true in
                        accordance with the reporting criteria at the time. So, what Tanjug did not
                        dare, but the journalists knew about it, was considered not their fault that
                        they did not write about it. In that sense, everything that Tanjug reported
                        was true. (int2)</quote>
                    <quote>You know what, we were always told from the top of the state, from the
                        state, party, political or whatever, “We are working in the interests of
                        this country and we are all doing the same job, you just do it in a
                        different way”. Let me tell you something, at that time we did not lie. We
                        kept some things quiet. We emphasised some things, we emphasised other
                        things a little less, but we did not lie. (…) You could write about
                        anything, about mistakes and I don't know what else, in a way that you did
                        not compromise your country and your people and their interests, and still
                        tell the truth. (int8)</quote>
                    <quote>I stuck to what Stane Dolanc [one of President Tito’s closest allies]
                        once said. I thought the man was right. He said something like, “Not all
                        news, even if it's good, is necessarily good for the state”. (int13)</quote>
                    <p>In addition, one interviewee used this strategy to add legitimacy to his
                        journalistic work for Tanjug by appropriating the notions of
                        ‘professionalism’ and ‘skill’.</p>
                    <quote>If you have accepted to work in journalism, don't dig around, you can,
                        but you won't last long. Yet, within the frame you could do whatever you
                        want. You could be a good professional, and skilful. (int5)</quote>
                    <quote>The second strategy of adaptation saw the framework of ‘deciding what’s
                        (not) news’ as part of ‘business as usual’, legitimising their other
                        “critical reports” (int2) for the Tanjug news agency and the boundaries in
                        their conduct as “normal” (int8) and “without a dilemma” (int14).</quote>
                    <quote>You could write critically about anything that was happening in
                        Yugoslavia, except Tito, (…), Non-Alignment, you also did not dare [to
                        criticise] the Yugoslav National Army, but the League of Communists you did.
                        There was criticism, even harsh [criticism]. Nobody went into experiments;
                        we just knew what we could do. (int2)</quote>
                    <quote>The briefings were at the Ministry of Foreign Affairs. I frequently went
                        there. This is done everywhere in the world. We come from all national
                        affairs newsrooms in the country without foreign correspondents, and the
                        minister said, “Please, we are interested that our state announced this,
                        that, this and that”. And, “Please ask this question”. That was a completely
                        normal thing and is everywhere around the world. (int8)</quote>
                    <p>The third adaptive strategy of remembering was to self-reflect on the
                        thematic boundaries of Tanjug news production by using the notion of
                        ‘self-censorship’, legitimising their past journalistic conduct as well as
                        their current reasoning of it.</p>
                    <quote>We just knew it. It was self-censorship, of course. We just knew what not
                        to write. If you write that, they will either delete it for you, or they
                        will release it somewhere, so you will have to answer for it in some way.
                        (int2)</quote>
                    <quote>I never lied. I guess my colleagues also did not lie. Maybe they kept
                        quiet about some things. (…) The truth can be told in different ways. Well,
                        they announced that truth in such a way that it was not in conflict with
                        state and party interests. It was self-censorship. It meant moving within
                        the general framework of state and national interests. (int8)</quote>
                    <p>One interviewee stressed that “keeping quiet about some things” was not
                        enough, you also had “spit on the other side” (int14). A similar adaptation
                        was expressed by another interviewee, operating with the notion of
                        “propaganda” to discuss journalistic objectivity with respect to the
                        thematic boundaries, while self-labelling Tanjug journalism as “regime” and
                        “Titoist” (int12).</p>
                    <quote>There was, foremost, objectivity as a kind of given framework in which
                        you move because you do not know the full truth. And then what you learned
                        and saw you tried to adjust it a little as befitted the propaganda. (…) As
                        far as the propaganda moment is concerned, it was exclusively Titoist in
                        internal political journalism. (…) Most seem to have believed that I was a
                        regime journalist based on what they could read. (int12)</quote>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Three collaborative journalistic roles</head>
                    <p>As a higher-order structure, the dominant collaborative function defined the
                        journalistic roles the interviewees constructed through ‘new’
                        re-negotiations of ‘old’ institutionalised orientations and practices. Three
                        collaborative journalistic roles were articulated in the interviews:
                        privileged disseminator, monitoring analyst, and educator.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Privileged disseminator.</hi> This role of disseminating
                        information was central in the interviewees’ narrations, expressed through a
                        contradictory mix of the idea of journalists as detached observers, the
                        aspiration to provide objective accounts of news, and the concept of a
                        mouthpiece relaying and curating official information. On one hand, the
                        interview data indicate Tanjug journalists disseminated news in line with
                        the “dual role” (int5) of the ‘General Service’, that is, informing about
                        general news with its federal and international network of offices and
                        correspondents, while having the “privilege” as a national agency to
                        exclusively access and disseminate news of great societal or state
                        importance.</p>
                    <quote>As time went on, the media scene developed more and more, newspapers and
                        stations began to ask the state authorities for some information, there were
                        situations when they said: “Wait for Tanjug”. We conveyed the official
                        government position. (int5)</quote>
                    <quote>We had to take care not to go out of certain frames and so on, but we had
                        the freedom to process and interpret the words of the highest-ranking
                        officials, looking for [relevant] information. And that is what was most
                        important in our work, that information. (int6)</quote>
                    <p>One interview explains the dissemination status of the Tanjug news agency
                        with an example of when an ‘official secret’ was published by mistake. He
                        had been late for a meeting at the Chamber of Commerce.</p>
                    <quote>The topic was the debts of the Non-Aligned countries, all due to
                        Yugoslavia. I sat down and wrote [what the chamber president was saying],
                        Iran owes so and so, Iraq so and so, Libya so and so, everyone owes us
                        [SFRY]. I came back to Tanjug, sat down and wrote the piece. The next
                        morning, all of the newspapers published the story on their front pages. (…)
                        The director, the editor-in-chief, called me and said, “Are you normal? You
                        have revealed a state secret”. (…) I had been late [for the meeting and had
                        not heard] the president of the chamber declare “This is not for
                        publication”. (int11)</quote>
                    <p>On the other hand, Tanjug journalists also disseminated news solemnly to the
                        state leadership and high officials as members of the ‘Newsroom for
                        Information Publications and Services’ (RIPS), which produced special
                        thematic ‘bulletins’ and the ‘Direct Telegraph Service’ (DTS). Through these
                        channels, they provided news that “should not have been published in the
                        General Service” (int2) and “should not have reached the press according to
                        some criteria” (int5), but was relevant for the state leadership, for
                        instance, what was being written about SFRY in the international press.</p>
                    <quote>In fact, all of us journalists vetted ourselves in some way. Because
                        there we transmitted agency news, which was very unfavourable to Yugoslavia,
                        to Tito. But there was no censorship. Interesting. Sometimes, that service
                        was three times better than the general service. (int13)</quote>
                    <p>One interviewee explained that a derivative of RIPS was ‘censorship’ of the
                        international press if there was “a negative text about Yugoslavia”
                        (int4):</p>
                    <quote>I worked as a censor at Tanjug for a while. There was a group of us
                        journalists who received all the Western press before it was distributed in
                        Yugoslavia and, if there was for instance news about a quarrel between Tito
                        and Jovanka [his wife], that copy did not go out to the kiosks. It was a
                        privilege for us because we could look at magazines and newspapers that
                        others could not. And then to review it all. (int4)</quote>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Monitoring analyst.</hi> This salient role involves
                        explaining events in the news or a certain relevant phenomenon in SFRY or
                        other countries by describing the background, revealing the details and
                        curating the statistical data gathered in order to scrutinise existing power
                        relations, respond to misconduct or exemplify social paradoxes. On one hand,
                        regarding this role the interviewees referred as Tanjug’s correspondents
                        from other countries, portraying their work as ‘critical’, yet closely
                        bounded by the position of SFRY in international relations.</p>
                    <quote>I had the luck, rather than misfortune, of publishing a lot from East
                        Berlin [as a correspondent]. Because they criticised us [SFRY] and I treated
                        them in the same way, within what is allowed in our occupation, of course.
                        (int2)</quote>
                    <quote>In January 1985, I went as the Tanjug correspondent to Bucharest. (…) [By
                        the end of the decade] I was the most western correspondent there. They were
                        all from the countries of the Warsaw Pact, and I was from Yugoslavia, I did
                        not fit in, I was disobedient. Because I was constantly critical. They were
                        looking for various ways, through the party, through the state, through the
                        government … And in the end, our people [Tanjug] pulled me out.
                        (int11)</quote>
                    <p>Some journalists stressed that it was common for a journalist to attend a
                        meeting at the Ministry of Foreign Affairs “not to get assignments”, but for
                        “a consultation” about the current problems of the country they were going
                        to cover as a correspondent (int8). In this context, the interviewees
                        stressed that through their news and analysis of other countries they were
                        indirectly critical of SFRY.</p>
                    <quote>In this way, the comparison became a matter of public opinion. When I was
                        writing about the elections, it was written about the multi-party system, it
                        could not have been avoided. The readers here [in SFRY] could conclude,
                        “Yes, it’s not just one party. You see, there are countries”. So, by the
                        nature of things, foreign news journalism provided many
                        possibilities.</quote>
                    <quote>[W]hat I reported on from Africa was a critique of the cult of
                        personality and dictatorship of one party. So, on two occasions, risking
                        being returned [to Yugoslavia], I criticised from Africa what was happening
                        in Yugoslavia and in Titoism. (int12)</quote>
                    <p>On the other hand, this role refers more directly to social relations within
                        SFRY, covering, for instance, breaches of workers’ rights based on the idea
                        of self-managed labour, corruption and crime, with a view to revealing what
                        “endangers the achievements of the revolution” (int5).</p>
                    <quote>Well, that's how it happened, in economic topics, not only at Tanjug,
                        everywhere in journalism, to expose a director of [a certain company] for
                        restricting the self-management rights of workers and then list economic
                        indicators that have nothing to do with self-management, but show that this
                        one is running the company badly and so on. (int5)</quote>
                    <quote>In all that, you could really write about irregularities, about the
                        corruption that was then, something small relative to today’s corruption,
                        about thefts, bad directors, you could write about everything without any
                        problems. (int3)</quote>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Educator.</hi> This role refers to the pedagogical function
                        of journalism whereby journalists educate, spread knowledge, and raise
                        awareness of the implications held by certain events or processes. The
                        journalistic role of educator is marginally articulated by the interviewees
                        with respect to ‘oral news’ performed in factories, mines, or army academies
                        – not only by journalists of Tanjug, but other media as well. The
                        editor-in-chief from the late 1980s stressed that oral news was “not part of
                        the Tanjug editorial policy” (int1), but only done occasionally, while
                        journalists from previous periods described it as “regular” and performed
                        “by mutual agreement” (int2).</p>
                    <quote>A few journalists gathered and then the oral news was announced and then
                        those journalists talked about what they would write in the newspaper. They
                        tell some interesting things, present political texts and so on. For
                        example, I took part in one, as a Tanjug journalist, on the [Yugoslav Navy
                        training] ship Galeb [used as an official boat by President Tito]. We were
                        with the cadets of the military academies who were sailing from Split on a
                        trip around the Mediterranean. (int2)</quote>
                    <quote>In 1974, when a new constitution was adopted, we who were working as
                        political journalists were engaged and asked to go to collectives and
                        explain what these changes in the constitution bring, how they affect
                        everyday life and so on. (int8)</quote>
                    <p>While explaining the main societal role of journalists in SFRY, one
                        interviewee stressed “being present among people” (int10) and gave an
                        example of oral news.</p>
                    <quote>So, we went to a company, a mine, and we told them about foreign or
                        domestic policy. There was always one journalist covering international
                        affairs, one for the current affairs, and then you had a conversation that
                        lasted for hours. They asked about politics, about everything. /…/ It was
                        actually a nice exchange with those people and then we prepared an article.
                        (int10)</quote>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Discussion and Conclusion</head>
                <p>This study aimed to determine how former Tanjug journalists re-articulated their
                    roles as they remembered their role orientations and performance based on the
                    occupational life history approach. During the oral interviews, the authors
                    tried to guide the former journalists to reflect on their own work, the
                    institutionalised practices at Tanjug, journalism practice in socialist
                    Yugoslavia more broadly, as well as the normative foundations and professional
                    ideals as they remembered them. Although the interviews were guided to
                    distinguish between these levels, our respondents flattened them in their
                    recollections, making it difficult to separate role orientations from
                    performance while analysing their responses. The portrayals of journalism’s
                    place in society during socialism emerged as condensed assessments reduced to
                    compact representations devoid of subtle distinctions and variations, largely
                    resting on simplified relational generalisations in a diachronic and synchronic
                    sense between journalism ‘then’ and ‘now’, journalism in Yugoslavia and
                    ‘elsewhere’, and the journalism of Tanjug and other media. Throughout the data,
                    inconsistencies, tensions and contradictions were apparent in the interviewees’
                    narrations between the normative foundations of professional journalism in
                    socialist Yugoslavia and beyond, dominant institutional values, attitudes and
                    beliefs regarding the place Tanjug held in social communication, and their
                    remembering of their performance as Tanjug journalists, editors and
                    correspondents.</p>
                <p>Moreover, it must be considered that we examined a long time period and
                    journalistic work in a socio-political system that was changing considerably
                    during its trajectory, ending with the breaking up of Yugoslavia along with the
                    fall of socialism. Historically, the place of journalism in society has always
                    been re-negotiated with respect to the prevailing views on freedom of the press,
                    the materiality and contradictions of news production, and the institutional
                    re-affirmation of journalism. Regarding this, the findings support previous
                    research into Tanjug’s diverse institutional development as concerns the news
                    agency’s organisational and financial autonomy and its integral position within
                    the changing journalism–power–citizenry nexus in SFRY.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn45" n="41">Robinson, <hi rend="italic">Tito’s Maverick
                        Media</hi>, 81–85. </note> The occupational life histories we gathered
                    confirm the general trajectories of Tanjug’s reconfiguration as a “transmission
                    belt” of the state, the news agency’s gradual autonomisation, and diverse
                    (re)affirmation of ‘taboo subjects’ throughout its development in SFRY.</p>
                <p>Observed within the boundaries of a national agency setting, the findings
                    correspond to the broader transfigurations of journalism in Yugoslavia. The
                    literature review shows that journalists in SFRY had difficulty attaining
                    independence from the (in)formal political power and were inclined to perform as
                    apologists rather than critics in the political realm.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn46" n="42">Ibid. Splichal, <hi rend="italic">Media Beyond Socialism</hi>.
                        Peruško, Vozab and Čuvalo, <hi rend="italic">Comparing </hi><hi
                            rend="italic">Post-Socialist Media Systems</hi>.</note> While such role
                    performance was congruent with the idea of journalists as socio-political
                    workers and the dominant conception of the “media as a means of education and
                        propaganda”,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn47" n="43">Splichal, <hi
                            rend="italic">Media Beyond Socialism</hi>.</note> it was gradually
                    contested by journalists as socialist self-management went into decay.
                    Journalism’s normative underpinnings and its idealisations were altered
                    alongside the structural and ideological changes occurring in politics, the
                    economy as well as international relations.</p>
                <p>These historical gradual dynamics surfaced in our interviews when dismissing the
                    notion of a socio-political worker as “ridiculous”, “irrelevant” and the
                    counter-notion of a “journalist” or a “professional”. Further, journalists were
                    remembering the “idea of a socio-political worker” as imposed from the outside
                    and used for surveillance and disciplining, especially of critical journalists.
                    However, against this de-alignment, we found the collaborative function to have
                    been dominant in the Tanjug journalists’ narrations. This kind of ambivalence
                    might illustrate contradictions between orientation and performance, narration
                    and practice, collective and individual in general, and journalistic
                    articulations of their roles during the SFRY period, vis-à-vis the temporal
                    re-evaluation of the journalism and society during socialist self-management in
                    particular.</p>
                <p>Against this backdrop, this study makes two original contributions. First, by
                    identifying inconsistencies in journalistic reflections the study reflects on
                    the remembering of journalistic roles as forms of ‘present’ personal perceptions
                    and (re)articulations of ‘past’ orientations and performances. These
                    inconsistencies proved to be valuable for identifying the adaptive strategies of
                    remembering the journalists used to legitimise themselves as professionals and
                    relevant interpreters of SFRY journalism. As the main adaptive strategies, we
                    identified the appropriating of the notions of truth, news and accuracy,
                    correcting news values, and interrogating self-censorship with respect to the
                    journalism–power relationship inside the country and the position of SFRY in the
                    international arena. Second, our analysis revealed more nuances within the
                    common, often simplified understandings held by journalists as collaborators
                    with the party and the state in socialist regimes. Here, the journalistic role
                    conceptualisation and the analytical framework based on elementary journalistic
                        functions<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn48" n="44">Hanitzsch, “Journalistic
                        Roles,” 1–9. Hanitzsch and Vos, “Journalism Beyond Democracy,” 146–64.
                    </note> proved to be fruitful for highlighting more specific manifestations of
                    the collaborative function (i.e., privileged disseminator, monitoring analyst,
                    educator). The study thus contributes to the journalistic roles scholarship by
                    introducing a historical approach to exploring journalistic reflection as a
                    “retrospective mechanism”,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn49" n="45">Hanitzsch,
                        “Journalistic Roles,” 1–9. </note> operating against norms, ideals and media
                    practices as well as the synchronic and diachronic complexities of personal,
                    institutional and societal articulations of journalistic roles.</p>
                <p>Still, we must acknowledge that human memory is generally associated with
                    incoherence and inconsistency in our interviews could be even more specific
                    because they relate to understanding socialism from a contemporary perspective,
                    from which the socialist politico-economic system and journalistic
                    collaborative-facilitative function might entail varying connotations. Namely,
                    we analysed journalists’ recollections of a system that is radically different
                    from the one they are living in today, and that fact surely skewed their
                    perceptions, at least somewhat. Therefore, the adaptive strategies and
                    contradictions arising between embracing and dismissing the collaborative role
                    in the journalists’ narratives could be discussed much further relative to the
                    question of journalism freedom from external and internal sources of influence,
                    especially the ideology in a given system and historical context. Although we
                    believe such an endeavour would generate interesting insights, that lies beyond
                    the scope of this study.</p>
                <p>This study also exposes the limits of oral history interviews, condensing
                    institutional and societal complexities through personal reflections based on
                    simplified relational generalisations. To overcome such limitations, we took
                    them into account and analysed the inconsistencies, tensions and contradictions
                    in the interviewees’ narrations against a firm theoretical basis and profound
                    contextual background. Still, our view is that further historical research into
                    journalistic roles should not only interrogate professional remembering
                    (interviews with former journalists), but also explore their historical
                    re-articulations by investigating institutionalised values, attitudes and
                    beliefs (i.e., analysis of internal media documents) and examining media
                    performance (i.e., content analysis of news). Given that, like in the political
                    and academic realms, journalism’s place in society during SFRY was chiefly
                    positioned with simplified monolithic descriptions, theoretically informed and
                    methodologically diverse scholarship is essential for shedding light on
                    diversities.</p>
            </div>

        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="bibliography">
                <head>Sources and Literature</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Literature</head>
                    <bibl>Banks, Miranda J. “Oral History and Media Industries.” <hi rend="italic"
                            >Cultural Studies</hi> 28, No. 4 (March 2014): 545–60.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Conway, Mike. “Oral History Interviews.” <hi rend="italic">The
                            International Encyclopedia of Media Studies</hi>, (December 2013):
                        155–78. John Wiley &amp; Sons. Available at: <ref
                            target="https://doi.org/10.1002/9781444361506.wbiems177"
                            >https://doi.org/10.1002/9781444361506.wbiems177</ref>.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Gorjup, Mitja. “Ponuditi moramo svetu nov tip informiranja.” In: Mitja
                            Gorjup,<hi rend="italic"> Samoupravno novinarstvo (Izbor govorov in
                            člankov)</hi>. Ed. Vlado Jarc, 59–66. Ljubljana: Delavska enotnost,
                        1975/1978.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Gorjup, Mitja. “Jugoslovanska “šola” novinarstva.” In: Mitja Gorjup, <hi
                            rend="italic"> Samoupravno novinarstvo (Izbor govorov in člankov).
                        </hi>Ed. Vlado Jarc, 56 –57. Ljubljana: Delavska enotnost, 1975/1978.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Hanitzsch, Thomas. “Journalistic Roles.” In: <hi rend="italic">The
                            International Encyclopedia of Journalism Studies</hi>. Eds Tim P. Vos
                        and Folker Hanusch, 1 –9. Hoboken: John Wiley &amp; Sons, 2019. DOI: <ref
                            target="https://doi.org/10.1002/9781118841570.iejs0029"
                            >10.1002/9781118841570.iejs0029</ref>.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Hanitzsch, Thomas and Tim P. Vos. “Journalism Beyond Democracy.” <hi
                            rend="italic">Journalism</hi> 19, No. 2 (February 2018): 146–64.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Hardt, Hanno. “Newsworkers, Technology, and Journalism History.” <hi
                            rend="italic">Cultural Studies in Mass Communication</hi> 7, No. 4
                        (1990): 346–65.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Hesse-Biber, Sharlene N. and Patricia Leavy. <hi rend="italic">The
                            Practice of Qualitative Research</hi>. London: Sage, 2005.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Meyers, Oren and Roei Davidson. “Interviewing Interviewers.” <hi
                            rend="italic">The Communication Review</hi> 20, No. 4 (October, 2017):
                        277–95. Available at: <ref
                            target="https://doi.org/10.1080/10714421.2017.1377952"
                            >https://doi.org/10.1080/10714421.2017.1377952</ref>.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Močnik, Rastko. “V boj za svobodo javne beside – danes.” In: Karl Marx,
                            <hi rend="italic">Cenzura in svoboda tiska</hi>. Ed. Rastko Močnik,
                        7–24. Ljubljana: KRT, 1986.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Peruško, Zrinjka, Dina Vozab and Antonija Čuvalo. <hi rend="italic"
                            >Comparing Post-Socialist Media Systems</hi>. London, New York:
                        Routledge, 2021.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Poler Kovačič, Melita. “Normative Role Orientations of Yugoslav Journalists.” <hi
                            rend="italic">Prispevki za novejšo zgodovino</hi> 62, No. 1
                        (2022): 64-81.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Robinson, Gertrude J. <hi rend="italic">Tito’s Maverick Media</hi>.
                        Chicago: University of Illinois Press, 1977.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Splichal, Slavko. <hi rend="italic">Media Beyond Socialism</hi>. Boulder:
                        Westview, 1994.</bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="italic">Tanjug: Četiri decenije</hi>. Beograd: Tanjug,
                        1983.</bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="italic">Teorija in praksa</hi> 25, No. 5 (1988). “Slovenski
                        novinarji nočejo biti družbenopolitični delavci: iz razprave na posvetovanju
                        DNS.”</bibl>
                    <bibl>Tito, Josip Broz. “Od novinara se nikad nije tražila slijepa poslušnost.”
                        In: <hi rend="italic">Tito o informisanju</hi>. Ed. Miroslav Đorđević,
                        179–80. Beograd: RTB, 1970/1980.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Tito, Josip Broz. “Ne slažem se sa štampom kada dramatizira pojedine
                        slučajeve.” In: <hi rend="italic">Tito o informisanju</hi>. Ed. Miroslav
                        Đorđević, 191. Beograd: RTB, 1971/1980.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Tito, Josip Broz. “Novinari odlično obavili posao u Havani.” In: <hi
                            rend="italic">Tito o informisanju. </hi>Ed. Miroslav Đorđević, 243, 244.
                        Beograd: RTB, 1979/1980.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Vozab, Dina and Dunja Majstorović. “The Transformation of Normative
                        Approaches to Journalism in Croatian Academic Literature.” <hi rend="italic"
                            >Croatian Political Science Review</hi> 58, No. 2 (2021): 7–32.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Vreg, France. “Tisk in družba: Ali je Leninova misel o vlogi tiska
                        zastarela.” In: France Vreg, <hi rend="italic">Demokratično komuniciranje,
                            izbrana dela</hi>. Eds. Slavko Splichal and Igor Vobič, 59–68.
                        Ljubljana: Založba FDV, 1957/2020.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Vreg, France. “Jugoslovanska šola novinarstva.” In: France Vreg, <hi
                            rend="italic">Demokratično komuniciranje, izbrana dela</hi>. Eds. Slavko
                        Splichal and Igor Vobič, 111–24. Ljubljana: Založba FDV, 1983/2020.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Vreg, France. <hi rend="italic">Demokratično komuniciranje</hi>. Maribor:
                        Obzorja, 1990.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Vukasovich, Christian and Oliver Boyd-Barrett. “Whatever Happened to
                        Tanjug?.” <hi rend="italic">International Communication Gazzette</hi> 74,
                        No. 8 (October 2012): 693–710.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Online sources</head>
                    <bibl>Vobič, Igor and Ana Milojević. <hi rend="italic">Novinarstvo tiskovne
                            agencije Tanjug v obdobju socialistične Jugoslavije, 2017 [Podatkovna
                            datoteka]</hi>. Ljubljana: Faculty of Social Sciences, Social
                        Science Data Archives, 2022. DOI: <ref
                            target="https://doi.org/10.17898/ADP_TANJUG17_V1"
                            >https://doi.org/10.17898/ADP_TANJUG17_V1</ref>.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
            <div type="summary" xml:lang="sl">
                <docAuthor>Igor Vobič</docAuthor>
                <docAuthor>Kristina Milić</docAuthor>
                <docAuthor>Ana Milojević</docAuthor>
                <head>SPOMINJANJE TANJUGA: ANALIZA REARTIKULACIJ NOVINARSKIH VLOG NACIONALNE
                    TISKOVNE AGENCIJE V SOCIALISTIČNI JUGOSLAVIJI</head>
                <head>POVZETEK</head>
                <p>Vloga novinarstva v družbi je zgodovinsko vezana na prevladujočo
                    konceptualizacijo svobode tiska ter specifične družbene, institucionalne in
                    materialne pogoje produkcije novic. Študija proučuje samopercepcije novinarjev,
                    ki so delovali v obdobju socialistične Jugoslavije, in sintetizira njihovo
                    spominjanje novinarskih usmeritev in delovanja z vidika položaja novinarstva v
                    družbi. Študija temelji na 14 ustnih zgodovinskih intervjujih z nekdanjimi
                    novinarji, ki so od poznih petdesetih do devetdesetih let prejšnjega stoletja
                    tudi kot uredniki in tuji dopisniki delali pri tiskovni agenciji Tanjug, ki je
                    veljala za informacijsko hrbtenico zveznega medijskega sistema v Jugoslaviji in
                    imela veljavo v mednarodnem prostoru. Intervjuji so bili opravljeni pozimi in
                    spomladi 2017 v Beogradu. Prepisi intervjujev so v celoti dostopni v Arhivu
                    družboslovnih podatkov Fakultete za družbene vede.</p>
                <p>Z združevanjem teoretskih, metodoloških in analitičnih pristopov v raziskavah
                    »novinarskih vlog« in »zgodovin poklicnega življenja« ima študija dvojni izvirni
                    prispevek. Prvič, z ugotavljanjem nedoslednosti v novinarskih refleksijah odraža
                    spominjanje na novinarske vloge kot denominacije »sedanjih« osebnih zaznav in
                    reartikulacije »preteklih« novinarskih usmeritev in delovanja. Te nedoslednosti
                    so se izkazale kot dragocene pri analizi napetosti med osebnim, institucionalnim
                    in družbenim, ob prepoznavanju prilagodljivih strategij spominjanja, s katerimi
                    so intervjuvani novinarji legitimirali sebe kot profesionalce in relevantne
                    interprete novinarstva v socialistični Jugoslaviji. V odgovorih intervjuvancev
                    se tako kažejo strategije prilagajanja raziskovalnemu in zgodovinskemu
                    kontekstu, in sicer skozi apropriacijo pojmov resnice, novic in točnosti,
                    prilagajanje kriterijev objavne vrednosti novic in preizpraševanje
                    (samo)cenzure. Drugič, analiza razkriva več odtenkov znotraj običajnega, pogosto
                    poenostavljenega razumevanja novinarjev kot sodelavcev oblasti v času socializma
                    in prepoznava tri novinarske vloge kot specifične manifestacije sodelovalne
                    funkcije novinarstva: novinarji kot privilegirani posredovalci, nadzorni
                    analitiki in razsvetljevalci. Študija tako prispeva k raziskovanju novinarskih
                    vlog z uvajanjem zgodovinskega pristopa k proučevanju novinarskih samopercepcij
                    kot »retrospektivnih mehanizmov«, ki delujejo v odnosu z normativnimi načeli,
                    idealizacijami in medijskimi praksami ter sinhronimi in diahronimi
                    kompleksnostmi osebnih, institucionalnih in družbenih reartikulacij novinarskih
                    vlog.</p>
                <p>Čeprav intervjuji potrjujejo splošne poti organizacijskega razvoja Tanjuga od
                    zgodnjih povojnih let, ko je bila agencija glasnik države, do razgibanega
                    procesa njene avtonomizacije, skozi katerega so se protislovno potrjevale »tabu
                    teme«, študija poudarja tudi omejitve ustnih zgodovinskih intervjujev. Te se
                    kažejo v poenostavljenih strnitvah institucionalnih in družbenih kompleksnosti
                    zgodovine Tanjuga skozi osebne refleksije nekdanjih novinarjev, ki temeljijo na
                    poenostavljenih relacijskih posplošitvah med »nekoč« in »zdaj«, med Jugoslavijo
                    in drugimi državami ter med Tanjugom in drugimi mediji. Da bi jih presegla, je
                    študija metodološke omejitve upoštevala in analizirala nedoslednosti, napetosti
                    in protislovja v intervjujih glede na teoretsko razumevanje odnosa med
                    novinarstvom, oblastjo in državljani ter kontekstualno poznavanje razvoja
                    novinarstva v socialistični Jugoslaviji.</p>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
