<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Archival Materials of the State Authorities Related to the Processes
                    of Democratisation and the Attainment of Independence of Slovenia</title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename>Vesna</forename>
                        <surname>Gotovina</surname>
                        <roleName>Head, Sector for the protection of Government
                            administration records after 1945</roleName>
                        <affiliation>Ministry of culture of the Republic of Slovenia, Archives of the Republic of Slovenia</affiliation>
                        <address>
                            <addrLine>Zvezdarska 1</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>SI–1127 Ljubljana</addrLine>
                        </address>
                        <email>vesna.gotovina@gov.si</email>
                    </name>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>2016-10-13</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>
                    <orgName xml:lang="sl">Inštitut za novejšo zgodovino</orgName>
                    <orgName xml:lang="en">Institute of Contemporary History</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Kongresni trg 1</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>SI-1000 Ljubljana</addrLine>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>http://ojs.inz.si/pnz/article/view/183</pubPlace>
                <date>2016</date>
                <availability status="free">
                    <licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title xml:lang="sl">Prispevki za novejšo zgodovino</title>
                <title xml:lang="en">Contributions to Contemporary History</title>
                <biblScope unit="volume">56</biblScope>
                <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
                <idno type="ISSN">2463-7807</idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source, born digital.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc xml:lang="en">
                <p>Contributions to Contemporary History is one of the central Slovenian scientific
                    historiographic journals, dedicated to publishing articles from the field of
                    contemporary history (the 19th and 20th century).</p>
                <p>The journal is published three times per year in Slovenian and in the following
                    foreign languages: English, German, Serbian, Croatian, Bosnian, Italian, Slovak
                    and Czech. The articles are all published with abstracts in English and
                    Slovenian as well as summaries in English.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <projectDesc xml:lang="sl">
                <p>Prispevki za novejšo zgodovino je ena osrednjih slovenskih znanstvenih
                    zgodovinopisnih revij, ki objavlja teme s področja novejše zgodovine (19. in 20.
                    stoletje).</p>
                <p>Revija izide trikrat letno v slovenskem jeziku in v naslednjih tujih jezikih:
                    angleščina, nemščina, srbščina, hrvaščina, bosanščina, italijanščina, slovaščina
                    in češčina. Članki izhajajo z izvlečki v angleščini in slovenščini ter povzetki
                    v angleščini.</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="sl"/>
                <language ident="en"/>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords xml:lang="en">
                    <term>archival materials</term>
                    <term>attainment of independence of Slovenia</term>
                    <term>accessibility of archival materials</term>
                    <term>preservation of archival
                        materials</term>
                    </keywords>
                <keywords xml:lang="sl">
                    <term>arhivsko gradivo</term>
                    <term>osamosvojitev Slovenije</term>
                    <term>dostopnost arhivskega gradiva</term>
                    <term>ohranjenost arhivskega gradiva</term>
                 </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change>
                    <date>2016-10-26</date>
                    <name>Neja Blaj Hribar</name>
                    <desc>Pretvorba iz DOCX v TEI, dodatno kodiranje</desc>
                </change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <docAuthor>Vesna Gotovina<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn1" n="*"><hi rend="bold">
                Head, Sector for the protection of Government
                administration records after 1945, Ministry of
                culture of the Republic of Slovenia, Archives of the Republic of Slovenia, Zvezdarska 1, SI–1127 Ljubljana, <ref
                    target="mailto:vesna.gotovina@gov.si">vesna.gotovina@gov.si</ref></hi></note></docAuthor>
            <docImprint>
                <idno type="cobissType">Cobiss tip: 1.01</idno>
                <idno type="UDC">UDK: </idno>
                <date>Prejeto 13. 10. 2016</date>
            </docImprint>
            <div type="abstract">
                <head>ABSTRACT</head>
                <p><hi rend="italic">The major part of the archival materials related to the processes
                    of democratisation and the attainment of independence of the Republic of
                    Slovenia is still in the custody of the creators or holders of the archival
                    materials. According to the archival legislation the materials are to be
                    submitted to the archives not later than thirty years after their creation.
                    Therefore the author of this contribution also points out various threats
                    endangering the archival materials which are yet to be acquired by the competent
                    archives.</hi></p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Keywords: archival materials, attainment of independence of
                    Slovenia, accessibility of archival materials, preservation of archival
                    materials</hi></p>
            </div>
            <div type="abstract" xml:lang="sl">
                <head type="main">IZVLEČEK</head>
                <head>ARHIVSKO GRADIVO DRŽAVNIH ORGANOV O PROCESIH DEMOKRATIZACIJE IN
                    OSAMOSVAJANJA SLOVENIJE</head>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Večji del arhivskega gradiva o procesih demokratizacije in
                    osamosvajanja Republike Slovenije se še vedno hrani pri ustvarjalcih ali
                    imetnikih arhivskega gradiva. Arhivska zakonodaja predpisuje, da se gradivo
                    izroča najkasneje trideset let po nastanku. Zato avtorica v prispevku opozarja
                    tudi na nekatere nevarnosti, ki ogrožajo arhivsko gradivo, še neprevzeto v
                    pristojne arhive.</hi></p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Ključne besede: arhivsko gradivo, osamosvojitev Slovenije,
                    dostopnost arhivskega gradiva, ohranjenost arhivskega gradiva</hi></p>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div>
            <head>Introduction</head>
            <p>One of the basic tasks of the Archives of the Republic of Slovenia is the
                preservation of the archival materials produced by the highest state administration,
                justice administration and legislative bodies during the implementation of their
                functions.</p>
            <p>What are archival materials? Archival materials are documentary materials with a
                long-term importance for history, other sciences and culture, or for the legal
                certainty of individuals; they constitute a cultural monument.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn2" n="1"> ZVDAGA, Article 2.</note> Since
                the attainment of independence this definition has been extended in the part
                referring to the "long-term importance for the legal certainty of individuals". In
                Slovenia the public archival materials are kept in the national archives (the
                Archives of the Republic of Slovenia), regional archives (regional and historical),
                and archives of the local self-governing communities.</p>
            <p>As archivists who appraise documentary materials on the basis of archival principles
                and appraisal criteria governed by law<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn3" n="2">
                        ZVDAGA, Article 40. The criteria for evaluation: requirements of
                        historiography, other sciences and culture; needs of persons for permanent
                        legal certainty; importance of the contents of the materials; specificity of
                        events and phenomena at a certain point in time; specificity of places or
                        regions; importance of public bodies; importance of the author; significance
                        of the materials from the viewpoint of cultural diversity; originality of
                        documents and their duplication (the materials most perfectly reflecting the
                        contents are specified); originality of data and information; representative
                        selection – samples; condition and volume of materials created; intrinsic
                        and external characteristics of the materials (language, artistic value,
                        means of recording); other criteria as specified by the competent
                        archives.</note>, we keep asking ourselves which contents and sorts of
                documentary materials – produced in extreme quantities in this day and age – should
                be preserved for the next generations. The burden of responsibility has become even
                heavier as our historical period represents a turning point and we ourselves, in a
                certain way, also shape the image of the times we live in. We are well-aware of this
                extremely important mission. Therefore the materials produced by some of the most
                important bodies in relation to the most important events from the period of the
                attainment of independence and democratisation of Slovenia are almost entirely
                defined as a cultural monument (the condition of the materials is also taken into
                    account).<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn4" n="3"> For
                        example, all materials kept by the Ministry of Defence have been declared as
                        archival materials up to and including 1991. The materials, created during
                        the operations of the Presidency of the Republic of Slovenia, will be
                        treated in a similar manner.</note></p>
            <p>The archivists who cooperate with the creators of the archival materials have to
                prepare "written expert instructions on the selection of archival materials from
                documentary materials" for each public body and update these instructions each time
                the body is restructured. Completely new expert instructions have to be prepared in
                the event of a major restructuring of the administration.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn5" n="4"> These are always reviewed by
                        commissions. Commissions consist of the members of the competent archive and
                        the public body for which the expert instructions are being verified.
                    </note> With the entry into force of the <hi rend="italic">Decree on
                    Administrative Operations</hi> in 2005, documentary materials gain the status of
                archival materials even before they are actually created.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn6" n="5"> Filing plans with retention periods
                        and provisions on the archival materials are implemented in the information
                        systems for the management of documentary materials.</note> Archival
                materials are acquired by archives in the original form, without any technological
                limitations, arranged, registered, in comprehensive and complete sets and in
                accordance with the technical provisions. Selecting and accessioning archive
                materials in digital form represents a specific challenge for the archival science,
                as it requires additional efforts in order to maintain accessibility, usefulness,
                integrity, authenticity and sustainability in comparison with the materials in paper
                (physical) form.</p>
            <p>Therefore the archival legislation lays down additional expert and technical
                instructions for the selection of digital materials. </p>
            </div>
            <div>
            <head>Archival Fonds and Types of Archival Materials of Public
                    Authorities</head>
            <p>Immediately after the attainment of independence of Slovenia we began to acquire the
                archival materials produced until 1990 by the administrative<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn7" n="6"> E.g. the Republic Committee for
                        Veterans and Disabled Servicemen, materials of the self-management
                        communities of interest, etc. </note> and other bodies that were
                abolished at that time.</p>
                <div>
            <head>The most important archival fonds bearing witness to the
                    processes of democratisation and the attainment of independence</head>
            <p>Researchers and other users of archival materials can access the basic data on
                archival fonds that are already registered in guides. They are published on the
                websites of the relevant archives and updated regularly. Therefore this contribution
                only states some of the most important fonds and collections for:</p>
                    <div>
            <head>Political history research:</head>
            <list type="unordered">
                <item>Government of Slovenia<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn8" n="7"> SI AS 223.</note> (1945–1992). Transcriptions
                    of the first government are not open for research. Access to these materials is
                    subject to approval by the Government of the Republic of Slovenia following a
                    proposal from the archival commission.</item>
                <item>Assembly of Slovenia<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn9" n="8"> SI AS 1115.</note> (1943–1990). The materials
                    are accessible in their entirety with the exception of submissions and appeals
                    containing protected personal data.</item>
                <item>Presidency of Slovenia<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn10" n="9"> SI AS 1944.</note> (1974–1990). The materials
                    are accessible in their entirety with the exception of applications and appeals
                    of individuals and data on clemencies granted to prisoners. </item>
                <item>Republic Electoral Commission<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn11" n="10"> SI AS 142.</note> (1963–2000). The materials
                    are accessible in their entirety. They also comprise data on the first
                    multiparty elections, the elections of the Presidency of the Republic of
                    Slovenia in 1990, and the presidential elections in 1992.</item>
                <item>The collection on plebiscite of 1990.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn12" n="11"> SI AS 1210.</note> The materials are
                    accessible in their entirety. All documentation related to the plebiscite and
                    its implementation has been declared a cultural monument.</item>
                <item>Government of the Republic of Slovenia Public Relations and Media Office<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn13" n="12"> SI AS
                        2057.</note> (1972–2001). The materials are accessible in their
                    entirety.</item>
                <item>Protocol Service of the Republic of Slovenia (1945–1991).<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn14" n="13"> SI AS 2055.</note> The
                    materials are accessible in their entirety.</item>
                <item>Office of the Government of the Republic of Slovenia for National
                        Minorities<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn15" n="14">
                            SI AS 2046.</note> (1974–2012). The materials contain protected
                    personal data.</item>
                <item>Office of the Republic of Slovenia for Immigration and Refugees<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn16" n="15"> SI AS
                        2113.</note> (1974–2012). The materials contain protected personal
                    data.</item>
                <item>Council for the Protection of Human Rights and Fundamental Freedoms<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn17" n="16"> SI AS
                        2120.</note> (1987–1995). The materials contain protected personal
                    data.</item>
                <item>Commission for Relations with Religious Communities<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn18" n="17"> SI AS 1211.</note>
                    (1953–1991). The materials contain protected personal data.</item>
            </list>
                    </div>
                    <div>
            <head>Economy, agriculture and transport research:</head>
            <list type="unordered">
                <item>Agency for the Audit of the Ownership Transformation of Companies<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn19" n="18"> SI AS
                        316.</note> (1993–2004);</item>
                <item>Social Accounting Service<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn20" n="19"> SI AS 1214.</note> (1974–2002);</item>
                <item>Ministry of Transport and Communications<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn21" n="20"> SI AS 2115.</note> (1975–1996);</item>
                <item>Court of Audit of the Republic of Slovenia<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn22" n="21"> SI AS 2053.</note> (1987–2003);</item>
                <item>Ministry of Economic Relations and Development<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn23" n="22"> SI AS 2089.</note>
                    (1994–2002);</item>
                <item>Ministry of Finance<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn24" n="23"> SI AS 1116.</note> (1945–1993);</item>
                <item>Republic Committee for Agriculture, Forestry and Food of the Socialist
                    Republic of Slovenia<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn25" n="24"> SI AS 1233.</note> (1972–1991);</item>
                <item>Republic Committee for Industry and Construction of the Socialist Republic of
                        Slovenia<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn26" n="25"> SI
                            AS 1265.</note> (1965–1991);</item>
                <item>Farmland and Forest Fund<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn27" n="26"> SI AS 2133.</note> (1918–2014);</item>
                <item>Slovenian Roads Agency<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn28" n="27"> SI AS 2079.</note> (1967–2008).</item>
            </list>
                    </div>
                    <div>
            <head>Culture, education and science research:</head>
            <list type="unordered">
                <item>Ministry of Education, Science and Sport of the Republic of Slovenia<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn29" n="28"> SI AS
                        2003.</note> (1967–2004). The materials contain protected personal
                    data.</item>
                <item>Slovenian Research Agency<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn30" n="29"> SI AS 2033.</note> (1986–2005);</item>
                <item>Ministry of Education and Sport<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn31" n="30"> SI AS 2026.</note> (1982–2003). The materials
                    contain protected personal data.</item>
            </list>
                    </div>
                    <div>
            <head>Defence policy research</head>
            <p>The Archives of the Republic of Slovenia signed an agreement with the Ministry of
                Defence of the Republic of Slovenia on the extension of the deadline for the
                submission of the archival materials older than 30 years until 31 December 2025 at
                the latest. That is the reason why the majority of these materials is not yet
                available to the public. The relevant Ministry departments are continuously
                cooperating with the Archives, arranging and describing the materials according to
                the instructions in order to complete the transfer.</p>
                    </div>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div>
            <head>Arrangement of Documentary and Archival Materials</head>
                <div>
            <head>Arrangement of the materials in the custody of creators and
                    holders</head>
            <p>With the establishment of the new state, administrative operations<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn32" n="31"> Vladimir Žumer, <hi rend="italic">Poslovanje z zapisi. Upravljanje in hramba dokumentarnega gradiva,
                            klasifikacijski načrti za razvrščanje gradiva z roki hrambe in
                            elektronska hramba gradiva v digitalni obliki</hi> (Ljubljana: Planet
                        GV, 2008).</note> continued in the context of individual government
                departments and did not involve any such significant changes as might have been
                expected. We can merely observe that the bodies were repeatedly renamed in a very
                short period of time.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn33" n="32"> For example Republic Committee for Education,
                        Schooling and Physical Culture (16 May 1990 – 22 June 1990), Republic
                        Secretariat for Education, Schooling and Physical Culture (23 June 1990 – 27
                        June 1991) and Ministry of Education and Sport (28 June 1991 – 14 May
                        1992).</note> These kinds of changes usually cause problems for
                archivists when it comes to the creation of fonds.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn34" n="33"> Archival fonds is the archival material, created
                        during the operations of a single legal entity, natural person or
                        family.</note> We can point out the clerical operations in the Assembly
                of the Republic of Slovenia as an extremely interesting example of administrative
                operations. Despite the change of the state regime and the transition from the
                delegate system to the multiparty system, session documents are the only materials
                we are able to classify according to terms of office – to the period before and
                after the first multiparty elections. The materials pertaining to the legislative
                procedure or the adoption of laws are arranged according to the contents of acts
                until 2008, regardless of the terms of office. Therefore we are not able to
                differentiate between the legislative procedure materials of the Assembly of the
                Republic of Slovenia and the National Assembly, established in 1992. Similar also
                applies to the operations of the other highest administrative and state bodies. As
                it is evident from the already acquired archival fonds, we have not decided to
                classify the fonds according to the period before and after the establishment of the
                Republic of Slovenia. The process of the dissolution of Yugoslavia and recognition
                of Slovenia was not a momentary, instantaneous event which would cause major and
                radical changes in the operations of the state authorities. The most profound and
                expected changes are apparent only in the administrative operations of the new
                ministerial fields of defence and foreign policy. </p>
            <p>The quality of documentary and archival materials arrangement fell alarmingly
                precisely during the processes of democratisation and attainment of independence.
                Since 1962 the materials were classified<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn35" n="34"> Rajka
                        Bućin,<hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve"> Klasifikacijski sustavi u spisovodstvu uprave. Povijesni razvoj i suvremena stremljenja </hi>(Zagreb:
                        Hrvatski državni arhiv, 2015), 176–241.</note> according to the content
                and on the basis of the prescribed filing plan. This plan became inadequate already
                at the end of 1980s and in the beginning of 1990s in terms of contents, especially
                due to the old, so-called socialist terminology (e.g. socio-political organisation,
                self-management, etc.). Therefore the existing filing plan was quickly abandoned,
                and public authorities were left to their own devices and innovativeness in clerical
                operations. For quite some time no one in the state was concerned with clerical
                operations and documentary materials management despite the warnings, expressed by
                the archives, that such treatment greatly endangered archival materials.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn36" n="35"> Vesna Gotovina,
                        »Sistemi poslovanja s spisi v Sloveniji od leta 1955 dalje,« <hi rend="italic">Arhivi</hi> 16, No. 1-2 (1993): 53.</note> Some state
                authorities even went so far in their operations that they completely abandoned
                classification when they introduced electronic registers. They were convinced that
                with modern technology it would be possible to search for data directly in the
                contents, which turned out to be completely inappropriate. The global expansion of
                electronic services also resulted in the emergence of the international
                    standards<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn37" n="36"> ISO
                        15489 – Information and documentation – Records management. </note> for
                the management of documentary materials. Slovenia re-established the single filing
                plan for public authorities in 2005<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn38" n="37">Vladimir Žumer, »Klasifikacijski načrti za razvrščanje
                        dokumentacije z roki hranjenja,« v:
                        <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Tehnični in vsebinski problemi klasičnega in elektronskega arhiviranja, </hi>eds.
                        Ivan Fras and Nina Gostečnik
                        (Radenci<hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">, </hi>2013), 353–68.
                    </note>. The period of incoherent and inconsistent classification of
                materials according to the contents in the public administration thus lasted
                approximately fifteen years. This means that we shall encounter major problems when
                selecting and accessioning the archival materials for the archives. Even today it is
                apparent that the materials from the period of the attainment of independence are
                poorly preserved. For example, there are no transcriptions, stenographic records,
                etc. in the session documents files of the most important state authorities. It is
                very likely that many problems will also arise with regard to the preservation of
                sound recordings. The administrative operations of the highest state authorities
                were unsupervised for almost fifteen years. Even today only the archives and the
                Culture and Media Inspectorate of the Republic of Slovenia deal with this matter.
                Between 2007 and 2015 only two preventive inspections<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn39" n="38"> Dragan Matić, »Stanje varstva
                        arhivskega in dokumentarnega gradiva na slovenskih ministrstvih,« v: <hi rend="italic">Tehnični in vsebinski problemi klasičnega in elektronskega
                            arhiviranja</hi>, 275–85.</note> of documentary and archival
                materials management were performed at all the ministries. Until 2006 the archival
                legislation did not include penal provisions for damaging or destroying archival
                materials. These provisions were only enforced with the Protection of Documents and
                Archives and Archival Institutions Act, but the penalties for infringements
                involving the non-implementation of the Act are merely symbolic.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn40" n="39"> ZVDAGA, Article 92 (from EUR 2000
                        to EUR 5000).</note>
            </p>
                </div>
                <div>
            <head>Arrangement of archival materials in the Archives of the Republic
                    of Slovenia</head>
            <p>In the past decades the archives acquired many archival materials which were not
                properly arranged and registered, especially due to the prevailing opinion that it
                was best to keep such materials safe in the archives as well, as they could be
                destroyed in the custody of creators and holders due to inappropriate handling. In
                view of the bad experience with the materials of the predecessors of the Ministry of
                the Interior and the intelligence services, such decisions were relatively
                justified. Nonetheless, the archival materials which have not been arranged and
                registered in detail represent a great burden for the archivists who work with the
                more recent materials. The quantity of these materials is vast, therefore the expert
                arrangement and description processes are exceptionally slow. </p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div>
            <head>Accessibility of Archival Materials</head>
            <p>Slovenia has one of the most liberal policies with regard to accessing the archival
                materials already kept in the archives.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn41" n="40"> Kersten Jedlitschka, »Arhiv Stasija – preteklost in
                        sedanjost,« v: <hi rend="italic">Primeri različnih praks v slovenskih
                            arhivih: 25. zborovanje</hi>, eds. Zdenka Bonin and Marjan Vogrin
                        (Ljubljana: Arhivsko društvo Slovenije, 2011), 19–31.</note> Researchers
                can use the materials free of charge which is rather uncommon in the majority of
                European countries.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn42" n="41"> Everyone is also
                        allowed to take digital photos of the archival materials free of
                    charge.</note> With the amendment of the Protection of Documents and
                Archives and Archival Institutions Act<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn43" n="42"> ZVDAGA, Article 65.</note> of 2014, the archival
                materials, acquired by the archives before the formation of the Assembly of the
                Republic of Slovenia on 17 May 1990, became accessible in their entirety – including
                the materials labelled with various levels of inaccessibility. Regarding these
                materials the archives only provide for the protection of personal data related to
                health status; sexuality; victims of crimes against sexual inviolability, matrimony,
                family and youth; perpetrators of crimes and offences except for the crimes and
                offences committed by persons prosecuted for opposing the one-party regime; as well
                as religious belief and ethnic adherence.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn44" n="43"> Bojan Cvelfar, »O dostopnosti arhivskega gradiva v
                        javnih arhivih pred in po uveljavitvi ZVDAGA-A,« v:
                        <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Arhivi na razpotju: 27. zborovanje, </hi>ed.
                        Jure Volčjak (Ptuj: Arhivsko društvo Slovenije, 2015), 8–17. </note> The
                documents containing the aforementioned data shall become accessible 75 years after
                their creation or 10 years after the death of the concerned individual, if the date
                of death is known and unless otherwise stipulated by other laws.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn45" n="44"> Vanja Pfajfer and Gregor Jenuš,
                        »Novela ZVDAGA - korak naprej? Dostop do arhivskega gradiva z osebnimi
                        podatki doma in na tujem,« v: <hi rend="italic">Arhivi na razpotju</hi>,
                        18–29. </note> The Government of the Republic of Slovenia can also grant
                claimants access to these materials on the basis of the prior opinion of the
                archival commission.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn46" n="45"> Igor Omerza, »Stališče z vidika uporabnika: Novela arhivskega zakona –
                        kratka predzgodovina in posledice,« v: <hi rend="italic">Arhivi na
                            razpotju</hi>, 33.</note></p>
            </div>
            <div>
            <head>The Attitude of the State and Its Policies Towards the Archives and
                    Archival Materials as a Cultural Monument</head>
            <p>The archival materials related to the formation of the Slovenian state in the
                historical period when Slovenians finally became a nation with their own independent
                and sovereign state represent a national treasure of the highest degree and are of
                exceptional importance for the preservation of national identity. The experience of
                the archival science demonstrates that people who have led this country since its
                establishment have not been sufficiently aware of this fact.</p>
            <p>The archives have not acquired any new buildings in 25 years, and the national
                archives have been waiting for almost as long for the renovation of the old barracks
                near the Poljanska cesta street.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn47" n="46"> Jedert Vodopivec, »Analiza stanja v slovenskih javnih
                        arhivih,« v:
                        <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Arhivski depoji v Sloveniji, </hi>ed.
                        Jedert Vodopivec (Ljubljana: Arhiv Republike Slovenije, 2008),
                    9–32.</note> The attitude towards archives, demonstrated by other countries
                that share a similar destiny, is substantially different. For example, Slovakia and
                the Czech Republic<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn48" n="47">
                        Jozef Hanus and Emília Hanusová, »Archival building – the basic condition
                        for proper functioning of the archives,« v: <hi rend="italic">Tehnični in
                            vsebinski problemi klasičnega in elektronskega arhiviranja</hi>, 217–24.
                    </note> have built completely new archives where they can preserve their
                national treasure.</p>
            <p>Archival legislation, adopted in 2006, represented a severe impediment for the
                development of the archival science as well. It significantly increased the
                jurisdictions of the national archives in the field of digital materials without
                ensuring enough suitably-trained staff to carry out these tasks. The flawed
                legislation, which was not written by the archival science at the time, later
                resulted in two referendums. For this reason we had to focus on political
                    issues<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn49" n="48"> Dragan
                        Matić, »Arhivska javna služba med politiko in stroko,« v: <hi rend="italic">Primeri različnih praks v slovenskih arhivih</hi>, 7–18.</note> for
                quite a few years instead of solving the professional archival challenges brought
                about by the digital age and the rapid development of various new technologies.</p>
            <p>After all, in the last twenty-five years archives have played an exceedingly
                important role. They were part of momentous processes, resulting from the
                emancipation and the change of the social order. The archival materials kept in the
                archives became extremely important for proving the rights of the state and
                individuals during the implementation of the legislation on denationalisation,
                righting the injustices suffered by the victims of wartime and post-war violence,
                etc. However, the archival science has not taken adequate advantage of this
                situation, as it has failed to ensure the deserved position for the national
                archives in the Republic of Slovenia. </p>
                <div>
            <head>Frequent restructuring of the public administration endanger
                    archival materials</head>
            <p>The very frequent restructuring of the public administration represents a severe
                danger for the archival materials kept by the state authorities, including those
                attesting to the democratisation and the formation of the state. In the last few
                years individual state bodies were abolished and re-established, while their duties
                were redistributed among the administrative bodies. This resulted in the documentary
                and archival materials being moved between locations. Every disorganised relocation
                represents an extreme risk for these materials. They can get mixed up; the initial
                arrangement is not preserved; they can get lost or even destroyed. Furthermore, all
                of the above results in huge financial expenses for repeated arrangement and
                description, while considerable compensations may result from the individual
                proceedings conducted by the administrative bodies in case of loss or destruction of
                the materials.</p>
            <p>Archival materials, created in digital form, are subject to an even greater risk as
                the materials on classic media. The latter may always be rearranged and described,
                which is what the creators of archival materials are doing for a number of years
                before submitting the archival materials to the archives. On the other hand, in case
                of digital materials inappropriate storage may result in complete loss in a single
                reckless moment, if these materials are not handled properly <hi rend="italic">ever
                    since their creation</hi>.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn50" n="49"> Tatjana Hajtnik,
                        <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Celovit pristop k pretvorbi elektronskih dokumentov v obliko za dolgoročno hrambo </hi>(Maribor:
                        Fakulteta za elektrotehniko, računalništvo in informatiko,
                        2016)<hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">, </hi>145.</note></p>
            <p>In certain cases the practice to date has turned out to be extremely inappropriate.
                Therefore every newly-formed government should precisely and unambiguously define
                the handling of documentary and consequently also archival materials since their
                very creation and during every subsequent restructuring. Moreover, suitable
                facilities for the storage of these materials for at least thirty years should be
                ensured. Perhaps this could also be achieved by designating the facilities for the
                storage of permanent collections (archives), where these materials could be kept
                until their submission to the competent archives, similarly as this matter is
                arranged in Austria, Germany, and in certain other EU countries.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div>
            <head>In Place of Conclusion</head>
            <p>Archival materials are already waiting for the researchers of all aspects of
                historiography and other sciences and attracting them to the archives. Every
                analysis of the contemporary archival materials calls for great enthusiasm,
                professionalism, and especially impartiality. The events and individual documents
                should be highlighted with all the accessible sources and from all angles, despite
                the historical distance of merely a quarter of a century. In order to underline the
                above, let me refer to the analysis of an extremely important document, signed on 6
                December 1990 in the Assembly of the Republic of Slovenia by all the political
                parties and groups of delegates. On the same day the delegates passed the Plebiscite
                on the Sovereignty and Independence of the Republic of Slovenia Act with an
                overwhelming majority. I am referring to the <hi rend="italic">Agreement of the
                    Political Parties and Groups of Delegates of the Assembly of the Republic of
                    Slovenia on the Joint Action at the Plebiscite on the Sovereignty and
                    Independence of the Republic of Slovenia.</hi> The parties and groups of
                deputies agreed on thirteen points, stated on three pages. The responsible
                representatives of the parties and groups signed the last page of the document. As
                the names and surnames of the signatories were not recorded on a single document,
                not all of them are still discernible today – only twenty-five years later.
                Meanwhile, the name and surname<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn51" n="50"> The name Vitomir Gros was stated for the Liberal Party
                        instead of Franc Golija.</note> of one of the signatories of the
                Agreement, stated on the cover or folder that contains the document, is wrong. Thus
                the error, which had already been published in literature beforehand, was only
                discovered at the twenty-fifth anniversary of the signing of this Agreement by
                subsequently checking the television recordings and oral testimonies of the
                signatories of the Agreement. The lack of historical distance is not always
                negative: in this concrete case it turned out to be very useful for fixing the
                inadvertent mistake.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="bibliography">
            <head>Sources and Literature</head>
            
            <list type="unordered">
                <head>Archive Sources:</head>
                <item>SI AS, Arhiv Republike Slovenije:<list>
                <item>SI AS 142 – Republic Electoral Commission, 1963–2000.</item>
                <item>SI AS 223 – Government of Slovenia, 1945–1992.</item>
                <item>SI AS 316 – Agency for the Audit of the Ownership Transformation of Companies,
                    1993–2004.</item>
                <item>SI AS 1115 – Assembly of Slovenia, 1943–1990.</item>
                <item>SI AS 1116 – Ministry of Finance, 1945–1993.</item>
                <item>SI AS 1210 – The collection on plebiscite of 1990.</item>
                <item>SI AS 1211 – Commission for Relations with Religious Communities,
                    1953–1991.</item>
                <item>SI AS 1214 – Social Accounting Service, 1947–2002.</item>
                <item>SI AS 1233 – Republic Committee for Agriculture, Forestry and Food of the
                    Socialist Republic of Slovenia, 1972–1991.</item>
                <item>SI AS 1265 – Republic Committee for Industry and Construction of the Socialist
                    Republic of Slovenia, 1965–1991.</item>
                <item>SI AS 1944 – Presidency of Slovenia, 1974–1990.</item>
                <item>SI AS 2003 – Ministry of Education, Science and Sport of the Republic of
                    Slovenia, 1967–2004.</item>
                <item>SI AS 2046 – Office of the Government of the Republic of Slovenia for National
                    Minorities, 1974–2012.</item>
                <item>SI AS 2053 – Court of Audit of the Republic of Slovenia, 1987–2003.</item>
                <item>SI AS 2055 – Protocol Service of the Republic of Slovenia, 1945–1991.</item>
                <item>SI AS 2057 – Government of the Republic of Slovenia Public Relations and Media
                    Office, 1972–2001.</item>
                <item>SI AS 2089 – Ministry of Economic Relations and Development, 1994–2002.</item>
                <item>SI AS 2113 – Office of the Republic of Slovenia for Immigration and Refugees,
                    1957–2010.</item>
                <item>SI AS 2115 – Ministry of Transport and Communications, 1975–1996.</item>
                <item>SI AS 2120 – Council for the Protection of Human Rights and Fundamental
                    Freedoms, 1987–1995.</item>
                <item>SI AS 2026 – Ministry of Education and Sport of the Republic of Slovenia,
                    1982–2003.</item>
                <item>SI AS 2033 – Slovenian Research Agency, 1986–2005.</item>
                <item>SI AS 2079 – Slovenian Roads Agency, 1967–2008.</item>
                    <item>SI AS 2133 – Farmland and Forest Fund, 1918–2014.</item></list></item>
                <item>ZVDAGA, Protection of Documents and Archives and Archival Institutions Act,
                    Official Gazette of the Republic of Slovenia, No. 30/06, 51/14.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Note: In the archival science, the materials in fonds are referred to as <hi rend="bold">SI AS and the number of fonds or collection.</hi> ARS is the old
                code for the current AS. SI is the code for Slovenia.</p>
            <p>Further examples of references to the fonds and collections of other archives: e.g.
                SI ZAC (Celje Historical Archives), SI ZAL (Ljubljana Historical Archives), SI PAK
                (Koper Regional Archives).</p>
                <listBibl>
            <head>Literature:</head>
               <bibl>Bućin, Rajka.<hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve"> Klasifikacijski sustavi u spisovodstvu uprave. Povijesni razvoj i suvremena stremljenja. </hi>Zagreb:
                    Hrvatski državni arhiv, 2015.
                </bibl>
                <bibl>Cvelfar, Bojan<hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">. </hi>»O dostopnosti
                    arhivskega gradiva v javnih arhivih pred in po uveljavitvi ZVDAGA-A.« V:
                    <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Arhivi na razpotju: 27. zborovanje, </hi>ed.
                    Jure Volčjak, pp. 8–17. Ptuj: Arhivsko društvo Slovenije, 2015.</bibl>
                <bibl>Hajtnik,
                    Tatjana.<hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve"> Celovit pristop k pretvorbi elektronskih dokumentov v obliko za dolgoročno hrambo. </hi>Maribor:
                    Fakulteta za elektrotehniko, računalništvo in informatiko, 2016.</bibl>
                <bibl>Gotovina, Vesna. »Sistemi poslovanja s spisi v Sloveniji od leta 1955 dalje.«
                    <hi rend="italic">Arhivi</hi> 16, No. 1-2 (1993): 45–54. </bibl>
                <bibl>Hanus, Jozef and Hanusová Emília. »Archival building – the basic condition for
                    proper functioning of the archives.« V: <hi rend="italic">Tehnični in vsebinski
                        problemi klasičnega in elektronskega arhiviranja</hi>, pp. 217–26. Radenci,
                    2011. </bibl>
                <bibl>Jedlitschka. Kersten. »Arhiv Stasija – preteklost in sedanjost.« V: <hi rend="italic">Primeri različnih praks v slovenskih arhivih: 25.
                    zborovanje</hi>, eds. Zdenka Bonin and Marjan Vogrin, pp. 19–31. Ljubljana:
                    Arhivsko društvo Slovenije, 2011.</bibl>
                <bibl>Matić, Dragan. »Arhivska javna služba med politiko in stroko.« V: <hi rend="italic">Primeri različnih praks v slovenskih arhivih: 25.
                    zborovanje</hi>, eds. Zdenka Bonin and Marjan Vogrin, pp. 7–18. Ljubljana:
                    Arhivsko društvo Slovenije, 2011.</bibl>
                <bibl>Matić, Dragan. »Stanje varstva arhivskega in dokumentarnega gradiva na
                    slovenskih ministrstvih.« V: <hi rend="italic">Tehnični in vsebinski problemi
                        klasičnega in elektronskega arhiviranja</hi>, pp. 275–85. Radenci,
                    2007.</bibl>
                <bibl>Omerza, Igor<hi rend="italic">.</hi> »Stališče z vidika uporabnika: Novela
                    arhivskega zakona – kratka predzgodovina in posledice.« V:
                    <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Arhivi na razpotju: 27. zborovanje, </hi>ed.
                    Jure Volčjak, pp. 30–35. Ptuj: Arhivsko društvo Slovenije, 2015.</bibl>
                <bibl>Pfajfer, Vanja and Gregor Jenuš. »Novela ZVDAGA - korak naprej? Dostop do
                    arhivskega gradiva z osebnimi podatki doma in na tujem.« V:
                    <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Arhivi na razpotju: 27. zborovanje, </hi>ed.
                    Jure Volčjak, pp. 18–29. Ptuj: Arhivsko društvo Slovenije, 2015.</bibl>
                <bibl>Vodopivec, Jedert. »Analiza stanja v slovenskih javnih arhivih.« V:
                    <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Arhivski depoji v Sloveniji, </hi>ed.
                    Jedert Vodopivec, pp. 9–32. Ljubljana: Arhiv Republike Slovenije, 2008. </bibl>
                <bibl>Žumer, Vladimir. »Klasifikacijski načrti za razvrščanje dokumentacije z roki
                    hranjenja.« V:
                    <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Tehnični in vsebinski problemi klasičnega in elektronskega arhiviranja, </hi>eds.
                    Ivan Fras and Nina Gostečnik, pp. 353–68.
                    Radenci<hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">, </hi>2013.</bibl>
                <bibl>Žumer, Vladimir<hi rend="italic">. Poslovanje z zapisi. Upravljanje in hramba
                    dokumentarnega gradiva, klasifikacijski načrti za razvrščanje gradiva z roki
                    hrambe in elektronska hramba gradiva v digitalni obliki</hi>. Ljubljana:
                    Planet GV, 2008.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
            <div type="summary" xml:lang="sl">
            <head type="main">ARHIVSKO GRADIVO DRŽAVNIH ORGANOV O PROCESIH DEMOKRATIZACIJE IN OSAMOSVAJANJA
                SLOVENIJE</head>
            <head>POVZETEK</head>
                <docAuthor>Vesna Gotovina</docAuthor>
            <p>Namen prispevka je predstavitev varstva arhivskega gradiva najpomembnejših državnih
                organov, ki je nastalo v procesih demokratizacije in osamosvajanja Slovenije.</p>
            <p>Arhivsko gradivo je dokumentarno gradivo, ki ima trajen pomen za zgodovino, druge
                znanosti in kulturo ali trajen pomen za pravno varnost oseb; arhivsko gradivo je
                kulturni spomenik. Najpomembnejše naloge arhivske stroke in arhivistov, ki se
                ukvarjajo z novejšim arhivskim gradivom so tudi vrednotenje, prevzemanje in
                ohranjanje arhivskega gradiva o procesih demokratizacije in osamosvajanja Slovenije.
                Bliža se 30 letni rok za izročitev arhivskega gradiva, zato na nekaterih
                najpomembnejših državnih organih že danes potekajo vsi potrebni in zakonsko
                predpisani postopki (urejanje, odbiranje, popisovanje, tehnično opremljanje..) za
                predajo arhivskega gradiva v Arhiv RS.</p>
            <p>Veliko arhivskega gradiva državnih organov iz obdobja konca osemdesetih in začetka
                devetdesetih let prejšnjega stoletja, je že danes shranjenega v nacionalnem arhivu.
                Med najpomembnejše arhivske fonde in zbirke lahko štejemo naslednje: Vlada Republike
                Slovenije (1945 do 1992), Skupščina Slovenije (1943 do 1990), Predsedstvo Slovenije
                (1974 do 1990), Republiška volilna komisija (1963 do 2000), Zbirka plebiscit 1990,
                Urad Vlade RS za informiranje (1972 do 2001), Protokol RS (1945 do 1991), Urad Vlade
                RS za narodnosti (1974 do 2012), Svet za varstvo človekovih pravic in temeljnih
                svoboščin (1987 do 1995). Znanstveniki, raziskovalci in drugi uporabniki lahko že
                danes na izvirnih arhivskih virih preučujejo različna področja življenja in dogodkov
                enega najpomembnejših zgodovinskih obdobij na teritoriju današnje Republike
                Slovenije. Gradivo prevzeto v arhive omogoča raziskovanje politične, gospodarske,
                socialne, šolske… zgodovine ter pomembnih procesov – npr. spremembe družbene
                ureditve, uvedbe večstrankarskega sistema, postopkov denacionalizacije in
                privatizacije družbene lastnine. </p>
            <p>Dostop do arhivskega gradiva v arhivih določa arhivska zakonodaja. Ta opredeljuje
                varovane osebne podatke in določa roke nedostopnosti, in sicer 75 letni od nastanka
                dokumenta ali 10 letni po smrti osebe na katero se nanašajo podatki. V arhivih niso
                40 let dostopni tajni podatki, ki jih morajo javnopravne osebe, ki izročajo tovrstno
                arhivsko gradivo ob izročitvi natančno opredeliti. Vlada RS imenuje Arhivsko
                komisijo, ki na podlagi vloge raziskovalca ali raziskovalne inštitucije lahko odobri
                dostope tudi do omenjenega gradiva.</p>
            <p>Arhivsko gradivo, ki je še vedno shranjeno pri ustvarjalcih in imetnikih, ogrožajo
                tudi nekateri dejavniki, na katere arhivska stroka ves čas opozarja. To so predvsem
                zelo pogoste reorganizacije uprave. Predpisi ob samih reorganizacijah ne
                opredeljujejo natančnih postopkov ravnanja z dokumentarnim in arhivskim gradivom ob
                razdružitvah, združitvah ali ukinitvah posameznih organov. Največja nevarnost, ki
                ogroža arhivsko gradivo, so neustrezni prostori za hrambo arhivskega gradiva tako
                pred prevzemom v arhive, kot tudi kasneje. V Sloveniji se večina arhivov srečuje s
                problematiko pomanjkanja ustreznih arhivskih prostorov. </p>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>