<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Milovan Djilas and
                    the British Labour Party, 1950–1960<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn1" n="1"> The paper was written as part of the research
                            project N6-0039 <hi rend="italic">The Yugoslav Self-Management Experiment
                                and the Discussion on Development of European Socialism between East and
                                West</hi>, which was financially supported by the Slovenian Research
                            Agency.</note></title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename>Mateja</forename>
                        <surname>Režek</surname>
                    </name>
                    <roleName>Senior Research Fellow</roleName>
                    <roleName>PhD</roleName>
                    <affiliation>Institute for Historical Studies, ZRS Koper</affiliation>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Garibaldijeva Street 1</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>SI-6000 Koper</addrLine>
                    </address>
                    <email>mateja.rezek@zrs-kp.si</email>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>2018-09-21</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>
                    <orgName xml:lang="sl">Inštitut za novejšo zgodovino</orgName>
                    <orgName xml:lang="en">Institute of Contemporary History</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Kongresni trg 1</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>SI-1000 Ljubljana</addrLine>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>http://ojs.inz.si/pnz/article/view/294</pubPlace>
                <date>2018</date>
                <availability status="free">
                    <licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title xml:lang="sl">Prispevki za novejšo zgodovino</title>
                <title xml:lang="en">Contributions to Contemporary History</title>
                <biblScope unit="volume">58</biblScope>
                <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
                <idno type="ISSN">2463-7807</idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source, born digital.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc xml:lang="en">
                <p>Contributions to Contemporary History is one of the central Slovenian scientific
                    historiographic journals, dedicated to publishing articles from the field of
                    contemporary history (the 19th and 20th century).</p>
                <p>The journal is published three times per year in Slovenian and in the following
                    foreign languages: English, German, Serbian, Croatian, Bosnian, Italian, Slovak
                    and Czech. The articles are all published with abstracts in English and
                    Slovenian as well as summaries in English.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <projectDesc xml:lang="sl">
                <p>Prispevki za novejšo zgodovino je ena osrednjih slovenskih znanstvenih
                    zgodovinopisnih revij, ki objavlja teme s področja novejše zgodovine (19. in 20.
                    stoletje).</p>
                <p>Revija izide trikrat letno v slovenskem jeziku in v naslednjih tujih jezikih:
                    angleščina, nemščina, srbščina, hrvaščina, bosanščina, italijanščina, slovaščina
                    in češčina. Članki izhajajo z izvlečki v angleščini in slovenščini ter povzetki
                    v angleščini.</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="sl"/>
                <language ident="en"/>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords xml:lang="en">
                    <term>Milovan Djilas</term>
                    <term>British Labour Party</term>
                    <term>Aneurin Bevan</term>
                    <term>socialism</term>
                    <term>dissent</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords xml:lang="sl">
                    <term>Milovan Đilas</term>
                    <term>britanska Laburistična stranka</term>
                    <term>Aneurin Bevan</term>
                    <term>socializem</term>
                    <term>disidentstvo</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change>
                    <date>2017-12-28</date>
                    <name>Neja Blaj Hribar</name>
                    <desc>Pretvorba iz DOCX v TEI, dodatno kodiranje</desc>
                </change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <docAuthor>Mateja Režek<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn2" n="*">
                    <hi rend="bold" xml:space="preserve">Senior Research Fellow, PhD, Znanstveno-raziskovalno središče Koper / Science and Research Centre Koper, Garibaldijeva 1, SI-6000 Koper, </hi><ref target="mailto:mateja.rezek@zrs-kp.si"><hi rend="bold">mateja.rezek@zrs-kp.si</hi></ref></note></docAuthor>
            <docImprint>
                <idno type="cobissType">Cobiss type: 1.01</idno>
                <idno type="UDC">UDC: 929Djilas M.:329(410)Lab"1950/1960"</idno>
            </docImprint>
            <div type="abstract" xml:lang="sl">
                <head>IZVLEČEK</head>
                <head>MILOVAN ĐILAS IN BRITANSKA
                    LABURISTIČNA STRANKA, 1950–1960</head>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Članek obravnava politično preobrazbo
                        Milovana Đilasa skozi analizo njegovih stikov z britanskimi laburisti in odziv
                        Laburistične stranke na afero Đilas. Po sporu z Informbirojem so jugoslovanski
                        voditelji skušali vzpostaviti alternativne mednarodne povezave tudi prek
                        zahodnih socialdemokratskih in socialističnih strank, kot najprimernejši partner
                        pa se je pokazala britanska Laburistična stranka. Uradni stiki z njo so bili
                        vzpostavljeni leta 1950, ključno vlogo v dialogu z britanskimi laburisti pa je
                        odigral predsednik Komisije za mednarodne odnose CK ZKJ Milovan Đilas. Po
                        njegovi odstranitvi iz političnega življenja in obsodbi na zaporno kazen so se
                        nekoč topli odnosi med britanskimi laburisti in jugoslovanskimi komunisti sicer
                        ohladili, vendar vodstvo Laburistične stranke ni želelo tvegati poslabšanja
                        odnosov z Jugoslavijo, zato se je na afero Đilas odzivalo zelo previdno. Čeprav
                        je Jugoslavija ostajala avtoritarna država pod vodstvom komunistične partije, je
                        v očeh Zahoda še vedno predstavljala pomemben dejavnik destabilizacije vzhodnega
                        bloka, prijateljski odnosi med Laburistično stranko in jugoslovanskimi komunisti
                        pa so temeljili predvsem na zunanjepolitičnih interesih obeh strani. V drugi
                        polovici petdesetih let je pragmatični geopolitični premislek povsem prevladal
                        nad ideološko afiniteto: zanimanje britanskih laburistov za jugoslovanski
                        samoupravni eksperiment je občutno upadlo, zamrl pa je tudi jugoslovanski
                        interes za demokratični socializem.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Ključne besede: Milovan Đilas, britanska Laburistična stranka, Aneurin Bevan, socializem, disidentstvo </hi></p>
            </div>
            <div type="abstract" xml:lang="en">
                <head>ABSTRACT</head>
                <p><hi rend="italic">The article deals with Milovan Djilas’
                    political transformation presented through an analysis of his connections with
                    the British Labourites, and with the reaction of the Labour Party to the Djilas
                    Affair. After the dispute with the Cominform, Yugoslav leaders tried to initiate
                    alternative international contacts through Western socialist and social
                    democratic parties, considering the most suitable partner the British Labour
                    Party. Official contacts with the latter were established in 1950, the key role
                    in the dialogue with the British Labourites played by the head of the Commission
                    for International Relations, Milovan Djilas. In the aftermath of the Djilas
                    Affair, the once warm relations between the British Labourites and Yugoslav
                    Communists grew rather cool, but the leadership of the Labour Party did not wish
                    to compromise their relations with Yugoslavia, and therefore reacted to it with
                    considerable wariness. Although Yugoslavia remained an authoritarian state under
                    the leadership of the Communist Party, in the eyes of the West it continued to
                    represent a significant factor in the destabilisation of the Eastern Bloc, and
                    the friendly relationship between the Labour Party and the Yugoslav Communists
                    were primarily based on foreign policy interests of the two parties. In the
                    second half of the 1950s, the relationship between the Labour Party and the
                    Yugoslav Communists rested, even more than before, on pragmatic geopolitical
                    consideration and not on ideological affinity; the interest of the British
                    Labourites in the Yugoslav self-management experiment decreased significantly,
                    as did the Yugoslav interest in democratic socialism.</hi></p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Keywords: Milovan Djilas, British Labour
                        Party, Aneurin Bevan, socialism, dissent</hi>
                </p>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div><p><hi style="font-size:12pt">Much has been written about Milovan Djilas,</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn3" n="2"> Stephen Clissold, <hi rend="italic">Djilas: the Progress of a Revolutionary</hi> (Hounslow,
                        Middlesex: Maurice Temple Smith, 1983). Joshua Muravchik, “The Intellectual
                        Odyssey of Milovan Djilas,” <hi rend="italic">World Affairs</hi> 145, No. 4
                        (1983): 323–46. Vasilije Kalezić,
                        <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Đilas, miljenik i otpadnik komunizma </hi>(Beograd:
                        Zodne, 1988). Momčilo Đorgović, <hi rend="italic">Đilas: vernik i
                            jeretik</hi> (Beograd: Akvarijus, 1989). Vladimir Dedijer, <hi rend="italic">Veliki buntovnik Milovan Đilas: prilozi za biografiju</hi>
                        (Beograd: Prosveta, 1991). Desimir Tošić, <hi rend="italic">Ko je Milovan
                            Đilas?: disidentstvo 1953–1995</hi> (Beograd: Otkrovenje, 2003). Mateja
                        Režek, “Defeat of the First Party Liberalism and the Echo of ‘Djilasism’ in
                        Slovenia,” <hi rend="italic">Slovene Studies</hi> 28, No. 1–2 (2006): 67–78.
                        Dejan Djokić, “Britain and Dissent in Tito’s Yugoslavia: the Djilas Affair,
                        ca. 1956,”
                        <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">European History Quarterly </hi>36,
                        No. 3 (2006): 371–95. Dobrilo Arnitović,
                        <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Milovan Đilas: bibliografija sa hronologijom života i rada </hi>(Beograd:
                        Službeni glasnik, 2008). Slavko Goldstein, “Predgovor: Povratak Milovana
                        Đilasa u Hrvatsku,” in:
                        <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Milovan Đilas, Vlast i pobuna: memoari </hi>(Zagreb:
                        Novi Liber, 2009). Jože Pirjevec, <hi rend="italic">Tito in tovariši</hi>
                        (Ljubljana: Cankarjeva založba, 2011). Veljko Stanić, “Unutrašnji emigrant:
                        političke ideje Milovana Đilasa 1954–1989,”
                        <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Poznańskie Studia Slawistyczne </hi>6
                        (2014): 213–29. Aleksandar V. Miletić, “Unrealised Nordic Dream: Milovan
                        Đilas and the Scandinavian Socialists,” <hi rend="italic">Tokovi
                            istorije</hi> 3 (2015): 89–106. Tomaž Ivešić, “Padec Milovana Đilasa,”
                        in: Milovan Đilas, <hi rend="italic">Anatomija neke morale in 19 znamenitih
                            člankov (oktober 1953 – januar 1954)</hi>, ed. Tomaž Ivešić (Ljubljana:
                        Inštitut Nove revije, 2015), 131–85. Etc.</note>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">much more than about the majority of Eastern European
                    dissidents; but the question why the former Communist dogmatist and one of the
                    closest Tito’s co-workers</hi>
                <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn4" n="3"> In addition to the
                        leader of the Party propaganda machine, Milovan Djilas, the closest circle
                        of Tito’s co-workers included the leading Party ideologist Edvard Kardelj
                        and head of the Yugoslav repressive apparatus Aleksandar
                    Ranković.</note>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">turned away from Communism, becoming an ardent advocate
                    of individual liberty and political pluralism, remains in many ways unanswered.
                    Not infrequently has his rebellious stance been ascribed to personal grudges
                    between Party comrades and to Djilas’ fiery temper, which Vladimir Dedijer
                    described as “a violent Dinaric type,”</hi>
                <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn5" n="4"> Dedijer, <hi rend="italic">Veliki buntovnik Milovan Đilas</hi>.</note>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">yet this can only be part of the equation. The present
                    article does not aspire to provide a comprehensive answer to this complex
                    question; its goal is to shed light on Djilas’ contacts with the British
                    Labourites, which influenced his political transformation, and outline the
                    reaction of the British Labour Party to the Djilas Affair.</hi></p>
            <p><hi style="font-size:12pt">The conflict with the Cominform was for Djilas, like for
                    other Yugoslav leaders, a dramatic personal experience and a major political
                    turning point. Under the weight of complete political isolation, Soviet economic
                    blockade and threat of military intervention, Yugoslav leaders soon started
                    turning their gaze towards the West. To ensure Western economic and military
                    aid, they had to moderate their image and prove that Yugoslavia was different
                    from the Soviet Union, while striving to preserve their national independence
                    and radical ideological image. It was in this context that the idea of
                    self-management emerged. It is impossible to claim with certainty who its
                    original author was. In several of the editions of his memoirs, Djilas asserted
                    that he had come to the idea himself and explained it one rainy day to Edvard
                    Kardelj and Boris Kidrič in a car parked in front of his villa,</hi>
                <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn6" n="5"> Đilas, <hi rend="italic">Vlast i pobuna</hi>, 296. Also: Milovan Đilas, <hi rend="italic">Druženje s Titom</hi> (Beograd: Zaslon, 1990), 57, 58.
                        Milovan Đilas, <hi rend="italic">Pad nove klase: povest o samorazaranju
                            komunizma</hi> (Beograd: Službeni list SRJ, 1994), 110. Etc.</note>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">whereas Tito’s and Djilas’ biographer Vladimir Dedijer
                    insisted that the originator of the idea about workers’ self-management was the
                    leader of Yugoslav economic policy, Boris Kidrič.</hi>
                <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn7" n="6"> Dedijer, <hi rend="italic">Veliki buntovnik Milovan Đilas</hi>, 384.</note>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">Regardless of the historical accuracy of Djilas’ story
                    about the birthplace of the idea of self-management, his memoirs clearly
                    illustrate how decisions were made in Yugoslavia – within a closed inner circle
                    of the Party leaders and from the top down, most often without any records. How
                    the Yugoslav Party leadership operated in the field of ideology has been
                    eloquently portrayed by the American historian Dennison Rusinow: “Ideology, like
                    power, remained highly centralised, and the inner ‘establishment’ of Titoism in
                    its formative years was still the small group of men, personally recruited by
                    Tito after 1937 /…/. They met at work and they met at play, they telephoned one
                    another in the middle of the night, and they talked incessantly. Ideas were
                    bounced from one to another until original authorship became undiscoverable as
                    well as unrecorded.”</hi>
                <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn8" n="7"> Dennison Rusinow,
                            <hi rend="italic">The Yugoslav Experiment 1948–1974</hi> (Berkeley and
                        Los Angeles: University of California Press, 1977),
                    49.</note><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve"> Milovan Djilas, Edvard Kardelj and Boris Kidrič were the most zealous ideological debaters, but the final decisions were made by Tito, although “he would stand aloof from these theoretical discussions: due to his overworking, hierarchical superiority, as well as non-theoretical mind-set …,” as Djilas wrote.</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn9" n="8"> Đilas, <hi rend="italic">Vlast i pobuna</hi>, 296.</note></p>
            <p><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve">In 1949 and 1950, the Yugoslav leaders abandoned the rigid imitation of the Soviet system and began experimenting with new ideas. In contrast to the Eastern Bloc, where the state was growing stronger, they began to propagate Marx’s thesis on the withering away of the state. They attempted to approach this ideal through the introduction of workers’ self-management and social ownership, as well as decentralisation of state power. Bureaucracy was seen as the greatest enemy of socialism, which, if its wings were not clipped, would transform into a ruling social class and then inevitably lead to the establishment of state capitalism like that in the Soviet Union. The critical reflections on the Soviet system also gave rise to thoughts of separating the Communist Party from the state. At its Sixth Congress in November 1952, the Communist Party of Yugoslavia (CPY) officially declared its renouncement of direct control and renamed itself the League of Communists of Yugoslavia (LCY). Its fundamental task was defined as providing the masses with ideological guidance and education in the spirit of socialism. Surely, the early 1950s brought about some radical shifts, particularly in ideological terms, though the actual practice lagged far behind the declarative and normative standards. </hi></p>
</div>            
            <div><head>“The Beginning of
                    Something Much More Lasting and Deeper”</head>
            <p><hi style="font-size:12pt">Following the Tito-Stalin split, the Yugoslav leaders,
                    eager to improve their image in the West, initiated contacts with the Western
                    Left that could be a valuable support to their policy. Towards the end of
                    December 1949, at the Third Plenum of the Central Committee of the CPY, the
                    foreign minister and leading party ideologist Edvard Kardelj announced a more
                    “agile” foreign policy</hi>
                <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn10" n="9"> Edvard Kardelj’s
                        paper <hi rend="italic">O spoljnopolitičkim pitanjima</hi> on the Third
                        Plenum of the Central Committee of CPY in: <hi rend="italic">Sednice
                            Centralnog komiteta KPJ: 1948–1952,</hi> eds. Branko Petranović et al.,
                        (Beograd: Komunist, 1985), 469–82. See also: Darko Bekić, <hi rend="italic">Jugoslavija u hladnom ratu: odnosi sa velikim silama 1949–1955</hi>
                        (Zagreb: Globus, 1988), 92, 93. Čedomir Štrbac, “Britanski laburisti u
                        Jugoslaviji 1950,” in: <hi rend="italic">Jugoslovensko-britanski
                        odnosi</hi>, ed. Petar Kačavenda (Beograd: Institut za savremenu istoriju,
                        1988), 332, 333.</note>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">and the intention to search for alternative international
                    connections, including the Western socialist and social democratic parties. To
                    this purpose, the Commission for International Relations of the Central
                    Committee of CPY was founded. It was headed by Milovan Djilas, with Vladimir
                    Dedijer as its Secretary.</hi></p>
            <p><hi style="font-size:12pt">In the Yugoslav desire to establish alternative
                    connections, the most suitable partner both in the fields of foreign policy and
                    ideology was Western Europe’s largest social democratic party – the British
                    Labour Party. Between 1945 and 1951, with the Labourites as the ruling party in
                    Britain, numerous socialist reforms were carried out, particularly the
                    nationalisation of key industries, as well as reforms of the health care and
                    social security systems. This made the Labour Party a palatable partner to the
                    Yugoslav leaders from an ideological point of view, although, contrary to the
                    Yugoslav Communist Party, it swore by political pluralism, rejected Marxism and
                    class struggle, and advocated a gradual transition into socialism.</hi>
            </p>
            <p><hi style="font-size:12pt">Due to the anti-communist climate in the West, the
                    invitation to the British Labourites to visit Yugoslavia was not extended on
                    behalf of the Communist Party, rather on behalf of the Popular Front. Between
                    7</hi><hi rend="superscript" style="font-size:12pt">th</hi><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve"> and 19</hi><hi rend="superscript" style="font-size:12pt">th</hi>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">September 1950, Yugoslav Communists in the disguise of
                    the Popular Front hosted the first official delegation of the Labour Party,
                    consisting of Morgan Phillips, the General Secretary of the Labour Party, Sam
                    Watson, the Chairman of the International Committee, and Harry Earnshaw, a
                    member of the National Executive Committee.</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn11" n="10"> For more details about this
                        visit, see: Štrbac, “Britanski laburisti u Jugoslaviji 1950.” Aleksandar V.
                        Miletić, “Prijem delegacije britanskih laburista kod maršala Tita u okviru
                        njihove prve posete Jugoslaviji, 1950. godine,”
                        <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Tokovi istorije </hi>1 (2011):
                        137–64.</note>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">This was the first official visit by any Western social
                    democratic or socialist party to Yugoslavia and it contributed appreciably to
                    the further expansion of Yugoslav relations with the Western Left.</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn12" n="11"> Vladimir
                        Unkovski-Korica, “The Yugoslav Communists’ Special Relationship with the
                        British Labour Party 1950–1956,”
                        <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Cold War History </hi>14, No. 1
                        (2014): 36.</note>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">During their stay in Yugoslavia, the Labourites visited
                    Belgrade, Zagreb, Ljubljana, and some smaller towns. They held several meetings
                    with Yugoslav leaders and visited factories, a copper mine, a collective farm,
                    and even a notorious political prison in Sremska Mitrovica, where, ironically,
                    Djilas would later be imprisoned. The Yugoslav side was represented by Milovan
                    Djilas, Moša Pijade, Boris Kidrič and a few others. Towards the end of their
                    visit, the Labourite delegation was received by the Yugoslav president Tito, who
                    was at the same time President of the Popular Front and Secretary-General of the
                    Communist Party. The discussions revolved around the liberalisation of economy,
                    life standards, the issue of individual liberty and repressive policies, the
                    different paths into socialism, and current foreign policy topics. They unfolded
                    in the spirit of searching for common points, not differences, with the British
                    guests giving plenty of leeway to their hosts. The Yugoslav side stressed their
                    achievements, but also admitted that limitations existed, the latter blamed on
                    Soviet remainders in domestic policy and the Soviet threat from outside.
                    However, Djilas surprised the British visitors by the frankness with which he
                    spoke of the recently held elections to the National Assembly. He admitted that
                    the officially declared results did not reflect the true state of feeling within
                    the country, since the pro-regime majority exercised a certain psychological and
                    political pressure on the others.</hi>
                <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn13" n="12"> Clissold, <hi rend="italic">Djilas</hi>, 217.</note>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">These discussions with the British Labourites were
                    characterised by a noticeable departure from the crude dogmatism of the first
                    post-war years, but that should not be regarded as a pure pragmatic attempt on
                    the part of the Yugoslav leaders to win the sympathies of Western Left,
                    particularly not in Djilas’ case. He noted in his memoirs that the debates with
                    the representatives of the Labour Party were “very frank and convergent” and
                    that “the Labourites, as well as other European socialists, were not just a
                    transitional stage in our cooperation with the West, but an active force, and
                    the cooperation with them plucked us from isolation, freeing us at the same time
                    of the ideological prejudices about Communists as the sole true representatives
                    of the working class and socialism.”</hi>
                <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn14" n="13"> Đilas, <hi rend="italic">Vlast i pobuna</hi>, 300.</note></p>
            <p><hi style="font-size:12pt">In a conversation between the representatives of the
                    Labour Party and Tito on 18</hi><hi rend="superscript" style="font-size:12pt">th</hi><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve"> September 1950, in which Milovan Djilas, Boris Kidrič, and Vladimir Dedijer as interpreter also took part, the question about the different paths to socialism was raised. While the two sides acknowledged their respective rights to reach socialism their own way, the Labourites wished to emphasise individual liberty in this context. Sam Watson stated that the fundamental conception of the Labourites was to create a social order in which a factory worker could do his best at work and then, when he got off, be a completely free individual. When Watson challenged his Yugoslav interlocutors with the question whether they, too, wanted to follow this path, Djilas assented, saying that was the way “according to Marx.” Watson replied that they were not familiar with Marx themselves, but they did want the individual to be free “to criticise or cheer for whomever they choose,”</hi>
                <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn15" n="14"> The transcript of
                        the conversation between Tito and the representatives of the Labour Party is
                        published in its entirety as a supplement to the article: Miletić, “Prijem
                        delegacije britanskih laburista,” 157.</note>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">thereby underlining the Labourites’ commitment to
                    parliamentary democracy. Morgan Phillips added that although the Labourites
                    might not proceed from Marxism, that did not mean they knew nothing about it, as
                    there were several ministers in the British government who had studied Marx.
                    Watson then reiterated: “The only way, and I say this as an old worker (he used
                    to work as a blaster in a coal mine – note by M. R.), is to give people maximum
                    freedom, because no initiative can develop without that.”</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn16" n="15"> Ibid., 158.</note>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">This time, the call to confrontation was answered by
                    Tito, who stressed that Yugoslavia was still insufficiently developed for that:
                    “Up until recently, we lived in the very harsh conditions of a backward Balkan
                    country. Freedom cannot be measured the same way in a developed country and in a
                    backward country, where all possible instincts are present. It is precisely this
                    backwardness that often, even against our will, imposes on us a certain
                    brutality, brutality from our standpoint. Which is nevertheless necessary! I
                    regard the whole country as a sort of school, and school requires a minimum of
                    discipline. We re-educate people in it.”</hi>
                <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn17" n="16"> Ibid.,
                    159.</note>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">Later on, Phillips pointed out the specific revolutionary
                    experience of Yugoslavia’s coming out of a liberation war, which was hardly
                    reproducible in any European country, but could set an example for Asian
                    countries liberating themselves from imperialist domination.</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn18" n="17"> Ibid., 159,
                    60.</note>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">This way he exhorted the Yugoslav leaders quite directly
                    to cooperate with the “Third World.” Despite ideological differences between the
                    Labour Party and the Yugoslav Communist Party or Popular Front, the conversation
                    proceeded in the spirit of mutual understanding and collaboration. In the end,
                    Watson emphasised in his toast that the British side would do everything to help
                    Yugoslavia and that they appreciated their hosts treating them as “intelligent
                    human beings” and not hiding their difficulties from them.</hi>
                <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn19" n="18"> Ibid.,
                    162.</note>
            </p>
            <p><hi style="font-size:12pt">But the Labourites had no illusions about the Yugoslav
                    regime. In his confidential report to the Executive Committee of the Labour
                    Party about the visit to Yugoslavia, Morgan Phillips wrote that the Yugoslav
                    leadership, with Tito at its head, were “100% communists” and that Yugoslavia
                    was a communist country, but anyone who thought that this regime could be
                    replaced by a parliamentary democracy modelled after the Western example, was
                    sadly mistaken – at best, it could be replaced by a “Cominformist communist
                    party.” He declared Yugoslavia “a police state” that was nevertheless quite
                    distinct from the Soviet Union in terms of the freedom of expression and the
                    privileges of the Party elite. He stressed that there were indeed fundamental
                    differences in ideology and practice between the two parties, but that
                    “Yugoslavia might prove to be an interesting experiment that could, if it
                    succeeded along the lines which it seems to be developing, have an influence on
                    other nations.”</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn20" n="19"> Štrbac, “Britanski laburisti u Jugoslaviji 1950,” 339,
                        40.</note></p>
            <p><hi style="font-size:12pt">The British guests were rather impressed by the Yugoslav
                    hosts and invited them to visit Britain. The President of the Commission for
                    International Relations Milovan Djilas and its Secretary Vladimir Dedijer, also
                    in the role of interpreter, travelled to London in January 1951. The real
                    purpose behind this trip was a Yugoslav request for arms from the British
                    government. Djilas was entrusted with the task of confidentially and personally
                    communicating this request to the British Prime Minister Clement Attlee. He
                    promised that it would be dealt with sympathetically,</hi>
                <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn21" n="20"> Clissold, <hi rend="italic">Djilas</hi>, 217, 18. Bekić, <hi rend="italic">Jugoslavija
                            u hladnom ratu</hi>, 250. Đilas, <hi rend="italic">Vlast i pobuna</hi>,
                        301. Dedijer, <hi rend="italic">Veliki buntovnik Milovan Đilas</hi>,
                        360.</note><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve"> and indeed, Yugoslavia received the requested support.</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn22" n="21"> For more details
                        about Western support in arms, see: Ivan Laković,
                        <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Zapadna vojna pomoć Jugoslaviji 1951–1958 </hi>(Podgorica:
                        Istorijski institut Crne Gore, 2006).</note>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">In addition, Djilas held a lecture at the Royal Institute
                    of International Affairs (Chatham House) about Yugoslav-Soviet relations, which
                    encountered a positive reception in the audience and in the media. On 4</hi><hi rend="superscript" style="font-size:12pt">th</hi>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve">February, </hi><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:12pt">The Observer</hi><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve"> wrote that Djilas views were more pre-Bolshevik Marxist than Leninist.</hi>
                <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn23" n="22"> Tošić, <hi rend="italic">Ko je Milovan Đilas</hi>, 28.</note></p>
            <p><hi style="font-size:12pt">Djilas’ visit to Britain was not only important from a
                    military-diplomatic perspective, but also in light of Djilas’ later dissent.
                    There he met the leaders of both the Labour and the Conservative Parties,
                    including Winston Churchill. But crucial for him was the encounter with the then
                    Minister for Health in the Labourite government, Aneurin Bevan, leader of the
                    left-wing of the Labour Party, the so-called “Bevanites”. Djilas met him on
                    31</hi>
                <hi rend="superscript" style="font-size:12pt">st</hi><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve"> January 1951 at a dinner organised by Prime Minister Attlee at Downing Street.</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn24" n="23"> Clissold, <hi rend="italic">Djilas</hi>, 219. Dedijer, <hi rend="italic">Veliki
                            buntovnik Milovan Đilas</hi>, 364.</note>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">Later he wrote that he found Bevan to be “a dynamic
                    personality, with a lively, unconventional mind,” and was most impressed by his
                    “perspicacious line of thought and the concurrent stubborn, original and popular
                    faith in socialism.”</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn25" n="24"> Đilas, <hi rend="italic">Vlast i pobuna</hi>, 302,
                        348.</note>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">Djilas was also otherwise quite enthusiastic about what
                    he saw in Britain. Returning from London, he and Dedijer stopped in Paris, where
                    Dedijer told the American journalist C. L. Sulzberger that Djilas was impressed
                    with Great Britain and that he had found the workers’ unions there to be a lot
                    less bureaucratized than the ones in Yugoslavia.</hi>
                <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn26" n="25"> Bekić, <hi rend="italic">Jugoslavija u hladnom ratu</hi>, 251.</note></p>
            <p><hi style="font-size:12pt">In April 1951, Bevan resigned from the position of the
                    Minister for Health following the introduction of prescription charges to help
                    finance the Korean War. Three months later he accepted an invitation to visit
                    Yugoslavia, where he arrived together with his wife, Jennie Lee, also a
                    prominent Labourite and a Member of Parliament. Their host Milovan Djilas
                    welcomed them in Belgrade and joined them on their visit to Tito in the Brijuni
                    Islands. The British guests spent their vacations immersed in political debates
                    with their hosts in the relaxed atmosphere at the Adriatic coast. Bevan’s
                    biographer Michael Foot wrote that they had come away “with indelible memories
                    of the special qualities of Yugoslav bravery, of their absolute resolve to
                    resist Soviet encroachment, of the greatness of Tito, and with another
                    possession more peculiar to Jennie and himself – an immediately established
                    affinity with Milovan Djilas.”</hi>
                <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn27" n="26"> Michael
                        Foot,<hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve"> Aneurin Bevan: A Biography, Vol. 2: 1945–1960 </hi>(London:
                        Davis-Poynter, 1973), 347. Clissold, <hi rend="italic">Djilas</hi>, 220,
                        21.</note>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve">The socialising brought forth a friendship and a cross-fertilisation of ideas between the Bevans and Djilas, both corroborated by their correspondence. Soon after the Bevans returned to Britain, Djilas wrote to them: “It is understandable that – in different countries under different conditions – identical or similar viewpoints are being born. /…/ I think that the personal relationship established between both of you and ourselves is only </hi>
                <hi rend="italic" style="font-size:12pt">the beginning of something much more
                    lasting and
                    deeper</hi><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve"> (emphasis by M. R.), the beginning of that unbreakable link between people who through different methods and even from different ideological positions truly fight for freedom.”</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn28" n="27">
                        Foot,<hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve"> Aneurin Bevan</hi>, 348.
                        Clissold, <hi rend="italic">Djilas</hi>, 220, 21.</note>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">Djilas and Bevan were not only similar in their political
                    outlooks, but also in character. “They were both poets, romantics,
                    unrestrainable individualists, strong unpredictable mountain types”, noted
                    Jennie Lee.</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn29" n="28"> Clissold, <hi rend="italic">Djilas</hi>,
                    219.</note><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve"> Vladimir Dedijer described them in much the same way, when he wrote that Bevan was known for his short temper, and that he, like Djilas, could be very charming, but would sometimes have sharp outbursts, so his wife labelled him “a violent Welsh type.”</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn30" n="29"> Dedijer, <hi rend="italic">Veliki buntovnik Milovan Đilas</hi>, 377.</note></p>
            <p><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve">Djilas only later became aware of the divide between Bevan’s way of thinking and his own, which originated in the different social realities of Yugoslavia and Britain. In his book </hi><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:12pt">The Unperfect Society</hi>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">Djilas described his conversation with Bevan and Jennie
                    Lee in the summer of 1953 in Montenegro, which was focused on the issue of how
                    to merge socialism and traditional political liberties. When Djilas suggested
                    the answer could be workers’ self-management, Bevan exclaimed: mixed economy. He
                    believed that Britain should only nationalise the industries that would become
                    more efficient if nationalised, while leaving the others in private hands, and
                    that this way the British parliamentarism would not be weakened. “There was
                    something in this Bevan’s thought that linked up with my later realisations,”
                    wrote Djilas three decades later, “namely, that the impasse and limitedness in
                    Communism, the impracticability of reforms in it, actually derive from the type
                    of ownership, which is social or state in form and interiorised and absolutized
                    as such, though in reality it is managed and commanded by Party bureaucracy
                    through state and economic organs.”</hi>
                <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn31" n="30"> Milovan Đilas, <hi rend="italic">Nesavršeno društvo: (i dalje od Nove klase)</hi> (Beograd:
                        Narodna knjiga, 1990), 115.</note></p>
            <p>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve">In 1952, Bevan published his first actual book, </hi><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:12pt">In Place of Fear</hi><hi style="font-size:12pt">, which in Britain became almost synonymous with all that
                    the welfare state stood for and what it sought to achieve. By 1952, a consensus
                    had formed in Britain that it was possible to create a society where all could
                    live without the fear of being hungry, poorly housed, or of living with or dying
                    in great pain – hence its title. In the book, Bevan presented his political
                    views, including those regarding National Health Service, which he had
                    established as the Minister for Health in the first post-war years. The writing
                    is also somewhat autobiographical, as through Bevan’s reflections on politics we
                    retrace his path from a Welsh miner to a minister in the Labourite government.
                    Interestingly, though not surprisingly given the Yugoslav political atmosphere
                    in 1952, the publication of his book in Britain was immediately followed by a
                    Serbian-language edition published in Yugoslavia.</hi>
                <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn32" n="31"> Aneurin Bevan, <hi rend="italic">Umesto straha</hi> (Beograd: Biblioteka Trideset dana,
                        1952).</note></p>
            <p>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">In February 1953, the Labour Party sent their delegation
                    to the Fourth Congress of the Popular Front, which on that occasion changed its
                    name to the Socialist Alliance of the Working People of Yugoslavia (SAWPY). The
                    latter was supposed to take over from the Party the task of managing current
                    policies, while the Party would mostly focus on ideological issues. Yugoslav
                    leaders even went as far as trying to make the Socialist Alliance a member of
                    the Socialist International, but nothing ever came of these endeavours. As
                    Western socialists and social democrats saw in the Socialist Alliance merely a
                    transmission of the Communist Party, much like they did in their predecessor,
                    the Popular Front, they rejected its affiliation to the Socialist
                    International.</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn33" n="32"> Mateja Režek, <hi rend="italic">Med resničnostjo in
                            iluzijo: slovenska in jugoslovanska politika v desetletju po sporu z
                            Informbirojem (1948–1958)</hi> (Ljubljana: Modrijan, 2005), 56,
                    57.</note><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve"> The greatest obstacle for establishing even closer relations with the Western Left was the Yugoslav single-party system. Clement Attlee, who visited Yugoslavia in August 1953, announced that the Socialist Alliance would not become a member of the Socialist International as long as Yugoslavia preserved its one-party system. He said: “With no opposition parties, the political life is dull, futile. It’s a one-horse race,” adding: “In Britain, I am the leader of the opposition, while here I am trying in vain to find a counterpart.”</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn34" n="33"> Ibid., 57,
                    58.</note></p>
            <p><hi style="font-size:12pt">Aneurin Bevan, who had a serious inter-party dispute with
                    Attlee, was visiting Yugoslavia at the same time, so his host Djilas made sure
                    the two never crossed paths. Upon Bevan’s wish to visit “authentic people” and
                    backward areas, Djilas took him and his wife to Bosnia and Herzegovina and to
                    Montenegro. Later he wrote: “I bid my farewell from the Bevans in Cetinje, from
                    where Dedijer accompanied them to see Tito: never did I suspect that that would
                    be my last encounter with Nye – the discontinuation of selfless joint searches
                    in socialism from two far ends of Europe, two different cultures and different
                    experience.”</hi>
                <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn35" n="34"> Đilas, <hi rend="italic">Vlast i pobuna</hi>, 348.</note></p>
            <p><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve">During the first half of the 1950s, Djilas would slowly grow disillusioned with Communism. He believed that the class struggle was over and that the principal enemy of socialism in Yugoslavia was no longer the bourgeoisie, but bureaucracy, and that Yugoslavia should proceed towards democratic socialism. Contrary to Djilas, in the mid-1953, the Yugoslav Party leadership adopted the opinion of the advocates of strong-arm politics, who saw in political liberalisation the beginning of the end of the Party’s rule. This political shift was triggered not only by Stalin’s death in March 1953 and by the prospects of a warming in relations with the Soviet Union, but also by Tito’s perception that the power of the Communist Party had weakened. The often inconsistent directives from above led to confusion and lack of discipline among Party members, which resulted in apathy and public discussions on current policy as well as in the emergence of opinions that were not always in accord with the views of the Party leadership, at least its majority. In mid-June 1953, Tito called a Central Committee Plenum in Brijuni Islands and made clear that the leading role of the Party was to be reasserted. Djilas was not prepared to accept this about face. In the autumn and winter of 1953/54, he wrote several articles for the newspaper </hi>
                <hi rend="italic" style="font-size:12pt">Borba</hi>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve">calling for greater democratization of Yugoslav political life, attacking the bureaucracy, and making quite clear that the Party as it was had to go. He concluded his last article </hi><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:12pt">League or Party</hi>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">with the thought that the Leninist Party and State were
                    obsolete and that at the current stage of development only reforms and evolution
                    could be constructive.</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn36" n="35"> Milovan Đilas, “Zveza ali partija,” <hi rend="italic">Ljudska pravica–Borba</hi>, 4. 1. 1954, 2, 3.</note>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve">He crowned his series of articles in </hi><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:12pt">Borba</hi>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">with the piece</hi>
                <hi rend="italic" style="font-size:12pt">Anatomy of a Moral,</hi>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">which he published in the magazine</hi>
                <hi rend="italic" style="font-size:12pt">Nova
                misao</hi><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve"> and in which he rebuked the morality of the political elite and inflamed the already smouldering personal grudges among Party leaders.</hi>
            </p>
            <p><hi style="font-size:12pt">At the Third Plenum of the Central Committee on 16</hi><hi rend="superscript" style="font-size:12pt">th</hi><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve"> and 17</hi><hi rend="superscript" style="font-size:12pt">th</hi>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve">January 1954, Djilas was accused of violation of party discipline, revisionism, “Bernsteinism,” social democratic deviations, and bourgeois liberalism. All the members of the Central Committee, with the exception of Vladimir Dedijer and Djilas’ former wife Mitra Mitrović, joined in the accusations, and the Serbian Party leader Petar Stambolić even reproached Djilas with having fallen under Bevan’s influence. Djilas was excluded from the Central Committee and stripped of all political functions, and later he resigned from the Party. In January 1955, criminal proceedings were initiated against him because of an interview he had given to </hi>
                <hi rend="italic" style="font-size:12pt">The New York Times</hi><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve">, in which he openly criticised the Yugoslav system and advocated political pluralism. He was given an 18-month suspended sentence, but then in December 1956 he was sentenced to 3 years of imprisonment for his article in the American leftist periodical </hi>
                <hi rend="italic" style="font-size:12pt">The New Leader</hi>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve">and his statement to the French press agency criticising Yugoslav apparent neutrality during the Hungarian Uprising. In October 1957, seven years of imprisonment were added to his sentence because of the book </hi>
                <hi rend="italic" style="font-size:12pt">The New
                    Class</hi><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve">, a powerful critique of communist elite that made Djilas the most significant Eastern European dissident. He earned an additional five years in prison in 1962 with the book </hi><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:12pt">Conversations with Stalin</hi>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">and by 1966, when he was released from prison, he had
                    served a total of nine years.</hi></p></div>
            <div><head>British Labourites
                    and the Djilas Affair</head>
            <p><hi style="font-size:12pt">Djilas’ political downfall somewhat complicated the
                    relationships between the British Labour Party and the Yugoslav Communists. The
                    Labour Party did not protest to the Yugoslav authorities about it, but the
                    reproach made at the Third Plenum in January 1954, that Djilas was under Bevan’s
                    influence, did not pass unnoticed. A few days after the Plenum, on 1</hi><hi rend="superscript" style="font-size:12pt">st</hi><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve"> February 1954, Bevan wrote to Tito that he was surprised by what had happened as “nothing that I saw or was told when I visited Yugoslavia in August prepared me for these calamitous events.” He underlined that he had no intention of interfering in the internal affairs of another country, but “some remarks which have fallen from people of high position in your country have suggested that I have had a bad influence on Milovan’s political outlook, and that our friendship has had something to do with his recent attitude. This does little credit to Milovan’s robust character and mental poise and I dismiss it as merely the rancour of political controversy.”</hi>
                <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn37" n="36"> Foot, <hi rend="italic">Aneurin Bevan</hi>, 420.</note>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">He concluded the letter saying that his only interest was
                    the welfare of Djilas and Dedijer, who initially took Djilas’ side.</hi></p>
            <p><hi style="font-size:12pt">Tito answered Bevan that during the discussion his name
                    had only been mentioned once and that he was sorry it garnered such publicity,
                    “because we do not believe that you exercised any influence upon Djilas as
                    regards the road upon which he had embarked, i.e., the road of anarchist
                    conceptions, because we know you as a realistic political worker.” He added that
                    Djilas had been relieved of all political functions, but was ensured the
                    economic safety befitting a high official and his personal freedom was not
                    curtailed. He was still a member of the Communist Party and could reflect and
                    correct his “erroneous conceptions”. “It is entirely and solely up to him,”
                    concluded Tito his letter to Bevan.</hi>
                <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn38" n="37"> Ibid.,
                    422.</note></p>
            <p><hi style="font-size:12pt">Djilas himself denied that Bevan had influenced his
                    political stance,</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn39" n="38"> Đilas, <hi rend="italic">Vlast i pobuna</hi>,
                    348.</note>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">but his former colleagues thought otherwise. Edvard
                    Kardelj, who found himself in the role of chief prosecutor against Djilas at the
                    Third Plenum, later told Dedijer that in the summer of 1953 Djilas had tried to
                    persuade him that it was necessary to establish a second political party in
                    Yugoslavia: “At that time, Bevan was visiting in our country. He must have
                    greatly influenced Djilas, although not directly, rather implanting in his mind
                    certain ideas. Djilas reflected about what Bevan had told him and started
                    putting forward suggestions that a labour party should be founded in Yugoslavia.
                    I told him I would not relate a word about this to Tito – although I should –
                    nor would I inform the Politburo, as I hoped he would renounce such ideas. But
                    he continued to spread these suggestions despite our conversation, so in the
                    end, we were forced to discuss the case in the Politburo.”</hi>
                <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn40" n="39"> Dedijer, <hi rend="italic">Veliki buntovnik Milovan Đilas</hi>, 377.</note>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">Up to 1953, there had been little divergence between
                    Kardelj’s and Djilas’ theoretical views of the development of Yugoslav
                    socialism, as foreign observers could also support. The British ambassador Frank
                    Roberts wrote as late as January 1955 that with regard to theory, he found no
                    major differences between Djilas and Kardelj – “the real distinction is in that
                    Djilas wants this theory to finally come to life in practice, whereas Kardelj
                    insists on the preservation, for a while at least, of a single-party system, in
                    the circumstances of which self-management institutions are now little more than
                    pretentiousness” – while also pointing out the danger of left-wing or right-wing
                    despotism should the bourgeois ideas of democracy be freely allowed into the
                    state.</hi>
                <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn41" n="40"> Katarina Spehnjak,
                        “Velika Britanija i ‘slučaj Đilas’ 1954,” in: <hi rend="italic">Spoljna
                            politika Jugoslavije 1950–1961: zbornik radova</hi>, ed. Slobodan
                        Selinić (Beograd: Institut za noviju istoriju Srbije, 2008),
                360.</note></p>
            <p><hi style="font-size:12pt">As a result of internal and foreign policy situation, the
                    retaliation against Djilas and the so-called “Djilasites” in 1954 was relatively
                    mild. Tito wanted to silence and isolate him, not turn him into a victim and
                    martyr. Also, he did not want to lose the favour of the West, which had been
                    watching with suspicion Yugoslavia flirt with the Soviet Union for a while now.
                    After Stalin’s death, the relationship between the two countries had been
                    gradually improving, although Yugoslavia insisted on paving its own way into
                    socialism. During the talks on reconciliation, the Soviet side even proposed
                    that the blame for the Soviet-Yugoslav dispute should be pinned on Milovan
                    Djilas and Lavrentiy Beria,</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn42" n="41"> Bekić, <hi rend="italic">Jugoslavija u hladnom
                            ratu</hi>, 582. See also: Andrej Edemskii, “The Role of Milovan Djilas
                        in Soviet-Yugoslav Relations 1944–1954,” in: <hi rend="italic">The Balkans
                            in the Cold War: Balkan Federations, Cominform, Yugoslav-Soviet
                            Conflict</hi>, ed. Vojislav G. Pavlović (Belgrade: Institute for Balkan
                        Studies, 2011).</note>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">the former head of the Soviet secret police, executed in
                    December 1953, but Tito strongly rejected the Soviet suggestion since it would
                    negate the significance of Yugoslavia’s resistance against Stalin. During 1955
                    and 1956 the Soviet-Yugoslav relations were completely restored, first at the
                    state and then at the Party level. The relationship between the two countries
                    was more or less stable from then on, although severely wavering on occasion:
                    first as early as the end of 1956 due to Tito’s public criticism of the first
                    Soviet intervention in Hungary.</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn43" n="42"> For more, see: Mateja Režek, “Vroča jesen 1956: sueška
                        kriza, madžarska vstaja in vloga Jugoslavije,” <hi rend="italic">Annales,
                            Series historia et sociologia</hi> 24, No. 4 (2014): 609,
                10.</note></p>
            <p><hi style="font-size:12pt">Since the West was not willing to risk deterioration in
                    the relationship with Yugoslavia, Western leaders were initially very cautious
                    in their reaction to Djilas’ political downfall. Any irrational decision or
                    behaviour could, in fact, push Yugoslavia to an even closer cooperation with the
                    Soviet Union or even back inside the Soviet sphere of influence. The greatest
                    problem therefore, at least at the beginning, for both the Yugoslav and Western
                    authorities, was the Western media, which displayed considerable interest in
                    Djilas’ case. In this context, the new British ambassador in Belgrade, Frank
                    Roberts, made the assessment towards the end of 1954 that the Djilas Affair
                    would not affect the relations between Yugoslavia and the West “unless the
                    Western media continue to take so much interest in it to make the already
                    irritable Yugoslav sense of independence reach a touchy point.”</hi>
                <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn44" n="43"> Spehnjak, “Velika
                        Britanija i ‘slučaj Đilas’ 1954,” 355.</note>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">In its dealings with Yugoslavia, the British conservative
                    government gave precedence to political realism and pragmatism and never
                    protested to the Yugoslav authorities with regard to the Djilas Affair. Also
                    telling was the fact that the leading pro-Labour newspaper,</hi>
                <hi rend="italic" style="font-size:12pt">The Daily Herald</hi><hi style="font-size:12pt">, never published any of Djilas’ articles, despite the
                    promise of Ernest Davies, a Labour Member of Parliament and former Parliamentary
                    Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, who visited Djilas in Belgrade in
                    1954. In his memoirs, Djilas considered this as evidence of opportunism on the
                    part of the Labour Party leadership in its relations with Tito.</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn45" n="44"> Đilas, <hi rend="italic">Vlast i pobuna</hi>, 388.</note>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">Also, in 1954, the leadership of the Fabian Society, the
                    oldest socialist organisation in Britain and a sort of think tank of the Labour
                    Party, expressed through the Yugoslav embassy in London a wish to hold its
                    summer school in Yugoslavia. The event was organised in cooperation with the
                    SAWPY Commission for International Issues, headed by Marija Vilfan, and the
                    summer school was successfully carried out from the end of August to
                    mid-September 1955 on the Red Island (Crveni otok) near Rovinj.</hi>
                <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn46" n="45"> AJ 507, IX,
                        133/II-79, Komisija za međunarodne odnose i veze CK SKJ, Fabijanska škola na
                        Crvenom otoku kod Rovinja, 29. 8.–12. 9. 1955.</note></p>
            <p><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve">More resolution about the conduct of the Yugoslav authorities towards their friend was demonstrated by Aneurin Bevan and Jennie Lee. After Djilas’ incarceration in December 1956 and the extension of the term of imprisonment the following year due to his publication of </hi>
                <hi rend="italic" style="font-size:12pt">The New Class</hi>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve">in the United States, the Bevans made consistent efforts to have him released. Djilas experienced Bevan’s death in 1960 “as a loss of a closest friend,” later dedicating his classic work </hi>
                <hi rend="italic" style="font-size:12pt">Conversations with Stalin</hi>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">to him.</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn47" n="46"> Đilas, <hi rend="italic">Vlast i pobuna</hi>,
                    349.</note></p>
            <p><hi style="font-size:12pt">In the spring of 1956, Morgan Phillips, General Secretary
                    of the Labour Party and president of the Socialist International, interceded
                    with Tito on behalf of Djilas in a private and confidential letter in which he
                    protested against the way the Yugoslav authorities treated Djilas. He had been
                    prompted to do this by Djilas himself, when on 12</hi>
                <hi rend="superscript" style="font-size:12pt">th</hi><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve"> April 1956 he sent Phillips a letter through secret channels, describing his situation, which had worsened appreciably after the suspended sentence in January 1955: he was kept in complete isolation, having his services pension withheld, while the members of his family and the friends who had not severed their contacts with him were pressured, as well. Djilas and his family lived on his wife’s salary in a relatively comfortable apartment in Belgrade, but Djilas had been informed a short time before that they would have to move into a smaller apartment. Also, he suspected that his home was wired and that all his mail was screened. In the conclusion of the letter he stressed that he was writing “to acquaint you with the truth, hoping for your moral support” and not to seek intervention to his benefit or an offer of material assistance.</hi>
                <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn48" n="47"> Djokić, “Britain
                        and Dissent in Tito’s Yugoslavia,” 385–87.</note></p>
            <p><hi style="font-size:12pt">Some days later, on 21</hi><hi rend="superscript" style="font-size:12pt">st</hi><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve"> April 1956, Phillips wrote to Tito that the Labourites had felt relieved in learning about Djilas’ suspended sentence, but that the subsequent conduct of the Yugoslav authorities towards Djilas brought them to realise that their relief had been misplaced. He proceeded to list the discriminatory measures used by the Yugoslav authorities against Djilas and ended the letter saying: “I must confess that I am appalled that the country which in 1950 I supported in articles and public speaking, and in private documents to the then Foreign Secretary of our own government – Ernest Bevin – should have slipped back into the evil ways of the Cominform countries. I do not know whether this is related to what appears to be a shift in the foreign policy of your country – that, however, is not my business. I am only concerned with the human aspect of administration, and I still hope that you can in your relation with individuals demonstrate to the world the fundamental superiority of a socialist system of society.”</hi>
                <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn49" n="48"> Ibid.,
                    388.</note></p>
            <p><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve">	Phillips did not hide his disappointment over the Yugoslav political shift towards the Soviet Union and his writing also revealed that he had a thorough knowledge of Djilas’ situation. Despite the letter being private and secret, it must have quite angered Tito. Contrary to Tito’s confidential and conciliatory reply to Bevan in February 1954, the Yugoslav authorities responded publicly this time – with an article officially authored by the new head of the Commission for International Relations, Veljko Vlahović, published in </hi>
                <hi rend="italic" style="font-size:12pt">Borba</hi>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">on 20</hi><hi rend="superscript" style="font-size:12pt">th</hi><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve"> May 1956. While Phillips’ letter focussed on the mistreatment that Djilas was subjected to by the Yugoslav authorities, the Yugoslav reply contained hardly any mention of him. The object of the article was to discredit Phillips as an irresponsible, uninformed and malicious person with a rather poor understanding of Yugoslav socialism and international politics. Apparently, the Yugoslav leadership was most annoyed by Phillips linking the actions of their authorities against Djilas with their shift towards the Soviet Union. In the reply they also rebuked the British for their imperialism, recommending to the Labourites that they concentrate on the conduct of the British government in Cyprus and Kenya instead of interfering with Yugoslav internal affairs.</hi>
                <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn50" n="49"> Ibid.,
                    376.</note></p>
            <p><hi style="font-size:12pt">The British Conservative government was anything but
                    pleased with Phillips’ protest letter to Tito. It had followed the Djilas’ case
                    primarily from the perspective of international relations and only started
                    paying more attention to the Yugoslav dissident after his imprisonment at the
                    end of 1956.</hi>
                <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn51" n="50"> Ibid.,
                    382.</note>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">Speculations surfaced in the foreign press that Djilas’
                    arrest might have been an attempt by the Yugoslav authorities to appease the
                    Soviet Union. The truth is, their reckoning with Djilas had far more to do with
                    internal than foreign affairs. Aware of the dissatisfaction of the population
                    with living conditions, the Yugoslav leaders were afraid of the repetition of
                    Hungarian events in Yugoslavia</hi>
                <hi rend="italic" style="font-size:12pt">,</hi>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">so they decided to get Djilas out of their way before he
                    turned into a Yugoslav Imre Nagy. By declaring in his article in</hi>
                <hi rend="italic" style="font-size:12pt">The New Leader</hi>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">that the Yugoslav “national Communism” was incapable of
                    carrying out reforms, and with his interview for the French press agency, in
                    which he condemned the Yugoslav reserved policy towards the Hungarian Uprising,
                    Djilas unintentionally made that easier for them.</hi></p>
            <p>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">After the sharp Yugoslav response to Phillips’s
                    intervention, Hugh Gaitskell, the new leader of the Labour Party and a prominent
                    right-winger, postponed his visit to Yugoslavia in mid-1956,</hi>
                <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn52" n="51"> Unkovski-Korica,
                        “The Yugoslav Communists’ Special Relationship with the British Labour
                        Party,” 41.</note>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">though, due to complex international developments that
                    year, he changed his mind and stressed the need to repair relations with
                    Yugoslavia. Although the latter remained an authoritarian, single-party state,
                    it still represented a potentially important factor in the destabilisation of
                    the Eastern Bloc, especially when the Yugoslav leaders faced renewed criticism
                    from the Soviet Union after the Hungarian Uprising. The Yugoslavs, on the other
                    hand, found convenient the Labourites’ opposition to the Anglo-French-Israeli
                    military action against Egypt after Nasser’s nationalisation of the Suez
                    Canal.</hi>
                <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn53" n="52"> Ibid.,
                    43.</note>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">Pragmatic common interests in foreign policy ensured the
                    continuing friendship between the Labour Party and the Yugoslav Communists, and
                    the reconciliation persisted despite some fundamental ideological disagreements
                    between the two parties.</hi>
            </p>
            <p><hi style="font-size:12pt">As an illustration of the depth of these divergences, let
                    us examine more thoroughly the talks held during the visit of a delegation of
                    the British Labour Party to Yugoslavia in 1960. Towards the end of August of
                    that year, the highest representatives of the Labour Party, Hugh Gaitskell, Sam
                    Watson, foreign policy adviser to the Labour Party Denis Healey, and secretary
                    to its international department David Ennals, met in Ljubljana and Bled with
                    Yugoslav leaders Edvard Kardelj, Vladimir Bakarić, Milentije Popović, Mika
                    Špiljak, Miha Marinko, and Vida Tomšič, who again appeared on behalf of the
                    Socialist Alliance. For the greater part the talks were focused on foreign
                    policy, particularly on the issues of the arms race, Soviet policy, the
                    Sino-Soviet conflict, the German question, and other current international
                    policy issues of the time. Subsequently, the focus shifted to the Yugoslav
                    internal situation, prompting the Labourites to raise some provocative questions
                    with their hosts, aimed at understanding the actual nature of the relationship
                    between the Socialist Alliance and the Communist Party, as well as that between
                    the Federal Assembly and Government, the functioning of workers’
                    self-management, the system of economic planning, the responsibilities of the
                    local authorities, the limitations on the freedom of speech, etc. During the
                    conversation, Gaitskell repeatedly expressed his disagreement with the absence
                    of political opposition in Yugoslavia and disapproval of the Yugoslav voting
                    system, and considered the announced expansion of the decentralisation of power
                    as well as of the competence of workers’ councils and self-management in
                    communes nonviable, impractical and, in the event of their hypothetical
                    translation into practice, as leading to localism and anarchy.</hi>
                <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn54" n="53"> AJ 507, IX,
                        133/II-247, Komisija za međunarodne odnose i veze CK SKJ, Stenografski
                        zapisnik razgovora izmedju jugoslovenskih funkcionera SZDLJ i delegacije
                        britanskih laburista u Ljubljani i na Bledu, 22.–23. 8. 1960, Zabeleška o
                        razgovorima izmedju pretstavnika SSRNJ i Laburističke partije Velike
                        Britanije, 22.–23. 8. 1960.</note></p>
            <p><hi style="font-size:12pt">At the end of the discussion, Gaitskell opened the Djilas’
                    case. Kardelj argued that Djilas was an ambitious and power-hungry man whose
                    actions practically forced the authorities to imprison him. Gaitskell kept
                    pushing, stating that it was the Djilas’ case that caused the deterioration of
                    the relations between the Labour Party and Yugoslavia and saying he wanted to
                    overcome that, but needed clear answers to do so. He also asked Kardelj what
                    would have happened in Yugoslavia if Djilas had not been imprisoned. Kardelj’s
                    reply was that it would have aggravated the internal political situation and
                    could have led to “an intervention from outside, /…/ because the door to a
                    discussion about the most various controversial political issues would have been
                    opened”,</hi>
                <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn55" n="54"> AJ 507, IX,
                        133/II-247, Komisija za međunarodne odnose i veze CK SKJ, Stenografski
                        zapisnik razgovora izmedju jugoslovenskih funkcionera SZDLJ i delegacije
                        britanskih laburista u Ljubljani i na Bledu, 22.–23. 8. 1960,
                    119.</note><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve"> adding that time had proved them right, not Djilas. The Labourites insisted that the Djilas’ case was a matter of principle in relation to which the right and left wings of the Labour Party held the same position – that it was unacceptable to imprison a person because of his conviction or because he publicly expressed an opinion that was opposed to the views of the ruling party. Despite political and ideological divergences, the debate ended in friendly and conciliatory tones, and with a conclusion that although the perspectives of the two sides differed in many ways, there still existed a common interest that warranted further cooperation between the parties, particularly in the field of foreign policy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve">The Djilas Affair somewhat cooled the once warm relationship between the British Labour Party and Yugoslav Communists, but the Labourites would not take the risk of having their relations with Yugoslavia deteriorate for Djilas’ sake. With regard to his case, there were no major differences in the positions of the left and right wings of the Labour Party: Aneurin Bevan and Jennie Lee, Djilas’ staunchest supporters, were in the left faction, and Morgan Phillips was not. Certain more prominent left-wing members even openly criticised Djilas and his work; for example, Barbara Castle and Richard Crossman, who had a very negative opinion of </hi>
                <hi rend="italic" style="font-size:12pt">The New Class</hi><hi style="font-size:12pt">.</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn56" n="55"> Djokić, “Britain and Dissent in Tito’s Yugoslavia,”
                        383. </note>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">But regardless of the different personal views of Djilas,
                    restricting the freedom of expression and incarcerating dissenters was
                    unacceptable to all. Yet the leadership of the Labour Party never went further
                    than standing by the private protests such as those of Bevan in 1954 and
                    Phillips in 1956.</hi>
            </p></div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="bibliography">
                <head>Sources and Literature</head>
            <list type="unordered">
                <head>Archival Sources:</head>
                <item><hi style="font-size:10pt">Archives of Yugoslavia:</hi>
                    <list type="unordered">
                        <item><hi style="font-size:10pt">AJ 507, IX, 133/II, Komisija za međunarodne
                            odnose i veze CK SKJ, Velika Britanija.</hi></item>
                    </list></item>
            </list>
            <listBibl>
                <head>Literature:</head>
                <bibl><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">Arnitović, Dobrilo. </hi><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Milovan Đilas: bibliografija sa
                    hronologijom života i
                    rada</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">. Beograd: Službeni glasnik, 2008. </hi></bibl>
                <bibl><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">Bekić, Darko. </hi><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Jugoslavija u hladnom ratu: odnosi sa
                    velikim silama 1949–1955</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt">. Zagreb: Globus,
                        1988.</hi></bibl>
                <bibl><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">Bevan, Aneurin. </hi><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Umesto straha</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt">. Beograd: Biblioteka Trideset dana,
                        1952.</hi></bibl>
                <bibl><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">Clissold, Stephen. </hi><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Djilas: The Progress of a
                    Revolutionary</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt">. Hounslow, Middlesex: Maurice
                        Temple Smith, 1983.</hi></bibl>
                <bibl><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">Dedijer, Vladimir. </hi><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Veliki buntovnik Milovan Đilas: prilozi
                    za biografiju</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt">. Beograd: Prosveta,
                        1991.</hi></bibl>
                <bibl><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">Djokić, Dejan. “Britain and Dissent in Tito’s Yugoslavia: The Djilas Affair, ca. 1956.” </hi><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">European History Quaterly </hi><hi style="font-size:10pt">36, No. 3 (2006): 371–95.</hi></bibl>
                <bibl><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">Đilas, Milovan. “Zveza ali partija,” </hi><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Ljudska pravica–Borba</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt">, 4. 1. 1954.</hi></bibl>
                <bibl><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">Đilas, Milovan. </hi><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Druženje s Titom</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt">. Beograd: Zaslon, 1990.</hi></bibl>
                <bibl><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">Đilas, Milovan. </hi><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Nesavršeno društvo: (i dalje od Nove
                    klase)</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt">. Beograd: Narodna knjiga,
                        1990.</hi></bibl>
                <bibl><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">Đilas, Milovan. </hi><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Pad nove klase: povest o samorazaranju
                    komunizma</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt">. Beograd: Službeni list SRJ,
                        1994.</hi></bibl>
                <bibl><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">Đilas, Milovan. </hi><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Vlast i pobuna: memoari</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt">. Zagreb: Novi Liber, 2009.</hi>
                </bibl>
                <bibl><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">Đorgović, Momčilo. </hi><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Đilas: vernik i jeretik</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt">. Beograd: Akvarijus, 1989.</hi></bibl>
                <bibl><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">Edemskii, Andrej. “The Role of Milovan Djilas in Soviet-Yugoslav Relations 1944–1954.” In: </hi><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">The Balkans in the Cold War: Balkan
                    Federations, Cominform, Yugoslav-Soviet Conflict</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt">, edited by Vojislav G. Pavlović, 185–219. Belgrade:
                        Institute for Balkan Studies, 2011.</hi></bibl>
                <bibl><hi style="font-size:10pt">Foot,
                    Michael.</hi><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve"> Aneurin Bevan: A Biography, Vol. 2: 1945–1960. </hi><hi style="font-size:10pt">London: Davis-Poynter, 1973.</hi></bibl>
                <bibl><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">Goldstein, Slavko. “Predgovor: Povratak Milovana Đilasa u Hrvatsku.” In: Đilas, Milovan. </hi><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Vlast i pobuna:
                    memoari</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">. Zagreb: Novi Liber, 2009. </hi>
                </bibl>
                <bibl><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">Ivešić, Tomaž. “Padec Milovana Đilasa.” In: Milovan Đilas, </hi><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Anatomija neke morale in 19 znamenitih
                    člankov (oktober 1953 – januar
                    1954)</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">, edited by Tomaž Ivešić, 131–85. Ljubljana: Inštitut Nove revije, 2015. </hi></bibl>
                <bibl><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">Kalezić, Vasilije. </hi><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Đilas, miljenik i otpadnik
                    komunizma</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">. Beograd: Zodne, 1988. </hi></bibl>
                <bibl><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">Laković, Ivan. </hi><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Zapadna vojna pomoć Jugoslaviji
                    1951–1958</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt">. Podgorica: Istorijski institut
                        Crne Gore, 2006.</hi></bibl>
                <bibl><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">Miletić, Aleksandar V. “Prijem delegacije britanskih laburista kod maršala Tita u okviru njihove prve posete Jugoslaviji, 1950. godine.” </hi><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Tokovi
                    istorije</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve"> 1 (2011): 137–64.</hi></bibl>
                <bibl><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">Miletić, Aleksandar V. “Unrealised Nordic Dream: Milovan Đilas and the Scandinavian Socialists.” </hi><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Tokovi
                    istorije</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve"> 3 (2015): 89–106.</hi></bibl>
                <bibl><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">Muravchik, Joshua. “The Intellectual Odyssey of Milovan Djilas.” </hi><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">World
                    Affairs</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve"> 145, No. 4 (1983): 323–46.</hi></bibl>
                <bibl><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">Nikolić, Kosta and Srđan Cvetković. </hi><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Rađanje jeretika: suđenje Milovanu
                    Đilasu i Vladimiru Dedijeru
                    1955</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">. Beograd: Institut za savremenu istoriju, 2011. </hi></bibl>
                <bibl><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">Petranović, Branko, Ranko Končar, and Radovan Radonjić, eds. </hi><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Sednice Centralnog komiteta KPJ:
                    1948–1952</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">. Beograd: Komunist, 1985. </hi></bibl>
                <bibl><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">Pirjevec, Jože. </hi><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Tito in tovariši</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt">. Ljubljana: Cankarjeva založba, 2011.</hi></bibl>
                <bibl><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">Režek, Mateja. “Defeat of the First Party Liberalism and the Echo of ‘Djilasism’ in Slovenia.” </hi><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Slovene
                    Studies</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve"> 28, No. 1–2 (2006): 67–78. </hi></bibl>
                <bibl><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">Režek, Mateja. “Vroča jesen 1956: sueška kriza, madžarska vstaja in vloga Jugoslavije.” </hi><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Annales, Series historia et
                    sociologia</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve"> 24, No. 4 (2014): 601–14. </hi></bibl>
                <bibl><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">Režek, Mateja. </hi><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">Med resničnostjo in iluzijo: slovenska in jugoslovanska politika v desetletju po sporu z Informbirojem (1948–1958). </hi><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">Ljubljana: Modrijan, 2005. </hi></bibl>
                <bibl><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">Rusinow, Dennison. </hi><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">The Yugoslav Experiment
                    1948–1974</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">. Berkeley and Los Angeles: University of California Press, 1977. </hi></bibl>
                <bibl><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">Spehnjak, Katarina. “Velika Britanija i ‘slučaj Đilas’ 1954.” In: </hi><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Spoljna politika Jugoslavije 1950–1961:
                    zbornik radova</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt">, edited by Slobodan Selinić,
                        350–62. Beograd: Institut za noviju istoriju Srbije, 2008.</hi></bibl>
                <bibl><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">Stanić, Veljko. “Unutrašnji emigrant: političke ideje Milovana Đilasa 1954–1989.” </hi><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">Poznańskie Studia Slawistyczne </hi><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">6 (2014): 213–29. </hi></bibl>
                <bibl><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">Štrbac, Čedomir. “Britanski laburisti u Jugoslaviji 1950.” In: </hi><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Jugoslovensko-britanski odnosi</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt">, edited by Petar Kačavenda, 331–41. Beograd:
                        Institut za savremenu istoriju, 1988.</hi></bibl>
                <bibl><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">Tošić, Desimir. </hi><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Ko je Milovan Đilas?: disidentstvo
                    1953–1995</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt">. Beograd: Otkrovenje,
                        2003.</hi></bibl>
                <bibl><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">Unkovski-Korica, Vladimir. “The Yugoslav Communists’ Special Relationship with the British Labour Party 1950–1956.” </hi><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">Cold War History </hi><hi style="font-size:10pt">14, No. 1 (2014): 23–46.</hi></bibl>
            </listBibl></div>
            <div type="summary">
                <docAuthor>Mateja Režek</docAuthor>
            <head>MILOVAN DJILAS AND THE BRITISH LABOUR PARTY, 1950–1960</head>
            <head>SUMMARY</head>
            <p><hi style="font-size:10pt">After the conflict with the Cominform in 1948, Yugoslav
                leaders began to search for alternative international connections in the West.
                In this context, they tried to restore their own credibility in the eyes of the
                Western socialist and social democratic parties, whereby the most powerful
                Western European social democratic party, the British Labour Party, proved to be
                the most suitable partner both in the fields of foreign policy and ideology.
                Official contacts between the Labour Party and the Yugoslav Communists in the
                disguise of the Popular Front, later the Socialist Alliance of the Working
                People, were established in 1950, which was followed by a brief, but vivacious
                period of exchange of ideas and views on the development of socialism in the
                early 1950s. Discussions between Yugoslav leaders and the British Labourites
                showed a considerable deviation of Yugoslav politics from the crude dogmatism of
                the early post-war years, but that should not be regarded only as a pragmatic
                attempt of the Yugoslav leaders to gain sympathies of the Western Left,
                certainly not in the case of Milovan Djilas. As President of the Commission for
                International Relations of the Central Committee of the Communist Party of
                Yugoslavia, Djilas played a key role in the dialogue with the British
                Labourites, and through personal meetings and correspondence, he and the leader
                of the left-wing of the Labour Party, Aneurin Bevan, formed a personal
                friendship.</hi>
            </p>
            <p><hi style="font-size:10pt">In the first half of the 1950s, Djilas’ illusions about
                the communist ideology and the Yugoslav socialism were gradually dispelled, and
                he became increasingly enthusiastic about democratic socialism. When, after
                Stalin’s death in 1953, the top leadership of the Yugoslav Party experienced the
                prevailing influence of those who advocated hard-line policies and saw political
                liberalisation as the beginning of the end of the Communist Party rule, Djilas
                was not ready to accept the return to the old path. In a series of articles
                published in the autumn and winter of 1953/54, he denied the Communist Party no
                less than the right to a political monopoly, and what is more, he criticised the
                moral values of the political elite. Due to his views, he was excluded from the
                Central Committee in January 1954 and stripped of all political functions, and
                later he spent nine years in prison because of his dissident posture and the
                publication of books abroad.</hi></p>
            <p><hi style="font-size:10pt">After Djilas’ political downfall, once warm relations
                between the British Labourites and the Yugoslav Communists grew considerably
                cold, but the leadership of the Labour Party did not want to risk the
                deterioration of relations with Yugoslavia, and therefore responded with great
                care when it came to the behaviour of the Yugoslav authorities towards Djilas.
                Nevertheless, Aneurin Bevan, his wife Jennie Lee, and Secretary General of the
                Labour Party Morgan Phillips, who was at the same time President of the
                Socialist International, were more determined, although none of them went
                further than trying to act through personal correspondence with Tito. Although
                Yugoslavia remained an authoritarian state under the leadership of the Communist
                Party, in the eyes of the West it continued to represent a significant factor in
                the destabilisation of the Eastern Bloc, and the friendly relationship between
                the Labour Party and the Yugoslav Communists were primarily based on foreign
                policy interests of the two parties. In the second half of the 1950s, a
                pragmatic geopolitical considaration completely overshadowed ideological
                affinity; the interest of the British Labourites in the Yugoslav self-management
                experiment decreased significantly, as did the Yugoslav interest in democratic
                socialism, the idea that Djilas was so passionate about.</hi>
            </p></div>
<div type="summary" xml:lang="sl">
    <docAuthor>Mateja
                Režek</docAuthor>
            <head>MILOVAN ĐILAS IN
                BRITANSKA LABURISTIČNA STRANKA, 1950–1960</head>
            <head>POVZETEK</head>
            <p><hi style="font-size:10pt">Po sporu z Informbirojem leta 1948 so jugoslovanski
                voditelji začeli iskati alternativne mednarodnopolitične povezave na Zahodu. V
                tem kontekstu so si skušali povrniti tudi verodostojnost v očeh zahodnih
                socialističnih in socialdemokratskih strank, pri čemer se je tako s političnega
                kot ideološkega vidika kot najprimernejši partner pokazala najmočnejša
                zahodnoevropska socialdemokratska stranka – britanska Laburistična stranka, ki
                je bila takrat tudi vladna stranka v Veliki Britaniji. Uradni stiki med
                Laburistično stranko in jugoslovanskimi komunisti v preobleki Ljudske fronte,
                kasneje Socialistične zveze delovnega ljudstva, so bili vzpostavljeni leta 1950,
                čemur je v začetku petdesetih let sledilo kratko, a živahno obdobje izmenjave
                idej in pogledov na razvoj socializma. Razprave jugoslovanskih voditeljev z
                britanskimi laburisti so kazale na precejšen odmik jugoslovanske politike od
                surovega dogmatizma prvih povojnih let, česar ne moremo pripisati zgolj
                pragmatičnim prizadevanjem jugoslovanskih voditeljev, da bi si pridobili
                simpatije zahodne levice, zagotovo ne v primeru Milovana Đilasa. Ta je kot
                predsednik Komisije za mednarodne odnose CK ZKJ odigral ključno vlogo v dialogu
                z britanskimi laburisti, skozi medsebojna srečanja in dopisovanja pa se je med
                njim in voditeljem levega krila Laburistične stranke Aneurinom Bevanom stkalo
                tudi osebno prijateljstvo.</hi></p>
            <p><hi style="font-size:10pt">Đilas je v prvi polovici petdesetih let postopoma
                izgubljal iluzije glede komunistične ideologije in jugoslovanske različice
                socializma ter se čedalje bolj spogledoval z demokratičnim socializmom. Ko so po
                Stalinovi smrti leta 1953 v jugoslovanskem partijskem vrhu znova prevladala
                stališča zagovornikov politike trde roke, ki so v politični liberalizaciji
                videli začetek konca partijske oblasti, Đilas ni bil pripravljen sprejeti
                vrnitve na stare tirnice. V seriji člankov, ki jih je objavil jeseni in pozimi
                1953/54, je komunistični partiji odrekel nič manj kot pravico do političnega
                monopola, za nameček pa se je obregnil še ob moralne vrednote partijske elite.
                Zaradi svojih stališč je bil januarja 1954 izključen iz CK ZKJ in razrešen vseh
                političnih funkcij, zaradi svoje disidentske drže in objave knjig v tujini pa je
                kasneje preživel devet let v zaporu.</hi>
            </p>
            <p><hi style="font-size:10pt">Po Đilasovem političnem padcu so se nekoč topli odnosi med
                britanskimi laburisti in jugoslovanskimi komunisti občutno ohladili, toda
                vodstvo Laburistične stranke ni želelo tvegati poslabšanja odnosov z
                Jugoslavijo, zato se je na ravnanje jugoslovanskih oblasti z Đilasom odzivalo
                zelo previdno. Bolj odločni so bili Aneurin Bevan in njegova žena Jennie Lee ter
                generalni sekretar Laburistične stranke Morgan Phillips, hkrati predsednik
                Socialistične internacionale, vendar nihče od njih ni šel dlje od osebne
                korespondence s Titom. Čeprav je Jugoslavija ostajala avtoritarna država pod
                vodstvom komunistične partije, je v očeh Zahoda še vedno predstavljala pomemben
                dejavnik destabilizacije vzhodnega bloka, prijateljski odnosi med Laburistično
                stranko in jugoslovanskimi komunisti pa so temeljili predvsem na
                zunanjepolitičnih interesih obeh strani. V drugi polovici petdesetih let je
                pragmatični geopolitični premislek povsem prevladal nad ideološko afiniteto.
                Zanimanje britanskih laburistov za jugoslovanski samoupravni eksperiment je
                občutno upadlo, zamrl pa je tudi jugoslovanski interes za demokratični
                socializem, nad katerim se je tako navduševal Đilas.</hi></p></div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>