<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>"However, the language here is changing gradually, and in the presence of so
                    many local dialects the Croatian and its kindred Slovenian world cannot be
                    separated very precisely" – Drawing the Slovenian-Croatian National Border in
                    the Territory of the Present-day Prekmurje Region<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn1" n="*"> The article is a result of the research project,
                        co-financed by the Slovenian Research Agency in the framework of "Slovene
                        History" (P6-0235) research core funding, and the project "History of
                        Administrative Borders and Boundaries: Slovenian-Croatian Border 1800 – 1991
                        (J6-4132; the article was finished in May 2016 and was translated from
                        Slovene by Borut Praper). I would hereby like to thank Rok Stergar and Marko
                        Zajc for their invaluable advice and assistance. </note></title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename>Jernej</forename>
                        <surname>Kosi</surname>
                    </name>
                    <roleName>Researcher</roleName>
                    <roleName>PhD</roleName>
                    <affiliation>Department of History, Faculty of Arts, University of
                        Ljubljana</affiliation>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Aškerčeva cesta 2</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>SI-1000 Ljubljana</addrLine>
                    </address>
                    <email>jernej.kosi@ff.uni-lj.si</email>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>2017-09-20</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>
                    <orgName xml:lang="sl">Inštitut za novejšo zgodovino</orgName>
                    <orgName xml:lang="en">Institute of Contemporary History</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Kongresni trg 1</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>SI-1000 Ljubljana</addrLine>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>http://ojs.inz.si/pnz/article/view/244</pubPlace>
                <date>2016</date>
                <availability status="free">
                    <licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title xml:lang="sl">Prispevki za novejšo zgodovino</title>
                <title xml:lang="en">Contributions to Contemporary History</title>
                <biblScope unit="volume">57</biblScope>
                <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
                <idno type="ISSN">2463-7807</idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source, born digital.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc xml:lang="en">
                <p>Contributions to Contemporary History is one of the central Slovenian scientific
                    historiographic journals, dedicated to publishing articles from the field of
                    contemporary history (the 19th and 20th century).</p>
                <p>The journal is published three times per year in Slovenian and in the following
                    foreign languages: English, German, Serbian, Croatian, Bosnian, Italian, Slovak
                    and Czech. The articles are all published with abstracts in English and
                    Slovenian as well as summaries in English.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <projectDesc xml:lang="sl">
                <p>Prispevki za novejšo zgodovino je ena osrednjih slovenskih znanstvenih
                    zgodovinopisnih revij, ki objavlja teme s področja novejše zgodovine (19. in 20.
                    stoletje).</p>
                <p>Revija izide trikrat letno v slovenskem jeziku in v naslednjih tujih jezikih:
                    angleščina, nemščina, srbščina, hrvaščina, bosanščina, italijanščina, slovaščina
                    in češčina. Članki izhajajo z izvlečki v angleščini in slovenščini ter povzetki
                    v angleščini.</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="sl"/>
                <language ident="en"/>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords xml:lang="en">
                    <term>national border</term>
                    <term>Slovenian national territory</term>
                    <term>Prekmurje</term>
                    <term>Slovenian national movement</term>
                    <term>Croats and Slovenians</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords xml:lang="sl">
                    <term>nacionalna meja</term>
                    <term>slovensko nacionalno ozemlje</term>
                    <term>Prekmurje</term>
                    <term>slovensko nacionalno gibanje</term>
                    <term>Hrvati in Slovenci</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change>
                    <date>2017-10-05</date>
                    <name>Neja Blaj Hribar</name>
                    <desc>Pretvorba iz DOCX v TEI, dodatno kodiranje</desc>
                </change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <docAuthor> Jernej Kosi<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn2" n="**">
                    <hi rend="bold">Researcher, PhD, Department of History, Faculty of Arts,
                        University of Ljubljana, Aškerčeva cesta 2, SI-1000 Ljubljana,</hi>
                    <ref target="jernej.kosi@ff.uni-lj.si"><hi rend="bold"
                            >jernej.kosi@ff.uni-lj.si</hi></ref></note>
            </docAuthor>
            <docImprint>
                <idno type="cobissType">Cobiss type: 1.01</idno>
                <idno type="UDC">UDC: </idno>
            </docImprint>
            <div type="abstract" xml:lang="sl">
                <head>IZVLEČEK</head>
                <head>"KER SE PA JEZIK TU PO MALEM SPREMENUJE, IN JE TOLIKO KRAJNIH NAREČIJ, SE
                    HERVAŠKI IN SORODNI SLOVENSKI SVET NE MORETA PRAV NA TANJKO S POTEZO LOČITI" –
                    ZAČRTOVANJE SLOVENSKO-HRVAŠKE NACIONALNE MEJE NA PODROČJU DANAŠNJEGA
                    PREKMURJA</head>
                <p><hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">V članku obravnavam proces nastajanja zamisli o meji med </hi>"<hi
                        rend="italic"
                        >slovenskim</hi>"<hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve"> in </hi>"<hi
                        rend="italic">hrvaškim</hi>" <hi rend="italic">nacionalnim ozemljem na
                        področju zahodne Ogrske. Zamisel je bila sprva artikulirana kot jezikovna
                        premisa v delih slavnega jezikoslovca Jerneja Kopitarja, ki je ozemlje
                        današnjega Prekmurja razumel kot prostor, kjer se govori slovenski jezik. Od
                        srede 19. stoletja naprej je Kopitarjevo klasifikacijo apropriiralo
                        slovensko nacionalno gibanje, ki je predpostavljalo, da so govorci
                        slovenskega jezika na Ogrskem tudi pripadniki zamišljene slovenske
                        skupnosti. V tem kontekstu je bila slovenska jezikovna – nacionalna meja
                        sredi 19. stoletja prvič upodobljena na zemljevidu (Peter Kozler). V vsega
                        nekaj desetletjih se je predstava o nacionalni ločnici v današnjem
                        Prekmurju, ki da v odnosu do Hrvatov poteka po reki Muri, dodobra utrdila
                        med slovenskimi nacionalnimi aktivisti na področju cislajtanskih dežel. Ob
                        razpadu Avstro-Ogrske in po podpisu trianonske mirovne pogodbe pa je tudi
                        dejansko začela razmejevati slovenski nacionalni prostor od sosednjega
                        hrvaškega.</hi></p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Ključne besede: nacionalna meja, slovensko nacionalno ozemlje,
                        Prekmurje, slovensko nacionalno gibanje, Hrvati in Slovenci</hi></p>
            </div>
            <div type="abstract">
                <head>ABSTRACT</head>
                <p><hi rend="italic">The article analyses the process involved in the formation of
                        the idea to separate the "Slovenian" and "Croatian" national territory in
                        the west of the Kingdom of Hungary. The concept was initially articulated as
                        a linguistic premise in the works written by the famous linguist Jernej
                        Kopitar, who understood the territory of the today's Prekmurje region as an
                        area where Slovenian language was spoken. As of the middle of the 19th
                        century, Kopitar's classification had been appropriated by the Slovenian
                        national movement, which presupposed that the speakers of the Slovenian
                        language in the Kingdom of Hungary were also members of the envisioned
                        Slovenian community. In this context the Slovenian linguistic – national
                        border was, in the middle of the 19th century, depicted on a map for the
                        first time (Peter Kozler). In just a few decades, the idea of the national
                        demarcation line in the today's Prekmurje, supposedly separating Slovenians
                        from Croats at the river Mura, had strengthened considerably among the
                        Slovenian national activists in the Cisleithanian lands. After the
                        dissolution of Austro-Hungary and the signing of the Treaty of Trianion,
                        this line in fact became a border between the Slovenian and the neighbouring
                        Croatian national space.</hi></p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Keywords: national border, Slovenian national territory,
                        Prekmurje, Slovenian national movement, Croats and Slovenians</hi></p>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <p>The territorial pretensions of the individual national movements and later political
                elites in the newly-established national states have been – approximately since
                1830, but especially as of 1848 – the most frequent reason for the changes and
                rearrangements of the European national and internal administrative borders.
                Numerous European national movements that managed to assert their social and
                political power notably after the middle of the 19th century proclaimed their
                demands for the adaptation of the political and administrative borders to the
                national boundaries as their primary long-term programme goal. The social, cultural,
                and especially political strategies of the European national movements within the
                "non-national" state entities or the state policies of the nationalist elites in the
                newly-established states were therefore, in the 19th and 20th century, largely
                focused precisely on the attainment of this primary programme goal.<note
                    place="foot" xml:id="ftn3" n="1"> For a comparative historical outline of the
                    European national movements and nationalism in the 19th century see Oliver
                    Zimmer, <hi rend="italic">Nationalism in Europe, 1890-1940</hi> (London:
                    Palgrave, 2003). The following work focuses on the national(ist) cultural
                    practices and symbolic representations: Joep Leersen, <hi rend="italic">National
                        Thought in Europe: A Cultural History</hi> (Amsterdam: AUP, 2006). In this
                    article the term nationalism and all the derived words are used in accordance
                    with Gellner's definition of the expression. Therefore, nationalism is
                    understood especially as "a political principle, which holds that the political
                    and the national unit should be congruent". – Ernest Gellner, <hi rend="italic"
                        >Nations and Nationalism</hi> (Oxford: Blackwell, 1983), 1.</note> This was
                also more or less characteristic for the Slovenian national movement, as the demand
                that "all Slovenians as well as their closest brothers should unite in a single
                nation, in order to create a united, single Slovenian Assembly" was clearly
                expressed already in 1848, in the first Slovenian national political programme.<note
                    place="foot" xml:id="ftn4" n="2"> In the text of the flier <hi rend="italic"
                        >What do Slovenians Want? (Kaj Slovenci terjamo?)</hi>, published by Matija
                    Majar (1809–1892) in the second half of March 1848, after he had received news
                    of the beginning of the revolution in Vienna.– The text of the flier is quoted
                    in Janko Prunk, <hi rend="italic">Slovenski narodni programi: narodni programi v
                        slovenski politični misli od 1848 do 1945</hi> (Ljubljana: Društvo 2000,
                    1986), 152–59. For the reproduction of the flier see Andreas Moritsch and
                    Vincenc Rajšp, eds., <hi rend="italic">Matija Majar-Ziljski</hi> (Klagenfurt:
                    Hermagoras, 1995), 105, 106.</note>
            </p>
            <p>It is absolutely certain that the social and political achievements of the European
                national movements and individual nationalist elites in the 19th and 20th century
                were by no means negligible. The specific unification, separatist, irredentist, or
                centralist national political programmes in fact contributed importantly to the
                dissolution of the existing empires and unification of what had previously been
                separated political-territorial units in the newly-formed national states.
                Furthermore, the new national(ist) elites in the newly-created national states were,
                in this period, quite successful in their efforts to abolish the "intra-state"
                social and regional differences as soon as possible, and effectively ensure that the
                class oppositions could be overcome. In this context the national movements
                attempted to fulfil their desire to gradually replace these sorts of differences and
                oppositions with the cultural unification of what had been very heterogeneous
                populations under the wing of national cultures. The circumstances were often such
                that the new national institutional frameworks had been created first, while the
                population was in fact nationalised subsequently (which, in turn, meant that modern
                national identity categories were adopted by the wider strata of the
                    population).<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn5" n="3"> For a comparative
                    description of these sort of efforts and activities in the name of the nation
                    and for the nation see Miroslav Hroch, <hi rend="italic">Das Europa der
                        Nationen: Die moderne Nationsbildung im europäischen Vergleich</hi>
                    (Göttingen: Vandenhoeck &amp; Ruprecht, 2005), 109–234. Comparatively on the
                    formation of the European mass nations: Hagen Schulze, <hi rend="italic">States,
                        Nations, and Nationalism: From the Middle Ages to the Present</hi> (Oxford:
                    Blackwell Publishing, 1996). On nationalist policies and national culture:
                    Leersen, <hi rend="italic">National Thought</hi>, 105–219. On the
                    nationalisation of the masses and nationalism as a mass phenomenon: Zimmer, <hi
                        rend="italic">Nationalism</hi>, 27–49. On state institutions as a means of
                    promoting the nationally-defined identity categories: Rogers Brubaker, <hi
                        rend="italic">Nationalism Reframed: Nationhood and the National Question in
                        the New Europe</hi> (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1996). A classic
                    study of the state's role in the "top to bottom" construction of a nation: Eugen
                    Weber, <hi rend="italic">Peasants Into Frenchmen</hi> (Stanford: Stanford
                    University Press, 1976).</note>
            </p>
            <p>The history of the creation and formation of the European national states in the
                    19<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> and 20<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> centuries
                confirms that numerous European national movements were quite successful in the
                realisation of their political programmes. In this regard we should obviously not
                overlook that precisely these attempts to implement the individual nationalist
                policies can be deemed as largely responsible for the unprecedented horrors that the
                European peoples have experienced in the past two hundred years. In the first half
                of the 20<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> century it turned out that the nationalist
                state policies and their intentional encouragement of the unexpected expansion of
                xenophobia and hatred between the nations contributed very significantly to the
                outbreak of two unprecedented military conflicts. In the nationalist imagery, such
                sacrifices as well as casualties of military conflicts, which the European national
                states had been involved in in the earlier as well as subsequent periods, were most
                often seen as expected and sensible. As such they were also worth remembering, at
                least judging from the frequency of commemorative gatherings and incidence of
                memorials that the national elites in the 19<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> and 20<hi
                    rend="superscript">th</hi> century dedicated to the preservation of the memory
                of their respective nations' heroic acts throughout the European continent. Within
                the national context of remembrance, sacrificing oneself for one's nation and in its
                name has been understood as a contribution to the realisation of the thousand-year
                national aspirations and endeavours, and at the same time also as a contribution to
                overcoming the at least equally ancient national traumas.<note place="foot"
                    xml:id="ftn6" n="4"> On commemorative practices: Zimmer, <hi rend="italic"
                        >Nationalism</hi>, 28–49; and literature listed therein. A classic work
                    about this topic: George L. Mosse, <hi rend="italic">Fallen Soldiers: Reshaping
                        the Memory of the World Wars</hi> (New York: Oxford University Press,
                    1990).</note>
            </p>
            <p>In the 19<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> and 20<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> century,
                national traumas and aspirations would very frequently focus on the issue of
                constituting national territories. Consequently, it is not surprising that so much
                attention in the context of commemorative practices and national imagery is
                dedicated to the idea that the military and civilian lives should be sacrificed on
                the altar of their respective homelands, precisely in the name of fighting for the
                preservation of the national territories or with the intention of establishing the
                supposedly more natural national borders of the individual national communities. As
                it was, in the minds of zealous nationalists of the 19<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>
                and 20<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> centuries, national territories would often be
                understood as incomplete, i.e. as something that had yet to be finalised – most
                often on the account of the neighbouring political entities. This would supposedly
                once and for all make up for all the national injustices that had supposedly taken
                place in the past.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn7" n="5"> Such conceptions could
                    also be mobilised for propaganda purposes, which is amply proven by an allegoric
                    example of a German postcard from the time of World War I (<hi rend="italic"
                        >Gegen welsche Tücke und Raubgier!</hi>), which defined the goals of the
                    armed conflicts as follows: "Wir wollen, daß deutsch bleibt, was deutsch ist,
                    und deutsch wird, was deutsch war!" ("We want what is German to remain German,
                    and what was German once to become German again!"). <hi rend="italic">–
                        Historische Bildpostkarten - 14.8 Bildpostkarten/Gegen welsche Tücke und
                        Raubgier!.</hi> accessed December 12, 2015, <ref
                        target="http://www.bildpostkarten.uni-osnabrueck.de/displayimage.php?album=102&amp;pos=87"
                        >http://www.bildpostkarten.uni-osnabrueck.de/displayimage.php?album=102&amp;pos=87</ref>.</note>
            </p>
            <p>It seems that all the tragedy and absurdity of the millions of deaths, caused by the
                world wars as well as by all the other European conflicts between nations in the
                    19<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> and 20<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> century,
                can be considered in the context of the fact that not even the armies of the
                victorious states have ever secured the true national borders. It is obvious that
                national borders are, in their essence, neither natural nor objectively
                identifiable: not a single unbiased, indisputable, and irrefutable criterion exists
                that could definitely and objectively draw the line between two national communities
                on the map. Not even geographical obstacles or characteristics that in themselves
                stand out as the most obvious, apparent, and therefore believable criteria meet such
                requirements. Even if it seems, at the first glance, that geographical features can
                easily adopt the role of national demarcation lines as well, numerous examples of
                successful national movements that did not consider such barriers as insurmountable
                for the expansion of their nationally-determined visions speak in favour of the
                opposite. For this reason, it was already Ernest Renan (1823–1892) in his work <hi
                    rend="italic">What is a Nation? (Qu'est-ce qu'une nation?</hi>, 1882) that
                proposed as well as convincingly argued in favour of the standpoint that national
                borders did not depend on the geographical features.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn8"
                    n="6"> Ernest Renan, “What is a Nation?,” in: <hi rend="italic">Becoming
                        National: A Reader</hi>, ed. Geoff Eley and Ronald Grigor Suny (Oxford:
                    Oxford University Press, 1996), 41–55.</note>
            </p>
            <p>It would be even harder to argue in favour of the thesis involving the existence of
                certain objectively specifiable cultural "markers", i.e. specific cultural
                characteristics, by means of which we could separate a certain population from
                another according to a definite national criterion. After all, the idea of hermetic
                and different mutually-exclusive national cultures and national cultural patterns
                can be immediately refuted, simply with a short and superficial excursion into the
                frontier-zone space on either side of any so-called national border. Precisely in
                such contemporary interstate or international regions we can easily note that the
                cultural and social phenomena are by no means conditioned solely with the adherence
                to a certain administrative-political unit or what we could, in the absence of a
                better expression, refer to as the "institutionally-supported national cultural
                framework". Quite the opposite: to a very significant extent, cultural patterns have
                never depended merely on the collection of the presupposed national determinants, as
                they have most often appeared either within wider supranational or narrower regional
                spaces, conditioned by very heterogeneous social and cultural forces. As Eric J.
                Wolf explained with a witty yet very extensively substantiated metaphor: nations,
                societies, or cultures simply do not possess any "qualities of internally
                homogeneous and externally distinctive bounded objects", which is why they do not
                spin off each other like billiard balls.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn9" n="7"> Eric
                    J. Wolf, <hi rend="italic">Europe and the People Without History</hi> (Berkeley
                    and Los Angeles: University of California, 2010), 6.</note>
            </p>
            <p>After all, national borders are hardly eternal, and they have especially not been
                with us always and forever. All of this is also true of the present-day Slovenian
                borders. It is certainly true that the national borders, envisioned in the past,
                could correspond to the older pre-existing administrative borders with a very long
                history. The southern border – today the border between Slovenia and Croatia – is an
                example of such an adaptation. The concept of the demarcation line between the
                "Slovenian" and "Croatian" nation that was formed in the 19<hi rend="superscript"
                    >th</hi> century largely corresponded to what had been a far older border of the
                medieval German state.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn10" n="8"> Bogo Grafenauer,
                    “Etnična struktura in zgodovinski pomen jugoslovanskih narodov v srednjem veku,”
                        <hi rend="italic">Zgodovinski časopis</hi> 21 (1967): 23.</note> Naturally,
                this by no means implies that the existing borders simply predestined the subsequent
                formation of national communities and consequently the creation of national borders.
                Quite the opposite: national borders, even Slovenian, could be drawn completely
                anew, <hi rend="italic">ex nihilo</hi>, so to speak; which is what the history of
                nationalisms and nationalistic political endeavours in the 19th and 20th centuries
                actually addresses.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn11" n="9"> See for instance Jason
                    D. Hansen, <hi rend="italic">Mapping the Germans: Statistical Science,
                        Cartography, and the Visualization of the German Nation, 1848-1914</hi> (New
                    York: Oxford University Press, 2015). </note> Generally we could therefore
                conclude that the creation of national borders depends, from the historical
                perspective, on a combination of numerous factors – and chance is one of them, as
                well. At the same time the European history of the last two centuries also amply
                confirms the following: the border between two national communities or national
                states can only be established when the majority agrees with the line, drawn on the
                maps; or at least when this is agreed by the majority of those that possess the
                decision-making power or simply the political power in a given moment.</p>
            <p>It seems that the history of establishing the Slovenian-Croatian border in the
                territory of the present-day Prekmurje region also underlines the importance of
                innovations, coincidences, and agreements for the definition and implementation of
                national borders. As it happened, in the 19th century, when this border was being
                defined, it was impossible to resort to the pre-existing administrative or political
                divisions and ascribe a new national significance to them. At the same time the
                Slovenian territory was impossible to clearly separate from the Croatian land, not
                even according to the linguistic criterion. Namely, the dialects, characteristic of
                this region – i.e. the today's Slovenian Prekmurje region dialects and the today's
                Croatian Kajkavian dialects from the Medjimurje region – have always been a part of
                the natural linguistic continuum.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn12" n="10"> Mijo
                    Lončarić and Anita Celinić, "Susret slovenskih prekmurskih i hrvatskih
                    međimurskih govora," <hi rend="italic">Slavistična revija</hi> 55 (2007): 41–46.
                    – See also Matej Šekli, “Zemljepisnojezikoslovna členitev kajkavščine ter
                    slovensko-kajkavska jezikovna meja,”
                    <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Slovenski jezik – Slovene Linguistic Studies </hi>9
                    (2013): 3–53. Šekli claims that present-day “distinctive marginal Kajkavian
                    local dialects” are, in the genetic-linguistic sense, “in fact part of the
                    diasystem of the Slovene language”. However, continues Šekli, such a linguistic
                    delineation obviously does not presuppose Slovene national adherence of local
                    population at the territory of Croatia.</note> This means that both groups of
                dialects would even be difficult to separate today, if they were not already divided
                precisely by the strict territorial-political, administrative and/or national
                border. Naturally, in the 19th century such a border did not yet exist in the
                territory of what is today Prekmurje. Furthermore, it is difficult to imagine that a
                Slovenian-Croatian national border, envisioned in the 19th century, could also in
                fact assert itself as the administrative or territorial delimitation without the
                radical transformation of the European interstate relations at the end of World War
                I – namely, the transformation that stemmed from the introduction of a new
                principle, according to which the European interstate and international relations
                would be settled from then on: the nations' right to self-determination. Only in
                this context and on the basis of the revolutionary movement in Hungary could
                Slovenian diplomats as a part of the Yugoslav delegation at the peace negotiations
                in Paris even have the opportunity to argue for the standpoint that certain parts in
                the west of the Kingdom of Hungary should be treated as parts of the Slovenian
                national territory and therefore annexed to the Kingdom of Serbs, Croats and
                    Slovenes.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn13" n="11"> On the self-determination of
                    nations as a principle of the territorial-political organisation, argued for and
                    promoted by the American President Wilson: Uroš Lipušček, <hi rend="italic">Ave
                        Wilson: ZDA in prekrajanje Slovenije v Versaillesu 1919-1920</hi>
                    (Ljubljana: Založba Sophia, 2003). On the legal aspects of the concept of
                    self-determination: Daniel Thürer and Thomas Burri, "Self-Determination," Max
                    Planck Encyclopedia of Public International Law, accessed October 20, 2015, <ref
                        target="http://opil.ouplaw.com/view/10.1093/law:epil/9780199231690/law-9780199231690-e873?rskey=YVjdhp&amp;result=1&amp;prd=EPIL"
                        >http://opil.ouplaw.com/view/10.1093/law:epil/9780199231690/law-9780199231690-e873?rskey=YVjdhp&amp;result=1&amp;prd=EPIL</ref>
                    A clear and in-depth insight into the activities of the Slovenian political
                    elite during and after World War I: Walter Lukan, <hi rend="italic">Iz
                        "črnožolte kletke narodov" v "zlato svobodo"? Habsburška monarhija in
                        Slovenci v prvi svetovni vojni</hi> (Ljubljana: Znanstvena založba FF,
                    2014). </note>
            </p>
            <p>To summarise: until as late as the dissolution of the Austro-Hungarian Empire at the
                end of World War I, the ideas of the Slovenian national activists about the national
                delimitations in the territory of the present-day Prekmurje region had nothing
                whatsoever to do with reality. The envisioned national border existed merely in the
                minds of a handful of Slovenians who lived and campaigned in the "Cisleithanian"
                territory, i.e. west of Prekmurje. The territory of what is today the Prekmurje
                region was, together with the territory of Medjimurje further to the south, a part
                of the Kingdom of Hungary for several centuries, since the Middle Ages until as late
                as the end of World War I.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn14" n="12"> On the formation
                    of the state border that had, since the Middle Ages, initially separated the
                    territory of the present-day Prekmurje (until 1919 a part of the Kingdom of
                    Hungary) from the rest of the present-day Slovene territory (in the late
                    imperial period a part of the various Cisleithanian crown lands): Peter Štih,
                    "Salzburg, Ptuj in nastanek štajersko-madžarske meje v današnji Sloveniji," <hi
                        rend="italic">Zgodovinski časopis</hi> 50 no. 4 (1996): 535–44.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The state border, established in such a manner on the river Mura, therefore very
                obviously separated the present-day Prekmurje from the other regions that the 19<hi
                    rend="superscript">th</hi>-century Slovenian national activists considered to be
                Slovenian. Moreover, Slovenian national activists in "Cisleithania" started using
                the name "Prekmurje" for the supposedly Slovenian regions on the opposite bank of
                Mura relatively late, not until the second half of the 19<hi rend="superscript"
                    >th</hi> century. The name became fully recognised at the end of World War I, in
                the context of the efforts to annex this territory to the Kingdom of Serbs, Croats
                and Slovenes at the 1919 Paris Peace Conference. In the materials, prepared for
                these purposes by Matija Slavič (1877–1958) and Fran Kovačič (1867–1939), the name
                Prekmurje was used consistently, and therefore it also officially asserted itself as
                the name for this distinct geographical and historical territory.<note place="foot"
                    xml:id="ftn15" n="13"> Metka Fujs, "Prekmurje – podoba prostora," <hi
                        rend="italic">Podravina: časopis za multidisciplinarna istraživanja</hi> 3,
                    no. 6 (2004): 49–61. </note> Otherwise the territory of the present-day
                Prekmurje "found itself in the same territorial unit: a diocese, although divided
                into two deanships – the Murska Sobota and Dolnja Lendava Deanship – separated by
                what had until then been the former Zagreb–Győr Diocese border, identical to the
                county border" as late as in 1777, after the establishment of the Diocese of
                    Szombathely.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn16" n="14"> Boris Golec<hi
                        rend="italic">, Nedokončana kroatizacija delov vzhodne Slovenije med 16. in
                        19. stoletjem: po sledeh hrvaškega lingvonima in etnonima v Beli krajini,
                        Kostelu, Prekmurju in Prlekiji</hi> (Ljubljana: Založba ZRC, 2012),
                    105.</note> Therefore the territory that is today the Prekmurje region had not
                existed as a unit in any sense until as late as the Marias Theresia's rearrangement
                of dioceses. Moreover, its southern part was especially strongly connected with
                Medjimurje across the river Mura (nowadays Croatia), as these regions had (until
                then) shared a common diocese and (until the very end) also administrative, i.e.
                county, framework. Before the merging within the borders of the same diocese (1777),
                the territory of the present day Prekmurje could be most easily defined
                descriptively, "as the frontier-zone space of the Kingdom of Hungary in the vicinity
                of the Holy Roman Empire, inhabited by the people who called themselves Sloveni and
                their language Slovenian".<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn17" n="15"> Ibid., 105,
                    106.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Ever since the Middle Ages and until the dissolution of Austro-Hungary, the state,
                administrative, and for the large part of this period also the customs frontier
                followed the flow of the river Mura between Radgona in the north and the territory
                east of Ljutomer in the south, separating the today's Slovenian part of the former
                Austrian crown land of Styria from the territory of the today's Prekmurje. The
                significance of this border and the strictness of the frontier-zone regime have
                changed through the centuries – naturally, depending on the broader political
                circumstances on the one hand and the territorial changes in the immediate
                surroundings on the other hand.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn18" n="16"> On the
                    Ottoman conquests and invasions of the north in particular, as in the 16th and
                    17th century the Ottomans got very close to the territory of the today's
                    Prekmurje and sporadically enforced their authority in this region: Bogo
                    Grafenauer, "O turški oblasti in o nastanku drobne zemljiške posesti v
                    Prekmurju," in: <hi rend="italic">Prekmurski Slovenci v zgodovini: zbornik
                        razprav o posebnih potezah zgodovinskega razvoja Prekmurja</hi>, ed. Bogo
                    Grafenauer (Murska Sobota: Pomurska založba, 1961), 79–90.</note> However, the
                border on the river Mura has certainly been never completely airtight for the
                frontier-zone population, even though these people lived in two different
                territorial-administrative units. The cross-border contacts strengthened
                significantly in the 19<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> century, when customs
                restrictions and controls on the Austrian-Hungarian border initially relaxed, only
                to be completely abolished for a while in 1850 and 1851.<note place="foot"
                    xml:id="ftn19" n="17"> On the customs regime and rules: Boštjan Hepe et al., <hi
                        rend="italic">Zgodovina carine na slovenskem od antike do slovenske
                        osamosvojitve</hi> (Ljubljana: Carinska uprava RS, 2011), 36–40.</note>
                Consequently the contacts in this period were particularly lively and diverse,
                actively participated in by the communities that inhabited both banks of the river
                and its immediate vicinity.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn20" n="18"> The fundamental
                    work explaining the history of cross-border relations and contacts between the
                    population on both sides of the border: Marko Zajc, <hi rend="italic">Kje se
                        slovensko neha in hrvaško začne: slovensko-hrvaška meja v 19. in na začetku
                        20. stoletja</hi> (Ljubljana: Modrijan, 2006), 287–320; and literature
                    listed therein. On the contacts between the inhabitants of the today's Prekmurje
                    and today's Slovenian Štajerska (Styria) regions: Fran Mohorič, "Prekmurje in
                    Medjimurje," <hi rend="italic">Časopis za zgodovino in narodopisje</hi> 16
                    (1920): 29.</note>
            </p>
            <p>However, even though the border by no means represented an insurmountable obstacle in
                the lives of the Habsburg subjects and simultaneously citizens of two different
                political entities on the left or the right bank of the river Mura in the 19<hi
                    rend="superscript">th</hi> century, from the political or administrative
                viewpoint this border was nevertheless understood as a fact –a very tangible fact,
                at that, which asserted itself as virtually unchangeable in the 19<hi
                    rend="superscript">th</hi> century due to what had by that time become a very
                long history of the extremely complicated relations between the Hungarian nobility
                and the Habsburg rulers. The river Mura represented the border, separating two
                administrative entities that may have shared a common ruler for a very long time,
                while they remained separate in the political and administrative sense. </p>
            <p>How, then, was the concept that the today's Prekmurje should count as a specific
                Slovenian territory established in light of such circumstances – in the context of
                the borders that apparently had no parallels with the actually existing
                administrative-territorial delimitations in the long 19th century? When and why was
                the today's region of Prekmurje registered as Slovenian territory?</p>
            <p>In the long 19th century, the idea of a distinct Slovenian territory – understood as
                the land inhabited by the members of the Slovenian nation – formed on the basis of
                the belief that all those subjects of the Austrian emperor who spoke Slovenian were
                also members of the Slovenian nation – in short, Slovenians. This sort of
                equalisation between the Slovenian language and Slovenian nation was, in turn, based
                on the completely new implications of the expressions "Slovenian language" or
                "Slovenians", as they had first been invented and disseminated by certain members of
                the intellectual circle that would gather regularly at the house of Sigismund Zois
                (1747–1819) in Ljubljana. These concepts were based on the so-called Carantanian
                Theory, initially formed by Anton Tomaž Linhart (1756–1795), as well as on the
                tradition of the Protestant literary endeavours in the Slovenian language,
                rediscovered and reinterpreted precisely at this time. Since the end of the first or
                the beginning of the second decade of the 19th century, what had in fact been a
                small circle of Inner Austrian intellectuals thus no longer used the expressions
                "Slovenian" and "Slovenian language" merely to denote the Slavic population and
                their language or to specifically refer to the Slavic people and their language in
                Styria or Carinthia, but rather, increasingly often, to define the Slavs and their
                language in the territory of Inner Austria, in the Kajkavian regions around Zagreb,
                and in certain western parts of Hungary.</p>
            <p>These intellectual processes and mental transformations can be illustrated
                appropriately with the example of Valentin Vodnik's (1758–1819) literary opus. In
                Vodnik's essays, poems, and correspondence, precisely at this time the Carniolan
                provincial identification or identification as Carniolans started to be replaced by
                the ideas of a sort of a Slovenian community in the present-day meaning of the word.
                The latter is very tellingly illustrated by the corrections of Vodnik's <hi
                    rend="italic">Poem for my Fellow Countrymen (Péſma na moje rojáke)</hi>,
                preserved as a part of his heritage. The poem was written towards the end of the
                18th century within the exceedingly Carniolan context and way of thinking. However,
                in one of his first corrections of 1816, Vodnik already entitled it <hi
                    rend="italic">A Wakeup Call for my Fellow Countrymen (Dramílo mojih
                    rojakov)</hi> and changed the first line of the first stanza – from "Carniolan!
                Your land is healthy" ("Krajnz! tvoja dežèla je sdrava") to "Slovenian, your land is
                healthy" ("Slovenz, tvoja zemla je zdrava").<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn21" n="19"
                    > Facsimile in Alfonz Gspan and Lino Legiša,
                    <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Zgodovina slovenskega slovstva I </hi>(Ljubljana:
                    Slovenska matica, 1956) 417. Valentin Vodnik, <hi rend="italic">Zbrano
                    delo</hi>, ed. Janko Kos (Ljubljana: DZS, 1988), 392, 393.</note> However, this
                was not the first time that Carniolans transformed into Slovenians in this poem by
                Vodnik. The line "Slovenz, tvoja zemla je zdrava" or "Slovene! dein Land iſt
                geſegnet" had already appeared three years earlier in the reader, compiled in Graz
                by Vodnik's former student and correspondent at the time, Janez Nepomuk Primic
                    (1785–1823).<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn22" n="20"> Janez Nepomuk Primic, <hi
                        rend="italic">Némshko-Slovénske branja = Deutsch-Slovenisches Lesebuch</hi>,
                    (Graz, 1813), 61.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The idea of this sort of a definition of the terms "Slovenian language" and
                "Slovenian", different in terms of contents, was based on the original
                classification of the Slavic peoples, constructed by Jernej Kopitar (1780–1844) on
                the basis of the previous historiographical findings of Anton Tomaž Linhart
                (1756–1795). Kopitar presented his classification for the first time in his renowned
                work entitled
                <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Grammar of the Slavic Language in Carniola, Carinthia, and Styria (Grammatik der Slavischen Sprache in Krain, Kärnten und Steyermark, </hi>1808).
                The originality of the scheme that Kopitar would further upgrade and substantiate in
                the years and decades to come stemmed from the fact – to put it briefly – that by
                agreeing with certain Linhart's claims, Kopitar rejected the thesis of the famous
                Czech philologist Josef Dobrovski (1753–1829), who claimed that the so-called <hi
                    rend="italic">Windisch</hi> language in Carniola, Styria, and Carinthia should
                be considered Croatian, which he counted as one of the five major Slavic dialects
                (besides Russian, Polish, Illyrian, and Czech).<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn23"
                    n="21"> Janko Kos, ed., <hi rend="italic">Izbrano delo / Jernej Kopitar, Matija
                        Čop</hi> (Ljubljana: Mladinska knjiga, 1973) 35, 36.</note> Even though
                Kopitar agreed with the claim that the (Kajkavian) Croatian and the Inner Austrian
                Slovenian language were parts of the same Slavic dialect, he also – unlike Dobrovski
                – believed that on the basis of the historical primate of Carantania this language
                should be defined as Carantanian language, language of Carantanian Slavs, or, in
                German, as <hi rend="italic">Windisch</hi> – i.e. Slovenian language. As it was,
                Carantanians were allegedly the oldest or longest-living Slavic people in this
                territory, and therefore they, as such, had the right to name the language after
                themselves rather than after Croats.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn24" n="22"> More
                    detailed account on the formation of Kopitar's classification in Jernej Kosi,
                        <hi rend="italic">Kako je nastal slovenski narod</hi> (Ljubljana: Sophia,
                    2013), 150–70; and literature listed therein. On the emergence of Slovene
                    national movement see also Joachim Hösler,
                    <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Von Krain zu Slowenien: die Anfänge der nationalen Differenzierungsprozesse in Krain und der Untersteiermark von der Aufklärung bis zur Revolution. 1768 bis 1848 </hi>(München
                    : R. Oldenbourg, 2006).</note>
            </p>
            <p>Consequently, immediately after the publication of his <hi rend="italic"
                >Grammar</hi>, Kopitar and his correspondents in fact started using the expression
                "Carantanian" and shortly afterwards the term "Slovenian language".<note
                    place="foot" xml:id="ftn25" n="23"> France Kidrič, <hi rend="italic">Dobrovský
                        in slovenski preporod njegove dobe</hi> (Ljubljana: Znanstveno društvo,
                    1930) 156.</note> In March 1811 Kopitar, in a letter to his patron Baron Žiga
                Zois (1747–1819), clearly defined the geographical dimensions of the envisioned
                separate Slavic language for the first time: "Therefore: 1. Slovenian in Carniola,
                Styria, and Carinthia; 2. so-called Croatian around Zagreb and so on; and 3.
                Slovenian (<hi rend="italic underline">ſtari</hi>
                <hi rend="italic">ſlovénski jesik</hi>) in the Hungarian counties near Lake Balaton;
                are three <hi rend="italic">eusdem</hi>
                <hi rend="italic underline">speciei</hi> variations"<note place="foot"
                    xml:id="ftn26" n="24"> France Kidrič, <hi rend="italic">Zoisova korespondenca
                        (1809–1810)</hi> (Ljubljana: Akademija znanosti in umetnosti, 1941), 144.
                    See also Luka Vidmar, <hi rend="italic">A Slavic Republic of Letters. The
                        Correspondence between Jernej Kopitar and Baron Žiga Zois</hi> (Frankfurt am
                    Main: Peter Lang, 2016).</note>, i.e., of the same kind. In the beginning of the
                19th century, Kopitar thus defined in the modern sense, for the first time, who
                Slovenians were at all: those subjects of the Austrian Emperor that spoke Slovenian
                within the geographical borders specified for this language by Kopitar. In the
                following decades it turned out, of course, that all the speakers of the language
                constructed in such a manner did not also become the members of the modern Slovenian
                national community. This was especially true of the Kajkavian area around Zagreb,
                the part of the Civil Croatia that Matija Majar referred to in 1848 as "Banatsko".
                Nevertheless, the following holds true: in the middle of the 19<hi
                    rend="superscript">th</hi> century, the equation between the geographical scope
                of Kopitar's Slovenian language on the one hand and the territorial dimensions of
                the Slovenian nation on the other hand asserted itself as the central ideological
                supposition of the nascent Slovenian national movement.</p>
            <p>Even the earliest recorded statements about the integration of the present-day
                Prekmurje region into the wider Slovenian space were, precisely for this reason,
                made in the field of linguistic research. As France Kidrič established, this
                occurred for the first time in the writings of Jernej Kopitar, who "on 3 August 1809
                in his letters to Zois and Zupan, but in the spring of 1810 also publicly,
                emphasised the adherence of the inhabitants of Prekmurje to the Slovenian
                    nation".<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn27" n="25"> France Kidrič, <hi
                        rend="italic">Dobrovský</hi>, 154.</note> On the basis of Jernej Kopitar's
                works, Janez Nepomuk Primic (1785–1823), a professor at the Department of Slovenian
                Language at the lyceum in Graz, counted certain parts of the western Hungary to <hi
                    rend="italic">Slovenien</hi> in his 1814 work <hi rend="italic">The New
                    German-Slovenian Reader (Novi Nemſhko-Slovenſki Bukvar).</hi><note place="foot"
                    xml:id="ftn28" n="26"> Janez Nepomuk Primic, <hi rend="italic">Novi
                        némshko-slovénshki bukvar, al A. B. C. otrokon léhko sastoplen = Neues
                        Slovenisch-Deutsches der Fassungskraft der Kinder angemessenes A. B. C.:
                        welches auserlesene, leichte und belehrende Aufgaben, Erzählungen und
                        Unterhaltungen enthält</hi> (Graz, 1814), 122.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Outside the field of linguistic research and discussions, the present-day territory
                of Prekmurje was registered as a Slovenian territory in the 1840s, on the pages of
                Bleiweis's <hi rend="italic">Kmetijske in rokodelske novice</hi> publication. In
                1846, in the <hi rend="italic">Novice</hi> newspaper, the Styrian priest Oroslav Caf
                (1814–1874) thus called upon the collectors of Slovenian words, urging them to send
                him their materials so that he could perfect his dictionary. On this occasion Caf
                wrote: "Slovenians! Do not forget or neglect the fact that your own authentic words
                are spoken in <hi rend="italic">six countries</hi> among a variety of neighbours: in
                Hungary, Styria, Croatia, Carniola, Italy, and Carinthia; and that you are speaking
                the <hi rend="italic">hallowed words</hi>, in which your great compatriot <hi
                    rend="italic">Kopitar</hi> chose to find the ancient Slavic language."<note
                    place="foot" xml:id="ftn29" n="27"> “Proglas zastran noviga slovenskiga slovnika
                    in slovnice,” <hi rend="italic">Kmetijske in rokodelske novice</hi>, March 11,
                    1846, 40.</note> In 1847 the author of the article entitled
                    <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Slovenian Dictionary for Education and Amusement </hi>(<hi
                    rend="italic">Slovenski besédnik za poduk in kratek čas</hi>) in the <hi
                    rend="italic">Novice</hi> newspaper listed the dioceses where Slovenians
                allegedly lived, and wrote the following: "In Hungary – in the Vas and Zala Counties
                – 52,000 Slovenians live in 160 villages, in 18 Catholic and 4 Protestant
                    parishes."<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn30" n="28">
                    <hi rend="italic">Kmetijske in rokodelske novice,</hi> April 21, 1847, 63. See
                    also Nataša Stergar, "Narodnostno vprašanje v predmarčnih letnikih Bleiweisovih
                    Novic," <hi rend="italic">Kronika: Časopis za slovensko krajevno zgodovino</hi>
                    25 no. 3 (1977): 184–89.</note>
            </p>
            <p>In the pre-March decades, Kopitar's construction of the separate Slovenian language,
                which also included the today's Prekmurje region in terms of territory, asserted
                itself among certain intellectuals who spoke and/or wrote in Slovenian; as did the
                conviction, based thereon, that the inhabitants of certain parts of western Hungary
                should count among Slovenians or among the speakers of Slovenian. With the onset of
                the revolutionary turmoil in 1848, very favourable political and social
                circumstances emerged as well, allowing for the politicisation of this kind of ideas
                and the public articulation of the nationally-defined political demands and
                expectations, thus paving the way for the formation of the Slovenian national
                movement.</p>
            <p>The beginnings of the Slovenian national movement are related to the journalistic
                contributions and political endeavours of the Klagenfurt vicar Matija Majar
                (1809–1892). His writings should be understood as a sort of a foundation for the
                Slovenian nationalist ideology, as he is focusing precisely on the demand that all
                Slovenians, who had until then lived in the various Habsburg provinces, should come
                together in a single territorial and administrative unit and elect their political
                representatives themselves. In March or April 1848, Majar illustrated the latter
                even more clearly in the flier <hi rend="italic">What do Slovenians Demand? (Kaj
                    Slovenci terjamo?)</hi>, which begins with the plea that "all Slovenians should
                unite in a single nation like brothers, and all of us should have a single Slovenian
                Provincial Assembly. There are 116,000 of us in Carinthia, 378,000 in Styria,
                438,000 in Carniola, 217,000 in the Gorizia and Trieste regions, 22,000 in Banatsko,
                60,000 in Hungary, and 230,000 in Istria. Thus we are divided between seven sides,
                all of us separated and paupers everywhere. Wherever we may raise our voices, there
                are not enough of us; whatever we may say can be easily ignored; but if we are
                united, there are almost a million and a half of us... Our word will have weight and
                will be heard everywhere; and all of us will benefit from this. We simply must have
                a single Assembly for the whole of Slovenia, joined by the estates and deputies from
                all the Slovenian lands with all the rights that they currently possess."<note
                    place="foot" xml:id="ftn31" n="29"> Cited in Prunk, <hi rend="italic">Slovenski
                        narodni</hi>.</note> Such nationally-defined political aspirations had not
                appeared before, in either the currently known pre-March or older sources. Even if
                Majar most probably based the formulation of his ideas extensively on the reports on
                the developments in the wider area of the German Confederation, his way of thinking
                and outlook on the social, territorial, and political organisation of the Habsburg
                lands was nevertheless completely original, nationally-influenced, and
                chronologically new. His assertion that the 60,000 Slovenians who lived "in Hungary"
                should be a part of this special Slovenian territorial-administrative unit as well
                is especially important for the research at hand.</p>
            <p>Judging from the available sources, the incorporation of the present-day territory of
                Prekmurje or the local population into the concept of the Slovenian territory,
                Slovenian language, and Slovenian nation should be observed in the context of the
                formation of the Slovenian national thought, its expansion, as well as the
                subsequent emergence and assertion of the Slovenian national movement as of 1848.
                This means that, chronologically speaking, the idea of the Slovenian adherence or
                the Slovenian character of the today's territory of Prekmurje formed in the first
                half of the 19th century, very gradually and step by step: i.e., from the idea of
                the linguistic adherence of this area; through the cultivation of the Slovenian
                national thought; to the political development of this way of thinking in 1848, when
                Slovenians "in Hungary" were for the first time understood as a part of the single
                Slovenian national political body, which should, as such, be embodied in a separate
                political-territorial entity: Slovenia. However, in this regard the following should
                be underlined as well: in the pre-March period, the idea of the Slovenian adherence
                of the territory of what is today Prekmurje remained at the theoretical level
                throughout that time. Namely, the borders of the Slovenian territory in the modern
                national sense of the expression had never been clearly defined in the western parts
                of Hungary until the middle of the 19th century. Only after the outbreak of the
                March Revolution was the extent of the territory where Slovenians allegedly lived
                specified more precisely. </p>
            <p>The first geographer to focus on the Slovenian geography and thus also the
                specification of the Slovenian border soon after the March events was, as it is very
                well known, Peter Kozler (1824–1879). His intention was to draw up "a map of the
                Slovenian land", which would, as he himself stated later, "show as precisely as
                possible how far and wide the Slovenian language is spoken".<note place="foot"
                    xml:id="ftn32" n="30"> Peter Kozler,
                    <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Kratek slovenski zemljopis in pregled politične in pravosodne razdelitve ilirskega kraljestva in štajerskega vojvodstva s pridanim slovenskim in nemškim imenikom mest, tergov, krajev i.t.d., </hi>reproduced
                    reprint (Ljubljana: Cankarjeva založba, 1975), unpaginated introduction.</note>
                To a degree, Kozler was able to base his efforts on certain pre-March ethnographic
                depictions and maps, but he also acquired extensive new information either by
                himself or with the assistance of friends and acquaintances. As a curiosity it is
                worth mentioning that he had not intended to include the today's territory of
                Prekmurje in the map, as he had been unable to gather enough reliable
                    information.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn33" n="31"> Valter Bohinec, <hi
                        rend="italic">Peter Kozler in prvi zemljevid slovenskega ozemlja</hi>
                    (Ljubljana: Cankarjeva založba, 1975). – On Kozler see also Ivan Kordiš, “Peter
                    Kozler and His Map of the Slovenian Land and Its Provinces (1849–1871),” <hi
                        rend="italic">Imago Mundi</hi>, 68, no. 2 (2016): 212–231.</note> He only
                acquired this information subsequently, and used it immediately for his article <hi
                    rend="italic">Slovenians in Hungary (Slovenci na Ogrskim)</hi>, published in the
                    <hi rend="italic">Slovenija</hi> newspaper in 1849. The article was intended to
                contribute "to a greater recognisability of Slovenians living in Hungary, kindred to
                the Slovenians living in Styria and Illyria."<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn34"
                    n="32">
                    <hi rend="italic">Slovenija</hi>, July 10, 1849, 220.</note> In his article,
                Kozler defined the supposed scope of the Slovenian national settlement in Hungary
                and concluded that "the whole Hungarian – Slovenian territory includes around 170
                towns and villages, located in 21 Catholic and 5 Protestant parishes".<note
                    place="foot" xml:id="ftn35" n="33"> Ibid.</note> Kozler went on to list and
                describe these parishes, in the administrative-political sense belonging to the Zala
                or Vas Counties, and name them with their Slovenian names.</p>
            <p>Furthermore, in 1849 everything was ready for the printing of the famous Kozler's
                map. Ultimately this did not occur that year, as the copperplate engraver whom
                Kozler had entrusted with the printing fled from Vienna and the copperplate vanished
                mysteriously. However, when the plate was finally located in 1851, Kozler organised
                the printing again, as well as prepared, as an annex to the map, "<hi rend="italic"
                    >A Short Slovenian Geography and Overview of Political and Legal Division of the
                    Illyrian Kingdom and Styrian Duchy with an Appendix of Slovenian and German
                    Registry of Towns, Hamlets, Places etc.</hi>" (<hi rend="italic">Kratek
                    slovenski zemljopis in pregled politične in pravosodne razdelitve Ilirskega
                    kraljestva in Štajerskega vojvodstva s pridanim slovenskim in nemškim imenikom
                    mest, tergov, krajev i.t.d.</hi>). Next year the <hi rend="italic">Novice</hi>
                newspaper published an advert for the pre-ordering of the map, which allegedly
                "shows the borders of the Slovenian nation, its language, and its domain". However,
                the map had been confiscated and subject to many complications; and albeit dated
                1853, it was not released until as late as 1861, i.e. eight years later.<note
                    place="foot" xml:id="ftn36" n="34"> Valter Bohinec, <hi rend="italic">Peter
                        Kozler</hi>, 11, 12.</note>
            </p>
            <p>As it has already been pointed out, the map was also accompanied by the <hi
                    rend="italic">Short Slovenian Geography (Kratek slovenski zemljopis)</hi>, where
                Kozler argued, in writing, "how far the Slovenian word reaches". In the booklet that
                accompanied the map (<hi rend="italic">Short Slovenian Geography</hi>), he defined
                the Slovenian-Croatian border in the territory of the today's Prekmurje as follows:
                »A dialect more similar to Slovenian rather than the Croatian language is spoken in
                the Croatian Littoral and by the Styrian border, in the Zagreb and Varaždin Counties
                nearly as far as Zagreb. However, the language here is changing gradually, and in
                the presence of so many local dialects the Croatian and its kindred Slovenian world
                cannot be separated very precisely. We can thus, for example, draw the border
                between these nations from the river Sava further towards Sotla, and the Styrian
                provincial borders as far as the rivers Drava and Mura.</p>
            <p>From Mura and further to the north, the Slovenian language borders on Hungarian –
                i.e. from Dolnja Lendava through Hodož towards Szentgotthárd on the Rába river, and
                from there the national border runs towards the borders of the province of Styria
                and the border stream of Kučenica.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn37" n="35"> Peter
                    Kozler, <hi rend="italic">Kratek slovenski zemljopis</hi>, XX-XXI.</note>
            </p>
            <p>This implies that at this time the initial Kopitar's idea of the scope of the
                Slovenian language in the south and east already digressed from the definition of
                the Slovenian-Croatian national borders. It is therefore obvious that in certain
                areas the idea of the linguistic border was not as relevant for the definition of
                the national territories as the old administrative borders. Moreover, in the case of
                Prekmurje, Kozler even had to resort to an analogy with the situation in Styria and
                promote the flow of the river Mura from the Styrian border as a sort of a dividing
                line between the nations, because, according to Kozler, "the language here is
                changing gradually, and in the presence of so many local dialects the Croatian and
                its kindred Slovenian world cannot be separated very precisely".</p>
            <p>Apparently the territorial proximity and linguistic familiarity or permeability of
                the frontier-zone "Slovenian" and "Croatian" dialects had to be even far more
                obvious in the period before the introduction of the standard national languages in
                the administrative apparatus and in schools than it is today, and the originators of
                the national or ethnographic borders in the middle of the 19th century were clearly
                very confused by this fact. It seems that the question where the Slovenian language
                ended and Croatian began was not easy to solve, taking into account the dialects of
                the local population. We can also note this dilemma in the renowned
                <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Ethnography of the Austrian Monarchy (Ethnographie der österreichischen Monarchie, </hi>1855–57),
                in which Czoernig – still following Kopitar's theory on the Slovenian adherence of
                the speakers of the Kajkavian dialect in the territory of Croatia – described the
                Slovenian-Croatian linguistic border as follows: »Die slovenisch-slovenokroatische
                Sprachgränze wird durch die Landesgränze zwischen Krain, Süd-Steiermark und Ungern
                einerseits, Kroatien anderseits bis Kott an der Mur gebildet. Doch zeigen manche
                Strecken, z.B. jene um Möttling in Krain, dann jene von Krapina bis gegen Varasdin,
                einen gegenseitigen sprachlichen Einfluss, so dass in ersterer kroatische und in
                letzerer häufiger als sonst slovenische Spracheigenheiten und Worte zu hören
                    sind.«<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn38" n="36"> Carl Czörnig, <hi rend="italic"
                        >Ethnographie der österreichischen Monarchie</hi> (Vienna, 1855),
                55.</note></p>
            <p>However, judging from certain subsequent ethnographic descriptions from this period
                we can definitely conclude that the consciousness of the Slovenian adherence of the
                today's Prekmurje region nevertheless spread and strengthened considerably among the
                intellectuals and national-aware Slovenian Habsburg subjects from Cisleithania in
                the second half of the 19th century.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn39" n="37"> See
                    for example Božidar Raič, "Črtice o Prekmurcih in o njihovem govoru," <hi
                        rend="italic">Narodni koledar in letopis matice slovenske za leto 1868</hi>
                    1 (1868): 54. – The first part of Raič's texts was published already in 1863 in
                    the <hi rend="italic">Naprej</hi> newspaper. Viljem Urbas, <hi rend="italic">Die
                        Slovenen: etnographische Skizze</hi> (Trst, 1870), 3. Josip Šuman, <hi
                        rend="italic">Die Slovenen</hi> (Vienna, Teschen: K. Prochaska, 1881), 1.
                    Anton Trstenjak, "Ogrski Slovenci," <hi rend="italic">Ljubljanski zvon</hi> 21
                    (1901): 173.</note> Furthermore, it seems that such a viewpoint was also
                unconditionally received among the readers of the Slovenian literature and
                supporters of the Slovenian national movement at the beginning of the 20th century.
                For this reason, it is also not surprising that the question of the adherence of
                Prekmurje also surfaced at the end of World War I, when the new borders between the
                newly-formed states were being defined and drawn after the defeat and dissolution of
                Austro-Hungary. At the Paris Peace Conference, the Yugoslav delegation thus insisted
                on the standpoint that Prekmurje should be included in the Kingdom of Serbs, Croats
                and Slovenes as a part of the Slovenian national territory. Eventually this in fact
                happened, despite the opposition from a certain percentage of the local inhabitants.
                In the favourable political circumstances, the Army of the Kingdom of SHS first
                occupied Prekmurje on 12 August 1919, and with the Treaty of Trianon a new state
                border with Hungary was determined on 4 June 1920. Thus Prekmurje in fact became a
                part of the Kingdom of SHS. Even though different proposals, opinions, and
                standpoints would occasionally be voiced in the post-war time, in this period the
                demarcation along the river Mura – i.e. the delimitation as proposed by Peter Kozler
                in the middle of the 19th century – was conclusively implemented as the dividing
                line that separated the "Slovenian" from the "Croatian" in this area.<note
                    place="foot" xml:id="ftn40" n="38"> On the diplomatic efforts for the
                    acquisition of Prekmurje at the Paris Peace Conference see Matija Slavič, <hi
                        rend="italic">Naše Prekmurje: zbrane razprave in članki</hi> (Murska Sobota:
                    Pomurska založba, 1999). On the social and political condition in Prekmurje in
                    the inter-war period: Miroslav Kokolj, <hi rend="italic">Prekmurski Slovenci od
                        narodne osvoboditve do nacistične okupacije:
                    1919</hi>–<hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">1941 </hi>(Murska Sobota:
                    Pomurska založba, 1984). – It should by all means be underlined that Prekmurje
                    remained a contentious territory in the inter-war period. Judging from the
                    article and map, published in the <hi rend="italic">Slovenski gospodar</hi>
                    newspaper – in which the readers were informed that "Prekmurje is not the same
                    as Medmurje" and that Medmurje was now inhabited by Croatians and Prekmurje by
                    Slovenians – some terminological and territorial confusion was still present as
                    late as in 1926. – "Prekmurje – Slovenska Krajina," <hi rend="italic">Slovenski
                        gospodar</hi>, September 1, 1926, accessied December 20, 2015, <ref
                        target="http://www.dlib.si/?URN=URN:NBN:SI:DOC-FW15RFZE%20"
                        >http://www.dlib.si/?URN=URN:NBN:SI:DOC-FW15RFZE</ref>.</note></p>
            <p>After the dissolution of Austro-Hungary and with the signing of the Treaty of
                Trianon, the administrative and subsequently also the state border that separated
                the Kingdom of Hungary into the Slovenian and Croatian part was finally implemented
                in the territory of the present-day Prekmurje, at the southern border with what is
                today the Croatian province of Međimurje. The dividing line between the two national
                communities, which had not formed as an idea until as late as the mid-19<hi
                    rend="superscript">th</hi> century, thus became the political reality a few
                decades later.</p>

        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="bibliography">
                <head>Sources and Literature</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Literature:</head>
                    <bibl>Brubaker, Rogers. <hi rend="italic">Nationalism reframed: Nationhood and
                            the national question in the New Europe</hi>. Cambridge: Cambridge
                        University Press, 1996. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Bohinec, Valter. <hi rend="italic">Peter Kozler in prvi zemljevid
                            slovenskega ozemlja</hi>. Ljubljana: Cankarjeva založba, 1975.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Fujs, Metka. "Prekmurje – podoba prostora." <hi rend="italic">Podravina:
                            časopis za multidisciplinarna istraživanja</hi> 3, no. 6 (2004):
                        49–61.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Gellner, Ernst. <hi rend="italic">Nations and Nationalism</hi>. Oxford:
                        Blackwell Publishing, 1983.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Golec,
                        Boris.<hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve"> Nedokončana kroatizacija delov vzhodne Slovenije med 16. in 19. stoletjem: po sledeh hrvaškega lingvonima in etnonima v Beli krajini, Kostelu, Prekmurju in Prlekiji</hi>.
                        Ljubljana: Založba ZRC, 2012.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Grafenauer, Bogo. "O turški oblasti in o nastanku drobne zemljiške posesti
                        v Prekmurju." In: <hi rend="italic">Prekmurski Slovenci v zgodovini: zbornik
                            razprav o posebnih potezah zgodovinskega razvoja Prekmurja</hi>, ed.
                        Bogo Grafenauer, 79–90. Murska Sobota: Pomurska založba, 1961.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Grafenauer, Bogo. "Etnična struktura in zgodovinski pomen jugoslovanskih
                        narodov v srednjem veku." <hi rend="italic">Zgodovinski časopis</hi> 21
                        (1967): 7–48.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Gspan, Alfonz and Lino Legiša<hi rend="italic">. Zgodovina slovenskega
                            slovstva I. Do začetkov romantike</hi>. Ljubljana: Slovenska matica,
                        1956.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Hansen, Jason D.
                        <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Mapping the Germans: Statistical Science, Cartography, and the Visualization of the German Nation, 1848–1914. </hi>Oxford
                        and New York: Oxford University Press, 2015.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Hösler, Joachim.
                        <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Von Krain zu Slowenien: die Anfänge der nationalen Differenzierungsprozesse in Krain und der Untersteiermark von der Aufklärung bis zur Revolution. 1768 bis 1848. </hi>München:
                        R. Oldenbourg, 2006.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Hepe, Boštjan, Katarina Janjič, Stanislav Mikuž and Ivan Živko. <hi
                            rend="italic">Zgodovina carine na Slovenskem od antike do slovenske
                            osamosvojitve</hi>. Ljubljana: Carinska uprava RS, 2011.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Hroch, Miroslav. <hi rend="italic">Das Europa der Nationen: Die moderne
                            Nationsbildung im europäischen Vergleich</hi>. Göttingen: Vandenhoeck
                        &amp; Ruprecht, 2005. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Kidrič, France. <hi rend="italic">Dobrovský in slovenski preporod njegove
                            dobe</hi>. Ljubljana: Znanstveno društvo, 1930.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Kidrič, France. <hi rend="italic">Zoisova korespondenca (1809–1810)</hi>.
                        Ljubljana: Akademija znanosti in umetnosti, 1941.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Kordiš, Ivan. "Peter Kozler and His Map of the Slovenian Land and Its
                        Provinces (1849–1871)." <hi rend="italic">Imago Mundi</hi>, 68, no. 2
                        (2016): 212–31.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Kokolj, Miroslav. <hi rend="italic">Prekmurski Slovenci od narodne
                            osvoboditve do nacistične okupacije: 1919–1941</hi>. Murska Sobota:
                        Pomurska založba, 1984.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Kosi, Jernej. <hi rend="italic">Kako je nastal slovenski narod. Začetki
                            slovenskega nacionalnega gibanja v prvi polovici 19. stoletja</hi>.
                        Ljubljana: Sophia, 2013.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Leersen, Joep. <hi rend="italic">National Thought in Europe: A Cultural
                            History</hi>. Amsterdam: Amsterdam University Press, 2006.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Lipušček, Uroš. <hi rend="italic">Ave Wilson: ZDA in prekrajanje Slovenije
                            v Versaillesu 1919-1920</hi>. Ljubljana: Založba Sophia, 2003.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Lončar, Dragotin. "Anton Globočnik in slovenski narodni program 1848.
                        leta." <hi rend="italic">Carniola: Izvestja muzejskega društva za
                            Kranjsko</hi> 3, no. 3 (1912): 208, 209.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Lončarić, Mijo and Anita Celinić. "Susret slovenskih prekmurskih i
                        hrvatskih međimurskih govora." <hi rend="italic">Slavistična revija</hi> 55
                        (2007): 41–46.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Lukan, Walter. <hi rend="italic">Iz "črnožolte kletke narodov" v "zlato
                            svobodo"? Habsburška monarhija in Slovenci v prvi svetovni vojni</hi>.
                        Ljubljana: Znanstvena založba FF, 2014.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Mohorič, Fran. "Prekmurje in Medjimurje." <hi rend="italic">Časopis za
                            zgodovino in narodopisje</hi> 16 (1920): 28–40.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Moritsch, Andreas and Vincenc Rajšp, ed. <hi rend="italic">Matija
                            Majar-Ziljski</hi>. Klagenfurt: Hermagoras, 1995.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Mosse, George L. <hi rend="italic">Fallen soldiers: reshaping the memory
                            of the world wars</hi>. Oxford: Oxford University Press, 1990.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Prunk, Janko. <hi rend="italic">Slovenski narodni programi: narodni
                            programi v slovenski politični misli od 1848 do 1945</hi>. Ljubljana:
                        Društvo 2000, 1986.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Schulze, Hagen. <hi rend="italic">States, Nations, and Nationalism: From
                            the Middle Ages to the Present</hi>. Oxford: Blackwell Publishing, 1996. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Stergar, Nataša. "Narodnostno vprašanje v predmarčnih letnikih
                        Bleiweisovih Novic." <hi rend="italic">Kronika: časopis za slovensko
                            krajevno zgodovino</hi> 25, no. 3 (1977): 184–89.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Slavič, Matija. <hi rend="italic">Naše Prekmurje: zbrane razprave in
                            članki</hi>. Murska Sobota: Pomurska založba, 1999.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Šekli, Matej. "Zemljepisnojezikoslovna členitev kajkavščine ter
                        slovensko-kajkavska jezikovna meja."
                        <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Slovenski jezik – Slovene Linguistic Studies </hi>9
                        (2013): 3–53.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Štih, Peter. "Salzburg, Ptuj in nastanek štajersko-madžarske meje v
                        današnji Sloveniji." <hi rend="italic">Zgodovinski časopis</hi> 50, no. 4
                        (1996): 535–44.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Thürer, Daniel and Thomas Burri. "Self-Determination." <hi rend="italic"
                            >Max Planck Encyclopedia of Public International Law</hi>. Accessed
                        October 20, 2015. <ref
                            target="http://opil.ouplaw.com/view/10.1093/law:epil/9780199231690/law-9780199231690-e873?rskey=YVjdhp&amp;result=1&amp;prd=EPIL"
                            >http://opil.ouplaw.com/view/10.1093/law:epil/9780199231690/law-9780199231690-e873?rskey=YVjdhp&amp;result=1&amp;prd=EPIL</ref><hi
                            rend="Hyperlink">.</hi></bibl>
                    <bibl>Vidmar, Luka. <hi rend="italic">A Slavic Republic of Letters. The
                            Correspondence between Jernej Kopitar and Baron Žiga Zois</hi>
                        (Frankfurt am Main: Peter Lang, 2016).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Weber, Eugen. <hi rend="italic">Peasants into Frenchmen</hi>. Stanford:
                        Stanford University Press, 1976.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Wolf, Eric J. <hi rend="italic">Europe and the People Without
                        History</hi>. 2<hi rend="superscript">nd</hi> edition. Berkeley and Los
                        Angeles: University of California, 2010.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Zajc, Marko. <hi rend="italic">Kje se slovensko neha in hrvaško začne:
                            slovensko-hrvaška meja v 19. in na začetku 20. stoletja</hi>. Ljubljana:
                        Modrijan, 2006.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Zimmer, Oliver. <hi rend="italic">Nationalism in Europe, 1890-1940</hi>.
                        London: Palgrave, 2003.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Newspaper sources:</head>
                    <bibl><hi rend="italic">Kmetijske in rokodelske Novice</hi>, March 11, 1846.
                        "Proglas zastran noviga slovenskiga slovnika in slovnice." </bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="italic">Kmetijske in rokodelske Novice,</hi> April 21, 1847.
                        "Slovenski besédnik za poduk in kratek čas." </bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="italic">Slovenija</hi>, July 10, 1849. "Slovenci na Ogrskim." </bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="italic">Slovenski gospodar</hi>, September 1, 1926. "Prekmurje –
                        Slovenska Krajina." Accessed December 20, 2015. <ref
                            target="http://www.dlib.si/?URN=URN:NBN:SI:DOC-FW15RFZE%20"
                            >http://www.dlib.si/?URN=URN:NBN:SI:DOC-FW15RFZE</ref>.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Other sources:</head>
                    <bibl>Czörnig, Carl. <hi rend="italic">Ethnographie der österreichischen
                            Monarchie</hi>. Wien, 1855.</bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="italic">Historische Bildpostkarten - 14.8 Bildpostkarten/Gegen
                            welsche Tücke und Raubgier!.</hi> Accessed December 16, 2015. <ref
                            target="http://www.bildpostkarten.uni-osnabrueck.de/displayimage.php?album=102&amp;pos=87"
                            >http://www.bildpostkarten.uni-osnabrueck.de/displayimage.php?album=102&amp;pos=87</ref><hi
                            rend="Hyperlink">.</hi></bibl>
                    <bibl>Kos, Janko, ed. <hi rend="italic">Izbrano delo / Jernej Kopitar, Matija
                            Čop</hi>. Ljubljana: Mladinska knjiga, 1973.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Kozler, Peter. <hi rend="italic">Kratek slovenski zemljopis in pregled
                            politične in pravosodne razdelitve ilirskega kraljestva in štajerskega
                            vojvodstva s pridanim slovenskim in nemškim imenikom mest, tergov,
                            krajev i.t.d.</hi> Ljubljana: Cankarjeva založba, 1975.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Primic, Janez Nepomuk. <hi rend="italic">Némshko-Slovénske branja =
                            Deutsch-Slovenisches Lesebuch</hi>. Graz, 1813.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Primic, Janez Nepomuk. <hi rend="italic">Novi némshko-slovénshki bukvar,
                            al A. B. C. otrokon léhko sastoplen = Neues Slovenisch-Deutsches der
                            Fassungskraft der Kinder angemessenes A. B. C. : welches auserlesene,
                            leichte und belehrende Aufgaben, Erzählungen und Unterhaltungen
                            enthält.</hi> Graz, 1814.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Raič, Božidar. "Črtice o Prekmurcih in o njihovem govoru." In: <hi
                            rend="italic">Narodni koledar in letopis matice slovenske za leto
                            1868</hi>, 53–76. Ljubljana: Matica Slovenska, 1867.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Renan, Ernest. "What is a Nation?." In: <hi rend="italic">Becoming
                            National: A Reader</hi>, ed. Geoff Eley and Ronald Grigor Suny, 41–55.
                        New York and Oxford: Oxford University Press, 1996. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Šuman, Josip. <hi rend="italic">Die Slovenen</hi>. Dunaj, Teschen: K.
                        Prochaska, 1881.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Trstenjak, Anton. "Ogrski Slovenci." <hi rend="italic">Ljubljanski
                            zvon</hi> 21 (1901): 173–78, 240–43, 313–16.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Urbas, Viljem. <hi rend="italic">Die Slovenen: etnographische Skizze</hi>.
                        Trieste, 1870.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Vodnik, Valentin. <hi rend="italic">Zbrano delo</hi>. Ed. Janko Kos.
                        Ljubljana: DZS, 1988.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
            <div type="summary" xml:lang="sl">
                <docAuthor>Jernej Kosi</docAuthor>
                <head>"KER SE PA JEZIK TU PO MALEM SPREMENUJE, IN JE TOLIKO KRAJNIH NAREČIJ, SE
                    HERVAŠKI IN SORODNI SLOVENSKI SVET NE MORETA PRAV NA TANJKO S POTEZO LOČITI" –
                    ZAČRTOVANJE SLOVENSKO-HRVAŠKE NACIONALNE MEJE NA PODROČJU DANAŠNJEGA
                    PREKMURJA</head>
                <head>POVZETEK</head>
                <p>V članku obravnavam proces nastajanja zamisli o meji med "slovenskim" in
                    "hrvaškim" nacionalnim ozemljem na področju zahodne Ogrske. Zamisel je bila
                    sprva artikulirana kot jezikovna premisa v delih slavnega jezikoslovca Jerneja
                    Kopitarja, ki je ozemlje današnjega Prekmurja razumel kot prostor, kjer se
                    govori slovenski jezik. Od srede 19. stoletja naprej je Kopitarjevo
                    klasifikacijo apropriiralo slovensko nacionalno gibanje, ki je predpostavljalo,
                    da so govorci slovenskega jezika na Ogrskem tudi pripadniki zamišljene slovenske
                    skupnosti. V tem kontekstu je bila slovenska jezikovna – nacionalna meja sredi
                    19. stoletja prvič upodobljena na zemljevidu (Peter Kozler). V vsega nekaj
                    desetletjih se je predstava o nacionalni ločnici v današnjem Prekmurju, ki da v
                    odnosu do Hrvatov poteka po reki Muri, dodobra utrdila med slovenskimi
                    nacionalnimi aktivisti na področju cislajtanskih dežel. Ob razpadu Avstro-Ogrske
                    in po podpisu trianonske mirovne pogodbe pa je tudi dejansko začela razmejevati
                    slovenski nacionalni prostor od sosednjega hrvaškega.</p>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
