<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Passing of Stalin Is Not the End, or the Unstoppable Integration of the
                    Socialist Market</title>
                <author>
                    <forename>Ondřej</forename>
                    <surname>Fišer</surname>
                    <roleName>Ph.D.</roleName>
                    <affiliation>Coordinator at the Institute for Study Abroad (Butler
                        University)</affiliation>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Havlickovy sady 58</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>Prague</addrLine>
                    </address>
                    <email>fiserondrej1@gmail.com</email>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>2023-04-14</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>
                    <orgName xml:lang="sl">Inštitut za novejšo zgodovino</orgName>
                    <orgName xml:lang="en">Institute of Contemporary History</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Privoz 11</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>SI-1000 Ljubljana</addrLine>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>http://ojs.inz.si/pnz/article/view/4155</pubPlace>
                <date>2023</date>
                <availability status="free">
                    <licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title xml:lang="sl">Prispevki za novejšo zgodovino</title>
                <title xml:lang="en">Contributions to Contemporary History</title>
                <biblScope unit="volume">63</biblScope>
                <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
                <idno type="ISSN">2463-7807</idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source, born digital.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc xml:lang="en">
                <p>Contributions to Contemporary History is one of the central Slovenian scientific
                    historiographic journals, dedicated to publishing articles from the field of
                    contemporary history (the 19th, 20th and 21st century).</p>
                <p>The journal is published three times per year in Slovenian and in the following
                    foreign languages: English, German, Serbian, Croatian, Bosnian, Italian, Slovak
                    and Czech. The articles are all published with abstracts in English and
                    Slovenian as well as summaries in English.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <projectDesc xml:lang="sl">
                <p>Prispevki za novejšo zgodovino je ena osrednjih slovenskih znanstvenih
                    zgodovinopisnih revij, ki objavlja teme s področja novejše zgodovine (19. 20. in 21.
                    stoletje).</p>
                <p>Revija izide trikrat letno v slovenskem jeziku in v naslednjih tujih jezikih:
                    angleščina, nemščina, srbščina, hrvaščina, bosanščina, italijanščina, slovaščina
                    in češčina. Članki izhajajo z izvlečki v angleščini in slovenščini ter povzetki
                    v angleščini.</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="sl"/>
                <language ident="en"/>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords xml:lang="en">
                    <term>USSR</term>
                    <term>Czechoslovakia</term>
                    <term>Cold War</term>
                    <term>economic cooperation</term>
                    <term>scientific-technical cooperation</term>
                    <term>trade</term>
                    <term>CMEA</term>
                    <term>COMECON</term>
                    <term>Antonín Novotný</term>
                    <term>Khrushchev Thaw</term>
                    <term>de-Stalinization</term>
                    <term>Prague Spring</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords xml:lang="sl">
                    <term>ZSSR</term>
                    <term>Češkoslovaška</term>
                    <term>hladna vojna</term>
                    <term>gospodarsko sodelovanje</term>
                    <term>znanstveno-tehnično sodelovanje</term>
                    <term>trgovina</term>
                    <term>SEV (CMEA / COMECON)</term>
                    <term>Antonín Novotný</term>
                    <term>Hruščova otoplitev</term>
                    <term>destalinizacija</term>
                    <term>praška pomlad</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change><date>2023-05-15T08:33:29Z</date><name>Mihael Ojsteršek</name></change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <docAuthor>Ondřej Fišer<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn1" n="*">Ph.D., Coordinator at the
                    Institute for Study Abroad (Butler University), Havlickovy sady 58, Prague; <ref
                        target="mailto:fiserondrej1@gmail.com"><hi rend="bold"
                            >fiserondrej1@gmail.com</hi></ref></note></docAuthor>
            <docImprint>
                <idno type="cobissType">Cobiss tip: 1.01</idno>
                <idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.51663/pnz.63.1.08</idno>
            </docImprint>
            <div type="abstract">
                <head>IZVLEČEK</head>
                <head>STALINOVA SMRT NE POMENI KONCA ALI NEZADRŽNA INTEGRACIJA
                        SOCIALISTIČNEGA TRGA</head>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Članek obravnava razvoj gospodarskega sodelovanja na
                        socialističnem trgu med letoma 1953 in 1968 z vidika češkoslovaškega
                        gospodarstva. Obdobje, ko je bil Antonín Novotný na čelu češkoslovaške
                        komunistične partije, je doslej veljalo za kontroverzno, saj so ga
                        zaznamovala prizadevanja za reformo stalinističnih anahronizmov, sprva pa
                        tudi težave pri zagotavljanju, da bi se te reforme trajno ukoreninile v
                        neugodnih razmerah hladne vojne. Vprašanje je, ali je tako imenovana
                        “Hruščova otoplitev”, ki se je pospešeno začela v drugi polovici petdesetih
                        let dvajsetega stoletja, omogočila, da so se nekatere reforme vendarle
                        začele izvajati in so dolgoročno obrodile sadove. Vprašati se je treba tudi
                        o naravi ključnih akterjev in ovir v postopku reformiranja sodelovanja
                        znotraj bloka. Pri raziskovanju teh vprašanj smo preučili zlasti arhive
                        češkoslovaških ministrstev za industrijo v Pragi.</hi></p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Ključne besede: ZSSR, Češkoslovaška, hladna vojna, gospodarsko
                        sodelovanje, znanstveno-tehnično sodelovanje, trgovina, SEV (CMEA /
                        COMECON), Antonín Novotný, Hruščova otoplitev, destalinizacija, praška
                        pomlad</hi></p>
            </div>
            <div type="abstract" xml:lang="en">
                <head>ABSTRACT</head>
                <p><hi rend="italic">This article deals with the development of economic cooperation
                        in the socialist market between 1953 and 1968 from the perspective of the
                        Czechoslovak economy. The period of Antonín Novotný at the helm of the
                        Czechoslovak Communist Party was a controversial one, as it was
                        characterized by both the efforts to reform Stalinist anachronisms and the
                        initially low capacity to sustainably root these reforms in the fragile
                        frozen ground of Cold War-era soil. The question is whether the gradually
                        unfolding Khrushchev Thaw that accelerated its onset from the second half of
                        the 1950s onwards made it possible to plant certain reforms and reap their
                        fruits in the longer term. It is also necessary to raise the question of the
                        nature of the key actors and obstacles in the process of reforming
                        intra-bloc cooperation. In particular, the archives of the Czechoslovak
                        industrial ministries located in Prague were consulted to research these
                        issues.</hi></p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Keywords: USSR, Czechoslovakia, Cold War, economic cooperation,
                        scientific-technical cooperation, trade, CMEA, COMECON, Antonín Novotný,
                        Khrushchev Thaw, de-Stalinization, Prague Spring</hi></p>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div>
                <head>Introduction</head>
                <p>Czech historiography of the early post-Velvet Revolution period seemed to
                    relegate questions of Czechoslovak communist-era intra-bloc economic cooperation
                    to the margins of its research interest. However, as new archival findings
                    indicate, understanding this aspect of the past may be a necessary prerequisite
                    not only for a correct interpretation of the Czechoslovak domestic economic
                    history, but also of the general history of the Cold War, the socialist market,
                    the Council for Mutual Economic Assistance (CMEA), East-West cooperation and
                    other closely related topics. </p>
                <p>Although a wide range of secondary sources from the 1960s-1980s, represented by
                    the studies of Bogomolov, Horský and Ernst, provide an analysis of intra-bloc
                    trade during the Novotný era, their reasoning was often produced under the
                    influence of ideology and the interpretation of their conclusions must therefore
                    be approached with caution and a certain amount of skepticism.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn2" n="1">O. Bogomolov, “Economic Cooperation among the Comecon
                        Countries,” <hi rend="italic">Eastern European Economics</hi> 2, no. 4
                        (1964): 3–10, <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1080/00128775.1964.11647864"
                            >https://doi.org/10.1080/00128775.1964.11647864</ref>. J. Horský, “The
                        Structure of Czechoslovak Foreign Trade and Prospects of Modifying It,” <hi
                            rend="italic">Soviet and Eastern European Foreign Trade</hi> 6, no.3/4
                        (1970): 268-83 . Miloslav Ernst, <hi rend="italic">Czechoslovakia and
                            International Economic Cooperation</hi> (Prague: Orbis, 1987).</note> In
                    this context, one of the major tasks of Czechoslovak contemporary historiography
                    is to use archival findings to subject these secondary sources to review and
                    objectify their conclusions. This is the case of this article, which aims to
                    review the main characteristics of Czechoslovak economic cooperation with
                    socialist countries in the period from Gottwald's death and Novotný's accession
                    to the post of First Secretary of the Central Committee of the Communist Party
                    of Czechoslovakia (<hi rend="italic">první tajemník Ústředního výboru
                        Komunistické strany Československa</hi>) in 1953 until his dismissal in
                    1968.</p>
                <p>Special attention is paid to the analysis of several key aspects of Czechoslovak
                    intra-bloc cooperation. Firstly, this concerns the actors that shaped the
                    overall system of trade and the individual flow of goods. Therefore a
                    (re-)evaluation of the influence of the CMEA seems to be an unavoidable task.
                    The aim here is to analyze the trading model of the Council from a new
                    perspective that is not biased by the downfall of the socialist economic system
                    or by the misinterpretation of historical sources produced under the influence
                    of communist ideology.</p>
                <p>Despite the officially maintained pro-Eastern course of the Czechoslovak economy,
                    the Novotný era was characterized by a gradual expansion of inter-bloc trade. As
                    CMEA archival records show, the process of partial pro-Western reorientation was
                    not only a result of the targeted development of East-West ties but was to a
                    large extent driven by the formation of cooperation within the Socialist Bloc.
                    This article’s goal is to use the analysis of Czechoslovak intra-bloc engagement
                    to conduct a more objective evaluation of inter-bloc ties.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn3" n="2">Abram Bergson, “The Geometry of Comecon Trade,” <hi
                            rend="italic">European Economic Review</hi> 14, no. 3 (1980): 291–306,
                            <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1016/s0014-2921(80)80002-x"
                            >https://doi.org/10.1016/s0014-2921(80)80002-x</ref>.</note> The central
                    object of interest is the CMEA, since its impact on the development of East-West
                    relations remains a hitherto unsettled subject of heated debate among
                    contemporary historians.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn4" n="3">Emil Hoffmann,
                            <hi rend="italic">COMECON: Der gemeinsame Markt in Osteuropa</hi>
                        (Opladen: C. W. Leske, 1961), 17–19. Andrzej Korbonski, “Theory and Practice
                        of Regional Integration: The Case of Comecon,” <hi rend="italic"
                            >International Organization </hi>24, no. 4 (1970): 942–77, <ref
                            target="https://doi.org/10.1017/s0020818300017574"
                            >https://doi.org/10.1017/s0020818300017574</ref>.</note>
                </p>
                <p>An analysis of Czechoslovak intra-bloc cooperation is also necessary for a
                    comprehensive evaluation of domestic economic transformations. As the
                    Czechoslovak economy was the most advanced in the Eastern Bloc, the Kremlin
                    assigned its industrial ministries the role of the main providers of economic
                    and scientific-technical assistance to other less developed socialist
                        countries.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn5" n="4">Lee K. Metcalf, “The Impact
                        of Foreign Trade on the Czechoslovak Economic Reforms of the 1960s,” <hi
                            rend="italic">Europe-Asia Studies</hi> 45, no. 6 (1993): 1071–90.</note>
                    The consequence of this imposed role was a two-fold reorientation from the West
                    to the East as well as from a consumer-oriented economy to a heavy industrial
                    one. Most of the Novotný era continued to be characterized by processes that
                    accompanied and followed this reorientation. In this regard, this article aims
                    to contribute to our understanding of the impact of these transformations on the
                    Czechoslovak economic system and its commercial ties <hi rend="italic"
                        >vis-à-vis</hi> the CMEA market. Particular emphasis is placed on whether
                    these transformation processes were entirely the result of top-imposed pressures
                    from the Communist Party of the Soviet Union (CPSU) and other CMEA leaders, or
                    whether they partially arose as a product of Czechoslovak autochthonous
                    developments.</p>
                <p>Furthermore, although contemporary historiography often treats Czechoslovak
                    intra-bloc cooperation in the Novotný era as an immutable phenomenon, new
                    findings point to a number of its previously undescribed aspects that indicate
                    the desirability of its more detailed periodization. The archives of
                    Czechoslovak industrial ministries, supplemented by data from different archives
                    of selected international organizations (the United Nations Economic Commission
                    for Europe (UN ECE), the CMEA, the Warsaw Pact, etc.), prove to be of particular
                        importance.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn6" n="5">Archives of the Ministry
                        of Foreign Affairs, MO-T, 1945-1955, carton 5. Libor Budinský, <hi
                            rend="italic">Deset prezidentů</hi> (Prague: Knižní klub, 2008). Václav
                        Průcha, <hi rend="italic">Hospodářské a sociální dějiny Československa
                            1918-1992: 2. díl. Období 1945-1992</hi> (Brno: Doplněk, 2009).</note> A
                    more in-depth periodization is necessary to clarify the inconsistent
                    interpretation of the Czechoslovak intra-bloc cooperation between Bogomolov, who
                    emphasizes the positive evolution of commercial exchange within the Eastern
                    Bloc, and Korbonski who points to the existence of fundamental
                    stagnation-generating aspects of the socialist cooperation model.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn7" n="6">Hoffmann, <hi rend="italic">COMECON.</hi>
                        Bogomolov, “Economic Cooperation among the Comecon Countries.” Korbonski,
                        “Theory and Practice of Regional Integration: The Case of Comecon.” See also
                        Karel Kaplan, <hi rend="italic">Rada vzájemné hospodářské pomoci a
                            Československo</hi>, <hi rend="italic">1957-1967</hi> (Prague: Karolinum Press,
                        2002), 94–107.</note> Given that the transformations that characterized this
                    period emerged both as a result of domestic political-economic processes and as
                    a consequence of international developments on both sides of the Iron Curtain,
                    their analysis and the following more detailed periodization need to be
                    implemented in a multifactorial way.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn8" n="7">Yale
                        Richmond, <hi rend="italic">Cultural Exchange &amp; the Cold War</hi> (Philadelphia: Penn
                        State University Press, 2003).</note>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>The Hardly Enforcable de-Stalinization</head>
                <p>The process of political de-Stalinization in Czechoslovakia proceeded in many
                    respects at an unsatisfactorily slow pace, which suppressed reformist voices
                    within the CCP leadership and made it impossible to take full advantage of the
                    growing opportunities offered by the onset of the Khrushchev Thaw.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn9" n="8">Karel Kaplan, <hi rend="italic"
                            >Československo v letech 1953-1966</hi> (Prague: SPN, 1992), 4. Jaromír
                        Procházka, <hi rend="italic">Poválečné Československo 1945-1989</hi>
                        (Prague: Karolinum, 1991), 77.</note> This was reflected, among others, in
                    the rigid maintenance of the system of autarky, which particularly between 1953
                    and 1955, continued to limit the potential of Czechoslovak intra-bloc
                        trade.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn10" n="9">Procházka, <hi rend="italic"
                            >Poválečné Československo</hi>, 77.</note> Moreover, it should be
                    emphasized that the reforms implemented in 1948-1953 forced the Zápotocký
                    government to invest heavily in the development of unprofitable sectors, which
                    significantly hindered the competitiveness and foreign trade capacities of the
                    Czechoslovak economy well into the early Novotný era.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn11" n="10">Karel Kaplan, <hi rend="italic">Československo v RVHP
                            1949-1956</hi> (Prague: ÚSD AV ČR, 1995), 175–85. National Archives,
                        finding aid 1204, fond 953, inventory no. 27, signature 056.1, carton 21,
                        inventory no. 28, signature 056.2. Erik Radisch, “The Struggle of the Soviet
                        Conception of Comecon, 1953-1957,” <hi rend="italic">Comparativ –
                            Zeitschrift für Globalgeschichte und vergleichende
                            Gesellschaftsforschung</hi> 27, no. 5/6 (2017): 29–33.</note>
                </p>
                <p>These findings clearly indicate that the starting point for the strengthening of
                    intra-bloc cooperation in the early post-Gottwald era was far from optimal.
                    However, although it took Czechoslovak leadership over 10 years to adopt a more
                    viable system of intra-bloc trade, early attempts to improve the worsening
                    position of Czechoslovak exports on the CMEA market were launched as early as
                        1953.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn12" n="11">Kaplan, <hi rend="italic"
                            >Československo v letech 1953-1966</hi>, 11.</note> The first important
                    measure adopted after Gottwald's death was monetary reform, which was intended
                    among others, to restore the balance of market supply and financial flows and
                    indirectly to strengthen the export capacity of the Czechoslovak consumer
                    sector. However, the consequences of the adopted measures were not anticipated
                    by the CCP leadership. The reform led to a substantial devaluation of domestic
                    savings and a further decrease in living standards. Its direct impact on
                    strengthening the position of Czechoslovak exports in the Eastern Bloc was
                    minimal. </p>
                <p>Yet, from a certain perspective, the monetary restructuring of 1953 had a
                    positive effect on transforming the stagnant <hi rend="italic">status quo</hi>.
                    The botched reform resulted in growing discontent of all citizens, especially
                    factory workers, who initiated uprisings and forced the Central Committee to
                    introduce further pro-trade measures, which became known as the “New Course”.
                    One of the main objectives of this reform package was to resolve the decline in
                    Czechoslovak intra-bloc exports that emerged due to the easing of international
                    tensions and the consequent reduction of interest in Czechoslovak arms and heavy
                    industry. The Široký administration therefore provided new investments in the
                    sectors of agriculture, electrical engineering and consumer industry, as these
                    were believed to alleviate both the domestic economic crisis as well as the
                    growing imbalance of Czechoslovak intra-bloc trade.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn13" n="12">Průcha, <hi rend="italic">Hospodářské a sociální
                            dějiny Československa 1918-1992,</hi> 285–88.</note> However, the
                    well-intended reforms of the New Course largely missed the mark. As Kaplan
                    points out, similar measures aimed at the transformation of economic capacities
                    were introduced in other countries of the Eastern Bloc, which led to a
                    significant disruption of trade agreements and a slowdown in intra-bloc flows of
                        goods.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn14" n="13">Kaplan, <hi
                            rend="italic">Československo v letech 1953-1966</hi>, 20–22.</note>
                    Moreover, the Czechoslovak New Course largely failed to transform the
                    composition of the export portfolio, since despite the rapid decline in the
                    importance of heavy industry after Stalin's death, Novotný with the support of
                    Malenkov's CPSU circles, continued to build an image of Czechoslovakia as the
                    main supplier of arms and heavy industry equipment to the entire Eastern
                        Bloc.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn15" n="14">National Archives, finding aid
                        1109, fond 935, inventory no. 122–135, cartons 79–87.</note>
                </p>
                <p>Thus, although the New Course reforms strived to refocus on strengthening the
                    intra-bloc trade in traditional economic sectors, due to persistent Stalinist
                    tendencies, the end of the first half of the 1950s was marked by the
                    reintroduction of the Gottwald-era system of Czechoslovak foreign trade. As a
                    result, Kaplan indicates that expenditure on the modernization of the
                    Czechoslovak army once again increased, and Czechoslovak FTEs made renewed
                    efforts to maintain high export rates of heavy industry products.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn16" n="15">Kaplan, <hi rend="italic">Československo
                            v letech 1953-1966</hi>, 20–28, 127, 128.</note>
                </p>
                <p>Even in the mid-1950s, when East-West trade opportunities were booming, the
                    Czechoslovak economy remained oriented toward socialist markets. The extent to
                    which the predominant commercial focus toward the East can be regarded as a
                    “domestic decision” or an “external imposition” remains a target of discussion
                    between contemporary historians. Procházka supplemented by archives of
                    Czechoslovak industrial ministries as well as those of the Czechoslovak Ministry
                    of Foreign Trade (<hi rend="italic">Ministerstvo zahraničního obchodu</hi>)
                    demonstrate several cases where further intensification of intra-bloc trade was
                    caused by the reluctance of the West to trade with Czechoslovakia rather than by
                    the decision of Czechoslovak economic leaders.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn17"
                        n="16">Zdeněk Procházka, <hi rend="italic">Hospodářská válka USA proti
                            Československu</hi> (Prague: Vojenská politická akademie, 1960), 102–13.
                        National Archives, archival aid 835, fond 936, inventory no. 156,
                        československé aktivity na mezinárodních veletrzích, jednání s
                        kapitalistickými státy. See also Archives of the Ministry of Foreign
                        Affairs, MO-OMO, 1955–1956, carton 85.</note> For example, the Czechoslovak
                    Ministry of Foreign Trade agreed to import spare parts for the aviation industry
                    from the USA, but as the American government decided to suspend all eastward
                    deliveries of these goods, Czechoslovak FTEs were forced to import them from the
                        USSR.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn18" n="17">National Archives, finding aid
                        835, fond 936, inventory no. 71; also consult Archives of the Ministry of
                        Foreign Affairs, MEO-O, 1945-1955, carton 52. Procházka, <hi rend="italic"
                            >Hospodářská válka USA proti Československu</hi>.</note> On the other
                    hand, Jackson presents a rather proactive pro-Eastern image of the Western Bloc.
                    In his view, the United Kingdom in particular was at the forefront of the
                    development of inter-bloc trade, and it was the unyielding, politicized
                    standpoints of the Czechoslovak government that were seen as the major cause of
                    the failure to develop closer inter-bloc ties.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn19"
                        n="18">Ian Jackson, <hi rend="italic">The Economic Cold War: America,
                            Britain and East-West Trade, 1948–63</hi> (Cold War History Series) (New
                        York: Palgrave, 2001).</note> Similar contradictory observations are
                    presented by Kaplan, who on the one hand argues that the Czechoslovak government
                    used the “power vacuum” that emerged after the deaths of Stalin and Gottwald and
                    tried to increase its commercial activities outside the CMEA, yet on the other
                    hand presents evidence of persistent Czechoslovak loyalty to Khrushchev's vision
                    of close intra-bloc cooperation.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn20" n="19">
                        Kaplan, <hi rend="italic">Československo v letech 1953-1966</hi>,
                        28.</note> </p>
                <p>These limited findings suggest that the existence of a divergence between
                    political-ideological rationale and practical economic needs was also visible in
                    the case of Czechoslovak economic cooperation in the early post-Gottwald era.
                    However, due to the overly slow de-Stalinization of the Czechoslovak political
                    environment in 1953-1954, the practical needs of the economy were at that time
                    unable to override the crucial importance of political loyalty leading to the
                    maintenance of the main orientation of Czechoslovak foreign trade towards the
                    CMEA market.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn21" n="20">Jindřich Jirka, and
                        Jaroslav Volný, <hi rend="italic">Československé strojírenství doma i za
                            hranicemi</hi> (Prague, 1959), 122.</note>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Crisis of the CMEA Model</head>
                <p>At the beginning of the second half of the 1950s, the situation in the CMEA
                    market began to change radically as a result of intensified disruptions to the
                    existing intra-bloc trading model. As archives of the CCP Central Committee
                    reveal, the inability and/or unwillingness of some of the Czechoslovak CMEA
                    partners to respect long-term trade agreements increased, which especially in
                    the period 1955-1956, led to short-term declines in intra-bloc trade. The
                    Czechoslovak Minister of Foreign Trade Richard Dvořák blamed the changing
                    preferences of socialist governments, whose leaders focused more on increasing
                    the standard of living in their countries than on fulfilling their trade
                        obligations.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn22" n="21">National Archives,
                        archiv ÚV KSČ, fond 01, schůze 6. - 7. 10. 1954.</note> The issues in
                    intra-bloc trade at that time forced Czechoslovak FTEs to search for alternative
                    sources of raw materials and production inputs both in the West and in the
                    Global South.</p>
                <p>Although many Czechoslovak historians, including Průcha, do not attribute a
                    significant role to the activities of individual CMEA bodies in the stagnation
                    of intra-bloc trade in the early second half of the 1950s, archives of the
                    Czechoslovak Ministry of Chemical Industry (<hi rend="italic">Ministerstvo
                        chemického průmyslu</hi>) indicate otherwise.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn23" n="22">Průcha, <hi rend="italic">Hospodářské a sociální
                            dějiny Československa 1918-1992</hi>.</note> The power vacuum that
                    emerged after the death of Stalin resulted in the absence of a clear CMEA vision
                    of intra-bloc trade. The various bodies of the Council found themselves in a
                    state of crisis as their formerly directive approach suddenly lacked
                    justification. This situation led to the exploitation by individual member
                    states, who began to act more independently and adopted a rather dilatory and
                    lax approach to fulfilling their intra-bloc trade obligations. The following
                    disruptions in mutual deliveries led especially the more developed socialist
                    economies, including Czechoslovakia, East Germany and to a certain extent
                    Poland, to initiate new cooperation projects with the intention of overcoming
                    the negative consequences of post-Stalinist lethargy. These projects, negotiated
                    through newly emerging bilateral, trilateral and multilateral channels, were
                    introduced to ensure the fulfilment of previously closed agreements, coordinate
                    production and trade plans and improve the system of scientific-technical
                        assistance.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn24" n="23">National Archives,
                        finding aid 1208, fond 967, inventory no. 482, cartons 636<hi rend="italic"
                            >–</hi>38.</note>
                </p>
                <p>However, as Kaplan shows in his extensive study of Czechoslovak participation in
                    the work of the CMEA, especially the multilateral projects often proved
                    unsuccessful. On this topic, the Chairman of the Czechoslovak State Planning
                    Office (<hi rend="italic">Státní úřad plánovací</hi>) Otakar Šimůnek expressed
                    his dissatisfaction even with the approach of more developed socialist economies
                    at the 6<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> CMEA Session in 1955. For example,
                    representatives of Poland were criticized for their reluctance to implement CMEA
                    recommendations on trade in coking coal. Polish trade negotiators offered
                    quantities approximately 25% lower than the CMEA recommended, while in return
                    demanding goods such as cotton that were not available in Czechoslovakia.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn25" n="24">Kaplan, <hi rend="italic">Československo
                            v RVHP 1949-1956</hi>, 197 <hi rend="italic">–</hi>205.</note> The
                    position of Polish representatives, points to the fact that even similarly
                    developed CMEA members occasionally pursued substantially different
                    visions of intra-bloc trade in the mid-1950s. </p>
                <p>However, it would be wrong to assume that the Czechoslovak leadership in contrast
                    to other socialist countries, accepted all CMEA proposals and thus placed the
                    interests of the Bloc above its own economic needs. Although the Czechoslovak
                    delegation was among the most proactive ones in the Council, it was by no means
                    a blind follower of all of its recommendations. If there were major unexpected
                    requirements on the Czechoslovak economy or if the volume and specifications of
                    pre-negotiated items to be traded radically changed, the Czechoslovak
                    negotiators requested a revision of the Council’s standpoints. For example, at
                    meetings of national planning authorities, the Soviet delegation repeatedly
                    promised to increase iron ore supplies, but later withdrew its commitments at
                    the 6<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> CMEA Session.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn26" n="25">Ibidem, 482, 483.</note> These unexpected changes then
                    became a target of Czechoslovak protests, as they seriously endangered the
                    fulfilment of national five-year plans.</p>
                <p>A similarly problematic factor in the development of intra-bloc trade was CMEA
                    reform that took place between 1955 and 1956. At this point it is necessary to
                    note that despite the relative merit of the newly established permanent
                    commissions, the reformed CMEA continued to struggle with the politicization of
                    its work, authoritarian interference from Moscow, diverging objectives of
                    individual members and other challenges that prevented it from implementing a
                    successful model of intra-bloc trade in the second half of the 1950s. Even the
                    pivotal decision to focus the work of the Council on coordinating production and
                    trade plans taken in May 1956 did not significantly improve the situation. As
                    the archives of the CCP Politburo show, although this decision partially
                    coincided with the long-standing efforts of the Czechoslovak government to
                    strengthen exports to the East by preventing the emergence of competing
                    industries, Viliam Široký, possibly after the negative experience of the
                    previous years, did not place high hopes in the CMEA plan and preferred to
                    target the unsatisfactory situation in Czechoslovak exports domestically and
                    bilaterally rather than through multilateral channels.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn27" n="26">National Archives, fond 02/2, schůze 16. 4. 1956 a 14.
                        5. 1956, příloha č. 28 a 29.</note> The skepticism of the Czechoslovak Prime
                    Minister proved well-founded, as the CMEA continued to be ineffective in
                    realizing the CCP’s vision of intra-bloc economic cooperation. As a result, the
                    early second half of the 1950s was marked by substantial economic fluctuations
                    and political-economic crises not only in Czechoslovakia, but in the whole CMEA
                    market. The situation was further aggravated by the ongoing industrial
                    restructuring in individual socialist economies, which led to the emergence of
                    analogous production facilities that reduced the exportability of Czechoslovak
                    goods.</p>
                <p> The unsatisfactory state of Czechoslovak intra-bloc cooperation is presented by
                    Metcalf, who shows that while the ratio of Czechoslovak trade with CMEA
                    countries in the aggregate of Czechoslovak foreign trade grew from 50% to 70%
                    between 1950 and 1955, Czechoslovakia’s share in the aggregate trade of other
                    CMEA economies decreased from 17% to 14%. There followed a similar pattern in
                    the second half of the 1950s, as the Czechoslovak share in intra-bloc trade
                    continued to fall. Metcalf’s findings point to the declining competitiveness of
                    the Czechoslovak economy and the correspondingly growing market share of the
                    newly industrialized CMEA members.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn28" n="27">
                        Metcalf, “The Impact of Foreign Trade on the Czechoslovak Economic Reforms
                        of the 1960s.”</note> Metcalf is supplemented by archives of the
                    Czechoslovak Ministries of Heavy Engineering (<hi rend="italic">Ministerstvo
                        těžkého strojírenství</hi>) and Precision Engineering (<hi rend="italic"
                        >Ministerstvo přesného strojírenství</hi>) as well as by Palous. A
                    comparative analysis of these sources reveals that specific export difficulties
                    were experienced especially by the machine building sector, which previously
                    constituted the backbone of Czechoslovak foreign trade with CMEA economies,
                    since the mid 1950s.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn29" n="28">National Archives,
                        finding aid 1109, fond 935, inventory no. 122<hi rend="italic">–</hi>135,
                        cartons 79<hi rend="italic">–</hi>87, consult also finding aid 1171, fond
                        1190. Jaroslav Palous, “Czechoslovak Foreign Trade Pattern Development,” <hi
                            rend="italic">Czechoslovak Foreign Trade</hi> 5 (1965): 9.</note> A
                    similar decline in the exportability to socialist markets was faced by the
                    Czechoslovak light industry. The extent of these intra-bloc trade challenges in
                    1955-1960 led to a rapid growth of Czechoslovak East-West cooperation.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn30" n="29">Jan M. Michal, “Czechoslovakia’s Foreign
                        Trade,” <hi rend="italic">Slavic Review</hi> 27, no. 2 (1968): 212–29, <ref
                            target="https://doi.org/10.23071965/2493711"
                            >https://doi.org/10.23071965/2493711</ref>. 218. Jirka and Volný, <hi
                            rend="italic">Československé strojírenství doma i za hranicemi</hi>,
                        122.</note></p>
                <p>A profound research would be necessary to create a comprehensive portrayal of the
                    development of the commodity structure of Czechoslovak intra-bloc trade in the
                    second half of the 1950s. However, at a general level it can be stated that the
                    composition of Czechoslovak trade with socialist countries did not change
                    significantly before 1962. Czechoslovak FTEs imported mostly foodstuff, fuels,
                    minerals, metals and other raw materials necessary for the realization of
                    Czechoslovak exports of vehicles, arms, capital equipment, machinery and other
                    value-added goods. Noteworthy transformations in the composition of Czechoslovak
                    exports were identifiable merely in the textile and food processing
                        industries.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn31" n="30">National Archives, fond
                        MZO/FMZO, carton 511, ročenky zahraničního obchodu.</note> The relatively
                    minor modifications in the composition of Czechoslovak intra-bloc trade in the
                    second half of the 1950s provide further proof of the rigidity of the
                    Czechoslovak economic system, which was not adaptable to the rapidly changing
                    conditions of the Khrushchev Thaw. </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>The Economic Crisis of 1962-1965, or Šik Into Action!</head>
                <p>The beginning of the 1960s did not bring the long-desired improvement of the
                    unsustainable model of intra-bloc trade, but on the contrary was characterized,
                    especially in Czechoslovakia, by a rapidly deteriorating balance of payments,
                    which in 1963 turned into a major economic crisis. Its emergence further
                    hindered the development of Czechoslovak international commerce, as its share in
                    world trade declined steadily between 1962 and 1966.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn32" n="31">J. M. Montias, <hi rend="italic">Uniformity and
                            Diversity in the East European Future</hi> (Yale University, 1964), 15,
                        16. See also Palous, “Czechoslovak Foreign Trade Pattern Development,”
                        9.</note> As new archival evidence shows, it cannot be assumed that the only
                    cause of the growing difficulties in Czechoslovak intra-bloc trade was the
                    emergence of the economic crisis or that the problems with the eastward export
                    of Czechoslovak goods were the sole trigger of the recession. In this regard, it
                    is necessary to consider both the emergence of the crisis and the long-standing
                    intra-bloc trade issues as interrelated and interacting phenomena. Building on
                    this premise, contemporary historiography should approach the analysis of the
                    economic crisis of 1962-1965 as inseparable from the development of Czechoslovak
                    international trade. </p>
                <p>The origins of the crisis can be traced back to the transformations of the
                    socialist market in the 1950s, which affected the intra-bloc exportability of
                    Czechoslovak goods. Later, at the beginning of the 1960s, Antonín Novotný,
                    Otakar Šimůnek and other CCP leaders tried to solve the escalating
                    unsatisfactory situation by promoting an integrative, intra-bloc approach to
                    economic and scientific-technical cooperation.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn33"
                        n="32">National Archives, finding aid 1020, fond 1189, inventory no.
                        347–348, carton 30.</note> However, this effort did not find sufficient
                    support among Soviet ministers, who moreover, began to condition the further
                    development of mutual trade by investment participation in the construction of
                    Soviet mining and manufacturing capacities. </p>
                <p>The dire Czechoslovak economic situation in the early 1960s was further
                    exacerbated by the changing attitude of the individual FTEs of other CMEA member
                    states, which requested very specific high-tech machines and consumer goods that
                    the Czechoslovak enterprises were not able to supply immediately.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn34" n="33">State Archive of the Russian Federation,
                        fond 2, inventory no. 1, signature 413/32/2, archival unit 1601, 5. See
                        also Timur Kashapov, “Andropov’s ‘Perestroika’ and Soviet-Czechoslovak
                        Relations in 1982-1984,” <hi rend="italic">West Bohemian Historical
                            Review</hi> 1, no. 2 (2011): 169–99.</note> Furthermore, although most
                    of the secondary literature written by post-Velvet Revolution historians
                    neglects the role of the Sino-Soviet split, analyses by communist-era economists
                    suggest that this event may also have significantly contributed to the outbreak
                    of the economic crisis of 1962-1965. As Golan stipulates , the Sino-Soviet
                    conflict led to the loss of an important traditional outlet for Czechoslovak
                    products. A similar situation occurred in the case of imports from China, which
                    fell from USD 110 million in 1960 to USD 12 million two years later.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn35" n="34">Galia Golan, <hi rend="italic">The
                            Czechoslovak Reform Movement: Communism in Crisis 1962-1968</hi>
                        (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1971), 84, 85. For more information
                        on the causes and consequences of the economic crisis of 1962-1965, see for
                        example: <ref
                            target="https://www.ceskatelevize.cz/porady/1064344210-akademik-ota-sik/26853103143/"
                            >https://www.ceskatelevize.cz/porady/1064344210-akademik-ota-sik/26853103143/</ref>.</note>
                    These predicaments were not alleviated even after 1964 when the intra-bloc
                    International Bank for Economic Cooperation introduced a common currency called
                    the transferrable rouble for denominating transactions among CMEA members.</p>
                <p>The first major recession of the communist Czechoslovakia disproved the
                    previously accepted theory on the non-existence of crises in planned economies.
                    The Široký, and later the Lenárt, administration understood that the worsening
                    position of Czechoslovak goods on socialist markets needed to be targeted, as
                    the growing dissatisfaction of Czechoslovak citizens threatened the stability of
                    the ruling establishment and its ideology. The Central Committee therefore
                    organized a group of progressive economists led by Ota Šik, whose aim was to
                    propose a reform package that would, among other things, improve the stagnating
                    level of Czechoslovak eastward exports.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn36" n="35">
                        Tamás Bauer, “Success and Failure: Emergence of Economic Reforms in
                        Czechoslovakia and Hungary,” in <hi rend="italic">The Evolution of Economic
                            Systems</hi>, edited by Kurt Dopfer and Karl-F. Raible (London: Palgrave
                        Macmillan, 1990), 245–55.</note> At this point it is important to emphasize
                    that although the name of Ota Šik is mainly associated in secondary literature
                    with pro-Western reforms, his proposed measures had a significant impact on the
                    development of intra-bloc trade. Šik’s plan was to increase the competitiveness
                    of Czechoslovak goods in both capitalist and socialist markets and thus
                    facilitate the influx of both the technology and the raw materials necessary to
                    overcome the economic crisis.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn37" n="36">Daniel R.
                        Fusfeld, J. Ron Stanfield, Sherman Howard, and W. Robert Brazelton, “The
                        Third Way,” <hi rend="italic">Journal of Economic Issues</hi> 12, no. 3
                        (1978): 697–708, <ref
                            target="https://doi.org/10.1080/00213624.1978.11503561"
                            >https://doi.org/10.1080/00213624.1978.11503561</ref>.</note> In order
                    to boost eastward exportability, Šik initiated a reorganization of state
                    trading, decentralization of enterprises and modernization of the Czechoslovak
                    commodity pattern.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn38" n="37">
                        <hi rend="italic">Statistická ročenka ČSSR 1965, 1966</hi> (Prague: SNTL,
                        1965-1966).</note>
                </p>
                <p>However, despite these general measures promoting the exportability of
                    Czechoslovak goods in all directions, it must be admitted that the pro-Western
                    facet of Czechoslovak foreign trade continued to intensify at a faster pace,
                    which became fully apparent circa 1966, when the commercial exchange with
                    capitalist countries increased for many categories of goods at the expense of
                    intra-bloc trade. A detailed analysis of Czechoslovak statistical annual records
                    show that while trade with the Eastern Bloc shrank on average by 2% between 1965
                    and 1966, trade volume with capitalist countries increased by 11% within the
                    same period. The greatest decline in Czechoslovak intra-bloc trade recorded was
                    in cooperation with the USSR and Poland, which stood at 5-10% in 1966.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn39" n="38">Ibid.</note>
                </p>
                <p>In addition to changes in the geographical orientation of Czechoslovak
                    international commerce, the composition of the export-import portfolio also
                    experienced a certain transformation. As the Czechoslovak government sought to
                    maintain the pro-Eastern exportability of traditional consumer goods, machine
                    tools and vehicles, it also decided to strengthen their competitiveness by
                    increasing imports of top-notch technologies mainly from the West. As a result,
                    imports in these categories grew from 11% in 1950 to 31% in 1968, which
                    subsequently enabled a partial reconquest of formerly lost socialist markets.
                    This theory is supported by Metcalf, who shows that, Czechoslovak FTEs were as a
                    result able to increase the share of exports of consumer goods to the CMEA from
                    14% in 1965 to 16% two years later.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn40" n="39">
                        Metcalf, “The Impact of Foreign Trade on the Czechoslovak Economic Reforms
                        of the 1960s,” 1089.</note> These findings indicate that Šik’s reforms had a
                    certain impact on the transformation of both Czechoslovak inter- and intra-bloc
                        trade.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn41" n="40">Jan M. Michal,
                        “Czechoslovakia’s Foreign Trade,” <hi rend="italic">Slavic Review</hi> 27,
                        no. 2 (1968): 212–29, <ref target="https://doi.org/10.2307/2493711"
                            >https://doi.org/10.2307/2493711</ref>. 212. UN Statistical Office. <hi
                            rend="italic">UN Statistical Yearbook 1948</hi> (New York: UN, 1948),
                        332, 337.</note> Although they strengthened commercial ties with capitalist
                    countries, they did not alter the core of Czechoslovak foreign economic policy,
                    which remained oriented towards socialist markets. The strong interconnection of
                    CMEA economies was not deconstructed even by the accelerated East-West <hi
                        rend="italic">détente</hi> during the period of the Prague Spring, which was
                    made possible by a series of incentives offered only by Eastern markets,
                    including relatively low prices, less demanding customers and reduced
                        competition.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn42" n="41">Joseph Pelzman, “Trade
                        Creation and Trade Diversion in the Council of Mutual Economic Assistance
                        1954-70,” <hi rend="italic">The American Economic Review</hi> 67, no. 4
                        (1977): 713. Alan P. Dobson, “From Instrumental to Expressive: The Changing
                        Goals of the U.S. Cold War Strategic Embargo,” <hi rend="italic">Journal of
                            Cold War Studies</hi> 12, no. 1 (2010): 101, <ref
                            target="https://doi.org/10.1162/jcws.2010.12.1.98"
                            >https://doi.org/10.1162/jcws.2010.12.1.98</ref>.</note></p>
                <p>In addition to the reforms Šik implemented domestically, the onset of the
                    economic crisis in 1962 prompted the Czechoslovak government to undertake
                    similar reform efforts on the CMEA platform. Although the Council itself was in
                    a state of crisis at the beginning of the 1960s, this did not discourage
                    Czechoslovak reformers from trying to use its sessions, commissions and other
                    bodies to target stagnating intra-bloc commerce.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn43" n="42">National Archives, finding aid 1188, fond 961,
                        inventory no. 30, záznamy RVHP komisí.</note> As new archival findings
                    indicate, the Czechoslovak representative in the CMEA, Otakar Šimůnek, sought to
                    strengthen the coordination of production and trade plans in particular, which
                    he saw as a way to overcome Czechoslovak export obstacles and tap the full
                    potential of Eastern markets.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn44" n="43">National
                        Archives, finding aid 1188., fond AN, archival unit 123, fond 02/1, folder
                        5, archival unit 4.</note>
                </p>
                <p>There were a number of stimuli that contributed to Czechoslovak proactivity in
                    strengthening cooperation with the CMEA in the mid-1960s. As already indicated,
                    socialist markets offered relatively low prices and were able to supply goods
                    that were otherwise unavailable in the West due to ongoing embargoes.
                    Furthermore, the fact that even less-developed socialist economies started to
                    receive Western scientific-technical assistance, created unfavorable conditions
                    for Czechoslovak enterprises, whose outdated products were no longer marketable
                    in the CMEA.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn45" n="44">National Archives, finding
                        aid 1188, fond 961, inventory no. 43, vědecko-technická spolupráce se
                        SSSR.</note> This phenomenon, reinforced by the sustained Sofia Principles,
                    made it impossible to maintain the competitiveness of the Czechoslovak product
                    portfolio and forced the Široký/Lenárt administration to seek greater
                    coordination within the CMEA to eliminate duplicate production and reduce
                    intra-bloc competition. </p>
                <p>However, as Korbonski and Kaplan supplemented by archival findings show,
                    Czechoslovak proactive efforts to improve the system of intra-bloc trade did not
                    always find sufficient support from other CMEA members, as Czechoslovak
                    delegates were often only sustained in their vision by Polish representatives.
                    For instance, since both the Czechoslovak and Polish economies were among the
                    most responsible in fulfilling the intra-bloc trade obligations, their delegates
                    tried to sanction non-compliance with trade protocols. However, this proposal
                    was not pushed through as it did not find wider support among delegations from
                    less developed member states.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn46" n="45">Adrzej
                        Korbonski, <hi rend="italic">Comecon</hi>. (International Conciliation no.
                        549) (New York: Carnegie Endowment for International Peace,1964), 49–52.
                        Kaplan, <hi rend="italic">Rada vzájemné hospodářské pomoci a
                            Československo</hi>, 103–09. National Archives, fond AN, 07/16, archival
                        units 97-98, carton 37, archival units 101-102, carton 38.</note> These
                    findings point to the fact that one of the major obstacles to strengthening
                    intra-bloc economic cooperation was the existence of diverging levels of
                    economic development of individual CMEA members. Less developed economies
                    preferred to maintain a <hi rend="italic">status quo </hi>as it provided them
                    sufficient amounts of goods and assistance and did not commit them to any
                    significant reciprocity. On the other hand, Czechoslovak companies rapidly lost
                    competitiveness and therefore had a strong incentive to reverse this state of
                    affairs. Greater coordination of economic plans was believed to be able to
                    equalize the rights and responsibilities of all CMEA members and thus ease the
                    burden shouldered by the Czechoslovak economy. However, the Council’s principle
                    of qualified unanimity, coupled with the principle of interest (stakeholder
                    involvement), made it impossible to take action because of the veto power of
                    each member.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn47" n="46">W. E. Butler. ed.,
                             <hi rend="italic">International Law and the International
                            System</hi> (Dordrecht, Boston, Lancaster: Martinus Nijhoff Publishers,
                        1978), 114.</note>
                </p>
                <p>Despite the failure to implement the Czechoslovak vision of economic cooperation
                    in the CMEA, Šik’s domestic reforms nevertheless improved the position of
                    Czechoslovak exports on socialist markets so that individual FTEs managed to
                    generate additional surpluses in their commercial exchange with other CMEA
                    countries. A positive balance of payments was achieved particularly in trade
                    with the USSR, with the Czechoslovak economy generating a surplus of USD 123
                    million between 1964 and 1966.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn48" n="47">
                        <hi rend="italic">Statistická ročenka ČSSR 1960-1966</hi>. See also National
                        Archives, finding aid 835, fond 936, inventory no. 39.</note> These findings
                    point to the fact that the reformed Czechoslovak economy was not only able to
                    overcome some of the challenges presented by globalization, increasing
                    international competition, domestic economic recession and the CMEA political
                    crisis, but at the same time also managed to strengthen its exports to the East,
                    whilst providing free know-how and financing the development of extraction and
                    processing capacities in other socialist countries. </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Conclusion</head>
                <p>This article, based mainly on the analysis of hitherto overlooked Czechoslovak
                    archival materials, has helped to reassess selected facets of intra-bloc
                    economic cooperation in the period between 1953-1968. A multifactorial analysis,
                    based on the evaluation of a wide range of data from different strata of the
                    economy, points to the existence of three major phases of Czechoslovak
                    intra-bloc engagement in the Novotný era. The first stage analyzed above was
                    characterized by early attempts at de-Stalinizing the model of intra-bloc
                    cooperation during 1953-1955. However, the implementation of these “New Course”
                    reforms did not proceed as the progressive wings of the CCP imagined, which once
                    again reinforced a retrograde attitude within the Party. The next phase of
                    Czechoslovak intra-bloc cooperation came in the second half of the 1950s as part
                    of a far-reaching transformation of the CMEA cooperation model. Although the
                    accompanying reforms were also characterized by a series of backward-looking
                    measures, they provided an important starting point for the significant
                    liberalization of intra-bloc trade that took place during the third development
                    phase, in the period after the outbreak of the Czechoslovak economic crisis in
                    1962. At the same time, the article facilitated a reassessment of the role of
                    selected actors of intra-bloc cooperation. In particular, the cumbersome CMEA
                    and the abysmal divergence in the political-economic nature of its individual
                    members proved to be a challenge to reforming the socialist model of
                    cooperation. These factors, reinforced by the lack of a Western currency and the
                    delayed de-Stalinization, led to unsuccessful attempts by the reformist wings of
                    the CCP to undertake a more fundamental pro-Western transformation of the
                    Czechoslovak foreign trade model. The Soviet Union thus remained the
                    Czechoslovak main trading partner and even the reforms immediately preceding the
                    Prague Spring period did not significantly change the <hi rend="italic">status
                        quo</hi> on the CMEA market.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="bibliography">
                <head>Sources and Literature</head>
                <list>
                    <item>Archives of the Ministry of Foreign Affairs: <list>
                            <item>MEO-O, 1945–1955.</item>
                            <item>MO-OMO, 1955–1956.</item>
                            <item>MO-T, 1945–1955.</item>
                        </list></item>
                    <item>National Archives: <list>
                            <item>Archiv ÚV KSČ, fond 01.</item>
                            <item>Archival aid 835, fond 936.</item>
                            <item>Finding aid 1020, fond 1189.</item>
                            <item>Finding aid 1109, fond 935.</item>
                            <item>Finding aid 1171, fond 1190.</item>
                            <item>Finding aid 1188, fond 961</item>
                            <item>Finding aid 1204, fond 953.</item>
                            <item>Finding aid 1208, fond 967.</item>
                            <item>Finding aid 835, fond 936.</item>
                            <item>Fond 02/2.</item>
                            <item>Fond AN, 07/16.</item>
                            <item>Fond AN.</item>
                            <item>Fond MZO/FMZO.</item>
                        </list></item>
                    <item>State Archive of the Russian Federation: <list>
                            <item>fond 2.</item>
                        </list></item>
                </list>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Literature</head>
                    <bibl>Bauer, Tamás. “Success and Failure: Emergence of Economic Reforms in
                        Czechoslovakia and Hungary.” In <hi rend="italic">The Evolution of Economic
                            Systems</hi>, edited by Kurt Dopfer, and Karl-F. Raible, 245–55. London:
                        Palgrave Macmillan, 1990.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Bergson, Abram. “The Geometry of Comecon Trade.” <hi rend="italic"
                            >European Economic Review</hi> 14, no. 3 (1980): 291–306. <ref
                            target="https://doi.org/10.1016/s0014-2921(80)80002-x"
                            >https://doi.org/10.1016/s0014-2921(80)80002-x</ref>.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Bogomolov, O. “Economic Cooperation among the Comecon Countries.” <hi
                            rend="italic">EasternEuropean Economics</hi> 2, no. 4 (1964): 3–10. <ref
                            target="https://doi.org/10.1080/00128775.1964.11647864"
                            >https://doi.org/10.1080/00128775.1964.11647864</ref>.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Budinský, Libor. <hi rend="italic">Deset prezidentů</hi>. Prague: Knižní
                        klub, 2008.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Butler, W. E. (ed.). <hi rend="italic">International Law and the
                            International System</hi>. Dordrecht, Boston, Lancaster: Martinus
                        Nijhoff Publishers, 1987.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Dobson, Alan P. “From Instrumental to Expressive: The Changing Goals of
                        the U.S. Cold War Strategic Embargo.” <hi rend="italic">Journal of Cold War
                            Studies</hi> 12, no. 1 (2010): 98–119. <ref
                            target="https://doi.org/10.1162/jcws.2010.12.1.98"
                            >https://doi.org/10.1162/jcws.2010.12.1.98</ref>.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Ernst, Miloslav. <hi rend="italic">Czechoslovakia and International
                            Economic Cooperation</hi>. Prague: Orbis, 1987. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Fusfeld, Daniel R., Stanfield, J. Ron, Howard Sherman, and Brazelton, W.
                        Robert. 1978. “The Third Way.” <hi rend="italic">Journal of Economic
                            Issues</hi> 12, no. 3 (1987): 697–708. <ref
                            target="https://doi.org/10.1080/00213624.1978.11503561"
                            >https://doi.org/10.1080/00213624.1978.11503561</ref>.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Golan, Galia. <hi rend="italic">The Czechoslovak Reform Movement:
                            Communism in Crisis 1962</hi>–<hi rend="italic">1968</hi>. Cambridge:
                        Cambridge University Press, 1971.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Hoffmann, Emil. <hi rend="italic">COMECON: Der gemeinsame Markt in
                            Osteuropa</hi>. Opladen: C. W. Leske, 1961.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Horský, J. “The Structure of Czechoslovak Foreign Trade and Prospects of
                        Modifying It.” <hi rend="italic">Soviet and Eastern European Foreign
                            Trade</hi> 6, no. 3/4 (1970): 268–83.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Jackson, Ian. <hi rend="italic">The Economic Cold War: America, Britain
                            and East-West Trade, 1948–63</hi> (Cold War History Series). New York:
                        Palgrave, 2001.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Jirka, Jindřich, and Jaroslav Volný. <hi rend="italic">Československé
                            strojírenství doma i za hranicemi</hi>. Prague, 1959.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Kaplan, Karel. <hi rend="italic">Československo v letech 1953</hi>–<hi
                            rend="italic">1966</hi>. Prague: SPN, 1992.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Kaplan, Karel. <hi rend="italic">Československo v RVHP 1949</hi>–<hi
                            rend="italic">1956</hi>. Prague: ÚSD AV ČR, 1995</bibl>
                    <bibl>Kaplan, Karel. <hi rend="italic">Rada vzájemné hospodářské pomoci a
                            Československo</hi>, 1957–1967. Prague: Karolinum Press. 2002.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Kashapov, Timur. “Andropov’s ‘Perestroika’ and Soviet-Czechoslovak
                        Relations in 1982–1984.” <hi rend="italic">West Bohemian Historical
                            Review</hi> 1, no. 2 (2011): 169–99. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Korbonski, Adrzej. <hi rend="italic">Comecon</hi>. International
                        Conciliation no. 549. New York: Carnegie Endowment for International Peace,
                        1964.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Korbonski, Andrzej. “Theory and Practice of Regional Integration: The Case
                        of Comecon.” <hi rend="italic">International Organization </hi>24, no. 4
                        (1970): 942–77. <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1017/s0020818300017574"
                            >https://doi.org/10.1017/s0020818300017574</ref>.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Metcalf, Lee K. “The Impact of Foreign Trade on the Czechoslovak Economic
                        Reforms of the 1960s.” <hi rend="italic">Europe-Asia Studies</hi> 45, no. 6
                        (1993): 1071–90. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Michal, Jan M. “Czechoslovakia’s Foreign Trade.” <hi rend="italic">Slavic
                            Review</hi> 27, no. 2 (1968): 212–29. <ref
                            target="https://doi.org/10.2307/2493711"
                            >https://doi.org/10.2307/2493711</ref>. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Montias, J. M. <hi rend="italic">Uniformity and Diversity in the East
                            European Future</hi>. Yale University, 1964.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Palous, Jaroslav. “Czechoslovak Foreign Trade Pattern Development.” <hi
                            rend="italic">Czechoslovak Foreign Trade </hi>5 (1965).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Pelzman, Joseph. “Trade Creation and Trade Diversion in the Council of
                        Mutual Economic Assistance 1954–70.” <hi rend="italic">The American Economic
                            Review</hi> 67, no. 4 (1977).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Procházka, Jaromír. <hi rend="italic">Poválečné Československo
                            1945</hi>–<hi rend="italic">1989</hi>. Prague: Karolinum, 1991.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Procházka, Zdeněk. <hi rend="italic">Hospodářská válka USA proti
                            Československu</hi>. Prague: Vojenská politická akademie, 1960. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Průcha, Václav. <hi rend="italic">Hospodářské a sociální dějiny
                            Československa 1918</hi>–<hi rend="italic">1992: 2. díl. Období
                            1945</hi>–<hi rend="italic">1992</hi>. Brno: Doplněk, 2009. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Radisch, Erik. “The Struggle of the Soviet Conception of Comecon,
                        1953–1957.” <hi rend="italic">Comparativ – Zeitschrift für Globalgeschichte
                            und vergleichende Gesellschaftsforschung</hi> 27, no. 5/6 (2017):
                        26-47.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Richmond, Yale. <hi rend="italic">Cultural Exchange &amp; the Cold
                            War.</hi> Philadelphia: Penn State University Press, 2003.</bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="italic">Statistická ročenka ČSSR 1960-1966</hi>. Prague: SNTL,
                        1960–1966. </bibl>
                    <bibl>UN Statistical Office. <hi rend="italic">UN Statistical Yearbook
                        1948</hi>. New York: UN, 1948.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
            <div type="summary">
                <head>Ondřej Fišer</head>
                <head>STALINOVA SMRT NE POMENI KONCA ALI NEZADRŽNA INTEGRACIJA SOCIALISTIČNEGA
                    TRGA</head>
                <head>POVZETEK</head>
                <p>Smrt Gottwalda in Stalina v prvi polovici leta 1953 je spodbudila ponovni
                    razmislek o obstoječih politikah socialističnih vlad. Vendar pa so se reforme
                    “nove smeri” kot odziv na nove razmere izkazale za dolgoročno nevzdržne, saj bi
                    lahko bistveno ogrozile izpolnjevanje predhodno sklenjenih dolgoročnih
                    trgovinskih sporazumov. Poleg tega Širokýjevi vladi ni uspelo preoblikovati
                    češkoslovaške industrije, zato so se morala proizvodna podjetja še naprej
                    osredotočati na razvoj težkega strojništva in proizvodnjo orožja. Zgodnje
                    poststalinistično obdobje se je tako izkazalo za čas, v katerem je nezadostno
                    destalinizirano vodstvo Komunistične partije Češkoslovaške še naprej dajalo
                    prednost politični zvestobi ZSSR in SEV pred praktičnimi potrebami domačega
                    gospodarstva. Negotovo gospodarsko okolje v vzhodnem bloku se v drugi polovici
                    petdesetih let ni izboljšalo. Od leta 1956 se je kriza v SEV začela poglabljati,
                    trgovina znotraj bloka pa je stagnirala. Poleg tega Hruščov in njegovi sodelavci
                    niso mogli več delovati tako avtoritativno kot Stalin, nastala oblastna praznina
                    v SEV pa je manj razvitim državam članicam omogočila, da so se odpovedale
                    trgovinskim sporazumom. Poleg tega je tako češkoslovaško kot poljsko
                    gospodarstvo trpelo zaradi pospešene industrializacije Bolgarije in Romunije,
                    kar je povečalo konkurenco znotraj bloka in zmanjšalo tržišče. Zaradi težav v
                    okviru SEV sta si Široký in Šimůnek pogosto prizadevala za razvoj dvostranskega
                    sodelovanja ali alternativnih večstranskih platform. Gospodarski položaj
                    Češkoslovaške se je v SEV nekoliko izboljšal šele z dokončno destalinizacijo
                    Komunistične partije Češkoslovaške in vstopom reformističnih komunistov, kot sta
                    bila Jozef Lenárt in Ota Šik, v vodstvo partije. Šikove reforme niso bile
                    ključne le za krepitev izvozne moči češkoslovaškega gospodarstva proti zahodu,
                    temveč so pripomogle tudi k večji konkurenčnosti češkoslovaških izdelkov na
                    socialističnem trgu. Zato reform pred praško pomladjo ni mogoče enostransko
                    obravnavati kot prozahodne, saj je treba priznati tudi njihov ključni vpliv na
                    ohranjanje provzhodnega jedra češkoslovaškega zunanjega sodelovanja. </p>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
