<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Creation of the Non-Aligned News Agencies Pool<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn1" n="*">The article is based on research supported by the
                        Slovenian Research Agency grants J5-1793 and P5-0051.</note></title>
                <author>
                    <forename>Sašo</forename>
                    <surname>Slaček</surname>
                    <surname>Brlek</surname>
                    <roleName>Research Associate</roleName>
                    <affiliation>Social Communication Research Centre, Faculty of Socal Sciences,
                        University of Ljubljana</affiliation>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Kardeljeva ploščad 5</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>SI-1000 Ljubljana</addrLine>
                    </address>
                    <email>saso.brlek-slacek@fdv.uni-lj.si</email>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>2022-04-21</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>
                    <orgName xml:lang="sl">Inštitut za novejšo zgodovino</orgName>
                    <orgName xml:lang="en">Institute of Contemporary History</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Privoz 11</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>SI-1000 Ljubljana</addrLine>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>http://ojs.inz.si/pnz/article/view/3984</pubPlace>
                <date>2022</date>
                <availability status="free">
                    <licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title xml:lang="sl">Prispevki za novejšo zgodovino</title>
                <title xml:lang="en">Contributions to Contemporary History</title>
                <biblScope unit="volume">62</biblScope>
                <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
                <idno type="ISSN">2463-7807</idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source, born digital.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc xml:lang="en">
                <p>Contributions to Contemporary History is one of the central Slovenian scientific
                    historiographic journals, dedicated to publishing articles from the field of
                    contemporary history (the 19th and 20th century).</p>
                <p>The journal is published three times per year in Slovenian and in the following
                    foreign languages: English, German, Serbian, Croatian, Bosnian, Italian, Slovak
                    and Czech. The articles are all published with abstracts in English and
                    Slovenian as well as summaries in English.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <projectDesc xml:lang="sl">
                <p>Prispevki za novejšo zgodovino je ena osrednjih slovenskih znanstvenih
                    zgodovinopisnih revij, ki objavlja teme s področja novejše zgodovine (19. in 20.
                    stoletje).</p>
                <p>Revija izide trikrat letno v slovenskem jeziku in v naslednjih tujih jezikih:
                    angleščina, nemščina, srbščina, hrvaščina, bosanščina, italijanščina, slovaščina
                    in češčina. Članki izhajajo z izvlečki v angleščini in slovenščini ter povzetki
                    v angleščini.</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="sl"/>
                <language ident="en"/>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords xml:lang="en">
                    <term>Yugoslavia</term>
                    <term>Non-aligned movement</term>
                    <term>Tanjug</term>
                    <term>Non-aligned news agencies pool</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords xml:lang="sl">
                    <term>Jugoslavija</term>
                    <term>gibanje neuvrščenih</term>
                    <term>Tanjug</term>
                    <term>Združenje neuvrščenih novičarskih agencij</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change><date>2022-04-28T08:10:22Z</date>
                    <name>Mihael Ojsteršek</name>
                    <desc>Pretvorba iz DOCX v TEI, dodatno kodiranje</desc></change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <docAuthor>Sašo Slaček Brlek<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn2" n="**"><hi rend="bold"
                        >Research Associate, Social Communication Research Centre, Faculty of Social
                        Sciences, University of Ljubljana, Kardeljeva ploščad 5, SI-1000 Ljubljana; <ref target="mailto:saso.brlek-slacek@fdv.uni-lj.si"
                            >saso.brlek-slacek@fdv.uni-lj.si</ref></hi></note></docAuthor>
            <docImprint>
                <idno type="cobissType">Cobiss tip: 1.01</idno>
                <idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.51663/pnz.62.1.2</idno>
            </docImprint>
            <div type="abstract" xml:lang="sl">
                <head>IZVLEČEK</head>
                <head><hi rend="italic">NASTANEK ZDRUŽENJA NEUVRŠČENIH TISKOVNIH AGENCIJ</hi></head>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Članek se osredotoča na proces oblikovanja Združenja
                        neuvrščenih novičarskih agencij in dejavnike, ki so oblikovali njegov
                        razvoj. Avtor pojasnjuje nastanek združenja s tremi skupinami dejavnikov.
                        Prvi so bili interesi in strategije jugoslovanskih političnih elit in
                        novičarske agencije Tanjug. Medtem ko se je Tanjug zanimal za povečanje
                        svojega globalnega dosega in položaja na svetovnem trgu novičarskih agencij,
                        so ga zvezne politične elite videle kot pomembno orodje zunanje politike.
                        Jugoslavija si je že v času pred četrtim vrhom neuvrščenih v Alžiru
                        prizadevala za institucionalizacijo informacijskega sodelovanja, čeprav so
                        bili objektivni pogoji ocenjeni kot minimalni. Drugi dejavnik so spremembe v
                        mednarodnih odnosih, saj se je združenje tiskovnih agencij pojavilo v
                        kontekstu institucionalizacije gibanja neuvrščenih v sedemdesetih letih
                        prejšnjega stoletja in njegovih prizadevanj »zanašanja na lastne sile«, da
                        bi države tako izboljšale svoj položaj v svetovnem gospodarstvu in
                        pogajalsko moč v odnosu do razvitih držav. Združenje je zato Tanjugove
                        dvostranske sporazume o izmenjavi novic rekontekstualiziralo v večstranski
                        projekt gospodarskega sodelovanja znotraj gibanja neuvrščenih, katerega cilj
                        sta bili krepitev medsebojnega razumevanja in osamosvojitev od globalnih
                        (predvsem zahodnih) virov novic. Kot tretje pa je razvoj združenja
                        oblikovala institucionalna zgodovina gibanja, saj je bilo združenje
                        zasnovano in institucionalizirano po vzoru že obstoječih oblik gospodarskega
                        sodelovanja. Za spoštovanje decentraliziranega duha gibanja je morala
                        Jugoslavija prikriti svoj angažma pri vzpostavljanju združenja tiskovnih
                        agencij in drugih oblik informacijskega sodelovanja ter jih predstaviti kot
                        večstranske projekte s široko podporo znotraj gibanja neuvrščenih.</hi></p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Ključne besede: Jugoslavija, gibanje neuvrščenih, Tanjug,
                        Združenje neuvrščenih novičarskih agencij</hi></p>
            </div>
            <div type="abstract" xml:lang="en">
                <head>ABSTRACT</head>
                <p><hi rend="italic">The article focuses on the process that led to the Non-Aligned
                        News Agencies Pool (NANAP) being established and the factors shaping its
                        emergence. The author explains NANAP’s emergence by referring to three
                        groups of factors. The first is the interests and strategies of Yugoslav
                        political elites and of Yugoslavia’s Tanjug news agency. While Tanjug was
                        interested in increasing its global reach and position in the global
                        marketplace of news agencies, the federal political elites saw Tanjug as an
                        important foreign policy tool. Yugoslavia was actively pushing to
                        institutionalise informational cooperation within the Non-Aligned Movement
                        (NAM) already in the run-up to the 4</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"
                        >th</hi><hi rend="italic"> NAM summit in Algiers, even though the objective
                        conditions were deemed minimal. The second factor is changes in
                        international relations given that NANAP developed in the context of the
                        institutionalisation of NAM in the 1970s and its efforts to build
                        “self-reliance” so as to increase its position within the global economy and
                        bargaining power vis-à-vis the developed countries. NANAP therefore
                        recontextualised Tanjug’s bilateral news exchange agreements into a
                        multilateral project of economic cooperation within NAM, aimed at
                        strengthening mutual understanding and gaining independence from global
                        (primarily Western) news sources. Finally, NANAP’s development was shaped by
                        the movement’s institutional history as NANAP was conceived and
                        institutionalised in the mould of pre-existing forms of economic
                        cooperation. To respect the movement’s decentralised ethos, Yugoslavia had
                        to downplay and disguise its significant level of involvement in
                        establishing NANAP and other forms of informational cooperation and to
                        present them as multilateral projects with broad support within
                    NAM.</hi></p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Keywords: Yugoslavia, Non-aligned movement, Tanjug, Non-aligned
                        news agencies pool</hi></p>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div>
                <head>Introduction</head>
                <p>The Non-Aligned News Agencies Pool (NANAP) was initiated by the Tanjug news
                    agency in January 1975. The pool was the most significant form of cooperation
                    between Non-Aligned media and a key project for strengthening “self-reliance” of
                    the Non-Aligned world. As the first form of informational cooperation between
                    Non-Aligned countries, it impacted future forms of cooperation like those
                    between Non-Aligned broadcasters (BONAC) as well as the institutionalisation of
                    informational cooperation within the Non-Aligned Movement (NAM). </p>
                <p>The pool served as a news exchange mechanism that allowed participating news
                    agencies to contribute their news items and make use of news items supplied by
                    other participating agencies. NANAP’s stated goal was to address the gap in
                    communication capacities between the Non-Aligned and other third world countries
                    on one hand and the rich countries of the global North on the other because this
                    gap was believed to have led to the inadequate and distorted representation of
                    Non-Aligned and other developing countries along with unbalanced global news
                        flows.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn3" n="1">Pero Ivačić, “The Flow of News:
                        Tanjug, the Pool, and the National Agencies,” <hi rend="italic">Journal of
                            Communication</hi>, 28, No. 4 (1978): 157–62.</note> By establishing
                    NANAP, Non-Aligned countries sought to create a system through which they could
                    exchange information about each other without relying on the big global news
                    agencies, which they viewed with suspicion as a legacy of the colonial past and
                    a tool of imperialism. At the same time, the goal was to increase the visibility
                    of the Non-Aligned world and improve its image in Western media.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn4" n="2">Branko Bogunović, “Informisanje o sebi i
                        svetu,” <hi rend="italic">Međunarodna politika</hi>, Feb 1, 1976. Pero
                        Ivačić, “Početak značajne aktivnosti: Međusobna informiranost nesvrstanih -
                        neophodan element saradnje,” <hi rend="italic">Međunarodna politika</hi>,
                        Feb 1, 1975.</note>
                </p>
                <p>NANAP’s creation and operation continue to be poorly understood. Like with the
                    Non-Aligned Movement in general,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn5" n="3">For the
                        historiography of the Non-Aligned Movement generally see Jürgen Dinkel, <hi
                            rend="italic">Die Bewegung Bündnisfreier Staaten</hi> (Oldenbourg: De
                        Gruyter, 2015), 7.</note> critical historical research is rare with most
                    published accounts coming from protagonists and contemporary sympathisers of
                    NAM, such as Pero Ivačić, the director-general of Tanjug,<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn6" n="4">Ivačić, ”Početak.” Pero Ivačić, ”The Non-Aligned
                        Countries Pool Their News,” <hi rend="italic">UNESCO Courier</hi>, April,
                        1977, 18–20. Ivačić ”Flow.” Pero Ivačić, “Toward a Freer and
                        Multidimensional Flow of Information,” in: <hi rend="italic">The Third World
                            and Press Freedom</hi>, ed. P. C. Horton (New York: Praeger, 1978),
                        135–50.</note> D. R. Mankekar,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn7" n="5">D. R.
                        Mankekar, <hi rend="italic">One Way Free Flow: Neo-Colonialism via News
                            Media</hi> (New Delhi: Clarion books, 1978).</note> the pool’s first
                    coordinator, and Mustapha Masmoudi,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn8" n="6"
                        >Mustapha Masmoudi, “The New World Information Order,” <hi rend="italic"
                            >Journal of Communication</hi>, 29, No. 2 (1979): 172–79.</note> the
                    Tunisian information minister. In 1983, an overview of NANAP’s operation up
                    until that point as well as relevant documents were published by the Indian
                    Institute of Mass Communication, with the publication still being the most
                    comprehensive official account of NANAP.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn9" n="7"
                        >Coordinating Committee, <hi rend="italic">News Agencies Pool of Non-Aligned
                            Countries</hi> (New Delhi: Indian Institute of Mass Communication,
                        1983).</note> Scholarly accounts are generally based either on available
                    published sources (mostly documents adopted by the Non-Aligned countries at
                    summits and ministerial meetings or their public statements)<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn10" n="8">Tran Van Dinh, “Non-Alignment and Cultural
                        Imperialism,” <hi rend="italic">The Black Scholar: Journal of Black Studies
                            and Research</hi>, 8, No. 3 (1976): 39–49.</note> or analyse aspects of
                    the pool’s operation.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn11" n="9"> Edward T. Pinch,
                        “The Flow of News: An Assessment of the Non-Aligned News Agencies Pool,” <hi
                            rend="italic">Journal of Communication</hi>, 28, No. 4 (1978): 163–71.
                        Karol Jakubowicz, “Third World News Cooperation Schemes in Building a New
                        International Communication Order: Do They Stand a Chance?,” <hi
                            rend="italic">Gazette</hi> 36 (1985): 81–93. Oliver Boyd-Barrett and
                        Daya Thussu, <hi rend="italic">Contra-Flow in Global News: International and
                            Regional News Exchange Mechanisms</hi>, (London: John Libbey,
                        1992).</note> The result is that almost nothing is known about NANAP’s
                    creation.</p>
                <p>This paper has two goals. The first is to reconstruct the process of NANAP’s
                    establishment in 1975 and its institutionalisation within NAM in 1976. The
                    second goal is to uncover the factors that shaped NANAP’s creation and early
                    development. Jürgen Dinkel provides a useful analytical toolbox by identifying
                    three groups of explanations for the formation of international institutions
                    like NAM: the first being internalist interpretations, which focus on
                    initiatives coming from within the individual nation states engaged in building
                    an association; the second are externalist interpretations which seek
                    explanations in the context of international relations; and third, approaches
                    grounded in institutional history concentrate on the ways bureaucratic culture
                    and path dependencies emerging from the history of association influence the
                    development of international institutions.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn12"
                        n="10">Dinkel, <hi rend="italic">Bewegung</hi>, 16–19.</note> These groups
                    of explanations are not mutually exclusive but can be productively combined to
                    offer a fuller explanation of an international association.</p>
                <p>I focus on these three groups of factors to explain the emergence and initial
                    institutionalisation of NANAP:</p>
                <list type="unordered">
                    <item>internal factors: goals and strategies pursued by actors within
                        Yugoslavia, primarily Tanjug and the federal political elite;</item>
                    <item>external factors: changes in international relations in both the global
                        economic and political context as well as within NAM; and</item>
                    <item>institutional history: the ways NAM’s institutional history shaped the
                        development of NANAP.</item>
                </list>
                <lb/>
                <p>My research is based on archival sources of the Archive of Yugoslavia in Belgrade
                    (cabinet of the President of the Republic, relevant commissions of the Central
                    Committee of the League of Communists of Yugoslavia and the Socialist League of
                    Working People of Yugoslavia) and the Diplomatic Archive of the Ministry of
                    Foreign Affairs of the Republic of Serbia (containing materials of the Federal
                    Secretariat for Foreign Affairs of the SFRY). Tanjug’s archives are
                    unfortunately only partly preserved at the Archive of Yugoslavia and do not
                    allow a significant insight into NANAP’s creation.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>The International Context</head>
                <p>After the second NAM summit in 1964, the movement fell into crisis partly due to
                    the changing international relations and partly to factors internal to several
                    participating countries that saw them become less active.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn13" n="11">Tvrtko Jakovina, <hi rend="italic">Treća strana
                            hladnog rata</hi> (Croatia: Fraktura, 2011), 51–55.</note> However, in
                    the late 1960s and early 1970s changes in international relations as well as
                    changes in several Non-Aligned countries sparked renewed interest in the
                    movement. The first significant international factor was the easing of tensions
                    between the USA and the USSR, which met with mixed feelings among third world
                    countries. On one hand, détente was viewed with relief, as the conflict between
                    the blocs had raised the prospect of nuclear annihilation and had drawn third
                    world countries into the power struggle between East and West. On the other
                    hand, it was feared that the third world would lose what little impact it had on
                    global politics as the USA and the USSR began to settle important issues
                    bilaterally. A further concern was that the most pressing issues for third world
                    countries like the persistence of Portugal’s colonial domination, apartheid in
                    South Africa, the Israeli occupation of Palestinian territories, and the
                    presence of military bases in third world countries would continue to be
                        ignored.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn14" n="12">Dinkel, <hi rend="italic"
                            >Bewegung</hi>, 151, 152.</note></p>
                <p>The second big international factor was the persisting and even growing
                    differences in development between the global North and South.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn15" n="13">Karl P. Sauvant, “Toward the New International
                        Economic Order,” in: <hi rend="italic">The New International Economic Order:
                            Confrontation of Cooperation Between North and South</hi>, eds. Karl P.
                        Sauvant and Hajo Hasenpflug (Boulder, Colorado: Westview Press, 1977),
                        3–19.</note> The fact that the institutions controlling the global economy –
                    the IMF, the World Bank and GATT – were under the control of the USA and their
                    European allies, gave credence to the idea that the post-war global economic
                    order was designed to protect the interests of the already rich, rather than
                    address the problems of global poverty and underdevelopment. In the 1960s,
                    developing countries turned their focus to the United Nations, with their
                    efforts leading to the United Nations Conference on Trade and Development
                    (UNCTAD) being established and the Group of 77 being formed in 1964,<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn16" n="14">Branislav Gosovic, <hi rend="italic"
                            >UNCTAD - Conflict and Compromise</hi> (Leiden: A. W. Sijthoff, 1972).
                        Karl P. Sauvant, ”The Early Days of the Group of 77,”
                        <ref target="https://www.un.org/en/chronicle/article/early-days-group-77">https://www.un.org/en/chronicle/article/early-days-group-77</ref>.</note> raising
                    hopes that the third world could effectively pursue its goals within the UN
                    system. This then meant the desire for further Non-Aligned conferences and the
                    movement’s institutionalisation was significantly reduced.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn17" n="15">Dinkel, <hi rend="italic">Bewegung</hi>, 127.</note>
                    Still, optimism soon turned to frustration upon the lack of results, as
                    expressed already in the Charter of Algiers adopted by the Group of 77 in
                        1967.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn18" n="16">”Charter of Algiers,” Algiers,
                            Algeria, 10. – 25.October 1967, <ref target="https://www.g77.org/doc/algier~1.htm">https://www.g77.org/doc/algier~1.htm</ref>.</note>
                    The absence of results from UN initiatives like UNCTAD and the UN development
                    decade led third world countries to re-evaluate their strategies and added to
                    the renewed interest in NAM.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn19" n="17">Dinkel, <hi
                            rend="italic">Bewegung</hi>, 153.</note></p>
                <p>Another impetus to the association of third world countries was the breakdown of
                    the Bretton Woods system in 1971 and the global crisis of US hegemony during the
                        1970s.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn20" n="18">Giovanni Arrighi, <hi
                            rend="italic">Adam Smith in Beijing</hi> (London and New York: Verso,
                        2007), 149–56.</note> These changes created both hopes and fears: hopes that
                    the entrenched structures of the global economic order, seen as inimical to the
                    interests of third world countries, were open to change, and fears that third
                    world countries and their interests would remain to be side-lined and ignored
                    unless they were to take decisive action to shape the course of events.</p>
                <p>NAM’s revival in the 1970s therefore also implied its reimagining, particularly
                    in the form of a reorientation on North-South disparities in economic
                    development, which would grow into NAM’s two interlinked projects in the 1970s:
                    the New International Economic Order (NIEO) and the New World Information and
                    Communication Order (NWICO). In addition to efforts within the UN system, NAM
                    focused on practical steps aimed at increasing economic cooperation of
                    Non-Aligned countries with a view to making those countries become less
                    dependent on the rich countries of the global North. The case of OPEC, which
                    made its power felt with the 1973 oil embargo, was a powerful demonstration of
                    the strength that can be gained from association.</p>
                <p>Efforts to strengthen South-South cooperation came to be known as “self-reliance”
                    and were of particular significance for Yugoslavia.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn21" n="19">See Boris Cizelj, <hi rend="italic">Ekonomsko
                            sodelovanje med deželami v razvoju: Teorija in praksa kolektivne opore
                            na lastne sile</hi> (Ljubljana: Komunist, 1982) for an overview of the
                        theory and practice of self-reliance from the Yugoslav perspective.</note>
                    The Yugoslav delegation at the Preparatory Committee’s meeting for the 4<hi
                        rend="superscript">th</hi> NAM summit in 1973 reported that: “We have
                    suggested that special emphasis be given in the agenda to issues of cooperation
                    and solidarity between Non-Aligned countries and the coordination of their
                    activities in the areas of education, science, culture, information and others,
                    which was accepted”.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn22" n="20"> RS DAMSPRS PA R
                        1973 F-131 Report of the Preparatory Committee meeting in Kabul
                        (Afghanistan), 28. 5. 1973, 422-43, p. 10.</note></p>
                <p>“Self-reliance” was not simply economically but also politically significant
                    since it provided a binding force for the movement, otherwise plagued by
                    considerable, sometimes irreconcilable, and often hostile political differences.
                    A telegram from the Yugoslav embassy in Algiers in the run-up to the Algiers
                    summit speaks quite candidly about this: “Based on talks with many
                    representatives of Non-Aligned countries, but especially the hosts, the
                    impression is that questions of economic development and the gap between rich
                    and poor will serve as the common denominator that should enable the unity of
                    NAM, which could never be achieved to this extent in the political realm due to
                    the political, religious, ideological etc. differences between individual
                    Non-Aligned countries.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn23" n="21"> RS DAMSPRS PA R
                        1973 F-133 Telegram from the Yugoslav embassy in Algiers, 434895, p.
                        1.</note>
                </p>
                <p>Following the summit, President Tito,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn24" n="22"
                        >Josip Broz – Tito, “Potvrda snage i vitalnosti politike nesvrstavanja,” <hi
                            rend="italic">Međunarodna politika</hi>, Nov 16, 1973.</note> Vice
                    President of the Federal Executive Council Anton Vratuša,<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn25" n="23">Anton Vratuša, “Sastanak nesvrstanih u Alžiru i
                        ostvarivanje međunarodne strategije razvoja,” <hi rend="italic">Međunarodna
                            politika</hi>, Nov 1, 1973.</note> and member of the SFRY Presidency
                    Augustin Papić<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn26" n="24">Augustin Papić, “Alžirska
                        konferencija: Mjere u oblasti ekonomske saradnje,” <hi rend="italic"
                            >Međunarodna politika</hi>, Oct 1, 1973.</note> all stressed concrete
                    measures for furthering economic cooperation as key achievements of the
                    summit.</p>
                <p>The focus on strengthening economic cooperation between NAM members shaped the
                    institutionalisation of the movement. The Georgetown ministerial conference in
                    1972 adopted an action programme for economic cooperation and named coordinators
                    for selected areas of economic cooperation, with both becoming an important part
                    of the movement’s operation and institutional make-up. Forms of informational
                    cooperation like NANAP developed within this institutional framework. Further,
                    the notion of “self-reliance” became central to both the NWICO and the
                        NIEO.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn27" n="25">Breda Pavlič and Cees J.
                        Hamelink, <hi rend="italic">The New International Economic Order: Links
                            Between Economics and Communications</hi> (Paris: UNESCO, 1985).</note>
                    It influenced NANAP by providing an overarching goal and by its framing of the
                    issues – boosting South-South cooperation to achieve independence from the rich
                    countries of the global North – as well as creating the institutional forms
                    through which cooperation was taking place.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Tanjug’s Role in Yugoslav Foreign Policy</head>
                <p>The 1970s saw renewed interest in NAM within Yugoslavia. Two factors were
                    paramount in reviving the Yugoslav leadership’s interest in the movement. The
                    first was the Soviet invasion of Czechoslovakia in 1968, which raised fears of
                    Soviet aggression against Yugoslavia and increased the need to foster
                    international contacts and alliances.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn28" n="26"
                        >Dinkel, <hi rend="italic">Bewegung</hi>, 143, 144, 160, 161. Jakovina, <hi
                            rend="italic">Treća strana</hi>, 59.</note> The second reason was the
                    decentralisation of power within Yugoslavia, which led the federal political
                    elites to look to the world stage as a way of boosting their power and prestige
                    within the federation.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn29" n="27">Dinkel, <hi
                            rend="italic">Bewegung</hi>, 161, 162. </note> The changing orientation of
                    foreign policy impacted Tanjug’s role as its position in international
                    communications became more pronounced, both in terms of gathering information as
                    well as promoting Yugoslav viewpoints around the world. The decentralisation of
                    decision-making meant that Tanjug’s role as the “backbone of the Yugoslav mass
                    media system”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn30" n="28"> Slavko Splichal and
                        France Vreg, <hi rend="italic">Množično komuniciranje in razvoj
                            demokracije</hi> (Ljubljana: Komunist, 1986), 111.</note> and the
                    gatekeeper of information coming from foreign information sources<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn31" n="29">Tanjug occupied a mediating role between
                        Yugoslav news media and foreign news agencies, receiving, selecting and
                        distributing agency news to Yugoslav media.</note> was an important asset
                    for the federal leadership of Yugoslavia. This role was especially significant
                    since information flows across the borders of the republics were otherwise
                    limited and unbalanced.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn32" n="30">See Splichal and
                        Vreg, <hi rend="italic">Množično komuniciranje</hi>, 77 for the circulation
                        of newspapers outside of their “native” republics. – Ibidem, 106 for the
                        exchange of television content.</note></p>
                <p>Concurrently with the changes in the Non-Aligned Movement, Tanjug was maturing as
                    a news agency. By the late 1960s it had developed significantly from an organ of
                    national resistance during the Second World War through a phase of an
                    “informative institution centred on the federal administration”,<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn33" n="31">RS AJ 130, 567 Information about the
                        Tanjug news agency, p. 1.</note> financed directly from the federal budget
                    until 1962,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn34" n="32">In 1962 it was established
                        as an autonomous organisation with the Decree on the Tanjug News Agency,
                        while in 1974 the normative basis for its operation became the Law on the
                        Tanjug News Agency.</note> to a largely professionalised journalistic
                        operation<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn35" n="33">Regarding Tanjug’s
                        significant degree of autonomy in relation to state institutions and
                        journalistic professionalism, see Gertrude J. Robinson,“Tanjug: Yugoslavia’s
                        Multi-Faceted National News Agency” (PhD diss., University of Illinois,
                        1968). Gertrude J. Robinson, “Foreign News Selection Is Non-Linear in
                        Yugoslavia’s Tanjug Agency,” <hi rend="italic">Journalism Quarterly</hi> 47,
                        No. 2 (1970): 340–51.</note> focused on both the domestic and world markets,
                    boasting in 1969 that the agency had: “gained its place in the harsh competitive
                    environment of the world market”.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn36" n="34">RS AJ
                        130 567 Programme for the development of Tanjug’s technical basis 1970-1974,
                        January 1969, p. 1.</note> Already in 1964, Tanjug’s operating budget was
                    USD 1.3 million, it employed 485 full-time personnel and was outputting 85,000
                    words per day (40,000 for local, 45,000 for international customers).<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn37" n="35">Robinson, ”Tanjug,” 166.</note> While
                    this was only a fraction of AP’s 2 million word output at the time, these
                    figures put Tanjug in eighth place in the international news market after the
                    five international agencies, China’s Xinhua and Egypt’s Middle East News
                        Agency.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn38" n="36">Ibid.</note></p>
                <p>To gather and disseminate information across the globe, Tanjug had been
                    conducting bilateral agreements with foreign agencies as a way of supplementing
                    its network of correspondents. These included commercial agreements with the
                    major global agencies (in 1968 Tanjug had commercial agreements with AP, Reuters
                    and AFP)<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn39" n="37">Ibid., 134.</note> and news
                    exchange agreements with smaller European and third world agencies, as well as
                    technical aid agreements. Technical aid was primarily in the form of radio
                    receivers, for example, in 1963 the federal government approved funds to Tanjug
                    to supply radio printers to news agencies in Tunisia, Sudan, Ceylon, Burma,
                    Cambodia and Afghanistan.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn40" n="38">RS AJ 130
                        F-567 Note by the Assistant Secretary of the Federal Executive Council, 28.
                        2. 1963.</note> By 1969, Tanjug had provided radio printers to national news
                    agencies in Ethiopia, Tunisia, Algiers, Ghana, Mali, Congo (Brazzaville),
                    Uganda, Cambodia, Afghanistan, Mexico and Bolivia and was in negotiations with
                    several countries in East Africa and the Middle East.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn41" n="39">RS AJ A. CK SKJ XXVI-K.3/1 Meeting materials: Social
                        role and position of the Tanjug news agency, 12. 11. 1969, pp. 6, 7.</note>
                    Technical aid was not entirely philanthropic as the “beneficiary is obliged to
                    use the equipment to receive Tanjug’s news wire and to forward one copy to our
                        embassy”.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn42" n="40">Ibid., p. 7</note></p>
                <p>New challenges and opportunities for Tanjug were emerging in the domestic market
                    along with the rapid proliferation of new media organisations. Between 1960 and
                    1986, the number of radio stations grew tenfold, newspaper circulation
                        threefold.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn43" n="41">Splichal and Vreg, <hi
                            rend="italic">Množično komuniciranje</hi>, 84</note> These changes meant
                    that Tanjug had gained autonomy in both an organisational sense – becoming a
                    self-managing working press organisation – and financially because Yugoslav
                    media and companies<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn44" n="42">According to
                        Ibid., 110, the
                        main income sources for Tanjug in 1977 were: 1) Yugoslav mass media,
                        accounting for 39.1% of its income; 2) socio-political communities and
                        organisations, accounting for 38.5%; and 3) and Yugoslav companies to which
                        Tanjug marketed an economic information service, accounting for
                        15.3%.</note> were becoming an ever more significant funding source.</p>
                <p>The Central Committee of the League of Communists of Yugoslavia took notice of
                    Tanjug’s changing role and affirmed the need for the agency to develop as an
                    “autonomous self-managing working organisation”,<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn45" n="43">RS AJ 507 A. CK SKJ XXVI K3.1 Social position and role
                        of Tanjug: summary of the position of the Commission of the Presidency of
                        the Central Committee of the League of Yugoslav Communists for Propaganda
                        and Informational Activities, 12. 12. 1969, p. 1.</note> while
                    simultaneously pointing to the need for close cooperation with the
                    socio-political organs and organisations of the federation and republics.
                    Especially in international communication, Tanjug had a “special obligation to
                    present and comment on the foreign-political positions of our country and its
                    international activities”.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn46" n="44"> Ibid., p.
                        3.</note> Tanjug’s relative degree of autonomy meant that it was not merely
                    acting as an organ of the government but was forming and pursuing its own goals,
                    albeit in close cooperation with the federal government. As is shown in the
                    remainder of this paper, the close cooperation with the Federal Secretariat for
                    Foreign Affairs and the Federal Secretariat for Information was in no way
                    one-sided. Instead, Tanjug had a considerable influence on NAM and on
                    Yugoslavia’s foreign as well as domestic policy.</p>
                <p>The significance of Tanjug in Yugoslavia’s foreign policy was visible in 1969
                    when Tanjug asked the federal government for funds for modernising its radio
                    equipment and its bid was supported by the Secretariat for Foreign Affairs:
                    “DSIP [<hi rend="italic">Državni sekretariat za inostrane poslove</hi> - State
                    Secretariat for Foreign Affairs] considers that it is in the interests of
                    Yugoslavia and Yugoslav politics that the position of Tanjug is consolidated and
                    further strengthened”.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn47" n="45">RS AJ 130, 567
                        Opinion of the State Secretariat for Foreign Affairs regarding the Programme
                        of development of Tanjug’s technical basis between 1970 and 1974, 20. 10.
                        1969, p. 1.</note> The Secretariat listed several reasons: the first
                    concerns Tanjug’s role in gathering information on important events around the
                    world and distributing it among Yugoslav authorities, especially when
                    communication with Yugoslavia’s diplomatic missions are interrupted during
                    crises or when foreign media content in Yugoslav languages is involved.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn48" n="46">Tanjug had the role of monitoring and
                        recording foreign media content in Yugoslav languages in addition to the
                        content of major news media, reflecting a concern for undue ideological
                        influences on Yugoslav citizens living abroad, particularly seasonal
                        workers.</note> The second relates to Tanjug’s foreign output, where the
                    Secretariat wanted to see foreign news agencies rely on Tanjug’s news when
                    reporting events from Yugoslavia. Moreover, the Secretariat argued that
                    strengthening collaboration with Non-Aligned news agencies would be beneficial
                    for the “break up the monopoly of the agencies of the great powers”.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn49" n="47">RS AJ 130, 567, Opinion of the State
                        Secretariat for Foreign Affairs regarding the Programme of development of
                        Tanjug’s technical basis between 1970 and 1974, 20. 10. 1969, p.
                    3.</note></p>
                <p>With the reorientation of Yugoslav foreign policy, Tanjug also began to pay more
                    attention to the Non-Aligned world. The Non-Aligned world and developing
                    countries generally were seen as an opportunity for expansion since “especially
                    in the areas of the developing countries there is an evident readiness to accept
                    information from a national agency of a Non-Aligned country like
                        Yugoslavia”.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn50" n="48">RS AJ A. CK SKJ
                        XXVI-K.3/1 Meeting materials: Social role and position of the Tanjug news
                        agency, 12. 11. 1969, p. 22.</note> In 1971, the Federal Secretariat for
                    Information recommended to the federal government that Tanjug increase the
                    duration of its broadcasting to Latin America, West Africa, and Benelux and open
                    three new permanent positions for correspondents in Western and Central Africa
                    (1 correspondent), East Africa (1 correspondent) and Turkey.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn51" n="49">RS AJ 130, 567 Proposal of the Federal Secretariat for
                        Information to increase the scope of the program of activities of the News
                        Agency Tanjug abroad and the newspaper Jugoslovenske novosti in 1971, 19. 8.
                        1970. </note>
                </p>
                <p>Despite Tanjug showing greater interest in the Non-Aligned and developing worlds,
                    its network of permanent correspondents still reflected a very strong focus on
                    Europe (both West and East), with hardly any permanent correspondents stationed
                    in Non-Aligned countries (see Table 1). In Africa, we can even see a reduction
                    in the number of correspondents between 1963 and 1970, with Tanjug having had
                    four permanent (Algiers, Cairo, Accra, Dar es Salam) and three part-time
                    (Khartoum, Addis Ababa, Leopoldville) correspondents stationed there in
                        1963.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn52" n="50">Tanjug, <hi rend="italic"
                            >Tanjug 1943–1963</hi> (Beograd: Tanjug, 1963), 39.</note></p>
                <table rend="rules">
                    <head>Table 1: Locations of Tanjug’s permanent correspondents in 1970</head>
                    <row>
                        <cell rend="left">
                            <hi rend="bold">I. Europe</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell rend="left"/>
                        <cell rend="left">
                            <hi rend="bold">II. Asia</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell rend="left"/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell rend="left"><hi rend="bold">Western</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="left"/>
                        <cell rend="left">Lebanon</cell>
                        <cell rend="left">Beirut</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell rend="left">Italy</cell>
                        <cell rend="left">Rome</cell>
                        <cell rend="left">India</cell>
                        <cell rend="left">New Delhi</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell rend="left">Austria</cell>
                        <cell rend="left">Vienna</cell>
                        <cell rend="left">Cambodia</cell>
                        <cell rend="left">Singapore</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell rend="left">Greece</cell>
                        <cell rend="left">Athens</cell>
                        <cell rend="left">Japan</cell>
                        <cell rend="left">Tokyo</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell rend="left">France</cell>
                        <cell rend="left">Paris</cell>
                        <cell rend="left">Indonesia</cell>
                        <cell rend="left">Jakarta</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell rend="left">West Germany</cell>
                        <cell rend="left">Bonn</cell>
                        <cell rend="left">
                            <hi rend="bold">III. Africa</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell rend="left"/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell rend="left">Great Britain</cell>
                        <cell rend="left">London</cell>
                        <cell rend="left">Egypt</cell>
                        <cell rend="left">Cairo</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell rend="left">Sweden</cell>
                        <cell rend="left">Stockholm</cell>
                        <cell rend="left">Kenya</cell>
                        <cell rend="left">Nairobi</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell rend="left"><hi rend="bold">Socialist countries</hi></cell>
                        <cell rend="left"/>
                        <cell rend="left">
                            <hi rend="bold">IV. North America</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell rend="left"/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell rend="left">USSR (2 correspondents)</cell>
                        <cell rend="left">Moscow</cell>
                        <cell rend="left">USA – UN</cell>
                        <cell rend="left">New York</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell rend="left">Poland</cell>
                        <cell rend="left">Warsaw</cell>
                        <cell rend="left">USA</cell>
                        <cell rend="left">Washington</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell rend="left">East Germany</cell>
                        <cell rend="left">Berlin</cell>
                        <cell rend="left">
                            <hi rend="bold">V. Latin America</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell rend="left"/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell rend="left">Czechoslovakia</cell>
                        <cell rend="left">Prague</cell>
                        <cell rend="left">Mexico</cell>
                        <cell rend="left"/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell rend="left">Hungary</cell>
                        <cell rend="left">Budapest</cell>
                        <cell rend="left">Brazil</cell>
                        <cell rend="left">Rio</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell rend="left">Romania</cell>
                        <cell rend="left">Bucharest</cell>
                        <cell rend="left"/>
                        <cell rend="left"/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell rend="left">Bulgaria</cell>
                        <cell rend="left">Sofia</cell>
                        <cell rend="left"/>
                        <cell rend="left"/>
                    </row>
                    <lb/>
                    <note xml:id="ftn53" n="">Source: RS AJ 130, 567 Proposal of the
                        Federal Secretariat for Information to increase the scope of the program
                        of activities of the News Agency Tanjug abroad and the newspaper
                        Jugoslovenske novosti in 1971, 19. 8. 1970, p. 9.</note>
                </table>
                <lb/>
                <p>Tanjug’s links with foreign agencies followed a similar pattern by being focused
                    on (Western) Europe. Of the 31 agreements with foreign news agencies in 1968,
                    almost half (15) were with agencies from Western Europe (including the global
                    Reuters and AFP), seven with agencies from Eastern Europe (including the Soviet
                    TASS), one with the US-based Associated Press, while just five were with
                    agencies from Africa and the Middle East and the sole agreement in Latin America
                    was with Cuba’s <hi rend="italic">Prensa Latina</hi>.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn54" n="51"> Robinson, <hi rend="italic">Tanjug</hi>,
                    133.</note></p>
                <p>This situation likely reflected Yugoslavia’s foreign policy priorities that had
                    turned away from the Non-Aligned movement during the latter half of the
                        1960s,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn55" n="52">Dinkel, <hi rend="italic"
                            >Bewegung</hi>, 142.</note> but it was also due to the underdevelopment
                    of communication infrastructure in third world countries. National news agencies
                    did not exist in many of such countries and, even where they did, they often did
                    not have the technical capacities to receive Tanjug’s news service, while Tanjug
                    itself lacked the equipment to transmit to large parts of the world: “Central
                    and South Africa and the northern part of South America remain uncovered.
                    Through technical aid we have given 13 complete radio receivers to national news
                    agencies in Asia, Africa and South America. However, Tanjug is unable to
                    guarantee all of them a reliable signal due to the lack of antennae and
                    sufficiently strong radio transmitters”.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn56" n="53"
                        >RS AJ 130, 567 Programme for the development of Tanjug’s technical basis
                        1970–1974, January 1969, p. 11.</note></p>
                <p>The objective conditions for the cooperation with Non-Aligned media and news
                    agencies were deemed “minimal” even as late as 1973.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn57" n="54"> RS DAMSPRS PA R 1973 F-131 Explanation of the draft
                        agenda, 3. 7. 1973, 427164, p. 29.</note> This view was echoed by the
                    interdepartmental group set up by the Federal Executive Council to implement the
                    decisions of the 4<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> NAM Summit: “The objective
                    conditions for furthering this sort of cooperation are minimal as the majority
                    of their [Non-Aligned] agencies do not have an adequate material, technical and
                    financial basis to disseminate information in their own country and to exchange
                    information with other countries”.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn58" n="55">RS
                        DAMSPRS PA R 1973 F-136 Proposal of measures for the implementation of the
                        decisions of the 4<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> NAM summit, december 1973, 451762, p. 39.</note>
                    Another barrier was the lack of trained personnel.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn59" n="56">RS DAMSPRS R 1976 F-180 Information on opportunities
                        for professional education of journalists from non-aligned countries in SFR
                        Yugoslavia, 1. 6. 1976, 439539, p. 3.</note> To help alleviate this
                    problem, the Yugoslav Institute for Journalism in Belgrade was organising short
                    elementary courses for students from developing and Non-Aligned countries after
                    1962, while Tanjug and the public broadcaster JRT were accepting journalists for
                    practical training.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn60" n="57"> Ibid.</note> While
                    Yugoslav universities did offer graduate and postgraduate level journalism
                    courses, few students from Non-Aligned countries applied, favouring the natural
                        sciences.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn61" n="58">RS DAMSPRS PA R 1980 F-219
                        Information on mutual cooperation of non-aligned countries in the field of
                        information, education and science, 4. 9. 1980, 455813, p. 15. </note></p>
                <p>Therefore, as Tanjug and the federal government were looking to expand to
                    Non-Aligned and other developing countries, they faced significant barriers.
                    Maintaining a global network of correspondents was costly and Tanjug attempted
                    to stretch its limited resources by relying on news exchange agreements.
                    However, national news agencies simply did not exist in many third world
                    countries or were unable to participate in news exchange by lacking equipment,
                    finances, and trained personnel. Tanjug’s attempts to stimulate NAM countries to
                    establish news agencies and to encourage cooperation were likely a consequence
                    of the fact that its existing growth strategy had reached its limits.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Establishing Information as an Area of Cooperation Within NAM</head>
                <p>At the 1972 Georgetown conference, economic cooperation between NAM members was
                    institutionalised in the form of coordinators for specific areas of cooperation
                    and an action plan for economic cooperation, which laid out concrete steps to be
                    taken in the future. As Yugoslavia was attempting to expand the areas of
                    economic cooperation to include information, these were the institutional forms
                    serving as a blueprint. To be compatible with the movement's institutional
                    history and ethos, NANAP had to be recontextualised in terms of multilateral
                    economic cooperation. Yet, at the same time, NANAP was used to expedite the
                    institutionalisation of informational cooperation within NAM since it was
                    believed that a practical success would prove to other NAM members that
                    strengthening informational cooperation was a worthwhile endeavour.</p>
                <p>The Yugoslav efforts to put information on NAM’s agenda could already be seen at
                    the 4<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> NAM summit in Algiers. A working paper
                    prepared by the Secretariat for Foreign Affairs following the Preparatory
                    Committee’s meeting in Kabul (13–15 May) stressed the need for closer
                    cooperation in the areas of education, culture, science and information of
                    Non-Aligned countries in order to further the “international affirmation and
                    emancipation of their natural cultures”.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn62" n="59"
                        >RS DAMSPRS PA R 1973 F-131 Explanation of the draft agenda of the 4<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> NAM
                        summit, 3. 7. 1973, 427167, p. 27.</note> Information was pointed out as an
                    area where “cooperation hardly exists” and Non-Aligned countries are beholden to
                    “the monopolies of the big global information sources”<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn63" n="60">Ibid., p. 29.</note>. The primary goal set out in the
                    document is to further cooperation between national news agencies where they
                    exist, and to help establish national news agencies where they do not. </p>
                <p>In the run-up to the summit, several Yugoslav news media came forward with
                    suggestions to expand Non-Aligned cooperation: The public broadcaster JRT
                    suggested that the summit recommend closer collaboration between Non-Aligned
                        media<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn64" n="61">RS DAMSPRS PA R 1973 F-131
                        Note on the conversation with comrade Frank Winter, Director-General of
                        Radio-Television Zagreb, 18. 7. 1973, 429625.</note> while the publishing
                    house <hi rend="italic">Novi List</hi> from Rijeka suggested the establishment
                    of a “League of newspapers, broadcasters and news agencies of Non-Aligned
                    countries” to further information exchange.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn65"
                        n="62">RS DAMSPRS PA R 1973 F-131 Proposal for the establishment of the
                        League of Newspapers, Broadcasting Stations and News Agencies of non-aligned
                        countries, 22. 8. 1973, 435471, p.1.</note> For this summit, a draft
                    resolution, outlining measures to strengthen news agencies in Non-Aligned
                    countries and the cooperation between them, was prepared by Tanjug in
                    cooperation with the Federal Secretariat for Information.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn66" n="63">RS AJ KPR 1973 I-4-a/15 Information on some proposals
                        of institutions and organizations regarding the 4th NAM Summit. 4. 4. 1973,
                        pp. 6–9.</note> Yugoslavia submitted a draft resolution calling for
                    strengthening the means of information and communication, increased cooperation
                    and exchange in more abstract terms than the draft resolution which had been
                    prepared by Tanjug and the Federal Secretariat for Information.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn67" n="64">RS AJ KPR 1973 I-4-a/15 Draft resolution
                        on cooperation of non-aligned countries in the fields of education, science,
                        culture, information and sports, 18. 8. 1973.</note></p>
                <p>The final summit documents contain sections promoting the cooperation of the mass
                    media and emphasising the need for Non-Aligned countries to mutually inform each
                    other about their activities and achievements in the action programme for
                    economic co-operation, as well as a section condemning the influence of
                    “imperialism” on national cultures in the political declaration. The final
                    documents of the summit are more abstract than the drafts prepared by Yugoslavia
                    and Tanjug and the political declaration is notably more aggressive in
                    condemning “imperialism”, “alien cultural domination” and “cultural alienation
                    /…/ imposed by imperialism and colonialism”.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn68"
                        n="65">”Documents of the 4th Summit Conference of Heads of State or
                        Government of the Non-Aligned Movement, Algiers, Algeria, 5. – 9. September
                        1973,”
                        <ref target="http://cns.miis.edu/nam/documents/Official_Document/4th_Summit_FD_Algiers_Declaration_1973_Whole.pdf">http://cns.miis.edu/nam/documents/Official_Document/4th_Summit_FD_Algiers_Declaration_1973_Whole.pdf</ref>,
                        73.</note> This is quite a change in direction from the very sombre and
                    practical Yugoslav drafts, which had sought to phrase the issues in a way that
                    would not antagonise the West.</p>
                <p>Yugoslavia continued its efforts at future events. At a meeting of the
                    Coordinating Bureau in Algiers (19–22 March 1974), the need to strengthen
                    cooperation between Non-Aligned mass media was reiterated.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn69" n="66">RS DAMSPRS PA R 1974 F-173 Telegram from the Yugoslav
                        embassy in Algiers, 22. 3. 1974, 413849. </note> Further steps were taken at
                    the first meeting of coordinators of economic activity in Belgrade (9–13
                    September 1974) where the Yugoslav delegation proposed to broaden the scope of
                    economic cooperation to cover new areas, including mass communications, science,
                    culture, and health.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn70" n="67">RS DAMSPRS PA R
                        1974 F-173 Telegram from the cabinet of adviser and assistant to the Federal
                        Secretary Berislav Badurina 23. 7. 1974, 434924. </note></p>
                <p>The Secretariat for Foreign Affairs soon after sent a telegram reminding all
                    diplomatic missions to work towards the goal of naming coordinators for the
                    field of information within NAM according to the agreement reached at the
                    Belgrade meeting of the Coordinating Bureau.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn71"
                        n="68">RS DAMSPRS PA R 1974 F-174 Addendum to the circular dispach from the
                        Federal Secretariat for Information, 26. 9. 1974, 445442. </note> Tunisia
                    was regarded as a preferred candidate for this position<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn72" n="69">RS DAMSPRS PA R 1974 F-174 Telegram from the cabinet
                        of the Deputy Federal Secretary, 23. 10. 1974, 450846. </note> and
                    Yugoslavia was engaging in intensive diplomatic activity to make it happen.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn73" n="70">RS DAMSPRS PA R F-172 Note on the
                        conversation between the President of the Federal Secretariat for
                        Information, Muhamed Berberović, and the Ambassador of the Republic of
                        Tunisia to the SFRY, Talib Sahbani, 13. 2. 1975, 47580, p. 1. </note></p>
                <p>Yugoslavia remained in close contact with Tunisia throughout this period,
                    especially with Mustapha Masmoudi, the Tunisian Minister for Information from
                    September 1974 onward. Bilateral relations between the countries were judged to
                    be excellent<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn74" n="71">RS DAMSPRS PA TUNIS 1976
                        F-151 Report on Tunisia's foreign and domestic policy and Yugoslav-Tunisian
                        bilateral relations in 1975, 28. 1. 1976, 45900. </note> and Masmoudi shared
                    Yugoslavia’s views on the need to institutionalise informational cooperation
                    within NAM. The Tunisian news agency TAP helped further Tanjug’s plans by
                    inviting Ivačić to a symposium of Afro-Arab news agencies that Tunisia was
                    chairing in 1975. The symposium endorsed participation in NANAP by adopting a
                    recommendation for Afro-Arab news agencies, which helped promote the pool’s
                    cause within NAM, and facilitated bilateral contacts between Tanjug and the
                    participating news agencies. </p>
                <p>The Yugoslav embassy in Tunis was particularly pleased that the recommendation
                    omits mention of Yugoslavia or Tanjug: “The recommendation does not mention
                    Tanjug and Yugoslavia and in this way the pool is given a broad multilateral
                    basis of non-alignment”.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn75" n="72">RS DAMSPRS PA R
                        1975 F-172 Telegram from the Yugoslav embassy in Tunis, 1. 3. 1975, 410687.
                    </note> It appears the Yugoslav diplomats were afraid Yugoslavia’s leading role
                    would be viewed with suspicion within NAM as an attempt to hegemonise the
                    movement and therefore wished to downplay and disguise its level of involvement.
                    The fact that very few other countries were showing initiative is a key reason
                    Yugoslavia was eager to institutionalise information as an area of cooperation
                    within NAM: “in this way more countries are included in responsibilities and
                    directly engaged in furthering these activities, in which our country has had a
                    pronounced leading role due to circumstances”.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn76"
                        n="73">RS DAMSPRS PA R 1974 F-174 Development of non-aligned cooperation in
                        the field of information, 23. 12. 1974, 461149, p. 11. </note>
                </p>
                <p>Yugoslavia hoped that a coordinator in the area of information would be named at
                    the ministerial conference in Lima.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn77" n="74">RS
                        DAMSPRS PA R 1975 F-175 Telegram from the cabinet of adviser and assistant
                        to the Federal Secretary Berislav Badurina, 18. 7. 1975, 436147. </note> In
                    the lead-up to the meeting, India began to show increased interest in
                    institutionalising NANAP and had prepared a draft working paper for the Lima
                        conference.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn78" n="75">RS DAMSPRS R 1975 F-175
                        Note on the conversation of special adviser A. Demajo with Indian press and
                        culture adviser Sakher, 6. 8. 1975, 438233, p. 1. </note> The Indian draft
                    heavily stresses the need to institutionalise NANAP on a multilateral basis, to
                    develop it according to a “polycentric basis” by establishing regional centres,
                    and suggests that its management be taken over by “a council of government
                    representatives or by a board of directors”.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn79"
                        n="76">Ibid., pp. 2–4.</note> The Federal Secretariat for Foreign Affairs
                    viewed the Indian initiative favourably.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn80" n="77"
                        >RS DAMSPRS PA R 1975 F-175 Telegram from the eighth administration to
                        Yugoslav embassy in New Delhi. 13. 8. 1975, 439523. </note> The ministerial
                    conference in Lima adopted a resolution (VI. Cooperation in the areas of
                    information and mass media), which gives support to NANAP and names Tunisia as
                    the coordinator for information.</p>
                <p>Two aspects emerge from the archival sources regarding the institutionalisation
                    of Non-Aligned cooperation in the information field. The first is that
                    Yugoslavia was clearly the driving force, while there seems to be a lack of
                    enthusiasm from other countries. The most likely cause is found in the
                    underdevelopment of communication infrastructure as even in 1973 the Yugoslav
                    estimates were that the conditions for the cooperation of Non-Aligned news
                    agencies and mass media were minimal. Even guaranteeing reliable radio
                    transmissions was a challenge, let alone creating the conditions for
                    professional journalistic production able to compete with the global agencies.
                    With the notable exception of Tunisia, which shared Yugoslavia’s views and
                    commitment to furthering Non-Aligned cooperation in the area of
                        information,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn81" n="78">RS DAMSPRS PA Tunis
                        1976 F-151 Report on Tunisia's foreign and domestic policy and
                        Yugoslav-Tunisian bilateral relations in 1975, 28. 1. 1976, 45900, pp.
                        43–47. </note> other Non-Aligned nations seemed hesitant to commit
                    themselves to the idea, as seen in Yugoslavia’s inability to ensure concrete
                    steps were taken in this direction. The position of India began to shift in
                    mid-1975, around the time Indira Gandhi had declared a state of emergency, when
                    India took a much more active interest particularly in NANAP and began pushing
                    for its multilateral institutionalisation and acting towards hosting the first
                    NANAP conference.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>The Launch of NANAP</head>
                <p>While progress in institutionalising information as an area of cooperation among
                    the Non-Aligned countries was slow, Yugoslavia was putting its hopes in
                    strengthening bilateral cooperation between national news agencies in
                    preparation for of NANAP’s launch in January 1975. In September 1974, all
                    Yugoslav diplomatic missions received a circular dispatch from the Federal
                    Secretariat for Information, informing them that the federal government had
                    adopted an action plan to further cooperation among Non-Aligned mass media as a
                    way of implementing the decisions of the 4<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> NAM
                        summit.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn82" n="79"> RS DAMSPRS PA R 1974 F-174
                        Elaboration of the decisions of the Algiers summit related to the field of
                        mass communications, 16. 9. 1974, 447476. </note> The dispatch describes
                    four ongoing activities:</p>
                <list type="unordered">
                    <item>strengthening Tanjug’s bilateral ties with other Non-Aligned news agencies
                        and actions to establish an “interagency ‘pool’”;</item>
                    <item>boosting cooperation among broadcasting organisations;</item>
                    <item>cooperation between national associations of journalists; and</item>
                    <item>facilitating cooperation among newsreel organisations.</item>
                </list>
                <lb/>
                <p>While the other activities were in their very early stages, NANAP was already
                    well advanced since Tanjug had in cooperation with Yugoslav embassies sounded
                    out existing Non-Aligned news agencies regarding the question of intensifying
                    cooperation and the feedback was deemed positive enough to proceed with the
                    planned launch of the pool.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn83" n="80">Ibid. pp. 1,
                        2.</note></p>
                <p>The goal was for NANAP to start its first phase of operation – meaning Tanjug
                    would extend its radio printer transmissions to include news items from the pool
                    – before the Coordinating Bureau meeting in February 1975 and the meeting of
                    news agencies of African and Arab countries in the same year.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn84" n="81"> RS DAMSPRS PA R 1974 F-174 Development of non-aligned
                        cooperation in the field of information, 23. 12. 1974, 461149, p. 3. </note>
                    This was seen as a way of influencing NAM’s decisions in favour of
                    institutionalising informational cooperation. The declaration from the Havana
                    meeting of the Coordinating Bureau confirms this, citing the existence of NANAP
                    as a reason for naming coordinators: “Given that cooperation in the area of
                    disseminating information and in the area of mass media is already ongoing /…/
                    the Bureau recommends that coordinators be named”.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn85" n="82">RS DAMSPRS PA R F-172 Declaration adopted at the
                        Ministerial Meeting of the Coordinating Bureau of Non-Aligned Countries,
                        held in Havana (Cuba) on 17–19 March 1975. March 1975, 414394, p.
                    25.</note></p>
                <p>In the second phase, pool items would be transmitted through several agencies
                    according to “geographic and linguistic keys”.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn86"
                        n="83">RS DAMSPRS PA R 1974 F-174 Development of non-aligned cooperation in
                        the field of information, 23. 12. 1974, 461149, p. 3 </note> This phase was
                    considered more delicate due to the “prestige-oriented and political interests
                    of some agencies”, for example the interests of certain agencies to maintain
                    existing regional alliances or their leading roles in their respective
                        regions.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn87" n="84">Ibid.</note> At this point,
                    11 news agencies had already agreed to take part in the pool (from Algiers,
                    Egypt, Tunisia, Iraq, Libya, Palestine, Mali, Sudan, Ghana, Cuba, Mexico), while
                    negotiations with a further 20 were still underway.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn88" n="85">Ibid., p. 4.</note>
                </p>
                <p>The Press Trust of India, the intended Indian partner, however, was conspicuous
                    by its absence from the list.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn89" n="86">RS DAMSPRS
                        PA R 1974 F-174 Development of non-aligned cooperation in the field of
                        information, 23. 12. 1974, 461149, p. 4. </note> The sources in the Yugoslav
                    archives do not provide more than speculation as to the causes, ranging from
                    technical difficulties to the influence of Reuters. In any case, PTI’s reticence
                    in joining the pool was seen as a problem because it was believed that “the
                    inclusion of India in the pool would stimulate the interest of other NA
                    [Non-Aligned] in Asia and would remove any suspicion that it was conceived on a
                    regional basis”.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn90" n="87">RS DAMSPRS PA 1975
                        F-172 Telegram from the Yugoslav embassy in New Delhi, 5. 2. 1975, 45458.
                    </note> The Yugoslav embassy in New Delhi reported that a spokesman for the
                    Indian Ministry of Foreign Affairs and for the government had informed them that
                    “the position of PTI is not the same as the official position of the Indian
                    government” and that “India will contribute news items to the pool via its
                    embassy in Belgrade regardless of PTI and its editor-in-chief Raghavan”.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn91" n="88">RS DAMSPRS PA 1975 F-172 Telegram from
                        the Yugoslav embassy in New Delhi, 19. 2. 1975 48333. </note> These initial
                    difficulties foreshadowed future problems as the participation of India’s
                    national news agencies became even more difficult after Indira Gandhi’s fall
                    from power, as NANAP was linked with the measures to suppress freedom of the
                    press during her state of emergency.</p>
                <p>The pool commenced operation on 20 January 1975 by transmitting the statements of
                    Non-Aligned leaders, beginning with the prime minister of Sri Lanka Sirimavo
                    Bandaranaike, followed by Tito the next day and further statements by
                    Non-Aligned leaders every day.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn92" n="89">RS
                        DAMSPRS PA 1975 F-172, Telegram from the cabinet of adviser and assistant to
                        the Federal Secretary Živan Berisavljević to all Yugoslav embassies and the
                        permanent missions in New York, Geneva and Unesco, Paris, 27. 1. 1975, p. 1.
                    </note> The information service of the UN (OPI-UN) as well as that of UNESCO
                    voiced their intentions to supply NANAP with their news,<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn93" n="90"> Ibid. p. 2.</note> while Živan Berisavljević, adviser
                    and assistant to the Federal Secretary for Foreign Affairs, noted the negative
                    reactions from certain Western news agencies (AFP, DPA, Reuters) and the
                    reserved stance of the USSR and the GDR on the initiative.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn94" n="91">Ibid.</note> The USSR remained unenthusiastic, as
                    “Latisev [the editor of TASS] expressed a negative attitude of the USSR towards
                    the pool” in March 1976.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn95" n="92">RS DAMSPRS PA R
                        1976 F-179 Telegram from the Yugoslav embassy in Moscow, 1. 3. 1976, 411249.
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p>Ensuring the success of NANAP was a priority of the Yugoslav government as may be
                    seen from the instructions issued to all Yugoslav diplomatic missions in
                    Non-Aligned countries: “It is required that all DKP [Diplomatic-consular
                    representations] in NA [Non-Aligned] countries keep up to date on the practical
                    effects (impact on publicity, technical and other eventual difficulties) as well
                    as the political ramifications of this pool. Full engagement and quick reactions
                    are expected from all DKPs, including suggestions for further developing this
                    action, which has a distinctly political character.”<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn96" n="93">RS DAMSPRS PA 1975 F-172 Telegram from the cabinet of
                        adviser and assistant to the Federal Secretary Živan Berisavljević to all
                        Yugoslav embassies and the permanent missions in New York, Geneva and
                        Unesco, Paris, 27. 1. 1975, 43488, p. 3. </note></p>
                <p>By April, the number of participating agencies had risen to 18 (19 including
                    Tanjug); in addition to the 11 starting members, these were: Argentina, India,
                    Bangladesh, Cambodia, the Provisional Revolutionary Government of South Vietnam,
                    Malesia, and Chad, while news agencies from Zambia and Mali had agreed to
                    participate but were unable to do so.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn97" n="94">RS
                        DAMSPRS PA R 1975 F-173 Telegram from cabinet of adviser and assistant to
                        the Federal Secretary Živan Berisavljević to Yugoslav embassies, 15. 4.
                        1975, 418539, p. 1. </note> Yet, it is unclear to what extent the named
                    agencies actually participated in the pool since India was still participating
                    via its embassy in Belgrade, while efforts were being taken to persuade PTI,
                    including a visit from Ivačić and “pressure from the government”.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn98" n="95">RS DAMSPRS PA R 1975 F-173 Telegram from
                        the Yugoslav embassy in New Delhi, 28. 4. 1975, 420925. </note></p>
                <p>There seems to have been some reluctance in the news media to make use of items
                    supplied through the pool: “We are not even satisfied with the attitude of our
                    own press, in which the inertia towards news items from news agencies is still
                    not overcome. Actions along state and party lines are being taken to quickly
                    overcome this state of affairs”.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn99" n="96">RS
                        DAMSPRS PA R 1975 F-173 Telegram from the cabinet of adviser and assistant
                        to the Federal Secretary Živan Berisavljević to Yugoslav embassies, 15. 4.
                        1975, 418539, p. 1. </note> The reluctance of news media to rely on NANAP
                    items was reported by Yugoslav embassies in Libya<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn100" n="97">RS DAMSPRS PA R 1975 F-173 Telegram from the Yugoslav
                        embassy in Tripoli, 21. 4. 1975, 419864. </note> and Egypt,<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn101" n="98">RS DAMSPRS PA R 1975 F-173 Telegram from
                        the Yugoslav embassy in Cairo, 30. 4. 1975, 421714. </note> while newspapers
                    in Ghana and one Mexican newspaper were described as making good use of
                        NANAP.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn102" n="99">RS DAMSPRS PA R 1975 F-175
                        Status and prospects of the Non-Aligned News Agencies Pool, 25. 7. 1975,
                        437390. </note> However, the circulation of pool items was not
                    systematically tracked and it is hard to tell how widely news items from the
                    pool were circulated at this point.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Institutionalising NANAP</head>
                <p>Activities intensified during 1976 as this was the year of the 5<hi
                        rend="superscript">th</hi> NAM summit in Colombo, which had to ratify what
                    had been achieved up until then. The activities in this year reflect remarkably
                    well the Yugoslav plans for further actions laid out in 1974. The symposium
                    proposed by the Yugoslav Institute for Journalism and other organisations was
                    held in Tunis in March, while in August India hosted a meeting of
                    representatives of news agencies and of ministers of information in New Delhi,
                    which adopted the NANAP statute and named its coordinating body. Finally,
                    Yugoslavia was able to attract Tunisia and India to take an active role in
                    furthering informational cooperation. </p>
                <p>The symposium in Tunis was viewed as a possibility to advance the
                    institutionalisation of informational cooperation.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn103" n="100">DA PA R 1975 F-174 Telegram from the Yugoslav
                        embassy in Tunis, 15. 11. 1975, 455140, p. 599. </note> The Federal
                    Secretariat for Information considered the symposium “very significant” and
                    attributed a “political character” to it.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn104"
                        n="101">DA PA R 1975 F-174 Telegram from the Federal Secretariat for
                        Information, 18. 12. 1975, 460018 , p. 1.</note> Even though Tunisia was the
                    official host, Yugoslavia was closely involved in all aspects of organising the
                    symposium, from the preparation of documents to logistical and financial
                    matters. The symposium was an opportunity for representatives from Non-Aligned
                    countries (media representatives, scholars, state representatives) to discuss
                    the Non-Aligned informational cooperation in depth. The symposium’s impact is
                    hard to judge since it only adopted recommendations, although its true value was
                    likely to be found in facilitating informal contacts and the open discussion
                    freed from the need to negotiate a resolution or declaration.</p>
                <p>The New Delhi meeting was in many ways the opposite of the Tunis symposium. If
                    the symposium was the culmination of cooperation between Yugoslavia and Tunisia,
                    in New Delhi India asserted its will against their wishes. While significant
                    political decisions were taken at the meeting, it was also marked by political
                    conflict and a battle for prestige. India seems to have increased its activity
                    regarding NANAP more for political and prestigious reasons than a genuine
                    interest in furthering the cooperation among news agencies. While Yugoslavia and
                    Tunisia argued that the meeting was to be held at the level of representatives
                    of news agencies and to focus on NANAP, India insisted that the meeting be held
                    on a ministerial level and the agenda be broadened to include all aspects of
                    informational cooperation. Yugoslavia accepted this since the belief was that
                    “we judged that it is very important to India to host a ministerial meeting of
                    NA [Non-Aligned], especially after similar Indian initiatives have failed (CB
                    [Coordinating Bureau], the summit of Asian NA), and this due to both
                    foreign-political and domestic-political reasons”.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn105" n="102">RS DAMSPRS PA R 1976 F-180 Telegram from the cabinet
                        of adviser and assistant to the Federal Secretary Živan Berisavljević to
                        Yugoslav diplomatic and consular missions, 7. 5. 1976, 425354, p. 2. </note>
                </p>
                <p>Because the New Delhi meeting had been elevated to a ministerial level, it was
                    disrupted by political conflicts: “First the minister of Laos attacked ASEAN
                    countries, calling them ‘an extended arm of NATO’. /…/ Then the Palestinians
                    attacked the Syrians because of the invasion of Lebanon and accused them of
                    hindering the liberation struggle of the nation of Palestine. /…/ The atmosphere
                    became especially heated when the minister of Sudan accused Libya of attempting
                    a coup and trying to murder Nimeiry. /…/ The Indians attempted to prevent these
                    accusations, pleading with the representatives that the conference was not a
                    place for such dialogue, yet without success.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn106"
                        n="103"> RS DAMSPRS PA R 1976 F-180, Telegram from the Yugoslav embassy in
                        New Delhi, 12. 7. 1976, 438623, p. 1. </note></p>
                <p>The events in New Delhi foreshadowed the way political divisions within NAM would
                    hinder the operation of NANAP, for instance, the conflict between the Arab
                    states and Egypt after Egypt had signed a peace treaty with Israel. Since the
                    Arab countries demanded that Egypt be expelled from NAM, they also put the
                    participation of Egypt’s news agency in NANAP in question. The second NANAP
                    conference, planned to be held before the 6<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> summit
                    in Havana, was postponed in the hope the issue of Egypt’s membership would be
                    settled there. However, as the resolution of the issue had simply been
                    rescheduled, the conflict between Egypt and the Arab states marked the NANAP
                    conference despite the postponement. </p>
                <p>Another political factor also came into the foreground as NANAP – and broader
                    questions of informational cooperation – became the fighting grounds for
                    political prestige. India’s ambitions caused some controversy on the side of
                    Tunisia, Masmoudi and Triki (director-general of the Tunisian news agency TAP)
                    “talked about the behaviour of the host – India – with indignation. They
                    believed the primary goal of India is to downplay the role of Tunisia as the
                    coordinator for the area of information and to impose themselves as the main
                    factor, diminishing everything that has been achieved so far”.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn107" n="104">RS DAMSPRS PA R 1976 F-180 Telegram from the
                        Yugoslav embassy in Tunis, 24. 7. 1976, 440376, p. 1. The view was echoed by
                        Tanzanian participants, see DA PA R 1976 F-180 Telegram from the Yugoslav
                        embassy in Dar es Salaam, 30. 7. 1976, 441829. </note> They suspected –
                    correctly, as it later turned out – that India would attempt to replace Tunisia
                    with Sri Lanka as the coordinator for information.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn108" n="105">RS DAMSPRS PA R 1976 F-180 Telegram from the
                        Yugoslav embassy in Tunis, 24. 7. 1976, 440376, p. 1. </note></p>
                <p>Despite such political differences, the delegates managed to conclude the
                    meeting, adopting the NANAP statute, a political declaration, two resolutions
                    (Action Plan of Cooperation and the Resolution Regarding Cable Rates) and a
                    draft paragraph for the 5<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> NAM summit, as well as
                    naming NANAP’s governing body. The Coordinating Committee of NANAP was “based on
                    regional parity and composed of directors of news agencies from the following
                    countries: India as chairman, Indonesia, Yugoslavia, Peru, Zaire, Iraq,
                    Mauritius, Egypt, Cuba, Ghana, Vietnam, Senegal, Tunisia and Mexico”.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn109" n="106">RS AJ KPR i-4-a/25 Report of the
                        Yugoslav delegation from the Conference of Ministers of Information of
                        Non-Aligned Countries on the POOL of news agencies, 21. 7. 1976, p. 4</note>
                    The statute specifies that the Coordinating Committee must meet at least once
                    annually, while representatives of governments and news agencies must meet at
                    the start of each summit year.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn110" n="107">
                        Ibid.</note> The Federal Secretariat for Information judged the results to
                    be “perfectly satisfactory”.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn111" n="108">RS
                        DAMSPRS PA R 1976 F-180 Circular dispatch from the Federal Secretariat for
                        Information to all Yugoslav diplomatic missions, 27. 7. 1976, 440566, p. 4.
                    </note></p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Summary and Discussion</head>
                <p>The main driving force behind the emergence and institutionalisation of NANAP was
                    Yugoslavia, where Tanjug and the federal political elites found a common cause
                    in strengthening Tanjug’s ties with Non-Aligned news agencies. Yugoslavia pushed
                    to include mass media cooperation in the documents of the 4<hi
                        rend="superscript">th</hi> NAM summit and to ensure further steps in
                    institutionalising mass media cooperation within NAM: the Tunis symposium on
                    communication and meetings of Non-Aligned information ministers and news
                    agencies, as well as BONAC and connections between Non-Aligned journalistic
                    institutes and associations. NANAP served as both a blueprint for other forms of
                    informational cooperation and as proof of concept since Yugoslavia wanted to
                    further informational cooperation and its institutionalisation by providing
                    other NAM leaders with a successful example.</p>
                <p>NANAP may be considered a success by several metrics. The institutionalisation of
                    news agencies’ cooperation within NAM helped Tanjug’s efforts by facilitating
                    contacts with other news agencies and encouraging the development of bilateral
                    relations. NANAP exhibited steady growth over the following 25 years, expanding
                    to encompass more than 50 news agencies and government information services by
                        1980<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn112" n="109">RS DAMSPRS PA R 1980 F-219
                        Informacija o medjusobnoj saradnji nesvrstanih zemalja u oblasti
                        informacija, obrazovanja i nauke, 4. 9. 1980, 455813, p. 4. </note> and 103
                    by 1992. To indicate scale, the 6th NAM summit in 1979 was attended by 89 member
                        states<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn113" n="110">”Documents of the 6th
                        Summit Conference of Heads of State or Government of the Non-Aligned
                        Movement, Havana, Cuba, 3. – 9. September 1979,”
                            <ref target="http://cns.miis.edu/nam/documents/Official_Document/6th_Summit_FD_Havana_Declaration_1979_Whole.pdf">http://cns.miis.edu/nam/documents/Official_Document/6th_Summit_FD_Havana_Declaration_1979_Whole.pdf</ref>,
                        6.</note> while the 10th NAM summit in 1992 attracted 101.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn114" n="111">”Documents of the 10th Summit Conference of Heads of
                        State or Government of the Non-Aligned Movement, Jakarta, Indonesia, 1. – 6.
                        September 1992,”
                            <ref target="http://cns.miis.edu/nam/documents/Official_Document/10th_Summit_FD_Jakarta_Declaration_1992_Whole.pdf">http://cns.miis.edu/nam/documents/Official_Document/10th_Summit_FD_Jakarta_Declaration_1992_Whole.pdf</ref>.</note>
                    NANAP’s output grew as well; in 1975, the average daily number of words
                    exchanged among participating news agencies was 8,000,<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn115" n="112">Boyd-Barrett and Thussu, <hi rend="italic"
                            >Contra-Flow</hi>, 71.</note> rising to 40,000 words by 1983<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn116" n="113"> Coordinating Committee, <hi
                            rend="italic">News Agencies Pool</hi>, 23.</note> and 120,000 by
                        1992<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn117" n="114">Boyd-Barrett and Thussu, <hi
                            rend="italic">Contra-Flow</hi>, 71.</note>. While this increase was
                    considerable, it still paled in comparison to the output of the ‘Big Four’.
                    Namely, in 1978 AP, UPI, AFP and Reuters were outputting 33 million words
                        daily.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn118" n="115">Phil Harris, “Le
                        monde des agences de presse,” <hi rend="italic">International Commission for
                            the Study of Communication Problems</hi>, 11 (Paris: UNESCO,
                        1978).</note> Further, NANAP was also credited for contributing to:
                    “improving telecommunication facilities, including satellites, lowering
                    transmission rates, and increasing training facilities for news agency
                    journalists and assistance to establishment of agencies in countries without
                    such services”.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn119" n="116">MacBride Commission,
                            <hi rend="italic">Many Voices, One World</hi> (Paris: Unesco, 1980),
                        85.</note></p>
                <p>In order to explain the process of NANAP’s creation and early
                    institutionalisation, I have presented three factors: internal, external, and
                    those rooted in NAM’s institutional history.</p>
                <p>Since Yugoslavia was the main driving force behind NANAP, the goals and
                    strategies of Yugoslav actors, chiefly those of Tanjug and the federal political
                    elites, were a key influence on NANAP’s development and the informational
                    cooperation within NAM more broadly. Tanjug had an interest in strengthening its
                    ties with Non-Aligned news agencies. There is no indication that the cause was a
                    political commitment to the idea of non-alignment, but it was framed through the
                    need to bolster the agency’s position in the competitive global marketplace of
                    news. News exchange agreements had already been established as the preferred way
                    of establishing ties with foreign news agencies and were not specific to Tanjug.
                    Especially for a relatively small – at least compared to the big global agencies
                    – and financially limited news agency like Tanjug, this was a way of stretching
                    its limited resources and supplementing its own network of correspondents.
                    Tanjug’s interests coincided with the interests of the federal political elites
                    as strengthening Tanjug’s position in the world market was seen as a way of
                    influencing public opinion in Yugoslavia’s favour. Tanjug’s expansion to the
                    Non-Aligned world was viewed positively and supported by the Yugoslav state,
                    especially the Federal Secretariat for Foreign Affairs, as Tanjug’s information
                    infrastructure was seen as helping to promote Yugoslavia’s viewpoints in the
                    world as well as a mechanism for facilitating information exchange between state
                    institutions.</p>
                <p>The second are external factors, namely, changes in international relations on a
                    global scale as well as within the Non-Aligned Movement. With the rising gap
                    between rich and poor countries, disillusionment with the UN, slowing global
                    economic growth and the breakdown of the Bretton-Woods system in 1971, NAM began
                    to focus attention on North-South economic disparities and practical efforts for
                    boosting “self-reliance”, that is, strengthening South-South cooperation to
                    improve its position within the global economy and increase its bargaining power
                    vis-à-vis the developed countries. These efforts came to encompass information
                    as well, largely due to Yugoslav efforts.</p>
                <p>The third are factors rooted in institutional history. Even though NANAP was an
                    extension of Tanjug’s bilateral relations with Non-Aligned agencies and its
                    interest in expanding to developing countries, the pool was recontextualised
                    within the drive to institutionalise “self-reliance” through economic
                    cooperation and had to be adapted to the established forms of this cooperation.
                    Pre-existing forms of economic cooperation thus provided a blueprint for the
                    institutionalisation of NANAP and informational cooperation more generally. The
                    prevailing institutional ethos of NAM, reflecting strong opposition to
                    centralisation, shaped the formation of NANAP as a decentralised, multilateral
                    project. Although Yugoslavia was clearly the leading force, it had to disguise
                    and downplay the level of its involvement and was investing considerable effort
                    to attract active cooperation from other NAM countries (particularly Tunisia and
                    India) and presenting NANAP as a multilateral project with a broad basis of
                    support from the outset, even though this was certainly not the case.</p>
                <p>While NANAP achieved impressive growth up until the end of the Cold War,
                    furthered Tanjug’s goals of expanding its presence in the Non-Aligned world and
                    boosted Yugoslavia’s prestige within NAM, there were also important limitations
                    to NANAP’s development. Political divisions within NAM came to hinder the
                    operation of NANAP, it became a battleground for prestige and influence within
                    the movement and was very publicly tied to undemocratic practices of NAM leaders
                    like Indira Gandhi. Curtailment of the freedom of the press by Non-Aligned
                    governments supplied the Western media – most of which were already hostile to
                    the very notion that imbalances in global information and communication flows
                    needed to be addressed – with proof that NANAP was simply a ploy whereby
                    autocrats wished to stifle freedom of expression.</p>
                <p>The factors shaping NANAP’s early development often contradicted each other, for
                    example, the interest of Tanjug and the Yugoslav federal elites in increasing
                    Tanjug’s presence in Western media was counteracted by the need to
                    institutionalise NANAP as a multilateral project within NAM. From the beginning,
                    we can see that the very benevolent rhetoric proposed by Yugoslavia for the
                    Algiers summit had turned into a belligerent battle cry against cultural
                    imperialism during the summit. While former colonies certainly had very good
                    reasons to feel antagonistic towards the cultural domination imposed by their
                    former colonial masters, this antagonistic stance flew in the face of Tanjug’s
                    efforts to cooperate with Western media, and the goal of increasing positive
                    portrayals of the Non-Aligned countries in the West. Similarly, Article 5 of the
                    NANAP statute tasked the pool with: “strengthening the unity of the member
                    countries of the Non-Aligned Movement and the decolonisation of
                        information”.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn120" n="117">Coordinating
                        Committee, <hi rend="italic">News Agencies Pool</hi>, 216.</note> Such an
                    explicit political mandate was antithetical to the dominant normative
                    conceptualisations of journalism in the West and likely strengthened suspicions
                    that information from NANAP could not be relied on.</p>
                <p>Moreover, the institutionalisation within NAM compounded another pre-existing
                    problem; namely, that many participating news agencies lacked autonomy from
                    state institutions and reproduced government propaganda, by further politicising
                    the pool’s operation. The conflict between the Arab states and Egypt caused the
                    second NANAP conference to be postponed until after the 6th NAM summit in
                    Havana, and continued to plague the conference since the summit failed to
                    resolve the issue. Another problem was that NAM states could easily regard the
                    inclusion of an item critical of them as an affront, and conflicts between
                    members were certainly impossible to report without causing a diplomatic
                    incident. The need to gain support within NAM and present NANAP as a
                    multilateral project from the very start led Yugoslavia to support India’s bid
                    to coordinate NANAP, even though Indian news agencies did not participate in
                    NANAP. India assumed the role of NANAP coordinator just as attempts to curtail
                    the freedom of the press were in full swing during Indira Gandhi’s state of
                        emergency.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn121" n="118">George Verghese,
                        “Press Censorship under Indira Gandhi,” <hi rend="italic">in: The Third World
                            and Press Freedom</hi>, ed. P. C. Horton (New York: Praeger, 1978),
                        220–30.</note> This unfortunate state of affairs not only added to animosity
                    in the West, but also permanently damaged NANAP’s reputation among Indian
                    journalists.</p>
                <p>Finally, NANAP’s establishment did not solve the problems of underdeveloped
                    information and communication infrastructure in third world countries: the lack
                    of technology, finances, trained personnel and in many cases of autonomy from
                    political institutions continued to plague NANAP’s operations in the time of its
                    existence. Contributions to the pool remained uneven, with just a few countries
                    contributing most of the items, the overall quality of news items remained low,
                    and they too often uncritically reproduced the official perspective of the
                    respective governments, news items from the pool were not widely used even
                    within NAM countries, while they barely had any presence in the West at
                        all.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn122" n="119">Cf. Boyd-Barrett and Thussu,
                            <hi rend="italic">Contra-Flow</hi>. Matthew Crain, “Non-Aligned News
                        Agencies Pool,” in: <hi rend="italic">Encyclopaedia of Social Movement
                            Media</hi>, ed. John D. H. Downing (Thousand Oaks: Sage, 2011),
                        367–69.</note> In the mid 1990s, NANAP finally stopped operating, unable to
                    survive the Western hostility, the end of the Cold War and resulting
                    geopolitical changes as well as losing its leading force following the collapse
                    of Yugoslavia.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn123" n="120">For the impact of
                        Yugoslavia’s dissolution on Tanjug, see Mark Thompson, <hi rend="italic"
                            >Forging War: The Media in Serbia, Croatia, Bosnia and Hercegovina</hi>
                        (Luton: University of Luton Press, 1999), 22–31.</note></p>
                <p>Acknowledging the limitations of NANAP as well as the double standards of the
                    Non-Aligned leaders, who were much less committed to democratising social
                    communication and supporting independent voices in their own countries than they
                    were in lambasting the dominance of Western information sources in international
                    communication, should not lead us to dismiss NANAP as simply a failure or to
                    affirm the reductionist claim that its primary purpose was to stifle freedom of
                    the press. Western media systematically distorted and misrepresented the NWICO
                        initiative<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn124" n="121">Colleen Roach,“French
                        Press Coverage of the Belgrade UNESCO Conference,” <hi rend="italic">Journal
                            of Communication</hi> 31, No. 4 (1981): 175–87. Colleen Roach, “The US
                        Position on the New World Information and Communication Order,” <hi
                            rend="italic">Journal of Communication</hi> 37, No. 4 (1987):
                        36–51.</note> because Non-Aligned demands for balancing the global flow of
                    information would have negatively impacted their global influence and profits.
                    The USA in particular saw the opposition to the policy of free flow of
                    information in a liberalised global market as a threat to the interest of its
                    transnational media corporations as well as the global influence of the American
                        state.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn125" n="122">Cf. Herbert I. Schiller,
                            <hi rend="italic">Communication and Cultural Domination</hi> (New York:
                        International Arts and Science Press, 1976), chapter 2. Diana Lemberg, <hi
                            rend="italic">Barriers Down: How American Power and Free-Flow Policies
                            Shaped Global Media</hi> (New York: Columbia University Press, 2019),
                        chapter 6.</note> Hence, the Western critiques of NANAP and NWICO also
                    suffered from a hefty dose of double standards since they largely ignored the
                    continuing legacy of colonial domination and the legitimacy of desires to
                    protect national cultures in the circumstances of extreme global power
                    imbalances, as well as ignore the specific limitations and challenges developing
                    countries were facing while attempting to develop their communications
                    infrastructure: “The fact that there was not a sufficient market to create
                    independent media systems in the South, and therefore the state was
                    indispensable to create national media, was lost in the debate. Why was the BBC
                    legitimate while Radio Tanzania was not?”.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn126"
                        n="123">Roberto Sauvio, “From New International Information Order to New
                        Information Market Order,” in: <hi rend="italic">From NWICO to WSIS: 30
                            Years of Communication Geopolitics</hi>, eds. Divina Frau-Meigs, Jeremie
                        Nicey, Michael Palmer, Julia Pohle, and Patricio Tupper (Bristol and
                        Chicago: Intellect, 2013), 236.</note>
                </p>
                <p>Instead, the case of NANAP demonstrates the significant structural barriers
                    Non-Aligned countries encountered while seeking to become less dependent on
                    Western news sources. The pooling of resources was meant to overcome this
                    dependence by increasing South-South cooperation, yet, even after pooling their
                    resources, the Non-Aligned countries remained collectively poor. While
                    Yugoslavia offered assistance in the form of technical aid and journalist
                    training, these efforts were woefully inadequate for addressing the
                    underdevelopment of communication infrastructure and the lack of trained
                    personnel, notably in the poorest Non-Aligned countries. This meant Non-Aligned
                    countries remained reliant on outside aid that could only come from the rich
                    countries of the global North and the international organisations largely
                    financed by these rich countries. Hence – paradoxically – the achievement of
                    “self-reliance” very much depended on the aid and support of the very powers the
                    Non-Aligned countries were attempting to break free from.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="bibliograpy">
                <head>Sources and Literature</head>
                <list>
                    <head>Archive sources</head>
                    <item>RS AJ – Archive of Yugoslavia:<list>
                            <item>837 KPR: Cabinet of the President of the Republic.</item>
                            <item>130 SIV: Federal Executive Council.</item>
                            <item>507 A. CK SKJ Central Committee of the League of Communists of
                                Yugoslavia.</item>
                        </list></item>
                    <item>RS DAMSPRS – Diplomatic Archive of the Ministry of Foreign Affairs of the
                        Republic of Serbia:<list type="unordered">
                            <item>Political archives (PA), R (1973–1975, 1980).</item>
                            <item>Political archives (PA), Tunis (1976).</item>
                        </list></item>
                </list>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Literature</head>
                    <bibl>Arrighi, Giovanni. <hi rend="italic">Adam Smith in Beijing</hi>. London
                        and New York: Verso, 2007.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Boyd-Barret, Oliver. “Western News Agencies and the ‘Media Imperialism’
                        Debate: What Kind of Data-Base.” <hi rend="italic">Journal of International
                            Affairs</hi> 3, No. 2 (1981): 247–60.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Boyd-Barrett, Oliver and Daya Thussu. <hi rend="italic">Contra-Flow in
                            Global News: International and Regional News Exchange Mechanisms</hi>.
                        London: John Libbey, 1992.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Cizelj, Boris. <hi rend="italic">Ekonomsko sodelovanje med deželami v
                            razvoju: Teorija in praksa kolektivne opore na lastne sile</hi>.
                        Ljubljana: Komunist, 1982.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Coordinating Committee. <hi rend="italic">News Agencies Pool of
                            Non-Aligned Countries</hi>. New Delhi: Indian Institute of Mass
                        Communication, 1983.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Crain, Matthew. “Non-Aligned News Agencies Pool.” In: <hi rend="italic"
                            >Encyclopaedia of Social Movement Media</hi>. Ed. John D. H. Downing,
                        367–69. Thousand Oaks: Sage, 2011.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Dinkel, Jürgen. <hi rend="italic">Die Bewegung Bündnisfreier Staaten:
                            Genese, Organisation und Politik (1927–1992)</hi>. Oldenbourg: De
                        Gruyter, 2015.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Gosovic, Branislav. <hi rend="italic">UNCTAD - Conflict and
                            Compromise</hi>. Leiden: A. W. Sijthoff, 1972.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Harris, Phil. “Le monde des agences de presse.” <hi rend="italic"
                            >International Commission for the Study of Communication Problems</hi>,
                        11. Paris: UNESCO, 1978.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Ivačić, Pero. “The Flow of News: Tanjug, the Pool, and the National
                        Agencies.” <hi rend="italic">Journal of Communication</hi> 28, No. 4 (1978):
                        157–62.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Ivačić, Pero. “Toward a Freer and Multidimensional Flow of Information.”
                        In: <hi rend="italic">The Third World and Press </hi>Freedom. Ed. P. C.
                        Horton, 135–50. New York: Praeger, 1978. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Jakovina, Tvrtko. <hi rend="italic">Treća strana hladnog rata</hi>.
                        Croatia: Fraktura, 2011.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Jakubowicz, Karol. “Third World News Cooperation Schemes in Building a New
                        International Communication Order: Do They Stand a Chance?.” <hi
                            rend="italic">Gazette</hi> 36 (1985): 81–93.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Lemberg, Diana. <hi rend="italic">Barriers Down: How American Power and
                            Free-Flow Policies Shaped Global Media</hi>. New York: Columbia
                        University Press, 2019.</bibl>
                    <bibl>MacBride Commission. <hi rend="italic">Many Voices, One World</hi>. Paris:
                        Unesco, 1980.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Mankekar, D. R. <hi rend="italic">One Way Free Flow. Neo-Colonialism via
                            News Media</hi>. New Delhi: Clarion books, 1978.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Masmoudi, Mustapha. “The New World Information Order.” <hi rend="italic"
                            >Journal of Communication</hi> 29, No. 2 (1979): 172–79.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Pavlič, Breda and Cees J. Hamelink. <hi rend="italic">The New
                            International Economic Order: Links Between Economics and
                            Communications</hi>. Paris: UNESCO, 1985.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Pinch, Edward T. “The Flow of News: An Assessment of the Non-Aligned News
                        Agencies Pool.” <hi rend="italic">Journal of Communication</hi> 28, No. 4
                        (1978): 163–71.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Roach, Colleen. “French Press Coverage of the Belgrade UNESCO Conference.”
                            <hi rend="italic">Journal of Communication</hi> 31, No. 4 (1981):
                        175–87.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Roach, Colleen. “The US Position on the New World Information and
                        Communication Order.” <hi rend="italic">Journal of Communication</hi> 37,
                        No. 4 (1987): 36–51.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Robinson, Gertrude J. “Tanjug: Yugoslavia’s Multi-Faceted National News
                        Agency.” PhD diss., University of Illinois, 1968. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Robinson, Gertrude J. “Foreign News Selection Is Non-Linear in
                        Yugoslavia’s Tanjug Agency.”<hi rend="italic"> Journalism Quarterly</hi> 47,
                        No. 2 (1970): 340–51.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Sauvant, Karl P. “Toward the New International Economic Order.” In: <hi
                            rend="italic">The New International Economic Order: Confrontation of
                            Cooperation Between North and South</hi>. Ed. Karl P. Sauvant and Hajo
                        Hasenpflug, 3–19. Boulder, Colorado: Westview Press, 1977. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Sauvio, Roberto. “From New International Information Order to New
                        Information Market Order.” In: <hi rend="italic">From NWICO to WSIS: 30
                            Years of Communication Geopolitics</hi>. Eds. Divina Frau-Meigs, Jeremie
                        Nicey, Michael Palmer, Julia Pohle and Patricio Tupper, 231–34. Bristol and
                        Chicago: Intellect, 2013. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Schiller, Herbert I. <hi rend="italic">Communication and Cultural
                            Domination</hi>. New York: International Arts and Science Press,
                        1976.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Splichal, Slavko and France Vreg. <hi rend="italic">Množično komuniciranje
                            in razvoj demokracije</hi>. Ljubljana: Komunist, 1986.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Tanjug. <hi rend="italic">Tanjug 1943–1963</hi>. Beograd: Tanjug,
                        1963.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Thompson, Mark. <hi rend="italic">Forging War: The Media in Serbia,
                            Croatia, Bosnia and Hercegovina</hi>. Luton: University of Luton Press,
                        1999.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Van Dinh, Tran. “Non-Alignment and Cultural Imperialism.” <hi
                            rend="italic">The Black Scholar: Journal of Black Studies and
                            Research</hi> 8, No. 3 (1976): 39–49.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Verghese, George. “Press Censorship under Indira Gandhi.” In: <hi
                            rend="italic">The Third World and Press Freedom</hi>. Ed. P. C. Horton,
                        220–30. New York: Praeger, 1978.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Newspaper sources</head>
                    <bibl>Bogunović, Branko. “Informisanje o sebi i svetu.” <hi rend="italic"
                            >Međunarodna politika</hi>, Feb 1, 1976.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Broz, Josip - Tito. “Potvrda snage i vitalnosti politike nesvrstavanja.”
                            <hi rend="italic">Međunarodna politika</hi>, Nov 16, 1973.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Ivačić, Pero. “Početak značajne aktivnosti: Međusobna informiranost
                        nesvrstanih - neophodan element saradnje.” <hi rend="italic">Međunarodna
                            politika,</hi> Feb 1, 1975.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Ivačić, Pero. “The Non-Aligned Countries Pool Their News.” <hi
                            rend="italic">UNESCO Courier</hi>, April 1977.</bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="italic">Međunarodna politika</hi>, Oct 1, 1975. “Rezolucija VI:
                        Saradnja u oblasti širenja informacija i sredstava masovnog informisanja.” </bibl>
                    <bibl>Papić, Augustin. “Alžirska konferencija: Mjere u oblasti ekonomske
                        saradnje.” <hi rend="italic">Međunarodna politika,</hi> Oct 1, 1973.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Vratuša, Anton. “Sastanak nesvrstanih u Alžiru i ostvarivanje međunarodne
                        strategije razvoja.” <hi rend="italic">Međunarodna politika</hi>, Nov 1,
                        1973.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Online sources</head>
                    <bibl>Charter of Algiers. Algiers, Algeria, 10. – 25. October 1967. Available
                        at: <ref target="https://www.g77.org/doc/algier~1.htm"
                            >https://www.g77.org/doc/algier~1.htm</ref>.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Documents of the 4th Summit Conference of Heads of State or Government of
                        the Non-Aligned Movement, Algiers, Algeria, 5. – 9. September 1973.
                        Available at: <ref
                            target="http://cns.miis.edu/nam/documents/Official_Document/4th_Summit_FD_Algiers_Declaration_1973_Whole.pdf"
                            >http://cns.miis.edu/nam/documents/Official_Document/4th_Summit_FD_Algiers_Declaration_1973_Whole.pdf</ref>.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Documents of the 6th Summit Conference of Heads of State or Government of
                        the Non-Aligned Movement, Havana, Cuba, 3. – 9. September 1979. Available
                        at: <ref
                            target="http://cns.miis.edu/nam/documents/Official_Document/6th_Summit_FD_Havana_Declaration_1979_Whole.pdf"
                            >http://cns.miis.edu/nam/documents/Official_Document/6th_Summit_FD_Havana_Declaration_1979_Whole.pdf</ref>
                        .</bibl>
                    <bibl>Documents of the 10th Summit Conference of Heads of State or Government of
                        the Non-Aligned Movement, Jakarta, Indonesia, 1. – 6. September 1992.
                        Available at: <ref
                            target="http://cns.miis.edu/nam/documents/Official_Document/10th_Summit_FD_Jakarta_Declaration_1992_Whole.pdf"
                            >http://cns.miis.edu/nam/documents/Official_Document/10th_Summit_FD_Jakarta_Declaration_1992_Whole.pdf</ref>
                        .</bibl>
                    <bibl>Sauvant, Karl P. 2014. The Early Days of the Group of 77. Available at:
                            <ref
                            target="https://www.un.org/en/chronicle/article/early-days-group-77"
                            >https://www.un.org/en/chronicle/article/early-days-group-77</ref>.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
            <div type="summary" xml:lang="sl">
                <docAuthor>Sašo Slaček Brlek</docAuthor>
                <head>NASTANEK ZDRUŽENJA NEUVRŠČENIH TISKOVNIH AGENCIJ</head>
                <head>POVZETEK</head>
                <p>Članek se osredotoča na proces oblikovanja Združenja neuvrščenih novičarskih
                    agencij in dejavnike, ki so oblikovali njegov razvoj. Avtor pojasnjuje nastanek
                    združenja s tremi skupinami dejavnikov: notranjimi (delovanje Tanjuga in
                    jugoslovanskih političnih elit), zunanjimi (spremembami v mednarodnih odnosih)
                    in tistimi, ki so zakoreninjeni v institucionalni zgodovini gibanja
                    neuvrščenih.</p>
                <p>Ker je bila Jugoslavija glavna gonilna sila združenja tiskovnih agencij
                    neuvrščenih, so bili cilji in strategije jugoslovanskih akterjev, predvsem
                    Tanjuga in zveznih političnih elit, ključnega pomena za razvoj združenja in
                    širše za informacijsko sodelovanje znotraj gibanja neuvrščenih. Tanjug je želel
                    krepiti sodelovanje z neuvrščenimi tiskovnimi agencijami in na tak način
                    izboljšati svoj položaj na globalnem trgu tiskovnih agencij. Ta interes je
                    sovpadal z interesi zveznih političnih elit, ki so s krepitvijo globalnega
                    dosega Tanjuga želele povečati svoj vpliv na medijsko poročanje in javno mnenje
                    v drugih državah, predvsem neuvrščenih in na Zahodu. Zvezne oblasti so podpirale
                    Tanjugovo širitev v neuvrščeni svet, saj so si od tega obetale učinkovitejšo
                    promocijo svojih stališč v svetu in boljši pretok informacij med državnimi
                    institucijami.</p>
                <p>Druga skupina dejavnikov so spremembe v mednarodnih odnosih. Z naraščajočo
                    vrzeljo med bogatimi in revnimi državami, popuščanjem napetosti med ZDA in
                    Sovjetsko zvezo, razočaranjem tretjega sveta nad Združenimi narodi,
                    upočasnitvijo svetovne gospodarske rasti in zlomom bretton-woodskega sistema
                    leta 1971 je gibanje neuvrščenih začelo usmerjati povečano pozornost na
                    gospodarske razlike med severom in jugom ter na praktična prizadevanja za
                    spodbujanje sodelovanja jug‒jug. Ta prizadevanja so predvsem zaradi
                    jugoslovanskih pobud vključevala tudi informacijsko sodelovanje, najprej v
                    obliki združenja tiskovnih agencij, po katerem so se zgledovale druge oblike
                    sodelovanja med neuvrščenimi množičnimi mediji.</p>
                <p>Tretja skupina so dejavniki, ki izhajajo iz institucionalne zgodovine gibanja.
                    Čeprav je združenje tiskovnih agencij izhajalo iz Tanjugovih dvostranskih
                    dogovorov z neuvrščenimi agencijami, je bilo rekontekstualizirano v okviru
                    težnje po institucionalizaciji sodelovanja jug‒jug z in ga je bilo treba
                    prilagoditi ustaljenim oblikam tega sodelovanja. Prevladujoči institucionalni
                    etos NAM, ki </p>
                <p>je nasprotoval centralizaciji, je vplival na to, da se je združenje tiskovnih
                    agencij razvijalo kot decentraliziran multilateralen projekt. Čeprav je bila
                    Jugoslavija očitno vodilna sila, je morala prikrivatii stopnjo svojega angažmaja
                    in je vlagala veliko truda, da bi pritegnila aktivno sodelovanje drugih
                    neuvrščenih držav (zlasti Tunizije in Indije) ter predstavila združenje kot
                    večstranski projekt s široko podporo že od samega začetka. </p>
                <p>Kljub temu da je združenje tiskovnih agencij ob koncu hladne vojne pritegnilo k
                    sodelovanju skorajda vse neuvrščene države, omogočalo Tanjugu okrepiti
                    prisotnost v neuvrščenem svetu in Jugoslaviji, da je utrdila svoj prestiž
                    znotraj gibanja, ter spodbujalo razvoj informacijske infrastrukture in
                    oblikovanje tiskovnih agencij v neuvrščenih državah, pa so že kmalu po
                    ustanovitvi postale očitne njegove omejitve. Delovanje združenja so hromile
                    politične delitve znotraj gibanja neuvrščenih, postalo je bojišče za prestiž in
                    vpliv znotraj gibanja in bilo zelo vidno povezano z nedemokratičnimi praksami
                    določenih voditeljev neuvrščenih držav. Prav tako je delovanje združenja ves čas
                    zaznamovalo pomanjkanje tehnične opreme, finančnih sredstev in usposobljenega
                    osebja.</p>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
