<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
             <title>Language Technologies and Digital Humanities
                 2020</title>
             <author>
                 <forename>Katja</forename>
                 <surname>Meden</surname>
             </author>
         </titleStmt>
          <editionStmt>
              <edition>
                  <date>2020-10-24</date>
              </edition>
          </editionStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
              <publisher>
                  <orgName xml:lang="sl">Inštitut za novejšo zgodovino</orgName>
                  <orgName xml:lang="en">Institute of Contemporary History</orgName>
                  <address>
                      <addrLine>Privoz 11</addrLine>
                      <addrLine>SI-1000 Ljubljana</addrLine>
                  </address>
              </publisher>
              <pubPlace>http://ojs.inz.si/pnz/article/view/2914</pubPlace>
              <date>2020</date>
              <availability status="free">
                  <licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</licence>
              </availability>
          </publicationStmt>
          <seriesStmt>
              <title xml:lang="sl">Prispevki za novejšo zgodovino</title>
              <title xml:lang="en">Contributions to Contemporary History</title>
              <biblScope unit="volume">60</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
              <idno type="ISSN">2463-7807</idno>
          </seriesStmt>
          <sourceDesc>
              <p>No source, born digital.</p>
          </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
       <encodingDesc>
           <projectDesc xml:lang="en">
               <p>Contributions to Contemporary History is one of the central Slovenian scientific
                   historiographic journals, dedicated to publishing articles from the field of
                   contemporary history (the 19th and 20th century).</p>
               <p>The journal is published three times per year in Slovenian and in the following
                   foreign languages: English, German, Serbian, Croatian, Bosnian, Italian, Slovak
                   and Czech. The articles are all published with abstracts in English and
                   Slovenian as well as summaries in English.</p>
           </projectDesc>
           <projectDesc xml:lang="sl">
               <p>Prispevki za novejšo zgodovino je ena osrednjih slovenskih znanstvenih
                   zgodovinopisnih revij, ki objavlja teme s področja novejše zgodovine (19. in 20.
                   stoletje).</p>
               <p>Revija izide trikrat letno v slovenskem jeziku in v naslednjih tujih jezikih:
                   angleščina, nemščina, srbščina, hrvaščina, bosanščina, italijanščina, slovaščina
                   in češčina. Članki izhajajo z izvlečki v angleščini in slovenščini ter povzetki
                   v angleščini.</p>
           </projectDesc>
       </encodingDesc>
       <revisionDesc>
           <listChange>
               <change>
                   <date>2020-12-21</date>
                   <name>Neja Blaj Hribar</name>
                   <desc>Pretvorba iz DOCX v TEI, dodatno kodiranje</desc>
               </change>
           </listChange>
       </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <docAuthor>Katja Meden</docAuthor>
        </front>
      <body>
          <p>The Conference on Language Technologies and Digital Humanities, organised biennially by the Slovenian Society for Language
                    Technologies (SDJT)<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn1" n="1">
                  <hi rend="italic">Slovenian Society for Language
                            Technologies (SDJT)</hi>, accessed on 23
                            November 2020,
                        <ref target="http://www.sdjt.si/wp/">http://www.sdjt.si/wp/</ref>.
            </note> in cooperation with the Institute of Contemporary History,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn2" n="2">
                        Institute of
                            Contemporary
                            History, accessed on 23 November 2020, <ref target="https://www.inz.si/">https://www.inz.si/</ref>.
            </note> the Centre for Language Resources and Technologies of the University of Ljubljana (CJVT),<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn3" n="3">
                        Center for Language
                            Resources and Technologies of the University of Ljubljana, accessed on 23
                        November 2020, <ref target="https://www.cjvt.si/en/">https://www.cjvt.si/en/</ref>.
            </note> and the research infrastructures CLARIN.SI<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn4" n="4">
                  <hi rend="italic">Common Language Resources and
                            Technology Infrastructure,
                            Slovenia</hi>, accessed on 23 November 2020, <ref target="https://www.clarin.si/info/about/">https://www.clarin.si/info/about/</ref>.
            </note> and DARIAH-SI,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn5" n="5">
                  <hi rend="italic">DARIAH-SI |Digitalna
                            humanistika</hi>, <ref target="http://www.dariah.si/en/">http://www.dariah.si/en/</ref>.
            </note> took place on 24 and 25 September. This was the twelfth iteration of the conference, which boasts more a tradition spanning more than twenty years. The conference has become an important link between the field of language technologies and digital humanities, as this years’ conference was also the third multidisciplinary iteration since the conference programme was extended to include the field of digital humanities in 2016. </p>
         <p>This years’ conference was initially set to take place at the Institute of Contemporary History in Ljubljana but was moved to the virtual environment because of the Covid-19 pandemic. The shift from the traditional to the virtual environment influenced the conference structure and organisation as well as presented new challenges. 
                Typically, the conference would take place over the span of two days. However, unlike the previous years, days and sessions were not divided by languages ​​in which the papers were presented. Instead, they were divided solely based on the themes of the papers. In this year’s implementation, the individual student contributions were placed within the thematically relevant sessions and not in a separate student panel. In the course of the Covid-19 pandemic, our way of life, work, and communication have changed drastically, forcing us to transfer our presentations and informative discussions to a virtual environment. Therefore, we asked the authors of the individual papers to pre-record their presentations, which were made public a few days before the start of the conference. This enabled us to focus on the dynamic flow of discourse, as the participants were able to
                    view the recordings and proceedings before the conference, while the authors
                    only presented brief summaries of their lectures, followed by
                discussions.</p>
         <p>The conference was opened by Sara Tonelli, the head of the Digital Humanities research group at the Bruno Kessler Foundation in Trento and associate professor at the Department of Psychology and Cognitive Sciences at the University of Trento. In her invited lecture, titled Abusive Language Detection:
                    Too Much Digital, Not Enough
                    Humanities? the lecturer created an overview of the modern approaches to recognising violent speech, emphasised the role as well as comprehension of the language used by various online communities, and presented the current research to understand this phenomenon better.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn6" n="6">
                       Sara Tonelli, “Abusive Language Detection: Too Much Digital, Not Enough Humanities?”, in <hi rend="italic">Proceedings of the Conference on
                            Language Technologies &amp; Digital Humanities</hi>, edited by Darja Fišer and Tomaž Erjavec
                            (Ljubljana: Inštitut za novejšo zgodovino, 2020), 1
            </note>
                The discussion that followed the
                    lecture was moderated by Filip Dobranić.</p>
         <p>The invited lecture was followed by the first session on
                    the topic of language and speech technologies, moderated by Tanja Samardžić.
                    Anka Supej, Matej Ulčar, Marko Robnik Šikonja and Senja Pollak presented their
                    work in which they compared the sexual bias of models (or their embedding) with
                    different configurations and approaches to computing analogies.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn7" n="7">
                Anka Supej, Matej Ulčar, Marko Robnik-Šikonja, and Sanja Pollak, “Primerjava slovenskih besednih vektorskih vložitev z vidika spola na analogijah poklicev”, in <hi rend="italic">Proceedings of the Conference on
                            Language Technologies &amp; Digital
                        Humanities</hi>, edited by Darja Fišer and Tomaž Erjavec (Ljubljana: Inštitut za novejšo zgodovino, 2020), 93– 100. 
                    
            </note> During the presentations of extended abstracts, Darinka Verdonik presented the development and operation of the research infrastructure of the RI-SI CLARIN project on behalf of the co-authors. In his student paper, Andraž Pelicon presented the perception of sentiment in the news using deep neural networks.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn8" n="8">
                Andraž Pelicon, “Zaznavanje sentimenta v novicah z globokimi nevronskimi mrežami”, in <hi rend="italic">Proceedings of the Conference on
                            Language Technologies &amp; Digital Humanities</hi>, edited by Darja Fišer and Tomaž Erjavec
                            (Ljubljana: Inštitut za novejšo zgodovino, 2020), 150–57.
            </note>
         </p>
         <p>The next section, which dealt with language resources, was
                    moderated by Darinka Verdonik and included presentations of four full
                    contributions, three extended papers, and a student paper. Simon Krek (with
                    co-authors) presented the latest development and achievements of the ssj500k
                    learning corpus, the largest and most frequently used open-source database for
                    Slovenian language processing.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn9" n="9">
                Simon Krek, Tomaž Erjavec, Kaja Dobrovoljc, Polona Gantar, Špela Arhar Holdt, Jaka Čibej, and Janez Brank, “The ssj500k Training Corpus for Slovene Language Processing”, in <hi rend="italic">Proceedings of the Conference on
                            Language Technologies &amp; Digital
                        Humanities</hi>, edited by Darja Fišer and Tomaž Erjavec (Ljubljana: Inštitut za novejšo zgodovino, 2020), 24–33. 
            </note> Dolores Lemmenmeier-Batinić highlighted the lack of publicly available resources for the Serbian language and presented the methods for converting corpus data into the standardised XML format.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn10" n="10">
                     Dolores Lemmenmeier-Batinić, Nikola Ljubešić, and Tanja Samardžić, “XML-Encoding of a spoken Serbian corpus targeting forms of address”, in <hi rend="italic">Proceedings of the Conference on
                            Language Technologies &amp; Digital
                        Humanities</hi>, edited by Darja Fišer and Tomaž Erjavec (Ljubljana: Inštitut za novejšo zgodovino, 2020), 127–30. 
            </note> Finally, Špela Antloga concluded the session by presenting her student paper on the methodological starting points, development, and guidelines for marking metaphorical words in the KOMET 1.0 metaphor corpus.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn11" n="11">
                        Špela Antloga, “Korpus metafor KOMET 1.0”, in <hi rend="italic">Proceedings of the Conference on
                            Language Technologies &amp; Digital Humanities</hi>, edited by Darja Fišer and Tomaž Erjavec
                            (Ljubljana: Inštitut za novejšo zgodovino, 2020), 167–70.
            </note> The first day of the conference was concluded with a special panel of the RSDO project (<hi rend="italic">Development of Slovene in the Digital
                    Environment</hi>), during which the leaders of the
                    individual work packages presented the primary and intermediate goals to be
                    performed by the end of the project.
            </p>
         <p>The introduction to the second day of the conference, which set the tone for the day, was offered by the digital historian Kaspar Beelen of the Alan Turing Institute, who explores the use of machine learning in humanities research. In his invited lecture, titled 
                <hi rend="italic">Speaking on behalf of others: Why the
                    digital humanities should care about parliamentary data</hi>, he highlighted the importance and role of parliamentary
                    data, which provide insight into the language and worldview of the MPs and the
                    voters they are supposed to represent, thus offering detailed testimony on
                    almost every topic that has ever been the subject of public debate.
            </p>
         <p>In the third session, moderated by Kristina Štrkalj
                    Despot, contributions in the field of corpus analysis were presented. Kristina
                    Pahor de Maiti presented a study of the morphosyntactic characteristics of
                    comments on Facebook to identify those that are commonly seen in socially
                    unacceptable discourse (SUD).<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn12" n="12">
                        Kristina Pahor de Maiti, Darja Fišer, Nikola Ljubešić, and Tomaž Erjavec, “Grammatical Footprint of Socially Unacceptable Facebook Comments”, in <hi rend="italic">Proceedings of the Conference on
                            Language Technologies &amp; Digital
                        Humanities</hi>, edited by Darja Fišer and Tomaž Erjavec (Ljubljana: Inštitut za novejšo zgodovino, 2020), 48–57. 
            </note> Jakob Lenardič and Darja Fišer analysed epistemic modal adverbs in the 100-million-token corpus of Slovenian doctoral dissertations (the KAS corpus).<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn13" n="13">
                        Jakob Lenardič and Darja Fišer, “Epistemic modal adverbs in Slovenian academic discourse”, in <hi rend="italic">Proceedings of the conference on
                            Language Technologies &amp; Digital Humanities</hi>, edited by Darja Fišer and Tomaž Erjavec
                            (Ljubljana: Inštitut za novejšo zgodovino, 2020), 34–41.
            </note>
                The student contributions in the context of the relevant
                    session were presented by Zoran Fijavž and Eva Trivunović. In his paper, Zoran
                    Fijavž explored the impact of video content on the presence of socially
                    unacceptable discourse. He detected this from a set of comments related to LGBT
                    communities on Facebook, originating from the leading news sources in
                    Croatia.
                <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn14" n="14">
                        Zoran Fijavž, “Ambivalence of Queer Visibility in Video-Based Social Media Content”, in <hi rend="italic">Proceedings of the Conference on
                            Language Technologies &amp; Digital Humanities</hi>, edited by Darja Fišer and Tomaž Erjavec
                            (Ljubljana: Inštitut za novejšo zgodovino, 2020),
                    144–49.
            </note> Eva Trivunović concluded the session on corpus analysis with her presentation on the topic of biblical phrases, their variants, as well as the renewal and non-renewal modifications in the Gigafida 2.0, Janes, and slWaC corpora.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn15" n="15">
                        Eva Trivunović, “Variante in modifikacije (iz)biblijskih frazemov”, in <hi rend="italic">Proceedings of the Conference on
                            Language Technologies &amp; Digital Humanities</hi>, edited by Darja Fišer and Tomaž Erjavec
                            (Ljubljana: Inštitut za novejšo zgodovino, 2020), 158–66.
            </note>
         </p>
         <p>The final session, which combined digital humanities and
                    pedagogy (moderated by Miran Hladnik) was one of the more discussion-oriented
                    sessions, as presenters were able to either focus solely on addressing the
                    questions from the public or to give their opinion on a set of general
                    discussion points that the moderator had provided in advance. The questions
                    touched upon the problem of wiki-sourced tools and their lack of usage; usage of
                    proprietary tools such as Zoom versus open-source ones; as well as discussed
                    virtual communication, which has become the new normal. In the span of this
                    particular session, several presentations were made. Katja Meden and Ana Cvek
                    presented a technical upgrade of the Historiography Citation Index for the
                    systematic listing of cited works in the field of historiography.
                <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn16" n="16">
                      Katja Meden and Ana Cvek, “Nadgradnja Zgodovinarskega indeksa citiranosti”, in <hi rend="italic">Proceedings of the Conference on
                            Language Technologies &amp; Digital Humanities</hi>, edited by Darja Fišer and Tomaž Erjavec
                            (Ljubljana: Inštitut za novejšo zgodovino, 2020), 42–47.
            </note> Andrej Pančur then presented the latest acquisition in the field of victimological demographic research; the digital database of (military) victims of the World War I from the territory of the today’s Republic of Slovenia, created based on the cooperation between various research and cultural institutions as well as several individuals.
                <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn17" n="17">
                Andrej Pančur, Neja Blaj Hribar, Mihael Ojsteršek, and Mojca Šorn, “Projekt Vojaške žrtve prve svetovne vojne na Slovenskem”, in <hi rend="italic">Proceedings of the Conference on
                            Language Technologies &amp; Digital Humanities</hi>, edited by Darja Fišer and Tomaž Erjavec
                            (Ljubljana: Inštitut za novejšo zgodovino, 2020),
                    136–40.
            </note> Finally, in her student paper, Magdalena Schlintl presented working with digital tools in teacher education in the case of teaching-learning-laboratory.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn18" n="18">
                       Magdalena Schlintl, Kerstin Pawluch, Mara Rader, and Verena Novak-Geiger, “Working with Digital Devices in Teacher Training Using the Example of the Teaching-Learning-Lab”, in <hi rend="italic">Proceedings of the Conference on
                            Language Technologies &amp; Digital Humanities</hi>, edited by Darja Fišer and Tomaž Erjavec
                            (Ljubljana: Inštitut za novejšo zgodovino, 2020),
                    171–74.
            </note>
         </p>
         <p>The conference concluded with the award for the best student contribution, received by Zoran Fijavž for his paper titled 
                <hi rend="italic">Ambivalence of Queer Visibility and
                    Video-Based Social Media Content</hi>. As there were quite a few outstanding speakers among the pre-recorded presentations, during the conference, the programme committee decided to also give an audience award for the best recorded presentation. It went to Špela Antloga for the presentation of her article 
                <hi rend="italic">Corpus of Metaphors KOMET 1.0.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Despite the technical and organisational challenges posed
                    by the pandemic and the virtual environment, the 2020 Conference on Language
                    Technology and Digital Humanities was carried out successfully. Thanks to the
                    virtual environment, we were able to make all the presentations and discussion
                    recordings available on the conference website, along with the PDF versions of
                    the original papers. The presentations at the conference provided extensive
                    insight into the new methods, applications, upgrades, and the development of
                    research fields. The discussions that those presentations sparked gave us an
                    incentive to move our research forward and offered an insight into the
                    interdisciplinarity of the various thematic subfields of language technologies
                    and digital humanities. Simply put, the conference allowed us to work more
                    closely with the related fields and establish new building blocks in the efforts
                    to bridge the gap between language technologies and digital humanities.
            </p>
       </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
