<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>A Mixed-principle Rule-based Approach to the Automatic Syllabification of
                    Serbian</title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename>Aniko</forename>
                        <surname>Kovač</surname>
                        <affiliation>Department of Language Science and Technology</affiliation>
                        <address>
                            <addrLine>Saarland University Campus A2 2</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>66123 Saarbrücken, Germany</addrLine>
                        </address>
                        <email>anikok@coli.uni-saarland.de</email>
                    </name>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename>Maja</forename>
                        <surname>Marković</surname>
                        <affiliation>Department of English Language and Literature</affiliation>
                        <address>
                            <addrLine>Faculty of Philosophy, University of Novi Sad Dr Zorana
                                Đinđića 2</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>21000 Novi Sad, Serbia</addrLine>
                        </address>
                        <email>majamarkovic@ff.uns.ac.rs</email>
                    </name>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>2019-04-15</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>
                    <orgName xml:lang="sl">Inštitut za novejšo zgodovino</orgName>
                    <orgName xml:lang="en">Institute of Contemporary History</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Kongresni trg 1</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>SI-1000 Ljubljana</addrLine>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>http://ojs.inz.si/pnz/article/view/332</pubPlace>
                <date>2019</date>
                <availability status="free">
                    <licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title xml:lang="sl">Prispevki za novejšo zgodovino</title>
                <title xml:lang="en">Contributions to Contemporary History</title>
                <biblScope unit="volume">59</biblScope>
                <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
                <idno type="ISSN">2463-7807</idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source, born digital.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc xml:lang="en">
                <p>Contributions to Contemporary History is one of the central Slovenian scientific
                    historiographic journals, dedicated to publishing articles from the field of
                    contemporary history (the 19th and 20th century).</p>
                <p>The journal is published three times per year in Slovenian and in the following
                    foreign languages: English, German, Serbian, Croatian, Bosnian, Italian, Slovak
                    and Czech. The articles are all published with abstracts in English and
                    Slovenian as well as summaries in English.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <projectDesc xml:lang="sl">
                <p>Prispevki za novejšo zgodovino je ena osrednjih slovenskih znanstvenih
                    zgodovinopisnih revij, ki objavlja teme s področja novejše zgodovine (19. in 20.
                    stoletje).</p>
                <p>Revija izide trikrat letno v slovenskem jeziku in v naslednjih tujih jezikih:
                    angleščina, nemščina, srbščina, hrvaščina, bosanščina, italijanščina, slovaščina
                    in češčina. Članki izhajajo z izvlečki v angleščini in slovenščini ter povzetki
                    v angleščini.</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="sl"/>
                <language ident="en"/>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords xml:lang="en">
                    <term>syllable</term>
                    <term>rule-based approach</term>
                    <term>sonority</term>
                    <term>computational linguistics</term>
                    <term>phonology</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords xml:lang="sl">
                    <term>zlog</term>
                    <term>pristop na podlagi pravil</term>
                    <term>zvočnost</term>
                    <term>računalniško jezikoslovje</term>
                    <term>fonologija</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change>
                    <date>2019-06-03</date>
                    <name>Mihael Ojsteršek</name>
                    <desc>Pretvorba iz DOCX v TEI, dodatno kodiranje</desc>
                </change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <docAuthor>Aniko Kovač<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn1" n="*"><hi rend="bold" style="font-size:10pt">Department of Language
                    Science and Technology, Saarland University Campus A2 2, 66123 Saarbrücken,
                    Germany, <ref target="mailto:anikok@coli.uni-saarland.de">anikok@coli.uni-saarland.de</ref></hi></note></docAuthor>
            <docAuthor>Maja Markovič<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn2" n="**"><hi rend="bold" style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">Department of English
                    Language and Literature, Faculty of Philosophy, University of Novi Sad Dr Zorana
                    Đinđića 2, 21000 Novi Sad, Serbia, <ref target="mailto:majamarkovic@ff.uns.ac.rs">majamarkovic@ff.uns.ac.rs</ref></hi></note></docAuthor>
            <docImprint>
                <idno type="cobissType">Cobiss type: 1.01</idno>
                <idno type="UDC">UDC: </idno>
            </docImprint>
            <div type="abstract" xml:lang="sl">
                <head><hi rend="italic"/>IZVLEČEK</head>
                <head><hi rend="italic allcaps"/>Mešani pristop k avtomatskemu zlogovanju v srbščini
                    na podlagi načel in pravil</head>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">V tem prispevku predstavljamo mešani pristop k avtomatskemu
                        zlogovanju v srbščini na podlagi načel in pravil, ki temelji na predpisnih
                        pravilih tradicionalne slovnice v kombinaciji z načelom zaporedja glede na
                        zvočnost (Sonority Sequencing Principle). Proučujemo težave in omejitve obeh
                        uveljavljenih pristopov, ki temeljita na zbirki pravil in zvočnosti;
                        vpeljujemo algoritem, ki uporablja oba načina za doseganje natančnejše
                        členitve besed na zloge, ki bi bila skladnejša z intuicijo rojenih govorcev;
                        in predstavljamo statistične podatke, povezane z razporeditvijo zlogov in
                        njihovo strukturo v srbščini.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Ključne besede: zlog, pristop na podlagi pravil, zvočnost,
                        računalniško jezikoslovje, fonologija</hi>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="abstract">
                <head><hi rend="italic"/>ABSTRACT</head>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">In this paper we present a mixed-principle rule-based approach
                        to the automatic syllabification of Serbian, based on prescriptive rules
                        from traditional grammar in combination with the Sonority Sequencing
                        Principle. We explore the problems and limitations of the existing rule set
                        and sonority-based approaches, introduce an algorithm that utilizes both
                        means in an attempt to produce a more accurate segmentation of words into
                        syllables that is better aligned with the intuition of the native speakers,
                        and present the statistical data related to the distribution of syllables
                        and their structure in Serbian.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Keywords: syllable, rule-based approach, sonority,
                        computational linguistics, phonology</hi>
                </p>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div>
                <head>Introduction</head>
                <p> Syllables have been considered — although not unequivocally (cf. Koehler 1966) —
                    to be one of the basic units in phonology constituting the minimal units of
                    pronunciation, and to play a role in prosody, phonotactics, and phonological
                    processing (Ladefoged and Johnson 2014). The role of the segmentation of words
                    into syllables and their distributional properties began to see an increase in
                    importance in speech technologies in the 1990s (Iacoponi and Savy 2011), most
                    notably in the areas of speech recognition (SR) and text-to-speech synthesis
                    (TTS).</p>
                <p> Syllable segmentation today plays a role in speech technologies on the segmental
                    level — conditioning the length of segmental units such as consonants and vowels
                    — as well as on the prosodic level — governing rhythmical alternations (Bigi and
                    Petrone 2014). Syllable segmentation is also a key component in hyphenation
                    (e.g. Kaplar et al. 2018), although it should be noted that, at least in
                    Serbian, hyphenation is governed by a partially diverging set of rules from
                    those governing syllabification<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn3" n="1"
                        ><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve"> For example, hyphenation rules ban the segmentation after a syllable consisting of a single vowel at word onset, while this segmentation is allowed and expected according to the rules of syllabification.</hi></note>.
                    Syllable distribution data is also of crucial importance for psycholinguistic
                    experiments, as syllable frequency has been shown to play a role in the
                    processing of words (e.g. Barber et al. 2004; Cholin et al. 2006; Cholin and
                    Levelt 2009). Developing an automatic system of syllabification allows for the
                    segmentation of large-scale language corpora needed for the development of
                    automatic systems or the extraction of relevant data related to frequency
                    syllable distributions, which would otherwise require a large number of trained
                    annotators and would be a resource and cost heavy undertaking.</p>
                <p> The two generally distinguishable approaches to automatic syllabification are
                    rule-based versus data-driven approaches (Marchand et al. 2009). While
                    data-driven approaches have taken over many aspects of natural language
                    processing, and there are a number of data-driven models of syllable
                    segmentation using artificial neural networks (e.g. Daelemans and van den Bosch
                    1992; Hunt 1993; Stoianov et al. 1997; Landsiedel et al. 2011), the
                    unavailability of segmented data for Serbian makes rule-based approaches the
                    only viable option for automatic syllabification in Serbian.</p>
                <p> To the best of our knowledge, there is a single publicly available attempt at
                    developing a rule-based syllabifier for Serbian by Kaplar et al. (2018). In this
                    paper we lay out a number of problems and limitations with the ruleset used in
                    their syllabification system and why relying on the existing set of prescriptive
                    rule descriptions from traditional grammar is insufficient to capture and
                    describe a syllabification system that is aligned with the intuition of native
                    speakers of Serbian. A relatable attempt at automatic syllabification was
                    developed by Meštrović et al. (2015) for Croatian, the key difference between
                    their work and ours being in the principle behind the syllabification algorithm
                    which in their case relied solely on the onset maximization principle — limiting
                    possible syllable onsets to valid onsets at the beginning of words. Taking into
                    account Morelli’s (1999) limitations on possible syllable onsets in
                    Serbo-Croatian, the onset maximization principle employed by Meštrović et al.
                    could be considered a comparatively liberal system. In order to attempt to
                    constrain our syllabifer, we are decided on a different approach that will not
                    rely on onset maximization, but rather a combination of a number of alternative
                    principles.</p>
                <p> In this paper we present a mixed-principle rule-based approach to the
                    syllabification of Serbian. Our starting set of rules is based on the <hi
                        rend="italic">Gramatika srpskoga jezika</hi> by Stanojčić and Popović
                    (2005), a prescriptive textbook for Serbian grammar that presents a set of rule
                    descriptions for the segmentation of words into syllables. In a previous version
                    of our syllabification algorithm (Kovač and Marković 2018), we made a number of
                    changes to the rule descriptions of Stanojčić and Popović (2005) as the
                    formulation of some of the descriptions proved to be redundant, some were
                    example-based and not specific enough for a formal implementation, and we also
                    expanded them with three added modifications related to the treatment of nasals
                    and the alveolar sonorant /<hi rend="italic">r</hi>/ based on Kašić (2014) and
                    the treatment of alveolar sonorants /<hi rend="italic">l</hi>/ and /<hi
                        rend="italic">n</hi>/ based on Zec (2000). In this paper we extend our
                    previous algorithm to include a module for validating the structure of syllables
                    in terms of their compliance with the Sonority Sequencing Principle (SSP), thus
                    further fine-tuning the accuracy of our segmentation, and resolving a number of
                    problems noted in our earlier implementation.</p>
                <p> The goal of the paper is threefold: i) to improve our system for automatic
                    rule-based syllabification for Serbian based on the formalization of existing
                    rule descriptions by the addition of the sonority sequencing validation module,
                    ii) to provide an analysis of the outcomes of the automatic syllabification
                    process in order to address possible theoretical considerations and serve as a
                    basis for the development of future syllabifiers, and iii) to present
                    statistical data related to the distribution of syllables and their structure in
                    Serbian.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Prescriptive Rule Descriptions</head>
                <p> Our starting set of rules was based on the formalization of the rule
                    descriptions governing the segmentation of words into syllables from the <hi
                        rend="italic">Gramatika srpskoga jezika</hi> by Stanojčić and Popović
                    (2005). Being a prescriptive textbook on Serbian grammar used at a high school
                    level by all student profiles, we expected these rules to constitute the common
                    knowledge base shared by the majority of native speakers.</p>
                <p> Regarding syllable boundaries, Stanojčić and Popović (2005, 37) establish the
                    following general rule (1).</p>
                <p>(1)
                    <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">In words made up of multiple phonemes, consonants, sonorants and vowels, the syllable boundary comes after the vowel and before the consonant (e.g. </hi>či-ta-ti<hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve"> [</hi>to
                        read<hi rend="italic">]).</hi></p>
                <p>In addition to this general rule, they list the following rules — (2), (3), (4),
                    (5) and (6) — that further specify medial syllable boundaries depending on
                    consonant manner of articulation.</p>
                <p>(2)
                    <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Medially, in a consonant cluster which has an affricate or fricative sound in its initial position, the syllable boundary will be before that consonant cluster (e.g. </hi>po-šta
                        <hi rend="italic"
                    >[</hi>post<hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">], </hi>ma-čka <hi
                        rend="italic">[</hi>cat<hi rend="italic">]).</hi></p>
                <p>(3) <hi rend="italic">The syllable boundary will be before a consonant cluster
                        if, in a consonant cluster found medially in a word, the second position in
                        the cluster is occupied by one of the sonorants /</hi>v<hi rend="italic">/,
                        /</hi>j<hi rend="italic">/, /</hi>r<hi rend="italic">/, /</hi>l<hi
                        rend="italic">/ or
                    /</hi>ʎ<hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">/ preceded by any other consonant besides a sonorant (e.g. </hi>sve-tlost
                        <hi rend="italic">[</hi>light<hi rend="italic">]).</hi></p>
                <p>(4)
                    <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">If a consonant cluster consists of two sonorants, the syllable boundary will be between them so that one sonorant belongs to the preceding, and one sonorant belongs to the following syllable (e.g. </hi>lom-ljen
                        <hi rend="italic">[</hi>broken<hi rend="italic">]).</hi></p>
                <p>(5) <hi rend="italic">If a consonant cluster consists of a plosive in its initial
                        position and some other consonant except the sonorants /</hi>j<hi
                        rend="italic">/, /</hi>v<hi rend="italic">/, /</hi>l<hi rend="italic">/,
                        /</hi>ʎ<hi rend="italic">/ and
                    /</hi>r<hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">/, the syllable boundary will be between the consonants (e.g. </hi>lep-tir
                        <hi rend="italic">[</hi>butterfly<hi rend="italic">]).</hi></p>
                <p>(6) <hi rend="italic">If in a cluster of two sonorants, the second position is
                        occupied by the sonorant /</hi>j<hi rend="italic">/ from je corresponding to
                        the ijekavica dialect to
                    /</hi>e<hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">/ in the ekavica dialect, the syllable boundary will be before that group (e.g. </hi>čo-vjek
                        <hi rend="italic">[</hi>man<hi rend="italic">]).</hi></p>
                <p>Stanojčić and Popović (2005, 32) also introduce the rule descriptions (7) and (8)
                    to define when the sonorants /<hi rend="italic">r</hi>/, /<hi rend="italic"
                        >l</hi>/, and /<hi rend="italic">n</hi>/ constitute syllable nuclei.</p>
                <p>(7) <hi rend="italic">The sonorant /</hi>r<hi rend="italic">/ can be a syllable
                        carrier in standard Serbian when:</hi></p>
                <list type="ordered">
                    <item><hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">it is found medially between two consonants (e.g. </hi>tr-ča-ti
                            <hi rend="italic">[</hi>to run<hi rend="italic">]),</hi></item>
                    <item><hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">it is found initially before a consonant (e.g. </hi>r-va-ti
                        se <hi rend="italic">[</hi>to wrestle<hi rend="italic">]),</hi></item>
                    <item><hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">it is found after a vowel in compounds (e.g. </hi>za-r-đa-ti<hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve"> [</hi>to
                            rust<hi rend="italic">]),</hi></item>
                    <item><hi rend="italic">before /</hi>o<hi rend="italic">/ that is realized as an
                            /</hi>l<hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">/ in other members of the paradigm (e.g. </hi>o-tr-o
                        <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">(m.) from </hi>o-tr-la <hi
                            rend="italic">(f.) [</hi>wiped<hi rend="italic">]).</hi></item>
                </list>
                <p>(8) <hi rend="italic">The other two alveolar sonorants, /</hi>l<hi rend="italic"
                        >/ and
                    /</hi>n<hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">/ can be syllable carriers in dialectal toponyms (e.g. </hi>Stlp<hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">, </hi>Vlča
                    glava<hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">, </hi>Žlne<hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">) or foreign toponyms (e.g. </hi>Vltava<hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">, </hi>Plzen<hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">) but also in other personal names (e.g. English </hi>Idn
                    <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">or Arabic </hi>Ibn-Saud<hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">), and in the word </hi>bicikl
                        <hi rend="italic">[</hi>bicycle<hi rend="italic">].</hi></p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Revising the Existing Rule Set</head>
                <p> The development of our syllabification algorithm has been an iterative process
                    testing the existing rule set and making changes as needed. While other authors
                    (e.g. Kaplar et al. 2018) used the rule descriptions of Stanojčić and Popović
                    (2005) directly to implement a software architecture for syllabification in
                    Serbian, we have found a number of problems with this approach.</p>
                <p> The definition of the rule description under (1) causes the initial member of a
                    consonant cluster in the rule descriptions under (2)–(6) to be understood as the
                    first consonant following a vowel. However, given that the sonorants /<hi
                        rend="italic">r</hi>/, /<hi rend="italic">l</hi>/, and /<hi rend="italic"
                        >n</hi>/ can also constitute syllable nuclei in Serbian in certain
                    positions, as presented under rule descriptions (7) and (8), a more precise
                    definition would be that the initial member of a consonant cluster is the first
                    consonant following an element that constitutes a syllable nucleus. The general
                    rule under (1) should be then revised as follows.</p>
                <p>(1*) <hi rend="italic">In words made up of multiple phonemes, consonants,
                        sonorants and vowels, the syllable boundary comes after the vowel or
                        sonorants /</hi>r<hi rend="italic">/,
                    /</hi>l<hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">/, and /n/ in syllable bearing positions and before the consonant (e.g. </hi>či-ta-ti<hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve"> [</hi>to
                    read<hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">], </hi>tr-ča-ti<hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve"> [</hi>to
                        run<hi rend="italic">]).</hi></p>
                <p>In addition to our expansion of the general rule presented under (1) to include
                    the syllable bearing sonorants, while formalizing the rule descriptions via
                    finite-state automata, rules (2) and (3) proved to be redundant as they produced
                    identical outcomes to the general rule under (1*). Because of this, these rules
                    were disregarded in our syllabification algorithm.</p>
                <p> During our early testing of the verbatim implementation of the rule
                    descriptions, we also noticed that the existing rule descriptions treated a
                    consonant cluster consisting of a nasal in initial position followed by a
                    consonant that is not one of the sonorants /<hi rend="italic">j</hi>/, /<hi
                        rend="italic">v</hi>/, /<hi rend="italic">l</hi>/, /<hi rend="italic"
                    >ʎ</hi>/, and /<hi rend="italic">r</hi>/ as a part of the following syllable
                    onset, producing outcomes such as: <hi rend="italic">gu-ngula</hi> [<hi
                        rend="italic">commotion</hi>], <hi rend="italic">mo-mci</hi> [<hi
                        rend="italic">guys</hi>], <hi rend="italic">ka-ncelarije</hi> [<hi
                        rend="italic">offices</hi>], <hi rend="italic">su-nce</hi> [<hi
                        rend="italic">sun</hi>], etc. Contrary to Stanojčić and Popović (2005),
                    authors such as Kašić (2014) argue that nasals should be treated analogously to
                    plosives during syllabification because there is a complete occlusion in the
                    oral cavity during their production. If this principle were to be employed, rule
                    (5) should be revised as follows.</p>
                <p>(5*)<hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve"> If a consonant cluster consists of a plosive or nasal in its initial position and some other consonant except the sonorants</hi>
                        /<hi rend="italic">j</hi>/, /<hi rend="italic">v</hi>/, /<hi rend="italic"
                        >l</hi>/, /<hi rend="italic">ʎ</hi>/, and /<hi rend="italic"
                    >r</hi>/,<hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve"> the syllable boundary will be between the consonants.</hi></p>
                <p>Following rule (5*), the examples above would then be segmented as: <hi
                        rend="italic">gun-gula</hi> [<hi rend="italic">commotion</hi>], <hi
                        rend="italic">mom-ci</hi> [<hi rend="italic">guys</hi>], <hi rend="italic"
                        >kan-celarije</hi> [<hi rend="italic">offices</hi>], <hi rend="italic"
                        >sun-ce</hi> [<hi rend="italic">sun</hi>], etc. Even though in the earlier
                    implementation of our syllabifier (Kovač and Marković 2018) we did not want to
                    employ the Sonority Sequencing Principle (SSP), we opted for the treatment of
                    nasals by Kašić (2014) in our implementation, which respected the limitations
                    put forward by the Sonority Hierarchy, and was more in line with native speaker
                    intuition.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>The Sonority Hierarchy</head>
                <p> Sonority Theory accounts for the organization of segments into well-formed
                    sequences, both within the syllable and across syllabic boundaries. This
                    organization is driven by principles of sonority, a property that is used as the
                    basis of ranking all sounds along a scale, from less sonorous to more sonorous
                    ones. Although there is a general consensus that segments are ranked by their
                    inherent sonority, the notion of sonority itself is not unambiguously described
                    in the phonetic and phonological literature. Among the phonetic approaches,
                    Ladefoged (1982) defines sonority as the perceptual salience or loudness of a
                    sound, and Bloch and Trager (1942; according to Goldsmith 1995) define it as the
                    amount of airflow in the resonance chamber. For others, sonority is dependent on
                    multiple phonetic parameters (Ohala and Kawasaki 1984; Ohala 1990; Butt 1992).
                    In the phonological literature, sonority is generally defined as a multi-valued
                    feature (Foley 1972; Hankamer and Aissen 1974; Selkirk 1984), although there are
                    also authors who argue that it is derivable from the more basic binary features
                    of phonological theory (Clements 1990). Other questions that are often addressed
                    are whether sonority scales are universal or language-specific, allowing freedom
                    to languages in assigning sonority values, and how fine-grained distinctions
                    sonority scales should capture. For example, Clements’ universal sonority scale
                    includes only four major classes of consonants (Clements 1990), ranked from
                    least sonorous to most sonorous, as in (i):<lb/></p>
                <list type="ordered">
                    <item>O &lt; N &lt; L &lt; G</item>
                </list>
                <p rend="List Paragraph">(O=obstruents, N=nasals, L=liquids, G=glides)</p>
                <p><lb/>Selkirk (1984, 112) proposes a much more detailed scale, which divides all
                    sounds into 11 groups, assuming more subtle differences in sonority values.
                    Selkirk also states that the sonority indices may not be as important in
                    themselves as the sonority relations that they express. Selkirk’s scale of
                    sonority in consonants is given in (ii):</p>
                <p><lb/>(ii) p, t, k &lt; b, d, g &lt; f, θ &lt; v, z, ð &lt; s &lt; m, n &lt; l
                    &lt; r</p>
                <p><lb/>Sonority scales serve as the basis of constructing segment sequences within
                    syllables. The universal cross-linguistic generalization is that in the sequence
                    of segments, the one ranking highest on the sonority scale constitutes the peak
                    of the syllable, i.e. it is the syllabic nucleus. As for the other segments
                    around the nucleus, they are organized so that the more sonorous ones are closer
                    to the nucleus, and less sonorous ones are more distant. This generalization is
                    referred to as Sonority Sequencing Principle (SSP). Thus a syllable with an
                    ascending sonority slope in the onset and a descending slope in the coda, such
                    as, for example <hi rend="italic">blunt</hi>, is a well-formed syllable, whereas
                        *<hi rend="italic">lbutn</hi> is prohibited, due to the violation of the
                    SSP. Adopting thee SSP often solves the problems of syllabic consonants, since
                    they generally occur in environments where they constitute a sonority peak, as
                    in the Serbian word <hi rend="italic">pr-vi</hi>.<lb/></p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>The Need for Sonority</head>
                <p> Apart from the segmentation of nasals analogously to plosives following Kašić
                    (2014) that relied on principles of the SSP, in our initial attempt at the
                    formalization of the rule description under (8) of Stanojčić and Popović (2005)
                    we had to rely on sonority to define the criteria for when the alveolar
                    sonorants /<hi rend="italic">l</hi>/ and /<hi rend="italic">n</hi>/ act as
                    syllable nuclei. </p>
                <p> As Stanojčić and Popović gave no formal criteria defining the contexts of
                    syllable bearing /<hi rend="italic">l</hi>/ and /<hi rend="italic">n</hi>/, our
                    initial attempt to draw on generalizations based on their examples for syllable
                    carrying /<hi rend="italic">l</hi>/ (<hi rend="italic">Stlp, Vlča glava, Žlne,
                        Vlava, Plzen</hi>) and /<hi rend="italic">n</hi>/ (<hi rend="italic">Idn,
                        Ibn-Saud</hi>). In analogy to the rules descriptions under (7a) and (7b) and
                    our added rule (7c*) defining the contexts in which the alveolar phoneme /<hi
                        rend="italic">r</hi>/ can act as a syllable nucleus, we implemented rule
                    (8*) to define the conditions under which the phonemes /<hi rend="italic"
                    >l</hi>/ and /<hi rend="italic">n</hi>/ can act as syllable bearing nuclei.</p>
                <p>(8*)<hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve"> The other two alveolar sonorants, /</hi>l<hi
                        rend="italic">/ and /</hi>n<hi rend="italic">/, can be syllable carriers if
                        they are found:</hi></p>
                <list type="ordered">
                    <item><hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve"> medially between two consonants,</hi></item>
                    <item><hi rend="italic">initially before a consonant, or</hi></item>
                    <item><hi rend="italic">finally after a consonant.</hi></item>
                </list>
                <p>However, the formulation under (8*) allowed for outcomes such as: <hi
                        rend="italic">Be-rn</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Ka-rl</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
                        >erla-jn</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Kla-jn</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
                        >kasa-rn-skim</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Linko-ln</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
                        >Va-jl-om</hi>, etc. in which the phonemes /<hi rend="italic">l</hi>/ and
                        /<hi rend="italic">n</hi>/ identified as syllable nuclei have a lower
                    sonority level than the consonants in their onset or coda. Because the phonemes
                        /<hi rend="italic">r</hi>/ and /<hi rend="italic">j</hi>/ are more sonorous
                    than the phonemes /<hi rend="italic">l</hi>/ and /<hi rend="italic">n</hi>/, and
                    the lateral phoneme /<hi rend="italic">l</hi>/ is more sonorous than the nasal
                    phoneme /<hi rend="italic">n</hi>/, native speakers do not perceive the elements
                    of lower sonority as syllable nuclei in these contexts. Zec (2000) states that
                    alveolar sonorants can be syllable bearing elements in Serbian only in contexts
                    in which there is no segment of a higher level of sonority in their immediate
                    vicinity. Because of this, we needed to further specify rule (8*) to take
                    sonority constraints into consideration as follows.</p>
                <p>(8**)<hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve"> The other two alveolar sonorants, /</hi>l<hi
                        rend="italic">/ and /</hi>n<hi rend="italic">/, can be syllable carriers if
                        they are found:</hi></p>
                <list type="ordered">
                    <item><hi rend="italic">medially between two consonants of lower
                        sonority,</hi></item>
                    <item><hi rend="italic">initially before a consonant of lower sonority,
                        or</hi></item>
                    <item><hi rend="italic">finally after a consonant of lower sonority.</hi></item>
                </list>
                <p>It turns out that this principle can also account for the behavior of the
                    syllable bearing /<hi rend="italic">r</hi>/ in Serbian. In fact, it does not
                    only provide a general account for consonantal syllabic nuclei in Serbian that
                    subsumes the rules under (7) and (8**) it also accounts for our extension of
                    rule (7) that keeps the the consonant cluster /<hi rend="italic">rje</hi>/ of
                    the ijekavica dialect unsegmented in initial position<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn4" n="2"
                            ><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">   It should be noted that while sonority sequencing accounts for the non-syllabic treatment of /</hi><hi
                            rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">r</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt">/
                            before /</hi><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt"
                            >je</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">/ in initial position, our rule extension is still needed as it has a more general scope than the sonority rule and accounts for segmentation in medial positions as well (e.g. in words such as </hi><hi
                            rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt"
                            >isko-rje-nilo</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve"> [</hi><hi
                            rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">eradicated</hi><hi
                            style="font-size:10pt">]).</hi></note>. Because the phoneme /<hi
                        rend="italic">j</hi>/ has a higher level of sonority than /<hi rend="italic"
                        >r</hi>/, the phoneme /<hi rend="italic">r</hi>/ should not be treated as a
                    syllable nucleus initially in words such as
                        <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">rjeka </hi>[<hi rend="italic"
                        >river</hi>].</p>
                <p> In our previous implementation of the syllabifier (Kovač and Marković 2018), we
                    attempted to limit our reliance on the Sonority Sequencing Principle to the
                    cases above. However, during the evaluation of our algorithm, we encountered a
                    number of syllable structures that were unexpected due to their absence from the
                    onset maximization approach to syllabification developed for Croatian by
                    Meštrović et al. (2015). Namely, we encountered the syllable structure CCCCCVC
                    in <hi rend="italic">mo-na-</hi><hi rend="italic underline">rhstvom</hi> [<hi
                        rend="italic">with the monarchy</hi>], the structure CCCCCV in the words <hi
                        rend="italic">se-</hi><hi rend="italic underline">rbska</hi> [<hi
                        rend="italic">Serbian</hi>], <hi rend="italic">ca-</hi><hi
                        rend="italic underline">rstva</hi> [<hi rend="italic">kingdoms</hi>], and
                        <hi rend="italic">sta-ra-te-</hi><hi rend="italic underline">ljstva</hi>
                        [<hi rend="italic">custody</hi>], and the structure CCCCVC in <hi
                        rend="italic">se-</hi><hi rend="italic underline">rbskom</hi> [<hi
                        rend="italic">Serbian</hi>], <hi rend="italic">de-</hi><hi
                        rend="italic underline">jstvom</hi> [<hi rend="italic">with
                        effect</hi>],<hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve"> vo-</hi><hi
                        rend="italic underline">đstvom</hi> [<hi rend="italic">leadership</hi>], <hi
                        rend="italic">spo-</hi><hi rend="italic underline">rtskim</hi> [<hi
                        rend="italic">sport</hi>], and <hi rend="italic">a-</hi><hi
                        rend="italic underline">lpskog</hi> [<hi rend="italic">alpine</hi>].</p>
                <p> The way we attempted to remedy this issue was to limit the syllable onset length
                    three-syllable clusters, which is the maximum length of non-syllabic consonant
                    clusters word initially in Serbian (Kašić 2014). While this constraint, in
                    combination with rules (5) and (6), resolved the issues in the examples we
                    encountered — with this limitation, they are segmented as
                        <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">mo-narh-stvom </hi>[<hi rend="italic"
                        >with the monarchy</hi>],
                        <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">serb-ska </hi>[<hi rend="italic"
                        >Serbian</hi>] (three-syllable onset limitation + rule (5)),
                        <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">car-stva </hi>[<hi rend="italic"
                        >kingdoms</hi>], <hi rend="italic">sta-ra-telj-stva</hi> [<hi rend="italic"
                        >custody</hi>], <hi rend="italic">serb-skom</hi> [<hi rend="italic"
                        >Serbian</hi>],<hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve"> dej-stvom</hi> [<hi
                        rend="italic">with effect</hi>],
                        <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">vođ-stvom </hi>[<hi rend="italic"
                        >leadership</hi>],
                        <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">sport-skim </hi>[<hi rend="italic"
                        >sport</hi>], <hi rend="italic">alp-sko</hi>g [<hi rend="italic"
                    >alpine</hi>] — some medial clusters with a syllabic consonant still remained a
                    problem. For example, in the word
                        <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">najstrpljiviji </hi>[<hi
                        rend="italic">most patient</hi>], which contains a syllabic /<hi
                        rend="italic">r</hi>/, the syllable boundary that would be placed between
                        /<hi rend="italic">na</hi>/ and /<hi rend="italic">jstr</hi>/ — <hi
                        rend="italic">na-jstr-pljiviji</hi> — which does not coincide with native
                    speaker intuition. The Sonority Sequencing Principle seems like a perfect
                    solution for this cases, as it would require the structure of a syllable to
                    follow a sonority scale, with the syllable nucleus being the most sonorous
                    element, while sonority would gradually decrease towards the periphery of the
                    syllable (Zec 2000). With this added sonority requirement, the phoneme /<hi
                        rend="italic">j</hi>/, being more sonorous than /<hi rend="italic">s</hi>/
                    and /<hi rend="italic">t</hi>/, would have to constitute a part of the previous
                    syllable where it would be of a lower sonority when compared to its neighbouring
                    syllable bearing vowel, and the syllable boundary would be
                    <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">naj-str-pljiviji </hi>which is in line
                    with native speaker intuition.</p>
                <p> As a final check following rules (1)–(8**), we add rule (9) that has the ability
                    to shift the syllable boundary in order to avoid a violation of the sonority
                    hierarchy.</p>
                <p>(9)<hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve"> If the syllable structure resulting from rules (1)–(8**) does not conform to the Sonority Sequencing Principle, move the boundary so that the phoneme violating the sonority sequence is shifted into the neighboring syllable.</hi></p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>An Adapted Sonority Hierarchy</head>
                <p> In our sonority sequencing module, we relied on a combination of Selkirk’s
                    (1984) sonority scale, the sonority apertures for Serbian described by Subotić
                    et al. (2012), and some notes on sonority sequencing in Serbian from Zec (2000).
                    Our sonority scale is shown under (iii).</p>
                <p>(iii) p, t, k &lt; b, d, g &lt; ts, tʃ, tɕ &lt; f, ʃ, h &lt; v, z, ʒ &lt; s &lt;
                    m, n, ɲ &lt; l, ʎ &lt; j, r &lt; a, e, i o, u</p>
                <p>The highest sonority group in our implementation was made up by the vowels of
                    Serbian. As vowels constitute syllable nuclei and there can only be a single
                    vowel per syllable, we did not need to make a distinction between three sonority
                    apertures of vowels (i, u &lt; e, o &lt; a) as it is the case in the hierarchy
                    of Subotić et al. (2012). Following Selkirk (1984), we divided sonorants into
                    three sonority classes, and following Zec (2000), we treated liquids as more
                    sonorous than nasals, and, within liquids, the phoneme /<hi rend="italic"
                    >r</hi>/ as more sonorous than laterals. For the needs of our implementation, we
                    treated the phoneme /<hi rend="italic">r</hi>/ and glide /<hi rend="italic"
                        >j</hi>/ as a single sonority group, although from a theoretical standpoint
                        /<hi rend="italic">j</hi>/ would be considered as more sonorous out of the
                    two given its semi-vowel nature. We opted for treating /s/ as an element of
                    higher sonority than voiced fricative despite its voiceless nature following
                    Selkirk (1984), and expanded Selkirk’s hierarchy with the addition of affricates
                    between voiceless fricatives and voiced plosives as a parallel to the aperture
                    order presented by Subotić et al. (2012).</p>
                <p> It is important to note that there are sequences which clearly do not conform
                    with the SSP in a number of languages, and which may undermine the relevance and
                    power of the sonority hierarchy. A very common pattern, found across a number of
                    unrelated languages, is the possibility of an /<hi rend="italic">s</hi>/ +
                    plosive sequence in the syllable onset, which would be in clear violation if we
                    were to adopt the sonority scale outlined above. In Serbian, there is a known
                    ambiguity in syllable segmentation in the case of continuant fricative phonemes.
                    For example, the word <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">postaviti </hi>[<hi
                        rend="italic">to set</hi>] can be syllabified as both <hi rend="italic"
                        >po-sta-vi-ti</hi> and
                    <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">pos-ta-vi-ti </hi>(Gvozdanović 2011). We
                    therefore adopt the view put forward in Morelli (1999), who argues that
                    fricatives and plosives may be treated as a single class with respect to
                    sonority in these cases — since splitting them into separate classes would make
                    wrong typological predictions — and add an exception to our sonority sequencing
                    module that leaves fricative + plosive sequences as a viable sequence in the
                    syllable onset.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Our Algorithm<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn5" n="3"
                            ><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve"> Our implementation of the algorithm can be found at </hi><ref
                            target="https://github.com/versi-regular/rule-based_syllabifier_sr"><hi
                                style="font-size:10pt"
                                >https://github.com/versi-regular/rule-based_syllabifier_sr</hi></ref><hi
                            style="font-size:10pt">, licensed under the GNU General Public License
                            v3.0. It was developed using Python 3.x and processes 10380 tokens/s on
                            average estimated on a 4,681,713 token corpus processed on an Intel®
                            Core™ i5-3210M CPU @ 2.50GHz with 8.00 GBs of DDR3L-1600 SODIMM,
                            including pre-processing, clean-up, and
                    transliteration.</hi></note></head>
                <p> Our mixed-principle syllabification algorithms consists of the following
                    steps:</p>
                <list rend="numbered">
                    <item n="I">Identify vowels in the word and mark their positions as positions capable
                        of constituting syllable nuclei (based on (1)).</item>
                    <item n="II">If a word contains the
                        letters<hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve"> l</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
                            >n</hi> or the letter<hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve"> r</hi> not
                        followed by the sequence <hi rend="italic">je</hi> in the center of a
                        consonant cluster consisting of elements of lower sonority or at the
                        beginning or a word followed by a consonant of lower sonority, or the
                        letters <hi rend="italic">l</hi> or <hi rend="italic">n</hi> at the end of a
                        word preceded by a consonant of lower sonority, treat those positions in the
                        word as capable of constituting syllable nuclei (based on (1*), (7), and
                        (8**)).</item>
                    <item n="III">For each position identified as capable of constituting a syllable
                        nucleus:<list type="numbered">
                            <item n="A.">If it is followed by a sequence of two sonorants, mark the
                                syllable boundary between the two sonorants (based on (4)), except
                                if the second sonorant is <hi rend="italic">j</hi> and it is
                                followed by <hi rend="italic">e</hi>. If the second sonorant is <hi
                                    rend="italic">j</hi> followed by <hi rend="italic">e</hi>, mark
                                the syllable boundary before the sonorant cluster (based on
                                (6)).</item>
                            <item n="B.">If it is followed by a sequence of a plosive or nasal and a
                                plosive, fricative, affricate or nasal, mark the syllable boundary
                                between the two consonants (based on (5*)).</item>
                            <item n="C.">In all other cases mark the syllable boundary after the syllable
                                nucleus (based on (1*)).</item>
                        </list></item>
                    <item n="IV">Run a recursive sonority check (based on (9)):<list type="ordered">
                            <item>If the word consists of more than one syllable, convert the
                                syllable structures identified by the previous steps into sonority
                                group values.</item>
                            <item>For each syllable, check if there is a violation of the SSP at the
                                edges of the syllable ignoring the check at the onset on the
                                word-initial syllable and the check in the coda of the word-final
                                syllable.</item>
                            <item>If a violation found is a sequence of a fricative followed by a
                                plosive in the onset, ignore the violation.</item>
                            <item>If there is a violation, remove the letter from the edge of the
                                syllable, and add it onto the neighboring syllable.</item>
                            <item>Repeat until no violation is found.</item>
                        </list></item>
                </list>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Syllable Distribution Data</head>
                <p> In this section, we present the statistical distribution data of syllables in
                    Serbian based on our updated syllabification process applied to the Serbian
                    Lemmatized and PoS Annotated Corpus
                    <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">SrpLemKor </hi>(Popović 2010; Utvić
                    2011). We chose <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">SrpLemKor </hi>for our
                    analysis, because its annotation allowed us to filter out numbers, Roman
                    numerals, abbreviations and non-Serbian words or suffixes in compounds (at least
                    to some extent) and thus reduce noise in the data.</p>
                <p> The following results show the syllable distribution statistics based on
                    3,648,543 non-unique word-forms (word tokens) from <hi rend="italic"
                        >SrpLemKor</hi>. From a total of 4,681,713 entities (punctuation and word
                    tokens) in our version of the corpus, 113,679 (2.43%) entities of texts #260,
                    #4505 and #4517 were excluded because the files contained faulty encoding. Based
                    on corpus tags, we excluded 919,161 (19.63%) entities tagged PUNCT
                    (punctuation), SENT (sentence separator full-stops), RN (Roman numerals), NUM
                    @card@ (Arabic numerals), ABB (abbreviations) and ? (non-Serbian words and other
                    uncategorized entries). An additional 815 (0.02%) entities that contained the
                    characters w, q and x were removed in an attempt to further reduce noise
                    stemming from foreign words, as not all foreign words were tagged as such in the
                    corpus. In the process of syllabification, an additional 12,877 (0.28%) entities
                    were removed as they were solely made up of consonant clusters with no available
                    syllable nucleus candidate.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Syllable Type Distributions in Serbian</head>
                <p> In the 3,648,543 word-forms from <hi rend="italic">SrpLemKor</hi>, a total of
                    8,196,771 syllables were identified. Table 1 presents the syllable type
                    distribution based on our mixed-principle syllabification algorithm.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="table1.jpg"/>
                    <head>Table 1: Syllable structure distribution of syllables in the <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">SrpLemKor </hi>corpus</head>                    
                </figure>                
                <p> These results show the distribution of syllables in a somewhat noisy data. We
                    found there are still foreign words annotated as non-foreign in the corpus
                    constituting some of the less-frequent syllable structures listed as “Other” in
                    Table 1. For example, an instance of the syllable structure VCCCCC was found to
                    correspond to the segmentation of the German word <hi rend="italic">Pe-</hi><hi
                        rend="italic underline">itscht</hi> [<hi rend="italic">lashes</hi>], the
                    syllable structure CCCCVCCC was identified in the German word <hi rend="italic"
                        >Fle-i-</hi><hi rend="italic underline">schmarkt</hi> [<hi rend="italic"
                        >meat market</hi>], and the structure CCCCCVC was found in the German word
                        <hi rend="italic">Gle-i-</hi><hi rend="italic underline">chschal</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">-tung</hi> [<hi rend="italic">co-ordination</hi>]. The
                    structure CCCCCCVC was found in the German word <hi rend="italic">Na-</hi><hi
                        rend="italic underline">chtschat</hi><hi rend="italic">-ten</hi> [<hi
                        rend="italic">nightshade</hi>] and in the toponym <hi rend="italic"
                        >CRYSLER</hi>. The syllable structure CCVCCCC was found in the source
                    transcription of the last name <hi rend="italic">Pe-</hi><hi
                        rend="italic underline">tritsch</hi> and in the English word <hi
                        rend="italic">knights</hi>. The syllable structure CCCVCCC was identified to
                    be a part of the German words <hi rend="italic">Wol-</hi><hi
                        rend="italic underline">fsmilch</hi> [<hi rend="italic">spurge</hi>] and <hi
                        rend="italic">E-in-ge-</hi><hi rend="italic underline">schickt</hi> [<hi
                        rend="italic">sent in</hi>] and to correspond to the English word <hi
                        rend="italic">string</hi>. The syllable structure CCCCCCV was identified in
                    the German words <hi rend="italic">We-i-hna-</hi><hi rend="italic underline"
                        >chtsbra</hi><hi rend="italic">-e-u-che</hi> [<hi rend="italic">Christmas
                        trees</hi>], <hi rend="italic">Stor-</hi><hi rend="italic underline"
                        >chschna</hi><hi rend="italic">-bel</hi> [Crane’s bill], while the structure
                    CCCCCV was found in the words <hi rend="italic">Re-</hi><hi
                        rend="italic underline">chtsge</hi><hi rend="italic">-schi-chte</hi> [<hi
                        rend="italic">history of law</hi>] and <hi rend="italic">Um-gan-</hi><hi
                        rend="italic underline">gsspra</hi><hi rend="italic">-che</hi> [<hi
                        rend="italic">vernacular</hi>], as well as in the sequences <hi
                        rend="italic">šttske</hi> and <hi rend="italic">su-</hi><hi
                        rend="italic underline">žnjstva</hi>. The syllable structure CCCCVCC was
                    found in the German word <hi rend="italic">Ze-it-</hi><hi
                        rend="italic underline">schrift</hi> [<hi rend="italic">magazine</hi>], and
                    in multiple occurrences of the source spelling of the last names <hi
                        rend="italic">Schmidt</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Rot-</hi><hi
                        rend="italic underline">hchild</hi>. The structure VCCCC was found in the
                    German words <hi rend="italic">Deutsch</hi> [<hi rend="italic">German</hi>],
                        <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Ernst </hi>[<hi rend="italic"
                        >seriousness</hi>], in the sequence <hi rend="italic">der-demnaechst</hi>
                        [<hi rend="italic">soon</hi>], and in the strings
                    <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">ikvbv </hi>and <hi rend="italic"
                        >EHCmc</hi>. As can be seen from the examples above, besides foreign origin
                    words, noise in the data can also be found in typos and strings we did not
                    manage to identify. Another example of such string was
                    <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">ngBpJKTnQ </hi>identified as the
                    structure VCCCCCCCC. Most structures identified as CVCCCC were the result of
                    typos, e.g. serbsk, kra-levstv, pod-danstv, carstv, slav-jansk,
                    ju-go-slo-venskg, cr-no-gorskg, but also foreign origin names, e.g. <hi
                        rend="italic">Hirsch, Herbst</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Lokotsch</hi>, and <hi
                        rend="italic">Worlds</hi> in additions to strings such as <hi rend="italic"
                        >majnds and Gorrrr</hi>. In addition to these, one occurrence of the
                    syllable structure CVCCCCCCCC that stood for the onomatopoeic vulgarism <hi
                        rend="italic">mršššššššš</hi> [<hi rend="italic">go away</hi>].</p>
                <p> We also found 2 syllable structures that differed from the structures found by
                    Meštrović et al. (2005) for Croatian. The structure CCCCVC was identified in the
                    words <hi rend="italic">vo-</hi><hi rend="italic underline">đstvom</hi> [<hi
                        rend="italic">with leadership</hi>], <hi rend="italic">za-ko-no-da-</hi><hi
                        rend="italic underline">vstvom</hi> [<hi rend="italic">with
                    legislature</hi>], <hi rend="italic">mo-nar-hstvom</hi> [<hi rend="italic">with
                        monkhood</hi>], <hi rend="italic">lu-ka-</hi><hi rend="italic underline"
                        >vstvom</hi> [<hi rend="italic">with slyness</hi>], <hi rend="italic"
                        >be-zzglob-na</hi> [<hi rend="italic">without wrists</hi>], and in the
                    paradigm members of the word <hi rend="italic">po-</hi><hi
                        rend="italic underline">sthlad</hi><hi rend="italic">-no-ra-to-vski</hi>
                        [<hi rend="italic">post-cold-war</hi>]. It also occurred in the Russian word
                        <hi rend="italic">Zdra-</hi><hi rend="italic underline">vstvuj</hi> [hello],
                    in the German-origin word <hi rend="italic">Ha-up-</hi><hi
                        rend="italic underline"
                        >tstrum</hi><hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">-fi-rer </hi>[<hi
                        rend="italic">mid-level commander</hi>], in the German <hi rend="italic"
                        >Ra-u-</hi><hi rend="italic underline">schmit</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >-tel</hi> [<hi rend="italic">intoxicant</hi>] and <hi rend="italic"
                        >Li-e-be-</hi><hi rend="italic underline">spflan</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >-ze</hi> [<hi rend="italic">love plant</hi>] and in the misspelled Serbian
                    words <hi rend="italic">pri-ja-</hi><hi rend="italic underline">tljskih</hi>
                        [<hi rend="italic">friendly</hi>] and
                        <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">kvdrat </hi>[<hi rend="italic"
                        >square</hi>]. The structure CCCCV was found in the words <hi rend="italic"
                        >bi-</hi><hi rend="italic underline">vstvu</hi> [<hi rend="italic"
                        >existence</hi>], <hi rend="italic">va-zdu-ho-plo-</hi><hi
                        rend="italic underline">vstvo</hi> [<hi rend="italic">aviation</hi>], <hi
                        rend="italic">kra-lje-</hi><hi rend="italic underline">vstva</hi> [<hi
                        rend="italic">kingdoms</hi>], <hi rend="italic">zdra-</hi><hi
                        rend="italic underline">vstve</hi><hi rend="italic">-noj</hi> [<hi
                        rend="italic">health</hi>], <hi rend="italic">vo-</hi><hi
                        rend="italic underline">đstvo</hi> [<hi rend="italic">leadership</hi>], <hi
                        rend="italic">ču-</hi><hi rend="italic underline">vstva</hi> [<hi
                        rend="italic">feeling</hi>], <hi rend="italic">pre-i-mu-</hi><hi
                        rend="italic underline">ćstva</hi> [<hi rend="italic">advantages</hi>], and
                        <hi rend="italic">mo-gu-</hi><hi rend="italic underline">ćstvu</hi> [<hi
                        rend="italic">possibility</hi>]. It also occurred in German words such as
                        <hi rend="italic">Pfin-</hi><hi rend="italic underline"
                        >gstro</hi><hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">-se </hi>[<hi
                        rend="italic">peony</hi>], <hi rend="italic">Ke-u-</hi><hi
                        rend="italic underline"
                        >schhe</hi><hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">-it </hi>[<hi
                        rend="italic">chastity</hi>], <hi rend="italic underline"
                        >Schne</hi><hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">-e-glo-ec-kchen </hi>[<hi
                        rend="italic">snowdrop</hi>], <hi rend="italic underline"
                        >Schne</hi><hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">-e-ro-se </hi>[<hi
                        rend="italic">Chrismas rose</hi>], <hi rend="italic">Ge-i-</hi><hi
                        rend="italic underline">sskle</hi><hi rend="italic">-e</hi> [<hi
                        rend="italic">cystus</hi>], <hi rend="italic">Vol-</hi><hi
                        rend="italic underline">ksbra</hi><hi rend="italic">-uch</hi> [<hi
                        rend="italic">popular custom</hi>], <hi rend="italic">Vol-</hi><hi
                        rend="italic underline">ksgla</hi><hi rend="italic">-u-ben</hi> [<hi
                        rend="italic">popular belief</hi>], <hi rend="italic underline"
                        >Schri</hi><hi rend="italic">-ften</hi> [<hi rend="italic"
                    >regulations</hi>], <hi rend="italic underline">Schlu</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >-e-ssel-blu-me</hi> [<hi rend="italic">cowslip</hi>], and more<hi
                        rend="italic">.</hi> We discuss the implications of these for our
                    syllabification algorithm in the Discussion section below.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Syllable Type Positional Distributions in Serbian</head>
                <p> We also examined the syllable type frequencies with respect to their position in
                    a word. Four positional frequencies are presented in Table 2: syllable type
                    frequencies in monosyllabic words, and syllables type frequencies in the initial
                    position, in medial positions, and in the final position of polysyllabic
                    words.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="table2.jpg"/><head>Table 2: Syllable structure distribution of syllables in the
                    <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">SrpLemKor </hi>corpus categorized by
                    position</head></figure>
                <p>Based on <hi rend="italic">SrpLemKor</hi>, the most frequent monosyllabic
                    syllable structures in Serbian are CV (50%), V (25%) and CVC (11%). The most
                    frequent syllable structures in the initial position of polysyllabic words are
                    CV (56%), CCV (15%) and V (15%). In medial positions in polysyllabic words, the
                    most frequent syllable structures are CV (69%), CCV (14%) and CVC (10%). The
                    most frequent syllable structures in the final position of polysyllabic words
                    are CV (65%), CVC (16%) and CCV (8%). It is interesting to note the asymmetry
                    that the syllable structures CCCVCC, VCCC, and CCCCVC occurred only in
                    monosyllabic words and in the final position of polysyllabic words, while the
                    syllable structure CCCCVC occurred in all positions except the initial position
                    in polysyllabic words.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Syllable Nuclei Statistics in Serbian</head>
                <p> The distribution of different syllable nuclei in Serbian based on the <hi
                        rend="italic">SrpLemKor</hi> corpus is presented in Table 3.</p>
                <figure><graphic url="table3.jpg"/><head>Table 3: Syllable nuclei statistics and positional frequencies of syllables in
                    the <hi rend="italic">SrpLemKor</hi> corpus</head>                    
                </figure>
                <p>Based on the positional nucleus distribution data, it can be seen that overall
                    /a/ and /o/ constitute the most frequent nuclei in Serbian. However, there is
                    some positional variation. While the most frequent nuclei in final, medial, and
                    initial position of polysyllabic words are also /a/ and /o/, in monosyllabic
                    words, the most frequent nuclei are /a/ and /e/.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Discussion</head>
                <p> While our mixed-principle rule-based syllabification algorithm is suitable for
                    the segmentation of words into syllables following the ruleset we devised based
                    by the combination of prescriptive rule descriptions and the employment of the
                    Sonority Sequencing Principle, there are still some practical and theoretical
                    considerations to be addressed.</p>
                <p> While reporting on the syllable distribution data, we mentioned that the
                    3,648,543 word-forms extracted from <hi rend="italic">SrpLemKor</hi> used for
                    the calculation of statistical data related to the distribution of syllables and
                    their structure in Serbian still contained some noise such as foreign words,
                    typos, and possibly random character strings. Based on 500 random samples taken
                    from the syllable output data checked by a human evaluator, the estimate of the
                    amount of such noise in the data is &lt;2%. Given the nature of corpus-based
                    data, this noise should not significantly impact the reliability of the
                    distributional information.</p>
                <p> From a theoretical standpoint, in formulating our algorithm, we disregarded the
                    three-syllable consonant cluster limitation put forward by Kašić (2014) in favor
                    of exploring the limitations of the sonority module. The occurrence of the two
                    syllable types CCCCVC and CCCCV, which were not present in the
                    onset-maximization-based syllabification algorithm for Croatian (Meštrović et
                    al. 2015), shows that in a limited number of instances this constraint is needed
                    to exclude syllable clusters that are in accordance with the SSP and
                    prescriptive rule descriptions, but seem contrary to native speaker intuition
                    about syllable boundaries. In addition to this, there is the ambiguity in
                    syllable segmentation in the case of continuant fricative phonemes (Gvozdanović
                    2011) with the continuant constituting either the first place in the onset of
                    the syllable or the last place in the coda of the previous syllable, e.g. the
                    possibility to syllabify <hi rend="italic">postaviti</hi> [<hi rend="italic">to
                        set</hi>] as <hi rend="italic">po-sta-vi-ti</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
                        >pos-ta-vi-ti</hi>, would require a larger-scale study examining the
                    intuition of native speakers on syllabification to make an assumption about
                    contemporary tendencies in the segmentation in these contexts.</p>
                <p> In order to verify the syllabic status of different clusters, it would be
                    interesting to conduct a series of monitoring studies modeled after Mehler et
                    al. (1981), who have shown that reaction times to a word are faster if the word
                    is primed by a sequence corresponding to a syllable in the word when compared to
                    priming with a string that does not constitute a syllable. Bradley et al. (1993)
                    argue that these effects produce mixed results in some languages which contain a
                    large number of ambisyllabic segments, so these studies may also reveal whether
                    and to what extent syllables play a</p>
                <p>role in pre-lexical processing in Serbian.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Conclusion</head>
                <p> In this paper we presented a mixed-principle rule-based syllabifier modelled
                    after the rule descriptions found in Stanojčić and Popović (2005), extended by
                    rule specifications from Kašić (2014) and Zec (2000), and complemented by a
                    sonority sequencing module based on Selkirk (1984), Subotić et al. (2012), and
                    Zec (2000).</p>
                <p> An implementation of the existing prescriptive rules for the segmentation of
                    words into syllables allowed us to gain an insight into the problem areas of the
                    rule descriptions, and propose a number of revisions and amendments to the
                    existing rules. The sonority sequencing module revealed the need for an
                    additional onset-length limitation constraint, and pointed out the limitations
                    of sonority in ambiguous consonant clusters that would require further
                    exploration and validation by native speaker intuition. We have also gained an
                    insight into the distribution of different syllable structures and syllable
                    nuclei following this approach, which will be useful for comparison with the
                    performance of alternative syllabification systems.</p>
                <p> In the future, we plan to compare our system to an onset-maximization-based
                    syllabifier for Serbian in combination with the prescriptive rules to see if we
                    can create an alternative system that will produce outputs consistent with the
                    intuition of native speakers of Serbian. It would be interesting to see a
                    systematic comparison of our current approach and the onset-maximization
                    approach with data gathered from the intuition of contemporary native speakers
                    of Serbian.</p>
                <p> We also believe that, while phonological criteria present a basis for
                    syllabification, in the future we will also need to test whether and to what
                    extent approaches based solely on phonological criteria result in syllable
                    boundaries that coincide with morphological boundaries. Our assumption is that
                    phonological rules will need to be amended by morphological criteria to result
                    in syllabification that respects morphological boundaries as well.</p>
                <p> In addition to these, the question of the treatment of foreign origin words and
                    transcribed foreign words might be an additional point to consider. As an
                    extension of</p>
                <p>a syllabifier, a language detection algorithm might be employed to properly
                    segment the former, while the latter might not need special treatment as the
                    process of transcription should in itself contain a degree of phonological
                    adaptation.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Acknowledgment</head>
                <p> This research was supported by the Serbian Ministry of Education and Science
                    under the projects Development of Dialogue Systems for Serbian and Other South
                    Slavic Languages (TR-32035) and Languages and Cultures in Time and Space
                    (ON-178002).</p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="bibliography">
                <head>Sources and Literature</head>
                <head>Literature:</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">Barber, Horacio, Marta Vergara, and Manuel Carreiras. 2004. “Syllable-frequency effects in visual word recognition: evidence from ERPs.” </hi><hi
                            rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt"
                        >Neuroreport</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve"> 15 (3): 545–8.</hi></bibl>
                    <bibl><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">Bradley, Dianne C., Rosa M. Sánchez-Casas, and José E. García-Albea. 2007. “The status of the syllable in the perception of Spanish and English.” </hi><hi
                            rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Language and Cognitive
                            Processes</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve"> 8 (2): 197–233.</hi></bibl>
                    <bibl><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">Bigi, Brigitte, and Caterina Petrone. 2014. “A generic tool for the automatic syllabification of Italian.” In </hi><hi
                            rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Proceedings of The First Italian
                            Conference on Computational Linguistics,
                            CLiC-it</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">, 73–77. Pisa: Pisa University Press. </hi><ref
                            target="http://siti.fileli.unipi.it/projects/clic/proceedings/Proceedings-CLICit-2014.pdf"
                                ><hi style="font-size:10pt">http://siti.fileli.unipi.it/projects/clic/proceedings/Proceedings-CLICit-2014.pdf</hi></ref><hi
                            style="font-size:10pt">.</hi></bibl>
                    <bibl><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">Butt, Matthias. 1992. “Sonority and the Explanation of Syllable Structure.” </hi><hi
                            rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Linguistische
                        Berichte</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve"> 137: 45–67.</hi></bibl>
                    <bibl><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">Cholin, Joana, Willem J. M. Levelt, and Niels O. Schiller. 2006. “Effects of syllable frequency in speech production.” </hi><hi
                            rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt"
                        >Cognition</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve"> 99 (2): 205–35.</hi></bibl>
                    <bibl><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">Cholin Joana, and Willem J. M. Levelt. 2009. “Effects of syllable preparation and syllable frequency in speech production: Further evidence for syllabic units at a post-lexical level.” </hi><hi
                            rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Language and Cognitive
                            Processes</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve"> 24(5): 662–84.</hi></bibl>
                    <bibl><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">Clements, George N. 1990. “The Role of the Sonority Cycle in Core Syllabification.” In </hi><hi
                            rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Papers in Laboratory Phonology I:
                            Between the Grammar and Physics of Speech</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt"
                            >, edited by John Kingston, John and Mary E. Beckman, 282–333.
                            Cambridge: Cambridge University Press.</hi></bibl>
                    <bibl><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">Daelemans, Walter, and Antal van den Bosch. 1992. “Generalization Performance of Backpropagation Learning on a Syllabification Task.” In </hi><hi
                            rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Connectionism and Natural Language
                            Processing: Proceedings of the 3rd Twente Workshop on Language
                            Technology,
                            TWLT3</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">, 27–38. Enschede: University of Twente, Department of Computer Science. </hi><ref
                            target="https://pure.uvt.nl/portal/files/760578/generalization.pdf"><hi
                                style="font-size:10pt"
                                >https://pure.uvt.nl/portal/files/760578/generalization.pdf</hi></ref><hi
                            style="font-size:10pt">.</hi></bibl>
                    <bibl><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">Foley, James. 1972. “Rule Precursors and Phonological Change by Meta-rule.” In </hi><hi
                            rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Linguistic change and generative
                            theory</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt">, edited by Robert P. Stockwell
                            and Ronald K. S. Macaulay, 96–100. Bloomington: Indiana University
                            Press.</hi></bibl>
                    <bibl><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">Goldsmith, John A. 1995. </hi><hi
                            rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">The handbook of phonological
                            theory</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt">. London: Blackwell
                            Publishers.</hi></bibl>
                    <bibl><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">Gvozdanović, Jadranka. 2011. “Phonological domains.” In </hi><hi
                            rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Sandhi Phenomena in the Languages
                            of
                        Europe,</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve"> edited by Henning Andersen, 27–54. Berlin: Mouton de Gruyter.</hi>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">Hankamer, Jorge, and Judith Aissen. 1974. “The sonority hierarchy.” In </hi><hi
                            rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Papers from the Parasession on
                            Natural Phonology</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt">, edited by Anthony
                            Bruck, Robert Allen Fox, and Michael W. La Galy, 131–45. Chicago:
                            Chicago Linguistic Society.</hi></bibl>
                    <bibl><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">Hunt, Andrew. 1993. “Recurrent Neural Networks for Syllabification.” </hi><hi
                            rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Speech
                        Communication</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve"> 13 (3–4): 323–32.</hi></bibl>
                    <bibl><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">Iacoponi, Luca, and Renata Savy. 2011. “Sylli: Automatic Phonological Syllabification for Italian.” In </hi><hi
                            rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">INTERSPEECH 2011, 12th Annual
                            Conference of the International Speech Communication Association</hi><hi
                            style="font-size:10pt">, 641–44. Florence: International Speech
                            Communication Association.</hi>
                        <ref target="http://eden.rutgers.edu/~li51/php/papers/interspeech2011.pdf"
                                ><hi style="font-size:10pt"
                                >http://eden.rutgers.edu/~li51/php/papers/interspeech2011.pdf</hi></ref><hi
                            style="font-size:10pt">.</hi></bibl>
                    <bibl><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">Kaplar, Sebastijan, Marija Radojičić, Ivan Obradović, Biljana Lazić, and Ranka Stanković. 2018. “Solution for quantitative analysis of texts in Serbian based on syllables.” In </hi><hi
                            rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">ICIST 2018
                            Proceedings</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve"> 2, 315–20. Belgrade: Society for Information Systems and Computer Networks. </hi><ref
                            target="http://www.eventiotic.com/eventiotic/library/paper/429"><hi
                                style="font-size:10pt"
                                >http://www.eventiotic.com/eventiotic/library/paper/429</hi></ref><hi
                            style="font-size:10pt">.</hi></bibl>
                    <bibl><hi style="font-size:10pt">Kašić, Zorka. 2014. “Opšta lingvistika 2
                            (Fonologija).” Lecture Materials, Faculty of Philosophy, University of
                            Belgrade.</hi></bibl>
                    <bibl><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">Koehler, Klaus J. 1966. “Is the syllable a phonological universal?” </hi>
                        <hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Journal of
                        Linguistics</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve"> 2: 207–208.</hi></bibl>
                    <bibl><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">Kovač, Aniko, and Maja Marković. 2018. “A Rule-Based Syllabifier for Serbian.” In </hi><hi
                            rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Proceedings of the Conference on
                            Language Technologies and Digital Humanities 2018</hi><hi
                            style="font-size:10pt">, 140–46. Ljubljana: Ljubljana University
                            Press.</hi></bibl>
                    <bibl><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">Ladefoged, Peter, and Keith Johnson. 2014. </hi><hi
                            rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">A Course in Phonetics</hi><hi
                            style="font-size:10pt">. Belmont: Wadsworth Publishing.</hi></bibl>
                    <bibl><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">Ladefoged, Peter. 1982. </hi><hi
                            rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">A Course in Phonetics</hi><hi
                            style="font-size:10pt">. New York: Harcourt Brace
                        Jovanovich.</hi></bibl>
                    <bibl><hi style="font-size:10pt">Landsiedel, Christian, Jens Edlund, Florian
                            Eyben, Daniel Neiberg, and Björn Schuller. 2011. “Syllabification of
                            conversational speech using Bidirectional Long-Short-Term Memory Neural
                            Networks.”
                            In</hi><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve"> 2011 IEEE International Conference on Acoustics, Speech and Signal Processing (ICASSP)</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">, 5256–9. Prague: IEEE. </hi><ref
                            target="http://ieeexplore.ieee.org/abstract/document/5947543"><hi
                                style="font-size:10pt"
                                >http://ieeexplore.ieee.org/abstract/document/5947543</hi></ref><hi
                            style="font-size:10pt">.</hi></bibl>
                    <bibl><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">Marchand, Yannick, Connie R. Adsett, and Robert I. Damper. 2009. “Automatic syllabification in English: A comparison of different algorithms.” </hi><hi
                            rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Language and
                        Speech</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve"> 52 (1): 1–27.</hi></bibl>
                    <bibl><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">Mehler, Jacques, Jean Yves Dommergues, Uli Frauenfelder, and Juan Segui. 1981. “The syllable's role in speech segmentation.” </hi><hi
                            rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Journal of Verbal Learning and
                            Verbal
                        Behavior</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve"> 20 (3): 298–305.</hi></bibl>
                    <bibl><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">Meštrović, Ana, Sanda Martinčić-Ipšić, and Mihaela Matešić. 2015. “Postupak automatskoga slogovanja temeljem načela najvećega pristupa i statistika slogova za hrvatski jezik.” </hi><hi
                            rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Govor</hi><hi
                            style="font-size:10pt">, 32: 3–34.</hi></bibl>
                    <bibl><hi style="font-size:10pt">Morelli, Frida. 1999. “The phonotactics and
                            phonology of obstruent clusters in optimality theory.” PhD diss.,
                            University of Maryland.</hi></bibl>
                    <bibl><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">Ohala, John, and Haruko Kawasaki. 1984. “Prosodic Phonology and Phonetics.” </hi><hi
                            rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Phonology Yearbook</hi><hi
                            style="font-size:10pt">, 1: 113–27.</hi></bibl>
                    <bibl><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">Ohala, John. 1990. “The Phonetics and Phonology of Aspects of Assimilation.” In </hi><hi
                            rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Papers in Laboratory Phonology
                            I</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt">, edited by John Kingston, John and
                            Mary E. Beckman, 258–75. Cambridge: Cambridge University
                        Press.</hi></bibl>
                    <bibl><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">Popović, Zoran. 2010. “Taggers Applied on Texts in Serbian.” </hi><hi
                            rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt"
                        >INFOtheca</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve"> 11 (2): 21a–38a.</hi></bibl>
                    <bibl><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">Selkirk, Elisabeth O. 1984. “On the Major Class Features and Syllable Theory.” In </hi><hi
                            rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Language Sound Structure</hi><hi
                            style="font-size:10pt">, edited by Mark Aronoff and Richard T. Oehrle,
                            107–36. Cambridge: MIT Press.</hi></bibl>
                    <bibl><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">Stanojčić, Živojin, and Ljubomir Popović. 2005. </hi><hi
                            rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Gramatika srpskoga jezika</hi><hi
                            style="font-size:10pt">. Belgrade: Zavod za udžbenike i nastavna
                            sredstva Beograd.</hi></bibl>
                    <bibl><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">Stoianov, Ivelin, John Nerbonne, and Huub Bouma. 1997. “Modelling the phonotactic structure of natural language words with Simple Recurrent Networks.” In </hi><hi
                            rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Computational Linguistics in the
                            Netherlands 1997: Selected Papers from the Eight Clin Meeting</hi><hi
                            style="font-size:10pt">, 77–95. Amsterdam: Rodopi.</hi></bibl>
                    <bibl><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">Subotić, Ljiljana, Dejan Sredojević, and Isidora Bjelaković. 2012. </hi>
                        <hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Fonetika i fonologija: Ortoepska i
                            ortografska norma standardnog srpskog jezika</hi><hi
                            style="font-size:10pt">. Novi Sad: Filozofski fakultet Univerziteta u
                            Novom Sadu.</hi></bibl>
                    <bibl><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">Utvić, Miloš. 2011. “Annotating the Corpus of Contemporary Serbian.” </hi><hi
                            rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt"
                        >INFOtheca</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve"> 12 (2): 36a–37a.</hi></bibl>
                    <bibl><hi style="font-size:10pt">Zec, Draga. 2000. “O strukturi sloga u srpskom
                            jeziku.”</hi>
                        <hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Južnoslovenski
                        filolog</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve"> 56 (1-2): 435–48.</hi></bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
            <div type="summary">
                <docAuthor>Aniko Kovač</docAuthor>
                <docAuthor>Maja Marković</docAuthor>
                <head><hi rend="allcaps">A mixed-principle rule-based approach to the automatic syllabification of Serbian</hi></head>
                <head><hi rend="allcaps">SUMMARY</hi></head>
                <p>
                    <hi style="font-size:10pt">In this paper we present a mixed-principle rule-based
                        approach to the automatic syllabification of Serbian based on prescriptive
                        rule descriptions from traditional grammar found in Stanojčić and Popović
                        (2005), extended by rule specifications from Kašić (2014) and Zec (2000),
                        and complemented by a sonority sequencing module based on Selkirk (1984),
                        Subotić et al. (2012), and Zec (2000).</hi></p>
                <p>
                    <hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">Syllable segmentation plays a role in speech technologies – most notably in the areas of speech recognition and text-to-speech synthesis – at both the segmental and prosodic levels. It is also one of the governing factors in hyphenation, and syllable frequency distribution data is used in psycholinguistic experiments as a covariate. The unavailability of segmented data for Serbian makes a rule-based approach to automatic syllabification the only viable option as there is no data available for training a data-driven neural network model, and the segmentation of large-scale language corpora by trained annotators would be a resource and cost heavy undertaking. </hi></p>
                <p>
                    <hi style="font-size:10pt">Our goal in this paper is threefold: i) we extend and
                        improve an earlier version of our syllabification algorithm by introducing a
                        sonority sequencing validation module which resolves a number of issues
                        present in the earlier version of our syllabifier, ii) we provide a detailed
                        analysis of the outcomes of the automatic syllabification process in order
                        to address possible theoretical considerations and serve as a basis for the
                        development of future syllabifiers, and iii) we present the statistical data
                        related to the distribution of syllables and their structure in Serbian to
                        be used in psycholinguistic experiments.</hi></p>
                <p>
                    <hi style="font-size:10pt">The implementation of the existing set of
                        prescriptive rules for the segmentation of words into syllables in Serbian
                        allowed us to gain an insight into problem areas of the rule descriptions,
                        and propose a number of revisions and amendments to the existing rules. The
                        sonority sequencing module revealed the need for an additional onset-length
                        limitation constraint, and pointed out the limitations of sonority in
                        ambiguous consonant clusters – such is the case with continuant fricative
                        phonemes that seem to be able to occupy either the first place in the onset
                        of a syllable or the last place in the coda of a previous syllable – that
                        would require further exploration and validation by native speaker
                        intuition.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi style="font-size:10pt">The data on the distribution of different syllable
                        structures and syllable nuclei following this approach will be useful for
                        comparison with the performance of alternative syllabification systems. In
                        the future, it would be interesting to see a systematic comparison of our
                        current approach to alternative approaches such as an onset-maximization
                        approach evaluated on segmentation data gathered from the native speakers of
                        Serbian.</hi></p>
            </div>
            <div type="summary" xml:lang="sl">
                <head><hi rend="allcaps">Mešani pristop k avtomatskemu zlogovanju v srbščini na podlagi načel in pravil</hi></head>
                <head><hi rend="allcaps">Povzetek</hi></head>
                <p>
                    <hi style="font-size:10pt">V tem prispevku predstavljamo mešani pristop k
                        avtomatskemu zlogovanju v srbščini na podlagi načel in pravil, ki temelji na
                        opisih predpisnih pravil tradicionalne slovnice (kot jih navajata Stanojčić
                        in Popović 2005), razširjenih z opredelitvami pravil (kot jih navajata Kašić
                        (2014) in Zec (2000)) in dopolnjenih z modulom za zaporedje glede na
                        zvočnost (na podlagi del avtorjev Selkirk 1984; Subotić et al. 2012; Zec
                        2000).</hi></p>
                <p><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">	Členitev na zloge ima pomembno vlogo v govornih tehnologijah – zlasti na področjih prepoznavanja govora in pretvorbe besedila v govor – na segmentalni in prozodični ravni. Je tudi eden od vodilnih dejavnikov pri deljenju besed. Podatki o frekvenčni porazdelitvi zlogov se uporabljajo v psiholingvističnih poskusih kot sočasna spremenljivka. Pristop k avtomatskemu zlogovanju, ki temelji na pravilih, je edina smiselna izbira, saj za srbščino ni na voljo segmentiranih podatkov, iz katerih bi se model nevronske mreže lahko učil. Projekt, pri katerem bi usposobljeni komentatorji razčlenjevali obsežne jezikovne korupse, pa bi bil zelo zahteven in drag. </hi></p>
                <p>
                    <hi style="font-size:10pt">Naš prispevek ima tri cilje: i) razširiti in
                        izboljšati predhodno različico našega algoritma za zlogovanje z vpeljavo
                        modula za potrjevanje zaporedja glede na zvočnost, ki odpravlja vrsto težav
                        iz predhodne različice našega zlogovalnika; ii) predstaviti podrobno analizo
                        rezultatov avtomatskega postopka zlogovanja, da bi spodbudili morebitne
                        teoretične razmisleke in zagotovili podlago za razvoj prihodnjih
                        zlogovalnikov; in iii) predstaviti statistične podatke, povezane s
                        porazdelitvijo in strukturo zlogov v srbščini, ki jih bo mogoče uporabiti
                        pri psiholingivstičnih poskusih.</hi>
                </p>
                <p><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">Uporaba uveljavljene zbirke predpisnih pravil za členitev besed na zloge v srbščini nam je omogočila, da smo dobili podroben vpogled v težavna področja pri opisih pravil in predlagali vrsto sprememb in popravkov uveljavljenih pravil. Modul za zaporedje glede na zvočnost je razkril potrebo po dodatni omejitvi dolžine vzglasja in izpostavil omejitve zvočnosti pri dvoumnih soglasniških sklopih (na primer priporniki, ki očitno lahko zavzemajo prvo mesto na začetku zloga ali zadnje mesto na koncu predhodnega zloga), ki bi jih bilo treba dodatno raziskati in potrditi s pomočjo intuicije rojenega govorca.   </hi></p>
                <p><hi style="font-size:10pt"> Podatke o porazdelitvi različnih zlogovnih struktur
                        in jeder, pridobljene s tem pristopom, bo mogoče uporabiti za primerjavo z
                        delovanjem drugih sistemov za zlogovanje. Zanimivo bi bilo opraviti
                        sistematično primerjavo našega pristopa z drugimi pristopi, na primer
                        pristopom maksimizacije vzglasja, ovrednotenim na podlagi podatkov o
                        členitvi, pridobljenih od rojenih govorcev srbščine.</hi></p>
            </div>
        </back>

    </text>
</TEI>
