<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Eastern Enlargement or an All-European Transformation?</title>
                <author>
                    <forename>Adéla</forename>
                    <surname>Gjuričová</surname>
                    <roleName>PhD</roleName>PhD., at the Institute of Contemporary History of the
                    Czech Academy of Sciences, gjuricova@usd.cas.cz <roleName>Senior
                        researcher</roleName>
                    <affiliation>Institut of Contemporary History of the Czech Academy of
                        Sciences</affiliation>
                    <email>gjuricova@usd.cas.cz</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <forename>Jure</forename>
                    <surname>Gašparič</surname>
                    <roleName>Dr.</roleName>
                    <roleName>višji znanstveni sodelavec</roleName>
                    <affiliation>Inštitut za novejšo zgodovino</affiliation>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Privoz 11</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>SI-1000 Ljubljana</addrLine>
                    </address>
                    <email>jure.gasparic@inz.si</email>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>2023-09-18</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>
                    <orgName xml:lang="sl">Inštitut za novejšo zgodovino</orgName>
                    <orgName xml:lang="en">Institute of Contemporary History</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Privoz 11</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>SI-1000 Ljubljana</addrLine>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>http://ojs.inz.si/pnz/article/view/4223</pubPlace>
                <date>2023</date>
                <availability status="free">
                    <licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title xml:lang="sl">Prispevki za novejšo zgodovino</title>
                <title xml:lang="en">Contributions to Contemporary History</title>
                <biblScope unit="volume">63</biblScope>
                <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
                <idno type="ISSN">2463-7807</idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source, born digital.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc xml:lang="en">
                <p>Contributions to Contemporary History is one of the central Slovenian scientific
                    historiographic journals, dedicated to publishing articles from the field of
                    contemporary history (the 19th and 20th century).</p>
                <p>The journal is published three times per year in Slovenian and in the following
                    foreign languages: English, German, Serbian, Croatian, Bosnian, Italian, Slovak
                    and Czech. The articles are all published with abstracts in English and
                    Slovenian as well as summaries in English.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <projectDesc xml:lang="sl">
                <p>Prispevki za novejšo zgodovino je ena osrednjih slovenskih znanstvenih
                    zgodovinopisnih revij, ki objavlja teme s področja novejše zgodovine (19. in 20.
                    stoletje).</p>
                <p>Revija izide trikrat letno v slovenskem jeziku in v naslednjih tujih jezikih:
                    angleščina, nemščina, srbščina, hrvaščina, bosanščina, italijanščina, slovaščina
                    in češčina. Članki izhajajo z izvlečki v angleščini in slovenščini ter povzetki
                    v angleščini.</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="sl"/>
                <language ident="en"/>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords xml:lang="en">
                    <term>European Union</term>
                    <term>Eastern Enlargement</term>
                    <term>European Transformation</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords xml:lang="sl">
                    <term>Evropska unija</term>
                    <term>Vzhodna širitev</term>
                    <term>vseevropska preobrazba</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change>
                    <date>2023-09-22T07:40:56Z</date>
                    <name>Mihael Ojsteršek</name>
                    <desc>Pretvorba iz DOCX v TEI, dodatno kodiranje</desc>
                </change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <docAuthor>Adéla Gjuričová</docAuthor>
            <docAuthor>Jure Gašparič</docAuthor>
        </front>
        <body>
            <head>Eastern Enlargement, or an All-European Transformation?</head>
            <p>The following special issue contains articles written by scholars from several
                Eastern and Western European countries. The editors hope to encourage a shift in the
                debate about the 1990s, a period that has certainly received enough academic and
                popular attention, at least in the former socialist countries. Still, it is our
                sincere belief that a substantial modification is needed in order to supplement the
                previous emphasis on the national social and economic policies with a broader
                transnational context.</p>
            <p>The first versions of most papers contained in this issue were presented at the
                workshop titled “Eastern Enlargement or an All-European Transformation? The 1990s in
                European Politics”, held in Ljubljana on 29 September 2022 and organised by the
                Institutes of Contemporary History in Ljubljana and at the Czech Academy of Science
                in Prague. The purpose of the event was to continue the organisers’ successful
                cooperation with other specialists within the EuParl.net network, which has produced
                a number of fascinating comparative projects exploring the European parliamentary
                history, cultures, and institutions.</p>
            <p>We realised that our view of the post-1989 decade while observing the differences
                between the Slovenian and Czech(oslovak) institutional, economic, and social
                transformations tended to be restricted to the former political East. Now we sought
                to employ a broader European perspective. Following the former communist countries’
                accession to the European Union seemed like an obvious next thing to do. Many
                governments applied to join the European Union during the period under
                consideration, and their domestic elites began to relate intensively to the actors,
                processes, and requirements for membership. Simultaneously, however, Western Europe
                was equally transformed by the implementation of the Maastricht Treaty, and stronger
                and longer-lasting groups critical of the European integration process emerged in
                many countries. The present special issue thus represents the first attempt to
                explore the overlapping two contexts, bring the previously exclusive perspectives
                together, and rethink the forms and concepts of the Europeanisation of national
                policies.</p>
            <p>It is a great honour to have Mark Gilbert, the author of <hi rend="italic">European
                    Integration: The Political History</hi> and co-editor of <hi rend="italic"
                    >Euroscepticisms: The Historical Roots of a Political Challenge</hi>,<note
                    place="foot" xml:id="ftn1" n="1">Mark Gilbert, <hi
                            rend="italic">European Integration: A Political History</hi> (Rowman
                        &amp; Littlefield, 2020, 2<hi rend="superscript">nd</hi> edition). <hi
                            rend="italic">Euroscepticisms: The Historical Roots of a Political
                            Challenge</hi>, eds. Mark Gilbert and Daniele Pasquinucci (Leiden and
                        Boston: Brill, 2020).</note> join the debate. He has brought a striking
                analytical distance, experience, and, indeed, humour to this issue by comparing the
                British and Italian perceptions of the Maastricht Treaty in the opening article
                aptly titled “From the EC to the EU. Ready or Not”.</p>
            <p>Jure Gašparič and Andrej Pančur open the empirical section by addressing the politics
                of the accession – and the origins of Slovenian Euroscepticism – with a
                reconstruction of the EU-related vocabulary and sentiments in the Slovenian
                Parliament, using the methods of corpus analysis. Meanwhile, Adéla Gjuričová devoted
                her contribution to the Czech election campaign of 2002 and the stage of completing
                the negotiations with the EU, demonstrating the paradox of “Europeanising the
                national debate while ‘bilateralising’ the European politics.”</p>
            <p>The special issue at hand also presents several case studies exploring unexpected
                actors and connections in building up the image of Europe both in and outside the
                Union. Marko Zajc has collected fascinating materials from the mid-1990s <hi
                    rend="italic">Nova revija</hi> circle and focused on the text titled “The Hour
                of European Truth for Slovenia” to decipher the complicated intellectual position on
                Slovenian integration with the EU. Ivan Sablin studied the presence of the EU in the
                Russian State Duma debates, concluding that the Duma became an important stage for
                collecting anti-European sentiments vis-à-vis the government’s pro-European rhetoric
                at the time. Finally, Sven Jüngerkes and Tobias Kaiser presented their current
                project on the development of the German party system during the 1990s, encompassing
                the crucial issue of integrating the two Germanies’ political scenes and traditions.</p>
            <p>In recent years, the European Union faced significant challenges. Once again, both
                its reform and its enlargement appear on the agenda. We hope this issue brings
                forward some ideas for a historical reflection that provides the necessary distance
                from daily responsibilities and pressures. Understanding political actors and
                national and international institutions remains one of the crucial manners of
                grasping the development, its risks, and its potential. Besides, it is always wise
                to examine longer continuities and be aware of the history – and historical
                connotations – of the supposedly brand-new phenomena.</p>
            <byline><hi rend="italic">Adéla Gjuričová and Jure Gašparič</hi></byline>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
