<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Journal <hi rend="italic">Istarski Borac/IBOR</hi> in the Context of the Culture of Dissent</title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename>Lidija</forename>
                        <surname>Bencetić</surname>
                    </name>
                    <roleName>Research Fellow</roleName>
                    <roleName>PhD</roleName>
                    <affiliation>Croatian Institute of History</affiliation>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Opatička 10</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>10000–Zagreb</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>Croatia</addrLine>
                    </address>
                    <email>lidija.bencetic@gmail.com</email>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>2018-09-20</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>
                    <orgName xml:lang="sl">Inštitut za novejšo zgodovino</orgName>
                    <orgName xml:lang="en">Institute of Contemporary History</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Kongresni trg 1</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>SI-1000 Ljubljana</addrLine>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>http://ojs.inz.si/pnz/article/view/293</pubPlace>
                <date>2018</date>
                <availability status="free">
                    <licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title xml:lang="sl">Prispevki za novejšo zgodovino</title>
                <title xml:lang="en">Contributions to Contemporary History</title>
                <biblScope unit="volume">58</biblScope>
                <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
                <idno type="ISSN">2463-7807</idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source, born digital.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc xml:lang="en">
                <p>Contributions to Contemporary History is one of the central Slovenian scientific
                    historiographic journals, dedicated to publishing articles from the field of
                    contemporary history (the 19th and 20th century).</p>
                <p>The journal is published three times per year in Slovenian and in the following
                    foreign languages: English, German, Serbian, Croatian, Bosnian, Italian, Slovak
                    and Czech. The articles are all published with abstracts in English and
                    Slovenian as well as summaries in English.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <projectDesc xml:lang="sl">
                <p>Prispevki za novejšo zgodovino je ena osrednjih slovenskih znanstvenih
                    zgodovinopisnih revij, ki objavlja teme s področja novejše zgodovine (19. in 20.
                    stoletje).</p>
                <p>Revija izide trikrat letno v slovenskem jeziku in v naslednjih tujih jezikih:
                    angleščina, nemščina, srbščina, hrvaščina, bosanščina, italijanščina, slovaščina
                    in češčina. Članki izhajajo z izvlečki v angleščini in slovenščini ter povzetki
                    v angleščini.</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="sl"/>
                <language ident="en"/>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords xml:lang="en">
                    <term>Istarski borac</term>
                    <term>IBOR</term>
                    <term>culture of dissent</term>
                    <term>youth press</term>
                    <term>Yugoslavia</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords xml:lang="sl">
                    <term>Istarski borac</term>
                    <term>IBOR</term>
                    <term>kultura disidentstva</term>
                    <term>mladinski tisk</term>
                    <term>Jugoslavija</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change>
                    <date>2017-12-25</date>
                    <name>Neja Blaj Hribar</name>
                    <desc>Pretvorba iz DOCX v TEI, dodatno kodiranje</desc>
                </change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <docAuthor>Lidija Bencetić<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn1" n="*">
                <hi rend="bold">Research Fellow, PhD, Croatian Institute of History,
                    Opatička 10, 10000–Zagreb, Croatia,</hi>
                <ref target="mailto:lidija.bencetic@gmail.com"><hi rend="bold">lidija.bencetic@gmail.com</hi></ref></note></docAuthor>
            <docImprint>
                <idno type="cobissType">Cobiss type: 1.01</idno>
                <idno type="UDC">UDC: 070.18:329.052 (497.5)"1945/1990"</idno>
            </docImprint>
            <div type="abstract" xml:lang="sl"><head>IZVLEČEK</head>
                <head>ČASOPIS <hi rend="italic">ISTARSKI BORAC/IBOR</hi> V KONTEKSTU KULTURE DISIDENTSTVA</head>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Prvi hrvaški mladinski časopis Istarski borac/IBOR je z dvema
                        krajšima vmesnima premoroma izhajal med leti 1953 in 1979 v Pulju. Časopis je
                        izdajal Književni klub Istarski borac, in sicer z namenom ohranjanja hrvaškega
                        jezika v Istri kot temeljnim vodilom. V sedemdesetih letih 20. stoletja je
                        časopis prevzel značaj kritičnega medija in postopoma uvajal vse več kulturnih,
                        lokalnih in družbenih tem, katerih ton pa socialistična oblast ni dobro
                        sprejela. Jeseni 1979 je izbruhnil »primer IBOR«. Časopisu so istega leta
                        ukinili financiranje, zaradi česar je prenehal izhajati. Povod za ukinitev
                        časopisa je bila sicer pesem z naslovom Please, master (hrv.: Molim te,
                        učitelju) Allena Ginsberga, toda partijski dokumenti razkrivajo, da je bil
                        razlog političen. Pričujoča razprava poskuša odgovoriti na vprašanje, ali je
                        delovanje zadnjega uredništva časopisa Istarski borac/IBOR mogoče obravnavati
                        kot kulturo disidentstva.</hi></p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Ključne besede: Istarski borac, IBOR, kultura disidentstva, mladinski
                    tisk, Jugoslavija</hi></p></div>
            <div type="abstract">
                <head>ABSTRACT</head>
                <p><hi rend="italic">The first Croatian youth journal Istarski borac/IBOR was published
                    in Pula from 1953 to 1979 (with two minor interruptions). The journal was
                    published by the Istarski Borac Literary Club with the objective of preserving
                    the Croatian language in Istria. The journal developed a reputation as a
                    critical media in the 1970s, covering more and more cultural, local and social
                    themes whose tone was not well – received by the socialist authorities, so the
                    financing of the journal was cancelled in 1979 after which it ceased
                    publication. The reason for the suspension of the journal was the poem “Please
                    Master” by Allen Ginsberg, but the party documents reveal that the motive was
                    also political. The question this article is trying to answer is whether the
                    work of the last editorial board of Istarski borac/IBOR can be considered a
                    culture of dissent.</hi></p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Keywords: Istarski borac, IBOR, culture of dissent, youth press,
                    Yugoslavia</hi></p>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div><head>Introduction</head>
            <p>The youth journal of Pula Gymnasium students, <hi rend="italic">Istarski borac</hi>
                was launched in Pula on October 15, 1953. The first issue of <hi rend="italic">Istarski borac</hi> was released at the initiative of the literary section of
                the Branko Semelić Gymnasium and their mentor Ljubica Ivezić, with the subtitle
                Literary Section Gazette of the Branko Semelić Gymnasium. As of the second issue,
                the journal was called the “Istrian Youth Journal” and was financed by the National
                Youth District Committee, and this status was likely obtained through the party
                line. According to Ljubica Ivezić, the editorial section was reserved for
                ideological and political articles.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn2" n="1"> Ljubica Ivezić, “I jedna važna obljetnica između na
                        koju ne treba zaboraviti,” <hi rend="italic">Dometi</hi> (Rijeka), No. 5–6
                        (1992): 95–100. </note></p>
            <p>It was the first youth journal in Yugoslavia, which was published continually, with
                two interruptions (from 1964 to 1969 and from 1974 to 1976) until September 1979,
                i.e. until the “IBOR Case” arose. <hi rend="italic">Istarski borac</hi> is important
                to the development of the Croatian language, literature and culture in Istria,
                especially in terms of the development of young writers and intellectuals who later
                became important to the development of culture, history and socio–political life in
                Istria. Ljubica Ivezić, the initiator of <hi rend="italic">Istarski borac</hi>,
                explained it this way: the students “took on the task of using their literary and
                cultural work in the first place to fight for the affirmation of their domestic <hi rend="italic">word</hi>, which was severely persecuted under the Italian
                    fascism”.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn3" n="2"> Ibid.,
                        97. </note> In the introduction to the first issue of <hi rend="italic">Istarski borac</hi>, the editorial board explained the reasons for launching
                the journal: “The authors of original works will find their topics firstly in their
                personal lives, then in Istrian and Yugoslav socialistic reality. With this kind of
                work, we will foster a love for the mother tongue, for our socialist country and our
                people. We will constantly prove to each and every one that the youngest Istrian
                generations do not want to substitute their beloved native tongue with a foreign
                one, nor their national government for dominion by foreigners ever again”.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn4" n="3">
                        <hi rend="italic">Istarski borac</hi> (Pula), No. 1 (1953): 1. </note>
                The journal was intended for young people from elementary school to university
                students and mostly financed by the Self–management Interest Community (SIC,
                croatian: Samoupravna interesna zajednica – SIZ) for the culture of the Municipality
                of Pula. The funding of the journal was increased between 1973 and 1979, amounting
                from 20,000 dinars in 1973 to 50,000 in 1978 and 74,000 in 1979.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn5" n="4"> HR HDA 1220, Savez komunista
                        Hrvatske. Centralni komitet (further: HR HDA 1220, SKH. CK), No. D-11334,
                        “Analiza glasila mladih Istre ‘IBOR’”, 20 November 1979, 2, 3.
                </note></p>
            <p>However, as time passed, the circumstances, policies and generations changed and the
                editorial approach of <hi rend="italic">Istarski borac</hi> also changed, and it no
                longer sided with the Party. A different attitude toward the journal was first
                reflected in critiques of their work presented at the Party’s meetings as well as
                publicly, and later in the termination of their funding, which was the end of the
                journal. According to a member of the last editorial board, Boris Domagoj Biletić:
                    “<hi rend="italic">Istarski borac</hi> was the only truly democratic light of
                the written word not only by young people in Istria and beyond, sometimes formally
                but most often never under the control of any political institution, from the
                beginning of the 1950s until democratic changes in 1990”.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn6" n="5">
                        <hi rend="italic">Istarski borac</hi>,
                            <hi rend="color(212121)" xml:space="preserve">accessed December 18, 2018, </hi><hi rend="italic">Metelgrad - Digitalizirani časopisi</hi>, <ref target="http://library.foi.hr/m3/kds1.php?B=1&amp;sqlx=S02008&amp;ser=&amp;sqlid=1&amp;sqlnivo=&amp;css=&amp;H=pula&amp;U=05">http://library.foi.hr/m3/kds1.php?B=1&amp;sqlx=S02008&amp;ser=&amp;sqlid=1&amp;sqlnivo=&amp;css=&amp;H=pula&amp;U=05</ref>.
                    </note>
            </p>
            <p>Did <hi rend="italic">Istarski borac/IBOR</hi> really oppose the dogmas imposed by
                the Party and the self–managing socialist system that it was supposed to promote in
                its publications? Or was it about the generational gap and conservative social
                environment in which the journal was being published and where there was no place
                for poems like “Please Master”? Maybe it was a combination of one and the other,
                together with non-fulfillment of obligations by the editorial board that published
                only a half of the planned issues for 1978 and 1979?</p></div>
            <div><head>The Youth Press in the 1970s and 1980s</head>
            <p>The Yugoslav authorities used the youth press as a tool of youth organizations -
                Socialist Youth of Croatia (SYC, Croatian: Socijalistička omladina Hrvatske – SOH)
                and later the Alliance of Socialist Youth of Croatia (ASYC, Croatian: Savez
                socijalističke omladine Hrvatske – SSOH) to indoctrinate, educate and direct the
                activities of young people according to the guidelines of the League of Communists
                of Croatia (LCC, Croatian: Saveza komunista Hrvatske – SKH).<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn7" n="6"> Marko Zubak, <hi rend="italic">The
                            Yugoslav Youth Press: (1968–1980): student movements, youth subcultures
                            and Communist alternative media</hi> (Zagreb: Srednja Europa; Hrvatski
                        institut za povijest, 2018), 307.</note> However, with its engagement
                and the introduction of numerous novelties (design, popular culture from the West,
                analysis of neglected social themes) the youth press established itself among young
                people inclined toward the LCC/SKH, but also among a wider reading audience,
                becoming some sort of a brand. Youth journals were funded either from the funds of
                the Republic Self-management Interest Community for Culture (RSIC, Croatian:
                Republička samoupravna interesna zajednica kulture - RSIZ) and its local affiliates
                or through the ASYC/SSOH.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn8" n="7"> See: HR HDA 1231, Republička konferencija Saveza
                        socijalističke omladine Hrvatske (HR HDA 1231, RK SSOH) and HR HDA 1605,
                        Republička samoupravna interesna zajednica kulture (HR HDA 1605 RSIZ).
                    </note> The book <hi rend="italic">The Yugoslav Youth Press</hi> by author
                Marko Zubak should be consulted for a detailed description of the phenomenon of
                Yugoslav youth press.</p>
            <p>The youth press in Croatia went through sort of a crisis, primarily a financial one,
                but also a personnel crisis, in the 1970s. None of the youth journals were
                profitable, but they were financed from the republic or local budget because the
                political significance of their publication was greater than the financial one.
                Personnel problems are partly related to the inadequate number of highly educated
                young journalists, the “personnel void” created after the Croatian Spring in 1971
                and the dismissal of a large number of journalists, as well as their inadequate
                ideological background.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn9" n="8"> Željko Krušelj, <hi rend="italic">Igraonica za
                            odrasle: Polet 1976.–1990.</hi> (Rijeka: Adamić, 2015), 37.</note>
                Omladinski tjednik, the only Croatian journal with a broader republic and federal
                media reach, stopped coming out in 1976.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn10" n="9"> Ibid., 27. </note> Several local youth journals -
                    <hi rend="italic">Laus, Val</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Riječ mladih</hi> - were
                coming out in Croatia at the time, and Pula’s youth journal was launched again in
                1976 under the new name <hi rend="italic">IBOR</hi>. In the same year, <hi rend="italic">Omladinski tjednik</hi>, a journal whose launch has long been
                invoked by youth leaders from RC of ASYC/RK SSOH and the more prominent media (<hi rend="italic">Komunist</hi>), replaced <hi rend="italic">Polet</hi> as the
                republic youth journal.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn11" n="10"> Ibid., 30, 31. </note></p>
            <p>The Information Committee of the Republic Conference of the Alliance of Socialist
                Youth of Croatia (RC ASYC/RK SSOH) held a meeting on May 29, 1980. The topic of the
                meeting was “current problems of the youth press” and the writings of <hi rend="italic">Studentski list</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Omladinska iskra</hi> and
                    <hi rend="italic">Polet</hi> were discussed. An analysis of the situation in the
                youth newspapers was prepared for the meeting, from which the expectations of the
                government and the relationship towards the youth press can be seen.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn12" n="11"> HR HDA 1231, RK
                        SSOH, box. 586, “Aktualni problemi omladinske štampe,” May 27,
                    1980.</note> Their opinion is that “a lot of effort needs to be made to
                ensure that the youth press is truly an integral element of socio-political
                activities and in the role of the Alliance of Socialist Youth”.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn13" n="12"> Ibid., 1. </note> At the same
                time, the role and tasks of the youth press should be judged “precisely from the
                standpoint of putting them into the function of accomplishing the complex tasks of
                the Alliance of Socialist Youth of Croatia in social transformation and development
                of socialist self-management”.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn14" n="13"> Ibid., 2. </note> Furthermore, the ASYC/SSOH is of
                the opinion that youth newspapers in the self-managing society should work together
                with the ASYC/SSOH, and that the youth press serves not only to provide information,
                but must also work actively in the youth organization and the society as a whole.
                The ASYC/SSOH thought that in the youth newspapers there are visible deviations
                going to two extremes: “The youth newspapers informs about the actions of the
                Alliance of Socialist Youth of Croatia in a dull, non-communicative and to youth
                unattractive newsletter style, and other, far more often is that youth newspapers
                ‘forget’ their founder, their social role, responsibility and tasks, and turn not to
                the ASYC/SSOH, as a socio-political organization of youth, but simply to young
                people, forgetting that as the ASYC/SSOH journal they should be, not only
                generationally, but necessarily ideologically committed, therefore in the function
                of interests and activities of youth that is socialist-oriented”.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn15" n="14"> HR HDA1231, RK SSOH, box. 586,
                        “Aktualni problemi omladinske štampe,” May 27, 1980, 2. </note></p>
            <p>The aforementioned document about the state of the youth press in 1980 highlights
                that the overall information system is designed to activate and involve “working
                people” and youth in self-managing processes, in order to “objectively inform” the
                youth about the issues of “social life, work and creativity (...) and in the
                function of achieving the social tasks of the Alliance of Socialist Youth”. It is
                stated that the youth press has a great educational function in “explaining the
                essence and contradictions in our development, which clearly makes it an active
                element of the ideological struggle against provincialism (philistinism),
                bureaucratism, technocracy, nationalism, dogmatism, and other anti-socialist and
                anti-self-managing tendencies”.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn16" n="15"> Ibid., 3. </note> It is further stated that the
                youth press is largely focused on the “marginal problems of the society as a whole”,
                that it often problematizes the “marginal social groups and phenomena” and thus
                poses a certain “danger in the conceptual sense, not because these phenomena are not
                worth writing about but because in regards to the real problems, questions, and
                dilemmas concerning further development of society, these marginal problems are
                being overemphasized”, thus opening the possibility for the “manipulating
                anti-self-managing and anti-socialistic forces to misuse it”.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn17" n="16"> Ibid., 4, 5.</note> It was
                also mentioned that the youth newspapers should distinguish themselves by “engaging
                and affirming in the revolution”, but how such youth attitude was known to become “a
                dogma, turn into criticism, leftism, result in incidents, prohibitions, and wrongly
                highlighted social issues”.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn18" n="17"> Ibid., 3.</note></p>
            <p>The same document also states that the FR of Croatia had nine youth newspapers in the
                late 1970s: <hi rend="italic">Polet, Studentski list, Val, Laus, Pet, Omladinska
                    iskra, Lok, Ibor</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Omladinac</hi>, all of them having
                in common unresolved material, personnel and spatial requirements.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn19" n="18"> Ibid., 7. </note></p></div>
           <div> <head>Istarski Borac Literary Club and Journal <hi rend="italic">Istarski borac</hi>
                / <hi rend="italic bold">IBOR</hi></head>
            <p>The Istarski borac Literary Club was the literary section of Pula’s high school
                students, established in 1953. At its beginnings, the club was called the Literary
                Section of the Branko Semelić Gymnasium, and after its first issue in 1977 it was
                renamed the Istarski borac Literary Club. The year of the club’s establishment was
                also the year when the journal of the same name was launched. Ljubica Ivezić was the
                mentor of the club during its entire existence, and also its founder. According to
                the editorial board of the first issue, the purpose of forming the club and
                launching the journal was to preserve the Croatian language and Croatian heritage in
                Istria and foster the development and affirmation of Istrian writers and
                intellectuals, cultural workers, journalists, scholars and politicians.</p>
            <p>The activities of the Istarski borac Club are best known from the <hi rend="italic">Istarski borac</hi>. The journal was published from 1953 to 1979, with two
                interruptions (1964 to 1969 and from 1974 to 1976) and it changed its name several
                times: 1953 to 1961 it was called <hi rend="italic">Istarski borac</hi>, from 1961
                to 1964, <hi rend="italic">Glas mladih</hi>, from 1969 to 1974, <hi rend="italic">Istarski borac</hi>, and from 1976 to 1979, <hi rend="italic">IBOR</hi>.</p>
            <p>In the twenty-six years of its existence, the literary club had produced numerous
                intellectuals and artists who left a great mark in the cultural history of Istria
                and Croatia and it achieved its basic objective: preserving the Croatian language.
                According to the Marija Petener-Lorenzin, author of the bibliography of <hi rend="italic">Istarski borac</hi>/<hi rend="italic">IBOR</hi>, this periodical
                “left a mark in the recent cultural history of Istria and journalistic production in
                this area,” so that the compilation of its bibliography became a necessity.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn20" n="19"> Marija
                        Petener–Lorenzin, <hi rend="italic">Bibliografija časopisa “Istarski borac”
                            – “Ibor”: (1953.–1979.)</hi> (Pula: Istarski ogranak Društva hrvatskih
                        književnika, 2006), 5.</note>
            </p></div>
            <div><head>“IBOR Case”</head>
            <p>There was a debate going on among the government bodies of ASYC/SSOH and RSIC/RSIZ
                about the cessation of its funding even before <hi rend="italic">Istarski
                    borac/IBOR</hi> became the “IBOR Case”. The stated reasons for termination of
                funding were failure to fulfill the taken obligations, primarily half as many
                published issues as planned in the years 1978 and 1979, and not submitting annual
                work reports. After the “IBOR Case” became public, and after making a detailed
                analysis of the journal’s writing (see the succeeding text), objections were
                directed toward the journal’s wrong approach when writing about social issues and an
                “ideological orientation that is foreign to our self-managing socialist
                    society”.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn21" n="20"> HR
                        HDA 1220 SKH. CK, No. D-11334, “Analiza glasila mladih Istre ‘IBOR,’”
                        November 20, 1979, 2. </note></p>
            <p>Dolores Petrinić thinks that <hi rend="italic">Istarski borac</hi> was started “with
                the mission of spreading literacy and a positive attitude toward the Croatian
                language and literature”.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn22" n="21"> Dolores Petrinić, <hi rend="italic">Hrvatska
                            književnost u istarskim časopisima druge polovice XX. st</hi>. (Rijeka:
                        Društvo hrvatskih književnika, 2007), 9. </note> And since it published
                texts that “reflected the current cultural and social issues in a reasoned and
                engaging way” and how the <hi rend="italic">IBOR</hi> had a tendency of growing into
                a journal “that would seriously and critically address not only literature but also
                culture and society in general.” Petrinić believes that escaping political control
                led to the termination of the journal.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn23" n="22"> Ibid., 11. </note> The crucial moment was the
                publication of a translation of the English-language poem with
                paedophiliac/homosexual content, “Please Master,” by Allen Ginsberg, published under
                the issue’s theme “Total Institutions.” The Istrian editions of the daily newspaper
                    <hi rend="italic">Večernji list</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Glas Istre</hi>
                repeatedly wrote about the “IBOR Case,” and the youth journals in Zagreb also became
                interested. After several months of Party and media debate, funding for the journal
                was cancelled, and as the result of a private lawsuit by journalist Armand Černjul,
                the editorial board was convicted for defamation on October 8, 1980.</p>
            <p>Boris Domagoj Biletić was a member of the last editorial board of <hi rend="italic">IBOR</hi>, and one of the people conditionally sentenced to one month and
                fifteen days in prison for defamation of the journalist Armand Černjul. As Biletić
                testified, the formal reason for the verdict was “quasi-naive: translation of the
                poem ‘Please Master’ by Allen Ginsberg (who wrote a dedication to the last editorial
                board a few years later). But the real reasons were, in fact, that in some youthful
                texts (...) we had dared to question them (the Party!), and we were additionally
                interested in anti-psychiatry, in the almost poetically pure student year of 1968 in
                Europe and here, i.e. student protests, the Croatian Spring, Jim Morrison, anarchism
                (...) Can you imagine, at that time, some young people in some place called Pula
                wrote, published, and were the leaders of the whole generation, and not under the
                umbrella of the so-called socialist youth?!”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn24" n="23">
                        <hi rend="italic">Matica hrvatska</hi> [Matrix Croatica], <ref target="http://www.matica.hr/kolo/408/nacionalno-i-univerzalno-u-obzorima-zavicajnosti-23142/">http://www.matica.hr/kolo/408/nacionalno-i-univerzalno-u-obzorima-zavicajnosti-23142/</ref>.</note></p></div>
            <div><head>IBOR’s Last Issue and Poem “Please
                    Master”</head>
            <p>The last issue of <hi rend="italic">IBOR</hi> dealing with the topic of total
                institutions or comprehensive institutions, with special emphasis on psychiatric
                institutions, came out in September 1979. Using the deductive approach, starting
                with the profiling of totalitarian institutions, focusing on psychiatric
                institutions and their patients, the editorial draws conclusions, referring to
                eminent historical personalities from the fields of philosophy, historiography and
                culture, that an artist can only be a person who is either on the border of madness
                or has already passed that boundary. This is backed up by a series of texts and
                poems, the most provocative among them being “Please Master” by American poet Allen
                Ginsberg. The poem deals about a paedophiliac-homosexual relationship between a
                pupil and a teacher and is accompanied by a photo of a child named after the
                poem.</p>
            <p>The poem aroused great controversy in Pula’s Party and youth circles, and in
                republic, local and youth publications, and it was the formal reason for abolishing
                the journal’s funding. Speaking of topics that were considered undesirable in
                conservative Pula, but also about the social circumstances in Yugoslavia that
                bothered the state-party leadership, the <hi rend="italic">IBOR</hi> editorial
                board’s notable cultural-opposition activity was what ultimately led to the
                cessation of its funding.</p></div>
            <div><head>Governmental Attitude Toward “IBOR Case”</head>
            <p>The relation of socialist authorities toward the <hi rend="italic">IBOR</hi> journal
                and the “IBOR Case” can be seen from the documentation of the Alliance of Socialist
                Youth of Croatia (ASYC/SSOH), the Central Committee of the League of Communists of
                Croatia (CC LCC/SKH CK) and the Republic Self- Management Interest Community for
                Culture (RSIC/RSIZ).</p>
            <p>The work and funding of youth and other journals were followed by the RSIC/RSIZ
                Commission for Journals and Newspapers in Culture. In its report from February 1979,
                it mentioned <hi rend="italic">IBOR</hi> and journal <hi rend="italic">Vrabac</hi>,
                clearly stating that: “Following the work of these journals through 1978, the
                Commission concluded that contributions do not exceed the level of quality of the
                first attempts and therefore do not meet the criteria. The source of funding should
                certainly be the municipal SIC/SIZ for culture.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn25" n="24"> HR HDA 1605, RSIZ, box 4, 57. Session IO
                        (26.3.1979.), “Prijedlog programa časopisa za 1979. godinu,” February 1979,
                        10. </note> Two months later <hi rend="italic">IBOR</hi> was again
                mentioned in the report of the same commission because it did not submit the report
                and was therefore denied payment of the remaining funds for 1978: “The Commission
                proposes that the journals which did not carry out the obligation of submitting the
                report even after the repeated warning be denied payment of the remaining funds.
                This refers to journals: <hi rend="italic">Čakavska rič, Dubrovnik, Haiku, Ibor,
                    Polet</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Vidik</hi>.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn26" n="25"> HR HDA 1605, RSIZ, box 4, 58. Session IO
                        (13.4.1979.), “Prijedlog za isplatu preostalih sredstava iz 1978. godine,”
                        April 1979, 2. </note></p>
            <p>Certainly the most important document pertaining to the “IBOR Case” is the “Analysis
                of Istria’s Youth Journal “IBOR’”. The document, signed under the name “Workgroup”
                and dated Pula, November 20, 1979, was created for the 37<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> session of the Municipal Conference Committee of the LCC/SKH Pula held
                on November 27, 1979. The main topic of the meeting was the journal <hi rend="italic">IBOR</hi>. It is a seven-page document that analyzes <hi rend="italic">IBOR</hi>’s work from 1973 to the latest issue 4-5 in 1979. The
                analysis focuses primarily on the editorial and associate staff of the journal,
                which, following the conclusions of the analysis is not up to the task, and does not
                give enough space to young authors instead forcing the affirmed authors. At the same
                time, <hi rend="italic">IBOR</hi> was publishing primarily the works of the members
                of the Istarski Borac Literary Club, and very rarely the works of “young authors
                from the wider area of Istria”. <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn27" n="26"> HR HDA 1220, SKH. CK, No. D-11334, “Analiza glasila
                        mladih Istre ‘IBOR’”, November 20, 1979, 1. </note> It is seen from the
                document that the editorial board has been previously warned to give more space to
                the non-established authors. <hi rend="italic">IBOR</hi>’s unfulfilled obligations
                were also pointed out, as fewer issues than planned were published annually. For
                example, eight issues were planned for the year 1978 and only three (1, 2-3 and 4-5)
                were realized. Another eight issues were planned for the next year (1979), five were
                officially published, while only two double issues (1-3, 4-5) were actually
                published. The topics that the journal dealt with were also problematic, they were
                not satisfactory because they “exclusively dealt with the issues from the area of
                the Pula commune”.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn28" n="27">
                        Ibid., 1.</note></p>
            <p>From the document we find out that the Istarski Borac Literary Club had 50 members
                (20 high school students, 15 university students and 15 employees) in the final year
                of its publishing (1979), and was conceptually oriented toward three areas -
                culture, literary creativity and social issues.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn29" n="28"> Ibid. </note> The journal was criticized for
                not writing enough about young people “about young man’s role and place in our
                self-managing society, his problems and aspirations beyond the rock music and sports
                like problems of young people’s employment, student self-management, deviations in
                young people’s behavior”.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn30" n="29"> Ibid., 2.</note> It was also pointed out that in
                most cases <hi rend="italic">IBOR’s</hi> writing was destructive, and the reason for
                this was that for some authors “this approach and a way of writing about our social
                reality reflects their ideological orientation which is foreign to our self-managing
                socialist society”.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn31" n="30">
                        HR HDA 1220, SKH. CK, D-11334, “Analiza glasila mladih Istre ‘IBOR,’”
                        November 20, 1979, 2. </note></p>
            <p>The Executive Board of the SIC/SIZ discussed the <hi rend="italic">IBOR</hi> at its
                session on October 6, 1978, with a special emphasis on the “socio-political
                orientation and literary value of the journal”. It was then concluded: that the
                approved conception of the journal was not achieved; that the program orientation of
                the journal was to be taken over by the DC ASYC/OK SSOH Pula; that the journal
                should be made more “social” by applying the delegate principle, and that the funds
                are to be suspended until this condition are fulfilled.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn32" n="31"> Ibid., 4. </note> Soon the DC
                ASYC/OK SSOH Pula held another session which concluded that the financing of <hi rend="italic">IBOR</hi> should be continued until a joint youth journal for
                whole Istria is launched and that one representative from the DC ASYC/OK SSOH Pula
                and the SIC/SIZ for Culture Pula should enter the editorial board of <hi rend="italic">IBOR</hi>.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn33" n="32"> Ibid. </note> Aliče Davosyr as a representative of
                the SIC/SIZ and Ljubo Marčeta on behalf of the DC ASYC/OK SSOH entered the editorial
                board. As the plan for the first half of 1979 was not realized, the Republic SIC/SIZ
                suspended the financing of <hi rend="italic">IBOR</hi>.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn34" n="33"> Ibid., 5. </note> The
                Istarski Borac Literary Club proposed that the journal should also be funded in
                1980, but the Republic SIC/SIZ rejected it again. The SIC/SIZ thought that the <hi rend="italic">IBOR</hi> “is not oriented toward socially acceptable movements
                and that it must contain socially acceptable content”. The analysis concluded that
                financing of <hi rend="italic">IBOR</hi> should be continued but at the local
                    level.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn35" n="34"> Ibid.,
                        6, 7. </note> However, <hi rend="italic">IBOR’s</hi> funding was
                nevertheless suspended. It is not possible to determine from the archives why
                weren't the recommendations of the working group that made the analysis acted upon.
                The record of the session held on November 27, 1979, on which <hi rend="italic">IBOR</hi> was discussed, does not exist. In the Croatian State Archives in
                Zagreb and in the State Archives in Pazin there is only a call to the session and
                the document “Analysis of Istria’s Youth Journal ‘IBOR’” but not the record of the
                session itself.</p>
            <p>In the entire document, only one sentence mentions the last issue of <hi rend="italic">IBOR</hi> (4–5/1979) because of which the entire “IBOR Case” was
                initiated. The sentence reads: “Meanwhile, the latest double issue 4–5/79 came out
                containing a lot of inappropriate articles especially for the age group journal is
                intended for i.e. young people”.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn36" n="35"> Ibid., 6. </note> Such disregard for the content
                of the last issue gives the impression that the poem “Please Master” may not be a
                reason <hi rend="italic">IBOR</hi>’s funding got canceled. Even more so because the
                emphasis of the key analysis was on non-fulfilling the obligations, the absence of
                young non-established authors and the ideological turn of the editorial board which
                is reflected in improper writing about the Yugoslav self-managing socialist
                society.</p></div>
            <div><head>Media and “IBOR Case”</head>
            <p>The “IBOR Case” had, in addition to great interest of the government, also caused
                great interest of regional media and youth journals. As mentioned earlier – it was
                mostly written about in <hi rend="italic">Glas Istre</hi> and the Istrian edition of
                    <hi rend="italic">Večernji list</hi>, as well as the republican youth journals
                    <hi rend="italic">Polet</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Pitanja</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Studentski List</hi>. The republic newspaper <hi rend="italic">Vjesnik – Sedam dana</hi> devoted a series of seven articles to the “IBOR Case”
                in which the case was analyzed in detail. The articles published in <hi rend="italic">Glas Istre</hi> are of a more informative character and primarily
                present the conclusions of the DC LCC/OK SKH Pula and the DC ASYC/OK SSOH. The
                articles in the Istrian edition of <hi rend="italic">Vecernji list</hi> are signed
                by Armando Černjul, and are partly characterized by the informative approach and
                partly by the author’s engagement and his unreserved condemnation of the <hi rend="italic">IBOR’s</hi> editorial board for the poem “Please Master”. Youth
                journals make room for discussion by publishing articles signed by <hi rend="italic">IBOR</hi>’s last editorial board and articles by Armand Černjul, as well as
                texts by authors not directly related to the “IBOR Case”.</p>
            <p>In one of Armando Černjul’s first articles about the “IBOR Case” published in the
                Istrian edition of Večernji list the author wonders whether people in <hi rend="italic">IBOR</hi> think that Istria’s youth “for whom the journal is
                intended is interested in homosexual ranting?”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn37" n="36"> Armando Černjul, ‘Kome služi “Ibor’?,” <hi rend="italic">Večernji list</hi> (Istrian), October 3, 1979, 6.
                    </note> The <hi rend="italic">IBOR’s</hi> editorial staff answered in the
                same newspaper to the allegations in relation to publishing the poem “Please
                Master”. They stated that the “unfortunate Ginsberg is a cause of much casual gossip
                and labeling of IBOR’s editorial staff from the “filters” of social morality such as
                A. Č. The civil terms “swear words” and “vulgarities” simply fade away as archaism
                compared to those as stylemes without which one period of literary creativity is
                missing in the world and here. It seems that the individuals must be repeatedly
                reminded of the well-worn statement that the appreciation of the artistic level of a
                particular literary work is mainly in the domain of poetics, literary criticism and
                aesthetics, and by no means a tool for political discredit by drawing out of the
                context of a whole”.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn38" n="37"> IBOR Redaction, “Fusnote za A. Černjula”, <hi rend="italic">Večernji
                            list</hi> (Istrian), November 1, 1979, 6.</note> Černjul wrote his
                answer already in the next issue: “As for the poem ‘Please Master’ by A. Ginsberg,
                which is presented by the members of IBOR’s editorial staff, thinking perhaps that
                Pula and other places in Istria have problems with homosexuality in education, then
                they should have disclosed their opinion on their own, and not seek ‘help’ from the
                American poet and professor. How to otherwise explain to the reader of <hi rend="italic">IBOR</hi>, and now ‘Večernji List’, that the people in <hi rend="italic">IBOR</hi> are mistaken. They would have to look at the last page
                of the <hi rend="italic">IBOR</hi>, on which the photo was published showing at best
                three year old lying prone on the road, surrounded by adults and signed ‘Please
                Master’. If people in <hi rend="italic">IBOR</hi> don't know what they have done
                with it, then they are not up to the job they are doing, because the photograph in
                the context of the poem ‘Please Master’ by which it is named, undoubtedly puts the
                innocent child into the center of homosexual lust. Everyone must be disgusted by
                    it!”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn39" n="38"> Armando
                        Černjul, “Bez kormila,” <hi rend="italic">Večernji list</hi> (Istrian),
                        November 2, 1979, 6.</note></p>
            <p>A cosmopolitan, writer and scholar Predrag Matvejević also referred to “IBOR Case” in
                an interview for <hi rend="italic">Polet</hi>. When asked by journalist Vladimir
                Cvitan: “When it comes to ‘Ibor’ and dismissing its editorial staff, it is generally
                taken as known that by publishing Ginsberg’s poem ‘Please Master’ a mistake has been
                made?” Matvejević answered: “I think publishing one somewhat challenging poem of one
                good poet (a poem that speaks of homosexuality) is more mischief than a mistake. Do
                not forget that one issue of ‘Domet’ dedicated to erotics was nearly prohibited in
                    Rijeka.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn40" n="39">
                        Vladimir Cvitan, “Intervju: Predrag Matvejević. Dosta gruba smjenjivanja,”
                            <hi rend="italic">Polet</hi> (Zagreb), January 23, 1980, 9,
                    10.</note> Regarding Matvejević’s response in which he stated that the poem
                is of homosexual character, the question arises as to whether Matvejević was really
                familiar with the words of the poem and the fact that the editorial team accompanied
                the poem with a photograph which they named after the poem’s title and which shows
                the boy of preschool age. Given the words of the poem and the photograph which is
                explicitly related to the poem, it is more than obvious that it is a poem of
                pedophilic character, while the homosexual part of the poem’s character is probably
                less important because homosexualism was decriminalized in socialist Yugoslavia in
                1977. Armando Černjul referred to an interview with Matvejević in the earlier
                mentioned article “Enough with crude disinformation”. Černjul stated that Matvejević
                and journalist Cvitan give inaccurate information about the “IBOR Case” and how they
                are wrongly informed. Černjul thinks that one of the reasons for Matvejević’s
                misinformation is the visit of <hi rend="italic">IBOR</hi>’s editorial board to
                Professor Matvejević.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn41" n="40"> Armando Černjul, “Dosta grube dezinformacije,” <hi rend="italic">Polet</hi> (Zagreb), February 6, 1980, 2.</note></p>
            <p>Slavko Kalčić and Aldo Monfardin, two members of the last editorial board of <hi rend="italic">Istarski Borac/IBOR</hi>, published the article “IBOR Case” in the
                newspaper <hi rend="italic">Pitanja</hi> in 1980. In the article they respond to the
                attacks in other newspapers, especially Armando Černjul’s texts and the accusations
                from the DC ASYC/OK SSOH. As a defense to Černjul’s accusations of vulgarism, and in
                relation to the poem “Please Master”, they state that Černjul takes the photograph
                and the poem “out of the context of the issue’s theme (Total institutions),
                pretending not to understand or indeed not understanding the term <hi rend="italic">literary</hi>, simultaneously vulgarizing it and attacking IBOR with low blows
                using the arsenal of Christian moralism”.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn42" n="41"> Slavko Kalčić and Aldo Monfardin, “Slučaj ‘Ibor,’” <hi rend="italic">Pitanja</hi> (Zagreb), No. 3 (1980), 71–77. </note>
                Answering the accusations from the DC ASYC/OK SSOH (which were published in <hi rend="italic">Glas Istre,</hi> issue from December 3, 1979), that many articles
                published in <hi rend="italic">IBOR</hi> were “not suitable, especially for the age
                of those the journal was intended for”, the editorial staff relativised these claims
                and said that such a label could “usually be found on Danish-Swedish film
                co-productions!”. They focused on the second part of the accusations, which state
                that part of the inscriptions is unacceptable “as a way of presenting our social
                reality”. The part about presenting “our social reality” is deemed crucial by <hi rend="italic">IBOR</hi>’s editorial board, and they confirm it with Rakočević’s
                article published in the Istrian edition of <hi rend="italic">Večernji list</hi>
                from December 4, 1979. In the article Rakočević accused them of publishing the texts
                with “views that are foreign to our self-managing and socialist society, impose a
                destructive approach to the treatment of social topics and problems, and instead of
                being a forum for young people, <hi rend="italic">IBOR</hi> increasingly becomes a
                ground for the nebulous wisdom of individuals.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn43" n="42"> Ibid., 73.</note> Further in the text, as a
                sort of conclusion, the authors pointed out that one “poem instead of giving
                aesthetic and cognitive pleasure resulted in extraordinary sessions, work groups
                (...) It is wrong, however, to think that the song missed its purpose. On the
                contrary, it fulfilled it entirely by bringing to light the hereditary illness of a
                closed community. Instead of a word no one listens to under the dome of deaf
                indifference, the poem has become the catalyst for the events.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn44" n="43"> Ibid.</note> As a key part of
                their defense in this article, the authors emphasized the “Marxism” of their actions
                and the fact that “the coupling of sexual and political inhibition” is joined
                against them: “To speak out about this means to touch into the sacrosanctness of the
                ‘guardians’ of such activity. We come to an important problem in the whole case:
                isn’t the ‘freedom of speech’ lower in provincial conditions where the local totems
                rule, and where political and sexual are not yet free from taboos? It is not by
                chance that in one particular case sexual and political merge by cause and effect
                relationship as the initiators and the mechanisms of silencing. Historical analysis
                of the written/spoken word in relation to these two areas would show that they were,
                in fact, its limiters in societies without freedom/democracy. Boasting with
                progressive consciousness is not uncommon in these times, but progressive
                consciousness is not in Marxist phrases, but in Marxist deeds. We think that <hi rend="italic">IBOR’s</hi> work is Marxist in its critical, open and
                argumentative writing. In the surroundings where ideas are often critiques for the
                local autocracy, every critique is known to be met with intolerance. That is why
                people in <hi rend="italic">IBOR</hi> were marked as critics and were objected for
                not highlighting the positive examples from our reality”.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn45" n="44"> Slavko Kalčić and Aldo Monfardin,
                        “Slučaj ‘Ibor,’” <hi rend="italic">Pitanja</hi> (Zagreb), No. 3 (1980):
                        71–77.</note></p></div>
            <div><head>Verdict Against the IBOR Editorial Board</head>
            <p>The “IBOR Case” was mostly covered by journalist Armando Černjul, writing for the
                Istrian edition of the daily newspaper <hi rend="italic">Večernji list</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Polet</hi>. It was his article in <hi rend="italic">Polet</hi>
                (“Enough with crude disinformation,” February 6, 1980) that prompted <hi rend="italic">IBOR</hi>’s editorial board to react with another article in <hi rend="italic">Polet</hi> (“Photogenic falsifier,” February 19, 1980), in which
                they stated that Černjul has a “Zhdanovist temper”, that he is a “press-agent in the
                service of power”, and a philistine.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn46" n="45">
                        <hi rend="italic">Polet</hi> (Zagreb), February 19, 1980, 2.</note>
                Černjul filed a private lawsuit for slander and defamation against the <hi rend="italic">IBOR</hi>’s editorial staff. The court dismissed the part of the
                suit pertaining to slander, but ruled against members of the <hi rend="italic">IBOR</hi>’s editorial board (Nevenko Petrić, Boris Biletić, Slavko Kalčić,
                Miomir Kalčić, Josip Ivančić and Ivan Pletikos) for defamation and assigned each “a
                month and a half suspended sentence and one year of probation.” At the request of
                the plaintiff (Černjul), and pursuant to the court’s decision, the verdict was
                published in <hi rend="italic">Polet</hi>.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn47" n="46">
                        <hi rend="italic">Polet</hi> (Zagreb), November 5, 1980, 2.</note></p>
            <p>The trial was held at the County Court in Pula and the second-instance verdict was
                passed on October 8, 1980. The Council that issued the second-instance verdict was
                constituted of the Council’s president Zvonimir Pajdaš and members Ante Črnja and
                Milojka Vučković, while Željko Franješević
                defended<hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve"> IBOR</hi>’s editorial board. As
                mentioned earlier, the second-instance court rejected part of allegations referring
                to slander and the editorial board of <hi rend="italic">Istarski borac/IBOR</hi> was
                only convicted for defamation. In addition to paying the cost of publishing the
                verdict in the <hi rend="italic">Polet</hi> newspaper, the members of the editorial
                board were obliged to pay the costs of the criminal proceedings and each paid the
                sum of 200 dinars. The verdict contains the court’s belief that the offenders “will
                not repeat such and similar criminal offenses in the future”.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn48" n="47">
                        <hi rend="italic">Polet</hi> (Zagreb), November 5, 1980, 2. </note></p></div>
            <div><head>Conclusion</head>
            <p>Following all that was said, it is evident that the “IBOR Case” is very complex and
                it is not easy answering the question of whether it classifies as a culture of
                dissent or not. The <hi rend="italic">IBOR</hi> was discussed in the party circles
                even before it became a public case, i.e. prior to publishing the issue 4–5/79 and
                the poem “Please Master”. At the time <hi rend="italic">IBOR</hi> was criticized for
                not giving enough space to young authors, not submitting reports, publishing only a
                half of planned issues for 1978 and 1979, and dealing primarily with the issues of
                the Pula commune. After the outbreak of the
                “<hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">IBOR </hi>Case”, Party’s analysis of
                the<hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve"> IBOR</hi> put an emphasis on the
                non-fulfillment of obligations, the absence of young non-established authors and the
                ideological turn of the editorial board, which is reflected in improper writing
                about the Yugoslav self-managing socialist society. The analysis ignored the poem
                “Please Master” only briefly stating that the last issue of <hi rend="italic">IBOR</hi> was full of vulgarity. This disregard for content of the last issue
                gives the impression that the poem “Please Master” was perhaps not the reason why
                the financing of <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">IBOR </hi>was cancelled and
                that the reason lies in the “destructive” writing of some authors – “this approach
                and a way of writing about our social reality reflects their ideological orientation
                which is foreign to our self-managing socialist society”.</p>
            <p>On the other hand, the editorial board thought that their writing is critical, but
                not (culture of dissent) towards Marxism: “We think that <hi rend="italic">IBOR</hi>’s work is Marxist in its critical, open and argumentative writing” - but
                towards negative phenomena in society. Has the <hi rend="italic">IBOR</hi>’s
                editorial board really thought that their activity was Marxist or was it a defense
                against an attack that would reduce the damage done to <hi rend="italic">IBOR</hi>
                and to them as individuals – this remains an open question and is subject to further
                interpretation. The <hi rend="italic">IBOR</hi>’s last editorial board can hardly be
                denied the courage to write about topics which were taboo and caused discontent in
                Pula’s conservative surroundings. However, the editorial board was probably aware
                that the same topics would bring about discontent from the Party and that their
                actions put them at the limits of tolerance. With this kind of work, the editorial
                board of <hi rend="italic">IBOR</hi> showed courage and resisted, if not to Marxism
                as they themselves say, then to the community in which they lived and worked.</p></div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="bibliography"><head>Sources and References</head>
            <list type="unordered">
                <head>Archival Sources:</head>
                <item>HDA, Hrvatski državni arhiv, Zagreb:<list type="unordered">
                    <item>HR HDA 1220, Savez komunista Hrvatske. Centralni komitet.</item>
                    <item>HR HDA 1605, Republička samoupravna interesna zajednica
                        kulture.</item>
                    <item>HR HDA 1231, Republička konferencija Saveza socijalističke omladine
                        Hrvatske.</item>
                </list></item>
            </list>
            <listBibl>
                <head>Literature:</head>
                <bibl>Krušelj, Željko. <hi rend="italic">Igraonica za odrasle: Polet
                    1976.–1990.</hi> Rijeka: Adamić, 2015.</bibl>
                <bibl>Peternel–Lorenzin, Marija. <hi rend="italic">Bibliografija časopisa “Istarski
                    borac” – “Ibor”: (1953.–1979.)</hi>. Pula: Istarski ogranak Društva
                    hrvatskih književnika, 2006.</bibl>
                <bibl>Petrinić, Dolores. <hi rend="italic">Hrvatska književnost u istarskim
                    časopisima druge polovice XX. st</hi>. Rijeka: Društvo hrvatskih
                    književnika, 2007. </bibl>
                <bibl>Zubak, Marko. <hi rend="italic">The Yugoslav Youth Press: (1968 – 1980):
                    student movements, youth subcultures and Communist alternative media</hi>.
                    Zagreb: Srednja Europa; Hrvatski institut za povijest, 2018.</bibl>
            </listBibl>
            <listBibl>
                <head>Newspaper Sources:</head>
                <bibl>Crnobori, Albino. “Što je za moju generaciju značio literarni klub ‘Istarski
                    borac’.” <hi rend="italic">Istarski mozaik</hi>, No. 5–6 (1968): 412–15.</bibl>
                <bibl>Cvitan, Vladimir. “Intervju: Predrag Matvejević. Dosta gruba smjenjivanja.”
                    <hi rend="italic">Polet</hi> (Zagreb), January 23, 1980, 9, 10.</bibl>
                <bibl>Černjul, Armando. “Dosta grube dezinformacije.” <hi rend="italic">Polet</hi>
                    (Zagreb), February 6, 1980, 2.</bibl>
                <bibl>Černjul, Armando. “Kome služi ‘Ibor’?” <hi rend="italic">Večernji list</hi>
                    (Istrian), October 3, 1979, 6.</bibl>
                <bibl><hi rend="italic">Glas Istre</hi>, 1979.</bibl>
                <bibl>IBOR Redaction. “Fusnote za A. Černjula.” <hi rend="italic">Večernji list</hi>
                    (Istrian), November 1, 1979, 6.</bibl>
                <bibl><hi rend="italic">Istarski borac</hi>, 1953–1979.</bibl>
                <bibl>Ivezić, Ljubica. “I jedna važna obljetnica između na koju ne treba
                    zaboraviti,” <hi rend="italic">Dometi</hi> (Rijeka) No. 5–6 (1992):
                    95–100.</bibl>
                <bibl><hi rend="italic">Pitanja</hi>, 1980.</bibl>
                <bibl><hi rend="italic">Polet</hi>, 1980.</bibl>
                <bibl><hi rend="italic">Večernji list</hi> (Istrian), 1979.</bibl>
            </listBibl>
            <p>Online Sources:</p>
            <listBibl>
                <bibl><hi rend="italic">Istarski borac</hi>. Accessed December 18, 2018, <hi rend="italic">Metelgrad - Digitalizirani časopisi</hi>. <ref target="http://library.foi.hr/m3/kds1.php?B=1&amp;sqlx=S02008&amp;ser=&amp;sqlid=1&amp;sqlnivo=&amp;css=&amp;H=pula&amp;U=05">http://library.foi.hr/m3/kds1.php?B=1&amp;sqlx=S02008&amp;ser=&amp;sqlid=1&amp;sqlnivo=&amp;css=&amp;H=pula&amp;U=05</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl><hi rend="italic">Matica hrvatska</hi> [Matrix Croatica]. <ref target="http://www.matica.hr/kolo/408/nacionalno-i-univerzalno-u-obzorima-zavicajnosti-23142/">http://www.matica.hr/kolo/408/nacionalno-i-univerzalno-u-obzorima-zavicajnosti-23142/</ref>.</bibl>
            </listBibl></div>
            <div type="summary">
                <docAuthor>Lidija Bencetić</docAuthor>
            <head><hi rend="allcaps" xml:space="preserve">Journal </hi><hi rend="italic allcaps">Istarski
                Borac/IBOR</hi><hi rend="allcaps" xml:space="preserve"> in the Context of the Culture of Dissent</hi></head>
            <head>SUMMARY</head>
            <p>Following all that was said, it is evident that the “IBOR Case” is very complex and
                it is not easy answering the question of whether it classifies as a culture of
                dissent or not. The <hi rend="italic">IBOR</hi> was discussed in the party circles
                even before it became a public case, i.e. prior to publishing the issue 4–5/79 and
                the poem “Please Master”. At the time <hi rend="italic">IBOR</hi> was criticized for
                not giving enough space to young authors, not submitting reports, publishing only a
                half of planned issues for 1978 and 1979, and dealing primarily with the issues of
                the Pula commune. After the outbreak of the
                “<hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">IBOR </hi>Case”, Party’s analysis of
                the<hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve"> IBOR</hi> put an emphasis on the
                non-fulfillment of obligations, the absence of young non-established authors and the
                ideological turn of the editorial board, which is reflected in improper writing
                about the Yugoslav self-managing socialist society. The analysis ignored the poem
                “Please Master” only briefly stating that the last issue of <hi rend="italic">IBOR</hi> was full of vulgarity. This disregard for content of the last issue
                gives the impression that the poem “Please Master” was perhaps not the reason why
                the financing of <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">IBOR </hi>was cancelled and
                that the reason lies in the “destructive” writing of some authors – “this approach
                and a way of writing about our social reality reflects their ideological orientation
                which is foreign to our self-managing socialist society”.</p>
            <p>On the other hand, the editorial board thought that their writing is critical, but
                not (culture of dissent) towards Marxism: “We think that <hi rend="italic">IBOR</hi>’s work is Marxist in its critical, open and argumentative writing” - but
                towards negative phenomena in society. Has the <hi rend="italic">IBOR</hi>’s
                editorial board really thought that their activity was Marxist or was it a defense
                against an attack that would reduce the damage done to <hi rend="italic">IBOR</hi>
                and to them as individuals – this remains an open question and is subject to further
                interpretation. The <hi rend="italic">IBOR</hi>’s last editorial board can hardly be
                denied the courage to write about topics which were taboo and caused discontent in
                Pula’s conservative surroundings. However, the editorial board was probably aware
                that the same topics would bring about discontent from the Party and that their
                actions put them at the limits of tolerance. With this kind of work, the editorial
                board of <hi rend="italic">IBOR</hi> showed courage and resisted, if not to Marxism
                as they themselves say, then to the community in which they lived and worked.</p></div>
            <div type="summary" xml:lang="sl"><docAuthor>Lidija Bencetić</docAuthor>
            <head>ČASOPIS <hi rend="italic">ISTARSKI
                BORAC</hi>/<hi rend="italic">IBOR</hi> V KONTEKSTU KULTURE DISIDENTSTVA</head>
            <head>POVZETEK</head>
            <p>Prvi hrvaški mladinski časopis <hi rend="italic">Istarski borac</hi>/<hi rend="italic">IBOR</hi> je z dvema krajšima vmesnima premoroma izhajal med leti
                1953 in 1979 v Pulju. Časopis je izdajal Književni klub Istarski borac, in sicer z
                namenom ohranjanja hrvaškega jezika v Istri kot temeljnim vodilom. V sedemdesetih
                letih 20. stoletja je časopis prevzel značaj kritičnega medija in postopoma uvajal
                vse več kulturnih, lokalnih in družbenih tem, katerih ton pa socialistična oblast ni
                dobro sprejela. Jeseni leta 1979 je izbruhnil »primer IBOR«. Časopisu so istega leta
                ukinili financiranje, zaradi česar je prenehal izhajati. Povod za ukinitev časopisa
                je bila sicer pesem z naslovom <hi rend="italic">Please, master</hi> (hrv.: <hi rend="italic">Molim te, učitelju</hi>) Allena Ginsberga, toda partijski
                dokumenti razkrivajo, da je bil razlog političen. Pričujoča razprava poskuša
                odgovoriti na vprašanje, ali je delovanje zadnjega uredništva časopisa <hi rend="italic">Istarski borac</hi>/<hi rend="italic">IBOR</hi> mogoče obravnavati
                kot kulturo disidentstva. </p>
            <p>»<hi rend="italic">Primer IBOR</hi>« je dokaj zapleten, zato odgovor na vprašanje,
                ali je pri njem šlo za kulturo disidentstva ali ne, ni preprost. O časopisu <hi rend="italic">IBOR</hi> so v partijskih krogih razpravljali še pred javnim
                odprtjem primera oziroma pred izdajo številke 4–5/79 in pesmi <hi rend="italic">Please, master</hi>. Takrat se je govorilo, da časopis ne daje dovolj prostora
                mladim avtorjem, da ne oddaja poročil o delu, da je leta 1978 in 1979 objavil pol
                manj številk, kot je bilo predvideno, in da se ukvarja predvsem s problematiko
                puljske komune. Po izbruhu »primera <hi rend="italic">IBOR</hi>« je v partijski
                analizi opaziti poudarek na neizpolnjevanju obveznosti, izpustu mladih, še
                neuveljavljenih avtorjev in idejnem odklonu uredništva, kar naj bi se odražalo v
                nepravilnem pisanju o jugoslovanski samoupravni socialistični družbi. V analizi je
                sicer prezrta pesem <hi rend="italic">Please, master</hi>, pri čemer je zgolj na
                kratko omenjeno, da je zadnja številka časopisa <hi rend="italic">IBOR</hi> polna
                prostaštva. Tovrstno ignoriranje vsebine zadnje številke zbuja vtis, da pesem <hi rend="italic">Please, master</hi> ni bila razlog za umik financiranja časopisa
                <hi rend="italic">IBOR</hi>. Nakazuje namreč, da je razlog vendarle
                »destruktivno« pisanje nekaterih avtorjev, saj da »tak pristop in način pisanja o
                naši družbeni stvarnosti odražata idejno opredelitev, ki ni v skladu z našo
                samoupravno socialistično družbo«. </p>
            <p>Po drugi strani pa je samo uredništvo bilo mnenja, da je njihovo pisanje sicer
                kritično, vendar ni kritično (culture of dissent) do marksizma: »Menimo, da je
                delovanje časopisa <hi rend="italic">IBOR</hi> marksistično po svojem kritično
                usmerjenem, odprtem in argumentiranem pisanju«, toda kritično naravnano do
                negativnosti v družbi. Vprašanje o tem, ali je uredništvo časopisa <hi rend="italic">IBOR</hi> v resnici menilo, da je njihovo delovanje marksistično, ali je šlo
                zgolj za obrambo pred napadom, s katero so hoteli omiliti škodo, ki so jo utrpeli
                <hi rend="italic">IBOR</hi> in člani uredništva kot posamezniki, je ostalo
                odprto in predmet naknadnih interpretacij. Nikakor pa zadnjemu uredništvu časopisa
                <hi rend="italic">IBOR</hi> ne gre oporekati poguma, s katerim so se lotili
                pisanja o tabu temah, ki so izzvale nezadovoljstvo v konservativnem puljskem okolju.
                Kljub temu so se njegovi člani najbrž zavedali, da bodo ravno te teme povzročile
                negodovanje tudi v Partiji in da se s svojim delovanjem pomikajo proti sami meji
                tolerance. S takim delovanjem je uredništvo revije <hi rend="italic">IBOR</hi>
                pokazalo pogum in se uprlo, če že ne marksizmu, kot so dejali sami, pa gotovo vsaj
                skupnosti, v kateri so delovali in živeli.</p></div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>