<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Accepting the Border, Choosing the Border:
                    The Štrigova and Razkrižje Micro-region in the First Half of the
                        20<hi rend="bold superscript">th</hi> Century</title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename>Stipica</forename>
                        <surname>Grgić</surname>
                    </name>
                    <roleName>Research associate</roleName>
                    <roleName>PhD</roleName>
                    <affiliation>University of Zagreb’s Centre for Croatian Studies</affiliation>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Borongajska cesta 83d</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>10000-Zagreb</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>Croatia</addrLine>
                    </address>
                    <email>sgrgic@hrstud.hr</email>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>2017-08-09</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>
                    <orgName xml:lang="sl">Inštitut za novejšo zgodovino</orgName>
                    <orgName xml:lang="en">Institute of Contemporary History</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Kongresni trg 1</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>SI-1000 Ljubljana</addrLine>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>http://ojs.inz.si/pnz/article/view/234</pubPlace>
                <date>2016</date>
                <availability status="free">
                    <licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title xml:lang="sl">Prispevki za novejšo zgodovino</title>
                <title xml:lang="en">Contributions to Contemporary History</title>
                <biblScope unit="volume">57</biblScope>
                <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
                <idno type="ISSN">2463-7807</idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source, born digital.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc xml:lang="en">
                <p>Contributions to Contemporary History is one of the central Slovenian scientific
                    historiographic journals, dedicated to publishing articles from the field of
                    contemporary history (the 19th and 20th century).</p>
                <p>The journal is published three times per year in Slovenian and in the following
                    foreign languages: English, German, Serbian, Croatian, Bosnian, Italian, Slovak
                    and Czech. The articles are all published with abstracts in English and
                    Slovenian as well as summaries in English.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <projectDesc xml:lang="sl">
                <p>Prispevki za novejšo zgodovino je ena osrednjih slovenskih znanstvenih
                    zgodovinopisnih revij, ki objavlja teme s področja novejše zgodovine (19. in 20.
                    stoletje).</p>
                <p>Revija izide trikrat letno v slovenskem jeziku in v naslednjih tujih jezikih:
                    angleščina, nemščina, srbščina, hrvaščina, bosanščina, italijanščina, slovaščina
                    in češčina. Članki izhajajo z izvlečki v angleščini in slovenščini ter povzetki
                    v angleščini.</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="sl"/>
                <language ident="en"/>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords xml:lang="en">
                    <term>Slovenia-Croatia border</term>
                    <term>Štrigova</term>
                    <term>Razkrižje</term>
                    <term>demarcation</term>
                    <term>20th century</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords xml:lang="sl">
                    <term>slovensko-hrvaška meja</term>
                    <term>Štrigova</term>
                    <term>Razkrižje</term>
                    <term>demarkacija</term>
                    <term>20. stoletje</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change>
                    <date>2017-09-25</date>
                    <name>Neja Blaj Hribar</name>
                    <desc>Pretvorba iz DOCX v TEI, dodatno kodiranje</desc>
                </change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <docAuthor>Stipica Grgić<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn1" n="*"><hi rend="bold"> Research associate, PhD, University of Zagreb’s Centre for Croatian Studies, Borongajska cesta 83d, 10000</hi>-<hi rend="bold">Zagreb, Croatia, <ref target="mailto:sgrgic@hrstud.hr">sgrgic@hrstud.hr</ref></hi></note></docAuthor>
            <docImprint>
                <idno type="cobissType">Cobiss type: 1.01</idno>
                <idno type="UDC">UDC: </idno>
            </docImprint>
            <div type="abstract" xml:lang="sl">
                <head>IZVLEČEK</head>
                <head>SPREJEMANJE MEJE, IZBIRANJE MEJE: ŠTRIGOVA IN RAZKRIŽJE V PRVI POLOVICI 20. STOLETJA</head>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Meja med Slovenijo in Hrvaško na področju Razkrižja in Štrigove je
                    še vedno predmet raznih razprav. Do njene zadnje spremembe je prišlo leta 1946,
                    njen današnji potek pa so oblikovali razni elementi. Članek zato analizira potek
                    te meje v burnem obdobju prve polovice 20. stoletja.</hi></p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Ključne besede: slovensko-hrvaška meja, Štrigova, Razkrižje,
                    demarkacija, 20. stoletje</hi></p>
            </div>
            <div type="abstract">
                <head>ABSTRACT</head>
                <p><hi rend="italic">The border between Slovenia and Croatia in the area of
                    Razkrižje-Štrigova is still a subject of debate. Its last change occurred in
                    1946 and its present appearance was influenced by various elements. This article
                    will analyze the phenomenon of the emergence of this border in the turbulent
                    times of the first half of the 20</hi><hi rend="italic superscript">th</hi><hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve"> century.</hi></p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Key words: Slovenia-Croatia border, Štrigova, Razkrižje,
                    demarcation, 20th century</hi></p>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div><p>In 1946 a group of individuals, claiming to have the support of the majority of the
                residents in the former compact Municipality of Štrigova in the north-western part
                of Međimurje, visited various Yugoslav state institutions in Belgrade. Emphasizing
                transportation, economic, cultural, educational and national reasons, they appealed
                to the central authorities in order to ensure that their small region, consisting of
                several settlements, becomes a permanent part of the Federal People’s Republic of
                Slovenia. They claimed that the state institutions were the only relevant factor
                with the authority to resolve this inter-republic Slovenian-Croatian border conflict
                and propose a final solution in the era in which the state promoted “brotherhood and
                unity” and avoided even the smallest possibility of a national conflict.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn2" n="1"> Duško Dimitrijević, <hi rend="italic">Državne
                                granice nakon sukcesije SFR Jugoslavije</hi> [<hi rend="italic">State Borders after the succession of the SFR of Yugoslavia</hi>]
                            (Belgrade: Institute of International Politics and Economics, 2012),
                            399–404.</note> This case study will try to reconstruct what
                events led to a dispute over the Slovenian-Croatian border in this micro-region.</p>
            <p>The article will attempt to emphasize that the nationalizing (Slovenian-Croatian)
                processes only occurred in that micro-region during the first half of the 20<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> century, after the Hungarian rule was overthrown,
                with the further development of local institutions and articulation of political and
                institutional nationalism on a local level. It will also highlight the importance of
                various local educational, economic and other social conditions which contributed to
                the articulation of attitudes of these communities about their (national) belonging
                and their expressions of reluctance or even resistance after they were placed on –
                what they considered to be – the “wrong side” of the border. In addition to
                theoretical literature, the article is based on published and unpublished archival
                sources and newspapers covering the history of this area in the mentioned period.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn3" n="2"> Among other valuable titles, I would like to point
                            out: Peter Pavel Klasinc, <hi rend="italic">Arhivski dokumenti o
                                dogodkih v Štrigovi in okolici v prvih let po Drugi svetovni
                                vojni</hi> [<hi rend="italic">Archival documents on events in
                                Štrigova and its surroundings in the first years after the Second
                                World War</hi>] (Ljubljana: Zavod 25. junij, 2008). Although this
                            collection of documents is not without flaws (or agenda), they are still
                            the best source to give us a good insight into the entire
                            Slovene-Croatian border dispute.</note></p>
            <p>Conceptually, this case study relies on Thomas Wilson’s and Hastings Donnan’s theory
                of identities along borders. According to Wilson and Donnan, the population living
                in areas closer to borders can perceive them as “both barriers and
                    opportunities”.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn4" n="3"> Thomas M. Wilson and Hastings Donnan, <hi rend="italic">Border Identities: Nation and State at International
                                Frontiers</hi> (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1998),
                            22.</note> This article aims to observe how the various aspects
                of border perceptions influenced the local population and affected the process of
                their self-determination in terms on their local, national, political, economic and
                other affiliations.</p></div>
            <div><head>Reshaping the Borders, Shaping the Territory (1900-1945)</head>
            <p>The Municipality of Štrigova was formed in the mid-19th century. It comprised 45
                individual villages and hamlets scattered across 9.351 square acres of mountain
                terrain. The settlements were quite disjointed and had a relatively few number of
                inhabitants. In 1910 Štrigova itself had only 433 inhabitants and Razkrižje, one of
                the other larger settlements in the municipality, numbered only 229 inhabitants.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn5" n="4">
                            <hi rend="italic">A magyar szent korona országainak 1910. évi
                                népszámlálása. Első rész</hi> (Budapest: Magyar statisztikai
                            közlemények, 1912), 82, 83.</note> At the time, Štrigova
                Municipality was a part of Čakovec District, which was under the rule of the
                Hungarian-based Zala County. The Hungarian government and its policy of repression
                towards the Slavs, which was, for instance, evident in education, was in fact
                counterproductive; it slowly shaped the identity of the Slavic population in an
                undesired direction. In the first decades of the 20<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>
                century, the resistance directed towards the efforts of the Hungarian authorities
                was mostly peaceful. However, after the collapse of Austria-Hungary at the end of
                1918, an open revolt occurred. It was fueled by the difficult economic and political
                situation that came with the last year of the First World War. The Hungarian
                authorities’ decision to send their army to this area was entirely
                counterproductive. The local Croatian and Slovenian politicians, tempted by the idea
                of the South Slavic unity, begun seeking help from this newly created South Slavic
                    state.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn6" n="5"> Vladimir Kalšan, “Međimurje 1918. i 1919. godine,”
                            in: <hi rend="italic">1918. u hrvatskoj povijesti</hi> [<hi rend="italic">1918 in Croatian history</hi>], ed. Željko Holjevac
                            (Zagreb: Matica Hrvatska, 2012), 139–53. Vladimir Kapun, <hi rend="italic">Međimurje 1918</hi> (Čakovec: Zrinski, 1982), 308–28.
                        </note> In late December of 1918, Štrigova Municipality became a
                part of the Kingdom of Serbs, Croats and Slovenes, following the quick action of the
                Croatian volunteer corps, who had entered Međimurje and consequently placed it
                entirely under the jurisdiction of the Zagreb provincial administration. At the 1919
                Paris Peace Conference, the right of ethnic self-determination was recognized and
                thus began the integration of Međimurje (and the neighboring Prekmurje) into the
                administrative and other systems of the newly formed Kingdom of Serbs, Croats and
                Slovenes (Yugoslavia).<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn7" n="6"> Kalšan, <hi rend="italic">Međimurje 1918. i
                                1919.</hi>, 148. Miroslav Kokolj, <hi rend="italic">Prekmurski
                                Slovenci: Od narodne osvoboditve do nacistične okupacije
                                1919-1941</hi> [<hi rend="italic">Slovenes of
                                Prekmurje: From National Liberation to Nazi Occupation 1919-1941</hi>] (Pomurska Založba: Murska Sobota, 1984),
                            especially 35.</note></p>
            <p>Following a brief period of belonging to the Zagreb provincial administration
                (1918-1923), after <hi rend="italic">oblasts</hi> were formed, Štrigova
                Municipality, together with the rest of Međimurje, became a part of the Maribor
                Oblast (1924-1929). Only six years later, the oblasts were abolished and <hi rend="italic">banovinas</hi>, as the new, more centralized regional units in the
                era of the Sixth of January dictatorship, were formed. In 1929 the entire Međimurje
                fell under the Sava Banovina region, which had its seat in Zagreb. However, in 1931
                Štrigova Municipality was separated from Čakovec District and the rest of Međimurje
                and placed under the authority of the Ljubljana-based Drava Banovina and its
                Ljutomer District.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn8" n="7"> Ljubo Boban, <hi rend="italic">Croatian
                                borders
                            1918</hi>–<hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">1993 </hi>(Zagreb:
                            Školska knjiga, 1993), 58–60.</note> In an attempt to
                simultaneously build a unified state and nation, especially in the era of the Sixth
                of January Dictatorship (1929-1935), the Yugoslav government tried to create a new
                internal map of administrative units, from regional to municipal, in an effort to
                produce not only a functioning administration, but also a new set of allegiances
                towards themselves and the concept of integral Yugoslavism which they promoted. The
                state announced that their boundaries would be formed according to economic and
                transportation principles, and that former ethnic divisions between South Slavic
                people will simply disappear.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn9" n="8"> Laslo Sekelj, “Diktatur und die
                            jugoslawische politische Gemeinschaft – von König Alexander bis
                                Tito,”<hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve"> Autoritäre Regime in Ostmittel- und Südosteuropa 1919-1944</hi> (Paderborn: Ferdinand Schöningh Verlag,
                            2001), 519.</note> For this purpose, many small settlements
                were placed under the administration of regional centers of power, under which they
                had never been before.</p>
            <p>During the Second World War, the territory of predominantly Slovenian Drava Banovina
                was occupied and divided by the German, Italian and Hungarian forces. After a few
                months under the Third Reich, Međimurje, including the municipalities of Štrigova
                and Razkržije, was from 1941 to mid-1945 reincorporated into the administrative
                system of the Hungarian Zala County.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn10" n="9"> “Opčini Štrigova in Razkrižje
                            pod Madžarsko,” <hi rend="italic">Slovenski dom</hi>, June 25, 1941,
                            2.</note> In that form it welcomed the end of the War in spring
                of 1945 and the reunification with the Slovenian Ljutomer District in the now
                reconstructed Socialist Yugoslavia.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn11" n="10"> Vladimir Kalšan, <hi rend="italic">Međimurska povijest</hi> [<hi rend="italic">A history
                                of Međimurje</hi>] (Čakovec: V. Kalšan, 2006), 323,
                    324.</note></p>
            <p>All these changes were made without consulting the municipal or other local levels of
                government. It was clear to the inhabitants of this territory that the real reasons
                behind the border alterations lay in the changes which happened in the centers of
                power which surrounded them and claimed this territory. This shows the undemocratic
                character of the border changing processes in this area, which affected the behavior
                of the inhabitants and developed the idea of a border as something arbitrary, a line
                which, for some reason, does not include the area they would choose or approve
                of.</p></div>
            <div><head>Štrigova and Razkrižje Municipalities – the People and the
                    Institutions</head>
            <p>Frequent border changes produced a shift in self-awareness and border-awareness among
                the population, as well as a split in terms of identity within the once, at least
                nominally, homogeneous Štrigova Municipality. The last Hungarian censuses in 1900
                and 1910 reveal that a vast majority of Croats populated this area.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn12" n="11"> Comp. <hi rend="italic">A magyar szent korona
                                országainak 1900. évi népszámlálása. Első rész</hi> (Budapest:
                            Magyar statisztikai közlemények, 1902), 162–65 and <hi rend="italic">A
                                magyar szent korona országainak 1910</hi>, 82, 83.</note>
                According to the 1921 census (the only census which asked the Interwar Yugoslavs
                about their first language), Štrigova Municipality was home to a prevailing number
                of Croatian speaking population. Out of 6.076 inhabitants in total, 5.952 declared
                themselves as Croats, while only 96 (less than 1%) as Slovenes.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn13" n="12">
                            <hi rend="italic">Definitivni rezultati popisa stanovništva od 31
                                Januara 1921 god.</hi> [<hi rend="italic">Definitive Results of
                                State Census of January 31, 1921</hi>] (Sarajevo: Državna
                            štamparija, 1932), 290, 291.</note> The next census which shows
                how people declared themselves in terms of nationality gives us a completely
                different story. In 1948, the people living in the northern part of the former
                Municipality of Štrigova, better to say the new Municipality of Razkrižje, which in
                the meantime became a part of the Slovenian territory, declared themselves
                predominantly as Slovenes, while the others, who were placed under the rule of the
                People’s Republic of Croatia, declared themselves mostly as Croats.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn14" n="13"> According to the 1948 census, In the People’s
                            Republic of Slovenia’s district Ljutomer local people’s committees
                            [mjesni narodni odbor] Globoka (475 Slovenes and only 4 Croats),
                            Razkrižje (1100 Slovenes, 19 Croats) and Veržej (720 Slovenes, 7
                            Croats), while in People’s Republic of Croatia’s Čakovec district local
                            liberation committees Sveti Urban (61 Slovenes, 1199 Croats), Štrigova
                            (89 Slovenes, 1823 Croats) and Železna Gora (19 Slovenes, 1140 Croats).
                            –
                                <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Konačni rezultati popisa stanovništva od 15 marta 1948 godine: Knjiga IX </hi>[<hi rend="italic">The final results of the March 15, 1948 census: Book
                                IX</hi>] (Beograd: Savezni statistički zavod, 1954), 351,
                        405.</note> Subsequent censuses tell the same story; between 1921
                and 1948 a process of national differentiation occurred.</p>
            <p>But we can leave the numbers aside and take a look at the multi-level dispute within
                the municipal community. It manifested on a local level in economic, cultural and
                political manner. It should be noted that Štrigova Municipality in that era
                consisted of a lot of mountain territory and that the central settlement itself had
                only several hundred residents. The inhabitants of the marginal parts of this
                municipality, broken into a number of villages and hamlets, due to the terrain
                configuration, experienced transportation isolation and some had problems when
                trying to reach Štrigova, the center of the municipality, or Čakovec, the seat of
                their district.</p>
            <p>The dispute between the northern or Razkrižje part of the once unified Štrigova
                Municipality and its central or south part became more obvious during the 1930s. The
                inhabitants of Razkrižje and other “northern” settlements clearly resented the
                efforts of the local teachers and priest who came from Štrigova, and were sent by
                Zagreb’s administrative and ecclesiastical authorities. They accused them of being
                unable to adjust to local circumstances (language, mentality), but also of
                “denationalization” of their children. In 1933 they petitioned the Drava Banovina
                authorities for a teacher who would teach their children in the Slovenian language.
                Soon, the primary school in Šafarsko near Razkrižje was actually granted this
                    teacher.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn15" n="14"> “Razburjenost na Razkrižju in v Štrigovi,” <hi rend="italic">Slovenski narod</hi>, November 11, 1939,
                    2.</note> Furthermore, a few years later, they petitioned even more
                vigorously for the formation of the new Razkrižje Municipality.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn16" n="15"> “Štrigova,” <hi rend="italic">Jutro</hi>, October
                            15, 1937, 7.</note></p>
            <p>This demand coincided with the efforts of the Drava Banovina authorities. In mid
                1930s they started the process of redistribution of municipalities under their
                jurisdiction. Basically, this process was directed towards the merger of the
                existing municipalities, thus creating new, larger municipalities, with enough
                taxpayers to work for the good of the people. The number of municipalities in Drava
                Banovina decreased from 1069 to 407 in 1937.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn17" n="16"> Gašper Šmid, <hi rend="italic">Uprava Dravske banovine
                                1929</hi>–<hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">1941 </hi>[<hi rend="italic">Drava Banovina Administration 1929-1941</hi>]
                            (Ljubljana: Arhiv Republike Slovenije, 2003), 56, 57.</note>
                Despite the proclaimed efforts to create a bigger and more functional local
                administration, the Drava Banovina authorities decided to dismember the large
                Štrigova Municipality. In 1937 one part became the new Štrigova Municipality,
                encompassing two thirds of the previous municipal territory and population. The
                other, the northern third, seceded from Štrigova and it formed a new municipality -
                Razkrižje. During the distribution of settlements between Razkrižje and Štrigova,
                the principle of territorial integrity, according to which every settlement had to
                belong to one municipality, while a municipality may only be under the authority of
                one district, and a district under the jurisdiction of a single banovina, was not
                applied. Surprisingly, almost half of the individual settlements in this
                redistribution remained literally divided by house numbers between Štrigova and
                Razkrižje municipalities.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn18" n="17"> The Municipality of Razkrižje
                            included the villages and hamlets Gibna, Razkrižje, Šafarsko and
                            Vesčica, and parts of Jalšovec (house numbers 16-38), Grabrovnik (house
                            numbers: 36a. 104, 105. 110, 112-151), Banfije (home numbers: 1-15. 26,
                            27, 30, 31, 34, 44-72, 82, 84-128, 131, 150-171) and Robadije (house
                            numbers: 76-138, 148-179, 205-230). Other parts remained under the
                            jurisdiction of Štrigova Municipality. – “Ukaz o spojitvah, razdružitvah
                            in pregrupacijah občin in o spremembah imena in sedeža občin v območju
                            Dravske banovine,” <hi rend="italic">Službeni list Kraljevske banske
                                uprave Dravske banovine</hi>, October 16, 1937,
                790.</note></p>
            <p>The residents of Štrigova Municipality clearly disliked the actions of their
                neighbors in the new Razkrižje Municipality. They accused them of intentionally
                working on their separation from Croatian national territory with the authorities of
                Drava Banovina. They even cited some examples of arrests and fines sent to the
                people who declared themselves as Croats.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn19" n="18"> Besides the
                            supporters of the Croatian Peasant Party, the chaplain from Štrigova was
                            also fined several times “for holding patriotic sermons, which was seen
                            by the authorities as spreading of tribal hatred”. – “Nasilno
                            sloveniziranje Hrvata u Štrigovi,” <hi rend="italic">Hrvatsko
                                jedinstvo</hi>, June 8, 1940, 2. Such procedures were, to say the
                            least, inconvenient, because during that time (1939–1941) the Croatian
                            Peasant Party was cooperating with the Slovenian People’s Party on a
                            national level.</note> Furthermore, on a practical level, they
                argued that some of the settlements which were placed under the latter municipality
                were in fact much closer to Štrigova.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn20" n="19"> “Štrigova,” <hi rend="italic">Jutro</hi>, October 15, 1937, 7.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The dispute between the inhabitants of Štrigova and Razkrižje soon moved to the
                ecclesiastical level. After the separate municipality was formed, the malcontents
                form Razkrižje and surrounding villages started petitioning for their own parish,
                separate from Štrigova, and, of course, a Slovenian-speaking parson.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn21" n="20"> Breda Pogorelec, “Razkrižje,” <hi rend="italic">Jezik in slovstvo</hi> 38, no. 3 (1993): 108–12.</note>
                The priests from Štrigova, who were responsible for the entire parish, realized that
                the inhabitants of the newly formed Razkrižje Municipality provided resistance and
                emphasized that they do not feel they belong to the same (Croatian or “štokavian”)
                culture and language as their neighbors. Furthermore, they decided to suppress these
                sentiments by insisting even more on the Croatian character of the
                Štrigova-Razkrižje micro-region.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn22" n="21"> In August of 1940, the pupils
                            who attended the Catholic youth course came to Štrigova where they “sang
                            many [Croatian] patriotic songs, to remind everyone that Štrigova
                            belongs to Međimurje and not to Slovenia”. Two months later, the choral
                            society <hi rend="italic">Zrinski</hi> from Čakovec arrived in Štrigova,
                            where their outdoor performance turned into a great manifestation of
                            Croatian nationhood. – “Razkrižje,” <hi rend="italic">Hrvatsko
                                jedinstvo</hi>, August 24, 1940, 5. “Štrigova,” <hi rend="italic">Hrvatsko jedinstvo</hi>, October 5, 1940, 6.</note></p>
            <p>The Croatian-speaking priests from Štrigova clearly resented the petitioners who
                sought to establish a new “Slovenian” parish in Razkrižje and publicly refused to
                teach at the local school in Šafarsko after it replaced Croatian with Slovenian
                catechisms. The Drava Banovina administration responded in 1940 by ordering the
                local teachers to take over catechism teaching in Šafarsko, which was, according to
                the parishioners, against the law because in the area of their diocese only the
                bishop could appoint and dismiss religious teachers. The archbishop of Zagreb,
                Alojzije Stepinac, tried to reconcile the Razkrižje parishioners and the Štrigova
                priests in 1940/1941 but with little success. The conflict between the Croatian
                speaking priests and the predominantly Slovenian-speaking parishioners continued for
                decades, even after a separate Razkrižje parish was formed in 1942.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn23" n="22"> Pogorelec, “Razkrižje,” 110, 111. Razkrižje parish
                            remained under the administration of the Zagreb archdiocese all the way
                            until 1994. – “Župa Razkrižje Slovenska,” <hi rend="italic">Varaždinske
                                vijesti</hi>, September 14, 1994, 9.</note></p>
            <p>It seems that the process of national stratification advanced quite a lot in the
                Štrigova-Razkrižje micro-region due to the introduction of Slovenian school
                teachers, textbooks and municipal institutions in what was once, at least nominally,
                a homogeneous community. Perhaps the best indicator of that process were the results
                of the parliamentary elections. During the elections for the National Assembly in
                l938, the last major elections prior to the Second World War, a vast majority of the
                population in the municipality of Razkrižje voted for the Yugoslav Radical Union
                (YRU), which at the time included the Slovenian People’s Party, while in Štrigova
                most votes went for the United Opposition. i.e. the Croatian Peasant Party.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn24" n="23"> During the 1938 elections in the Razkrižje
                            municipality Yugoslav Radical Union got 291 votes, opposition
                            (altogether) – 83. In Štrigova Municipality YRU got 165, Croatian
                            Peasant Party 334 votes. – “Volivni izidi v Sloveniji,” <hi rend="italic">Slovenec</hi>, December 13, 1938, 3.</note>
                Although some malcontents from the Croatian side disputed these results, saying that
                “the local candidate of the YRU list was a farmer called I. Šajnović, who declares
                himself a Croat and is not a member of YRU”, this information shows that during the
                late 1930s in the newly created Razkrižje Municipality most of the locals voted for
                candidates who supported Slovenian programs, while in Štrigova Municipality a vast
                majority of people in the same indirect way declared themselves as Croats.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn25" n="24"> “Nasilno sloveniziranje,” 2.</note></p>
            <p>There were several announcements in 1939 and 1940 that during the reorganization of
                Yugoslav internal borders government will take into account the Štrigova-Razkrižje
                issue, which will be resolved by placing this micro-region under the jurisdiction of
                the newly formed Banovina of Croatia. The talks on this “replacement of the
                territory” between the leaders of the most prominent Slovenian and Croatian parties,
                Franc Kulovec and Vladko Maček, were intensified in late 1940.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn26" n="25"> Tomaž Ivešić, “Delovanje dr. Franca Kulovca na
                            čelu SLS in ključni dogodki pred vojno,” <hi rend="italic">Časopis za
                                zgodovino in narodopisje</hi> 49, no. 1 (2013): 93,
                    94.</note>However, due to the outbreak of the Second World War this
                plan never materialized.</p></div>
            <div><head>The Border after the Second World War</head>
            <p>The aftermath of the Second World War saw the establishment of the new socialist
                Yugoslavia. It was supposed to be the state of all the “brethren Yugoslav nations”
                organized in six “fraternal republics”, which were conceptualized as a solution to
                the national question that the prior, monarchist Yugoslavia never managed to
                    resolve.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn27" n="26"> Sabrina P. Ramet<hi rend="italic">, The Three
                                Yugoslavias: State-Building and Legitimation, 1918-2005</hi> (Washington: Woodrow Wilson Center Press,
                            2006), 163–65. Boban, <hi rend="italic">Croatian borders</hi>, 52. § 1-2
                            of the Constitution of the Federal People’s Republic of Yugoslavia
                            (1946), in: <hi rend="italic">Constitution of the Federal People’s
                                Republic of Yugoslavia</hi> [Ustav Federativne Narodne Republike
                            Jugoslavije], (s.n.: Belgrade, 1946), 5.</note> The border
                between the newly formed People’s Republics’ of Slovenia and Croatia remained for
                the most part the same as the old banovinas border established in 1931. Štrigova and
                Razkrižje municipalities, along with their newly established local authorities, <hi rend="italic">local people’s committees</hi>, provisionally became a part of
                Slovenia. The end of the War, especially April and May of 1945, was especially hard
                for the locals. Many homes and other buildings had to be rebuilt and there was a
                shortage of basic supplies, which in 1945/1946 forced some locals to fight the
                authorities and become outlaws.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn28" n="27"> Klasinc, <hi rend="italic">Arhivski</hi>, 221–27, doc 122.</note></p>
            <p>In the first few critical years after the War, food and other supplies came mostly
                from the authorities on the Slovenian side, i.e. Maribor and Ljutomer.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn29" n="28"> Ibid., 59, 60. doc 21.</note> Only in
                late 1945 did the Croatian side show some interest in this territory. The central
                government in Belgrade was well aware of the fact that certain areas were
                controversial in a manner that it was necessary to resolve which of the Republics
                they belonged to. In September 1945, the Ministry for the Constitutional Assembly
                clearly listed the problem of Istria and Štrigova along the Slovenian-Croatian
                border, where “a strong conflict between individual [Communist Party] executives
                from Slovenia and Croatia broke out some time ago”.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn30" n="29"> Ibid., 28, doc
                            6.</note></p>
            <p>In September 1945, after the agreement between the ministries of the interior of
                Slovenia and Croatia, the area of the former Municipality of Štrigova was supposed
                to be transferred to the jurisdiction of SR Croatia. However, the implementation of
                the decision was postponed because the elections for the local people’s committees
                were in progress, as the new, lowest, forms of self-government, and the authorities
                were afraid that any change at this point could cause “a negative stimulation to the
                [Croatian and Slovenian] national question and boost chauvinism”.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn31" n="30"> Ibid., 26, doc 5.</note></p>
            <p>By the end of October of the same year, the Slovenian and Croatian ministries of the
                interior published the “Guidelines for the temporary enforcement of border relations
                in the former Štrigova Municipality”, which transferred the villages and hamlets
                Razkrižje, Šafarsko, Goibina, Robadije, Spornec, Presika, Leskovec, Sveti Urban and
                Leskovec under the authority of SR Slovenia’s Ljutomer Disctrict, while all other
                settlements in the former Štrigova municipality became a part of the SR Croatia’s
                Čakovec District. Furthermore, the “Guidelines” stated that the transfer of people
                and goods between the two republics should run completely freely and they even
                created mixed commissions with the aim of resolving issues connected to private
                property disputes.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn32" n="31"> Ibid., 31, 32, doc 8.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The provisional nature of this solution encouraged many inhabitants to raise the
                question of the final drawing of the border in this area. Some of them clearly
                stated in their letters and petitions that most of the settlements were more
                inclined to staying under Slovenia than becoming a part of Croatia. Curiously, some
                advocates of the Slovenian side declared themselves as Croats and even requested
                Croatian speaking teachers in their villages (eg. Grabrovnik). Other, pro-Croatian
                executives resented this idea, saying that the entire former Štrigova Municipality
                is a part of Međimurje, and Međimurje a constituent part of Croatia.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn33" n="32"> Ibid., 34, doc 9.</note></p>
            <p>It is curious to see some signs of national indifference. Some people, although they
                declared themselves as Croats, were more prone to becoming Slovenes, or were
                indifferent to active participation in the local Slovenia-Croatia dispute. A large
                number of them were from the villages even further from the border and more oriented
                to Croatia.</p>
            <p>The Štrigova-Razkrižje micro-region was a territory very dependent on agriculture.
                That is why the lure of better prices and the vicinity of the Slovenian market (the
                villages of the micro-region gravitated towards the market in Ljutomer, which was
                only 3-10 km away, as opposed to the Čakovec market, 22-30 km away) played a
                significant role in the process of these people’s self-determination.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn34" n="33"> Ibid., 92, 141, doc 43 and 73.</note>
            </p>
            <p>For some of the people living in this border area the concept of “national” dropped
                down on the list of interests in the economically and politically difficult times
                after the Second World War – to make way for a better life. For instance, in June
                1946, the Croatian authorities attempted to speak to the residents of Štrigova and
                the surrounding area, in order to assess the situation. They concluded that
                Slovenian propaganda had an impact on ordinary inhabitants, mostly farmers and small
                winegrowers, because they used various socio-economic examples. For instance, they
                pointed out that their wine sells for 60 dinars in Slovenia and 35 dinars in
                Croatia, and that the Slovenian side could build infrastructure and bring
                electricity to their households much faster than the Croatian authorities.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn35" n="34"> CSA, CCLSCC; Calls, box 5, The meeting between the
                            people and the envoy of Varaždin County, June 19, 1946.
                </note></p>
            <p>At the beginning of April 1946, a big meeting of the local people’s committee in
                Razkrižje was adjourned. Most of the local residents attended and were very
                interested in the solution for the final demarcation of their area. At this meeting,
                the people from Razkrižje and its immediate surroundings, led by the president of
                the local people’s committee Simon Kutnjak, protested against the alleged new
                agreement that was struck between the ministers of the interior of Slovenia and
                Croatia. According to that deal, which was perhaps only an oral agreement between
                the two ministers (Ivan Maček and Ivan Krajačić), the entire area in question was
                marked, again only provisionally, as a territory of SR of Croatia.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn36" n="35"> Klasinc, <hi rend="italic">Arhivski</hi>, 94, doc
                            43.</note> Without the involvement of the central (Yugoslav)
                state government, Croatian authorities decided to negotiate with their Slovenian
                counterparts about the “swift return” of these territories under the Croatian
                authority. The Croatian minister of the interior claimed that the population is
                almost entirely Croatian and that it represents a unification of Međimurje as a
                whole, the way it used to be during the Austro-Hungarian period. The Slovenian
                minister of the interior and the Ljutomer District authorities accepted these
                    claims.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn37" n="36"> Dimitrijević, <hi rend="italic">Državne
                                granice</hi>, 407.</note> The verbal deal was struck, but
                the transition of authority was followed by something that neither side had
                previously been able to imagine: the discontent of the people they argued about.</p>
            <p>The news about the agreement in 1946 only caused further polarization in the
                Štrigova-Razkrižje micro-region. Two distinct groups were formed; one advocating
                that the entire area, or most of it, should become a part of Slovenia. This group
                enjoyed strong support among the inhabitants, especially in Razkrižje itself. The
                Slovenian side, led by Simon Kutnjak and Ivan Horvatič, both from Razkrižje, were
                promising a better life, less taxes and a market (in Ljutomer) more open to the sale
                of the farmers’ products and wine than the one in the Croatian district centre
                    (Čakovec).<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn38" n="37"> Klasinc, <hi rend="italic">Arhivski</hi>, 92, doc
                            43.</note> They also fought against the officials, teachers and
                priests who were sent from Zagreb, claiming that they were conducting an unwanted
                linguistic and cultural unification of the population that is almost completely
                    Slovenian.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn39" n="38"> Ibid.</note></p>
            <p>The other, pro-Croatian side, disagreed with these claims, but was somewhat weaker in
                its propaganda efforts. It emphasized historical connection of this area to Croatia
                and even used data from the former census to support this. The Croatian side, led by
                Josip Alt from Štrigova, pointed out that 98% of the population in the area felt
                    Croatian.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn40" n="39"> Ibid., 73, 91, doc 30 and 43.</note> But
                they too underlined the need to respect the will of the people in the new democratic
                Yugoslavia.</p>
            <p>Both sides were supported, at least formally, by various local pro-communist leaders.
                Furthermore, both sides discredited advocates of the other with unsubstantiated
                claims of “cooperation with the enemy” during the Second World War, the accumulation
                of wealth in the first post-war year and other accusations which should have served
                as a red rag to the authorities of the new socialist Yugoslavia.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn41" n="40"> Ibid., 122–29, 158–62, doc. 62 and
                    79.</note></p>
            <p>Both sides cautiously accused one another of national chauvinism but also emphasized
                their desire for “fraternal coexistence”, not the national dispute with their
                “brethren”. Depending on the standpoint, Slovenian and Croatian police forces,
                teachers of both nationalities, priests and Ljutomer and Čakovec authorities were
                also blamed for further incitement of this hatred. Indeed, some procedures of the
                listed accused parties did not calm the situation. In fact, in 1946 they stirred up
                the conflict even more.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn42" n="41"> Ibid., 151–53, doc 75.</note></p>
            <p>In their requests, sent to the republican and state authorities, both sides sometimes
                referred to the Constitution of the Federal People’s Republic of Yugoslavia. Its
                article 12 stated that the National Assembly of Yugoslavia, as its highest
                legislature, was responsible for the division of territories between the republics.
                However, the same article explained that any border changes involving the republics
                were not valid without the consent of each republic.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn43" n="42"> § 12 of the 1946
                            Constitution, 5.</note> This shows that the writers of the
                Yugoslav constitution considered the possibility of border changes, and even
                incorporated some vague and ambiguous mechanisms to ensure that the will of the
                people is respected.</p>
            <p>Although the highest state authorities at first had no intention of interfering,
                prompted by numerous complaints, at the beginning of August 1946, the National
                Assembly did react. First they sent letters to the governments of Slovenia and
                Croatia, asking for a full cooperation in resolving this issue. They asked both
                governments to form a joint commission which would finally resolve the problem of
                delimitation in this area “due to the inconvenient tapering that occurred between
                the local Croatian and Slovene populations”. They even suggested a solution,
                according to which “the territory of the local committees of Razkrižje and Robadije
                should be placed under the People’s Republic of Slovenia, and the rest of the former
                Municipality of Štrigova under the People’s Republic of Croatia”.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn44" n="43"> Klasinc, <hi rend="italic">Arhivski</hi>, 117, doc
                            57.</note> In the following few weeks, while the commission was
                being formed, the situation escalated even more as the local police arrested some
                pro-Slovenian protesters.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn45" n="44"> Ibid., 127, 152, doc 62 and
                            75.</note></p></div>
            <div><head>Towards the Solution</head>
            <p>The central government and the National Assembly of the new socialist Yugoslavia
                could no longer close their eyes to the Štrigova-Razkrižje issue, especially after
                Kutnjak and Horvatič visited Belgrade in June of 1946, emerging with the credentials
                of the local people’s committees from Jalšovec, Robadije, Razkrižje, Stanetinec,
                Sveti Urban and Železna Gora, demanding the revision of the Slovenian-Croatian
                border during multiple audiences with the highest state-executives.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn46" n="45"> Dimitrijević, <hi rend="italic">Državne
                                granice</hi>, 399–404.</note></p>
            <p>The situation intensified and became more serious. For instance, Simon Kutnjak was
                arrested shortly after he returned from Belgrade. The Croatian side claimed that he
                was incarcerated for the economic crimes he had committed as president of
                Razkrižje’s people’s committee, while the Slovenian side claimed he was arrested for
                his agitation.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn47" n="46"> Klasinc, <hi rend="italic">Arhivski</hi>, 151–53,
                            doc 75.</note> Furthermore, during the summer of 1946, various
                banners and triumphal arches appeared in the villages, bearing slogans such as
                “Štrigova is Slovene”, “We are Slovenes, and we will stay Slovenes”, while during
                one celebration in Ljutomer, a large number of farmers from Razkrižje and Robadije
                appeared with a banner saying: “Trieste is Yugoslavia, Razkrižje is Slovenia”.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn48" n="47"> Ibid.</note></p>
            <p>The Yugoslav authorities had to react and resolve this issue as it might have
                deepened the dispute between their two constituent nations and their republics.
                Prompted by official complaints, the federal <hi rend="italic">Control
                    Commission</hi> was sent to examine the Štrigova-Razkrižje border problem. This
                Commission, which was to decide about the demarcation in the Štrigova-Razkrižje area
                consisted of three members: Lepa Perović, Pavle Gregorić and Vida Tomšić. Gregorić
                and Tomšić were actually presidents of the Croatian and Slovenian republican Control
                Commissions, while Lepa Perović, as the inspector general of the federal Control
                Commission, had seniority.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn49" n="48"> Dimitrijević, <hi rend="italic">Državne granice</hi>, 405.</note></p>
            <p>The three members of the Commission tried to to objectively determine the
                Slovenian-Croatian border in this area and offer reconciliation, with the intention
                of providing the best solution possible for the people. The Commission conducted a
                multitude of interviews with various citizens, farmers, teachers, common people,
                etc. They wrote down all the valid and invalid arguments of both sides, who admitted
                that there were little or no differences in the language, culture and mentality
                between the inhabitants of Razkrižje and Štrigova. The Croatian side claimed that
                the commoners were seduced by stories of better life in Slovenia. At the same time
                they still acknowledged that the inhabitants of Razkrižje, Šafarsko, Gibina, Veščica
                and Robadije were indeed more linked to Ljutomer, at least in terms of
                transportation and economy.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn50" n="49"> CSA, CCLCC; Calls, box 5, The
                            Control Commission – meeting with the inhabitants in Štrigova, July 26,
                            1946.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Interestingly, when confronted with the direct questions of their national and
                cultural belonging, some people gave vague answers. For instance, although the
                commission concluded that the residents of the villages closer to Ljutomer “didn’t
                have a clearly defined national affiliation, and were in many ways (mentality,
                similar language) closer to Slovenes”, the answer to the question of what language
                residents of Razkrižje should use was: “The same as in Štrigova”. <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn51" n="50"> Klasinc, <hi rend="italic">Arhivski</hi>, 150, doc
                            75.</note> Self-declaration on the basis of language shows that
                the process of nation-building was not completed in this area by 1946. In reality,
                the people who opted for Slovenia felt that their language was Slovenian, and those
                who opted for Croatia felt that they spoke and wrote Croatian. In fact, individuals
                often refused to declare themselves nationally, preferring regional self-awareness.
                Even when they were directly confronted by the Control Commission about whether they
                felt as Slovenes or Croats, most of the interviewed residents often argued that they
                were in fact “Međimurci”.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn52" n="51"> Ibid., 148, doc
                        75.</note></p>
            <p>The most direct interviewees were children. When Croatian authorities asked them what
                language they would like to learn in their elementary school, the majority voted for
                Slovenian. “Some of them even said it was because the Croatian language was the
                language of cows [?]”.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn53" n="52"> CSA, CCLCC; Calls, box 5, The Croatian
                            official concluded his report with a statement that this was a clear
                            sign of Slovenian agitation among the pupils and that parents obviously
                            do not pay enough attention to the education of their children. Meeting
                            between the people and the envoy of Varaždin County, June 19, 1946.
                        </note> Furthermore, the attempt to replace Slovene teachers with
                teachers form Croatia in June 1946 had a disastrous effect. The residents of
                Razkrižje and the surrounding villages gathered and refused to let new teachers into
                their schools and also stopped sending their children to school.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn54" n="53"> Dimitrijević, <hi rend="italic">Državne
                                granice</hi>, 403.</note></p>
            <p>The Commission concluded that it was necessary to avoid a deeper national dispute and
                apathy towards the authorities of socialist Yugoslavia.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn55" n="54"> Klasinc,
                                <hi rend="italic">Arhivski</hi>, doc 75, 150–154.</note>
                Their final report concluded that the entire Štrigova-Razkrižje micro-region was
                historically a part of the Croatian Međimurje and that in the past the inhabitants
                of this territory used both languages, received and read books and newspapers
                printed both in Slovenia and Croatia. Nevertheless, they stated that this does not
                change the fact that in “this moment [1946] one part of the [Štrigova] municipality
                now declares itself Slovene”, especially because young people and women are a
                predominant factor in siding with Slovenia.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn56" n="55"> Ibid., 153, doc
                            75.</note> They also acknowledged the fact that authorities in
                this dispute made many errors in terms of handling the situation, while the leaders
                of both sides, – i.e. Alt, Horvatič and Kutnjak were described as “kulaks” and
                    “nationalists”.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn57" n="56"> Ibid., 152, 162, doc 75 and
                    79.</note> The Commission concluded that they need to be placed under a
                close watch and, if possible, removed from their positions. In the meantime, new,
                reconciling and more responsible faces should accept the leadership of the local
                people’s committees and hold joint meetings with the people living in the area, in
                order to interpret the benefits of “the politics of brotherhood and unity, and
                explain how harmful national hatred could be”.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn58" n="57"> Ibid., 153, doc
                            75.</note></p>
            <p>Of course, the most important thing was to resolve the border issue. Following
                discussions in which some maps were drawn, the Commission adopted a temporary
                solution according to which the northern part, or one third of the disputed
                territory, should belong to Slovenia, while the southern and western part should
                belong to Croatia. The border line was described as temporary, subject to further
                and final direct negotiations between the Slovenian and Croatian sides. It followed
                the 1937 delineation between the municipalities of Štrigova and Razkrižje for almost
                its entire course. The Commission clearly identified that this line also served as
                an ethnic border, since in the north most of the people declared themselves as
                Slovenes and in the south as Croats. In addition, they were against additional
                border redrawing, because it could have lead to further border disputes.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn59" n="58"> Ibid., 165, doc 79.</note> The final
                report informed both sides that after this temporary solution, which they thought
                could become a permanent one, definitive delimitation between Croatia and Slovenia
                would be resolved with a special act which would be passed by the National Assembly
                of Yugoslavia.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn60" n="59"> Ibid., 159, doc 78.</note></p>
                <figure>
                    <head>Maps 1 and 2: Undated maps – The Control Commission’s attempts to
                        determine the Slovenia-Croatia border (1946)</head>
                    <graphic url="map1.jpg" height="600px"/>
                </figure>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="map2.jpg" height="500px"/>
                    <p>Source: CSA, CCLCC; Calls, box 5.</p>
                </figure>
            <p><hi rend="italic"></hi></p>
            <p>At the end of 1946, having accepted that the villages and hamlets Globoka, Veščica,
                Gibina, Razkrižje, Šafarsko and a greater part of Banfi, become a part of Slovenia,
                while other settlements in the wide disputed area become a part of Croatia
                (Grabrovnik, Leskovec, Jalšovec, Sveti Urban, Stanetinec, Mali Leskovec, Robadije,
                Štrigova, Železna Gora, and a small part of the village Banfi), the Croatian side
                informed the central Yugoslav government and the federal Slovenian government that
                it no longer had any territorial disputes with Slovenia. They also stated that it
                was their opinion that this temporary solution should become the definitive
                demarcation between the two republics. <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn61" n="60"> Ibid., 174, doc
                        83.</note> It is unclear whether Slovenian government gave any
                similar statement.</p>
            <p>Both republics, Croatia and Slovenia, accepted this solution and accepted their
                exclusive right to install school teachers, police officers and other civil servants
                in the area that now respectively belonged to Croatia and Slovenia. On the other
                hand, after some new letters came during the summer of 1946, the federal Control
                Commission clearly emphasized that it would reject all new redrawing demands, except
                those requests which resulted from thorough discussions among the relevant district
                or county authorities (Ljutomer and Maribor on the Slovenian side, Čakovec and
                Varaždin on the Croatian side). They thought these types of requests “just [serve]
                to incite chauvinistic hatred and ruin the reputation of the [Yugoslav communist]
                    <hi rend="italic">people’s power</hi>”.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn62" n="61"> Ibid., 159, doc
                            78.</note></p>
            <p>In a similar way, in the late 1946, the <hi rend="italic">Maršalat</hi>, i.e. the
                office of Josip Broz Tito, rated these demands as products of “reactionary
                individuals”, “former Korošec’s people”, who sought to sow the seed of national
                discord between Slovenes and Croats. “With this campaign, they gained popularity
                among the people, while the [local] representatives of the national authorities –
                instead of working in the spirit of brotherhood and unity – joined their efforts,
                while the work on reconstruction and construction [of the state] remained
                    neglected.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn63" n="62"> Dimitrijević, <hi rend="italic">Državne
                                granice</hi>, 378.</note></p>
            <p>Ultimately, after the Control Commission announced this solution, drew the temporary
                border and insisted on preventing further spread of national hatred, the situation
                actually calmed down in the Razkrižje-Štrigova area. Indeed, with some exceptions,
                it seemed that both sides accepted this transitional solution.</p>
            <p>In the decades which followed there were some local initiatives from this area which
                applied for the “correction” of this part of the Slovenia-Croatia border, especially
                in the last 25 years, after Slovenia and Croatia became independent countries.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn64" n="63"> For instance: Klasinc, <hi rend="italic">Arhivski</hi>, 184–200, doc 93–107,</note> However, the
                governments of both Slovenia and Croatia have not shown much interest in becoming
                involved in the border dispute(s) in this area. Ultimately, the above mentioned
                temporary solution of the border problem became a permanent solution. It is valid
                even today and the people who live in this area are well aware of all the positive
                and negative effects of the border. Nevertheless, most of the institutions which
                claim responsibilities for this area from both sides of the border agree that
                cooperation is better than conflict.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn65" n="64"> Ivica Beti, “Humano
                            preseljenje u Sloveniju?,” <hi rend="italic">Večernji list</hi>, July 9,
                            2017, 10–13.</note></p></div>
            <div><head>Conclusion</head>
            <p>The problem of the Slovenian-Croatian border in Međimurje, in today’s municipalities
                of Štrigova and Razkrižje, is more complex than it first appears. We can argue that
                many factors conditioned the present configuration of the border. One of the most
                important ones is the constant change of the state borders in this area. From the
                end of the First World War in 1918 until 1946, the first year after the end of World
                War II, this whole area was under the Hungarian authorities twice (1918, 1941-1945),
                three times under Slovenian authority (1924-1929, 1931-1941, 1945-1946), three times
                under Croatian authority (1918-1924, 1929-1931, 1946), and even under the Third
                Reich for a few months (1941). This brought instability, especially in an area where
                people identified themselves differently and national division had not yet been
                clearly established. However, in the early 20<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> century,
                due to the work of some “old” institutions (the Catholic Church, schools), as well
                as some new institutions (for instance the new Municipality of Razkrižje,
                established in 1937), the inhabitants became increasingly politically fragmented and
                they started to notice their differences in terms of language, school and economic
                preferences. By the summer of 1946, the situation changed again. Harsh post-war
                years brought economic and political instability and generated the local
                Štrigova-Razkrižje conflict, which grew into a conflict between the pro-Slovene and
                pro-Croatian sides. Both sides claimed that they had the support of most of the
                inhabitants of the Štrigova-Razkrižje micro-region and promised the people a better
                life if they supported their claims. After a large number of complaints reached the
                highest state authorities, three members of the federal Control Commission came out
                to this territory in 1946. They conducted interviews with the residents and in the
                end they draw a temporary border between the two republics in this area, the border
                that for the most part followed the 1937 border between the municipalities of
                Štrigova and Razkrižje. Although the National Assembly later never discussed nor
                passed the law concerning the Slovene-Croatian border in this area, this line became
                the national border between the Republic of Slovenia and Republic of Croatia as we
                know it today.</p></div>
            
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="bibliography">
            <head>Sources and Literature</head>
            <head>Archive sources:</head>
            <list type="unordered">
                <item> CSA – Croatian State Archives:<list>
                <item> CCLCC; Calls – Central Committee of the League of Communists of Croatia -
                    Calls and session suggestions. </item></list></item>
            </list>
            <listBibl>
                <head>Literature:</head>
                <bibl>Boban, Ljubo. <hi rend="italic">Croatian borders 1918-1993</hi>. Zagreb: Školska knjiga, 1993.</bibl>
                <bibl>Dimitrijević, Duško. <hi rend="italic">Državne granice nakon sukcesije SFR
                    Jugoslavije</hi>. Belgrade: Institute of International Politics and
                    Economics, 2012.</bibl>
                <bibl>Ivešić, Tomaž. “Delovanje dr. Franca Kulovca na čelu SLS in ključni dogodki
                    pred vojno.” <hi rend="italic">Časopis za zgodovino in narodopisje</hi> 49, no.
                    1 (2013): 83–118.</bibl>
                <bibl>Kalšan, Vladimir. “Međimurje 1918. i 1919. godine.” In: <hi rend="italic">1918. u hrvatskoj povijesti</hi>, ed. Željko Holjevac. 139–54. Zagreb:
                    Matica Hrvatska, 2012.</bibl>
                <bibl>Kalšan, Vladimir. <hi rend="italic">Međimurska povijest</hi>. Čakovec: V.
                    Kalšan, 2006.</bibl>
                <bibl>Kapun, Vladimir. <hi rend="italic">Međimurje 1918.</hi> Čakovec: Zrinski,
                    1982.</bibl>
                <bibl>Kokolj, Miroslav. <hi rend="italic">Prekmurski Slovenci: Od narodne
                    osvoboditve do nacistične okupacije 1919-1941</hi>.
                    Pomurska Založba: Murska Sobota, 1984.</bibl>
                <bibl>Klasinc, Peter Pavel. <hi rend="italic">Arhivski dokumenti o dogodkih v
                    Štrigovi in okolici v prvih let po Drugi svetovni vojni</hi>. Ljubljana:
                    Zavod 25. junij, 2008.</bibl>
                <bibl>Pogorelec, Breda. “Razkrižje.” <hi rend="italic">Jezik in slovstvo</hi> 38,
                    no. 3 (1993): 108–13.</bibl>
                <bibl>Ramet, Sabrina P. <hi rend="italic">The Three Yugoslavias: State-Building and
                    Legitimation, 1918-2005</hi>. Washington: Woodrow
                    Wilson Center Press, 2006.</bibl>
                <bibl>Sekelj, Laslo. “Diktatur und die jugoslawische politische Gemeinschaft – von
                    König Alexander bis Tito.“ In: <hi rend="italic">Autoritäre Regime in Ostmittel-
                        und Südosteuropa 1919-1944</hi>., ed. Erwin
                    Oberländer, 499–537. Paderborn: Ferdinand Schöningh Verlag, 2001.</bibl>
                <bibl>Šmid, Gašper. <hi rend="italic">Uprava Dravske banovine 1929-1941</hi>. Ljubljana: Arhiv Republike Slovenije, 2003.</bibl>
                <bibl>Wilson, Thomas M. and Hastings Donnan. <hi rend="italic">Border Identities:
                    Nation and State at International Frontiers</hi>. Cambridge: Cambridge
                    University Press, 1998.</bibl>
            </listBibl>
            <listBibl>
                <head>Newspaper sources:</head>
                <bibl>Beti, Ivica. “Humano preseljenje u Sloveniju?.“ <hi rend="italic">Večernji
                    list</hi>, July 9, 2017, 10–13.</bibl>
                <bibl><hi rend="italic">Hrvatsko jedinstvo</hi>. “Nasilno sloveniziranje Hrvata u
                    Štrigovi,” June 8, 1940, 2.</bibl>
                <bibl><hi rend="italic">Hrvatsko jedinstvo</hi>. “Razkrižje,” August 24, 1940,
                    5.</bibl>
                <bibl><hi rend="italic">Hrvatsko jedinstvo</hi>. “Štrigova,” October 5, 1940,
                    6.</bibl>
                <bibl><hi rend="italic">Jutro</hi>. “Štrigova,” October 15, 1937, 7.</bibl>
                <bibl><hi rend="italic">Slovenec</hi>. “Volivni izidi v Sloveniji,” December 13,
                    1938, 3.</bibl>
                <bibl><hi rend="italic">Slovenski dom</hi>. “Opčini Štrigova in Razkrižje pod
                    Madžarsko,” June 25, 1941, 2.</bibl>
                <bibl><hi rend="italic">Slovenski narod</hi>. “Razburjenost na Razkrižju in v
                    Štrigovi,” November 11, 1939, 2.</bibl>
                <bibl><hi rend="italic">Službeni list Kraljevske banske uprave Dravske
                    banovine</hi>. “Ukaz o spojitvah, razdružitvah in pregrupacijah občin in o
                    spremembah imena in sedeža občin v območju Dravske banovine,” October 16, 1937,
                    790.</bibl>
                <bibl><hi rend="italic">Varaždinske vijesti</hi>. “Župa Razkrižje Slovenska,”
                    September 14, 1994, 9.</bibl>
            </listBibl>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Other printed sources:</head>
                <bibl><hi rend="italic">A magyar szent korona országainak 1900. évi népszámlálása.
                    Első rész.</hi> Budapest: Magyar statisztikai közlemények, 1902.</bibl>
                <bibl><hi rend="italic">A magyar szent korona országainak 1910. évi népszámlálása.
                    Első rész.</hi> Budapest: Magyar statisztikai közlemények, 1912.</bibl>
                <bibl><hi rend="italic">Definitivni rezultati popisa stanovništva od 31 Januara 1921
                    god</hi>. Sarajevo: Državna štamparija, 1932.</bibl>
                <bibl><hi rend="italic">Konačni rezultati popisa stanovništva od 15 marta 1948
                    godine: Knjiga IX.</hi> Beograd: Savezni statistički zavod, 1954.</bibl>
                <bibl><hi rend="italic">Ustav Federativne Narodne Republike Jugoslavije</hi>. s.n.:
                    Belgrade, 1946.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
            <div type="summary" xml:lang="sl">
                <docAuthor>Stipica Grgić</docAuthor>
                <head>SPREJEMANJE MEJE, IZBIRANJE MEJE: ŠTRIGOVA IN RAZKRIŽJE V PRVI POLOVICI 20. STOLETJA</head>
                <head>POVZETEK</head>
            <p>Oblikovanje slovensko-hrvaške meje na področju Štrigova–Razkrižje je zgodba o
                kompleksnosti določanja državnih mej ter o dolgotrajnih učinkih, ki so vodili do
                njenih današnjih obrisov. Res je mogoče trditi, da je na določanje meje pustilo
                veliko sled pogosto spreminjanje administrativnih meja na tem področju v
                preteklosti, saj je samo od leta 1918 pa do leta 1946 področje občine Štrigova, od
                katere je bil leta 1937 odcepljen del in ustanovljena samostojna občina Razkrižje, z
                vidika središč, ki so bila zanj pristojna, celo devetkrat zamenjalo pripadnost med
                današnjo Madžarsko, Slovenijo in Hrvaško. Poleg tega lahko rečemo, da niti sami
                prebivalci tega kraja niso imeli popolnoma jasne predstave o svoji nacionalni
                identiteti ter da so se opredeljevali za prebivalce posameznih naselij ali pa
                regionalno kot Medžimurci.</p>
            <p>Kljub dolgoročnemu delovanju raznih lokalnih institucij, ki so se trudile z
                nacionalnim profiliranjem prebivalcev (šole, cerkev, občine), je konec druge
                svetovne vojne temu pretežno agrarnemu kraju prinesel nove težave. Gospodarska in
                politična nestabilnost je leta 1946 privedla do vse močnejšega profiliranja
                lokalnega prebivalstva v proslovensko in prohrvaško strujo, ki so se trudile, da bi
                področje prejšnjih občin Razkrižje in Štrigova spadalo v Slovenijo oziroma Hrvaško.
                Ker je spor teh dveh taborov vse bolj preraščal v nacionalni spor, so se v določanje
                meje vključile osrednje institucije socialistične Jugoslavije. Nadzorna komisija
                Zvezne skupščine je leta 1946 ustanovila posebno tričlansko komisijo (Lepa Perović,
                Vida Tomšič, Pavle Gregorić), ki je prišla na teren in po preučitvi vseh argumentov
                leta 1946 določila mejo, in sicer tako, da je severna tretjina spornega območja
                pripadla Sloveniji (vasi in zaselki Globoka, Veščica, Gibina, Razkrižje, Šafarsko in
                del vasi Banfi), preostali del pa je pripadel Hrvaški (vasi in zaselki Grabrovnik,
                Leskovec, Jalšovec, Sveti Urban, Stanetinec, Mali Leskovec, Robadije, Štrigova,
                Železna Gora in manjši del vasi Banfi). Ta začasna odločitev nikoli ni bila
                potrjena, a jo v bistvu še danes sprejemata tako slovenska kot hrvaška stran kot
                končno mejo dveh suverenih držav na tem področju.</p></div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>