<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Irredentist Actions
                    of the Slovenian Organisation of Yugoslav Nationalists (the ORJUNA) in Italy and
                    Austria (1922-1930)</title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename>Vasilije</forename>
                        <surname>Dragosavljević</surname>
                        <roleName>Dr.</roleName>
                        <affiliation>Istorijski Institut Beograd</affiliation>
                        <address>
                            <addrLine>Knez Mihajlova 36/II</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>SR-11000 Beograd</addrLine>
                        </address>
                        <email>v.dragosavljevic@yahoo.com</email>
                    </name>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>2019-09-19</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>
                    <orgName xml:lang="sl">Inštitut za novejšo zgodovino</orgName>
                    <orgName xml:lang="en">Institute of Contemporary History</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Kongresni trg 1</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>SI-1000 Ljubljana</addrLine>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>http://ojs.inz.si/pnz/article/view/292</pubPlace>
                <date>2019</date>
                <availability status="free">
                    <licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title xml:lang="sl">Prispevki za novejšo zgodovino</title>
                <title xml:lang="en">Contributions to Contemporary History</title>
                <biblScope unit="volume">59</biblScope>
                <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
                <idno type="ISSN">2463-7807</idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source, born digital.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc xml:lang="en">
                <p>Contributions to Contemporary History is one of the central Slovenian scientific
                    historiographic journals, dedicated to publishing articles from the field of
                    contemporary history (the 19th and 20th century).</p>
                <p>The journal is published three times per year in Slovenian and in the following
                    foreign languages: English, German, Serbian, Croatian, Bosnian, Italian, Slovak
                    and Czech. The articles are all published with abstracts in English and
                    Slovenian as well as summaries in English.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <projectDesc xml:lang="sl">
                <p>Prispevki za novejšo zgodovino je ena osrednjih slovenskih znanstvenih
                    zgodovinopisnih revij, ki objavlja teme s področja novejše zgodovine (19. in 20.
                    stoletje).</p>
                <p>Revija izide trikrat letno v slovenskem jeziku in v naslednjih tujih jezikih:
                    angleščina, nemščina, srbščina, hrvaščina, bosanščina, italijanščina, slovaščina
                    in češčina. Članki izhajajo z izvlečki v angleščini in slovenščini ter povzetki
                    v angleščini.</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="sl"/>
                <language ident="en"/>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords xml:lang="en">
                    <term>expansionism</term>
                    <term>ORJUNAVIT Slovenia</term>
                    <term>Organisation of Yugoslav Nationalists</term>
                    <term>Trieste</term>
                    <term>Istria</term>
                    <term>Carinthia</term>
                    <term>Fantovska zveza</term>
                    <term>Marko Kranjec</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords xml:lang="sl">
                    <term>ekspanzionizem</term>
                    <term>Orjunavit Slovenija</term>
                    <term>Organizacija jugoslovanskih nacionalistov</term>
                    <term>Trst</term>
                    <term>Istra</term>
                    <term>Koroška</term>
                    <term>Fantovska zveza</term>
                    <term>Marko Kranjec</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change>
                    <date>2019-02-12</date>
                    <name>Neja Blaj Hribar</name>
                    <desc>Pretvorba iz DOCX v TEI, dodatno kodiranje</desc>
                </change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <docAuthor>Vasilije Dragosavljević<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn1" n="*"><hi rend="bold">Dr., Istorijski Institut Beograd, Knez Mihajlova 36/II, SR-11000 Beograd, </hi><ref target="mailto:v.dragosavljevic@yahoo.com"><hi rend="bold">v.dragosavljevic@yahoo.com</hi></ref></note></docAuthor>
            <docImprint>
                <idno type="cobissType">Cobiss tip: 1.01</idno>
                <idno type="UDC">UDC: 613.888.15: 618.39(497.1)"1918/1991"</idno>
            </docImprint>
            <div type="abstract" xml:lang="sl">
                <head>IZVLEČEK</head>
                <head>IREDENTISTIČNE AKCIJE SLOVENSKE
                    ORGANIZACIJE JUGOSLOVANSKIH NACIONALISTOV (ORJUNE) V ITALIJI IN AVSTRIJI
                    (1922–1930)</head>
                <p><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">V prispevku so na podlagi razpoložljivega
                    gradiva iz Arhiva Republike Slovenije, Hrvaškega državnega arhiva ter strateških
                    načrtov in projektov, objavljenih v tiskovinah Organizacije jugoslovanskih
                    nacionalistov (Orjune), predstavljena idejna načela, na katerih so temeljili
                    ekspanzionistični načrti te organizacije. Posebna pozornost je posvečena
                    iredentističnim akcijam, ki jih je slovenska veje Orjune opravila na ozemlju
                    Italije (Trst, Gorica in Istra) in Avstrije (Koroška). Podrobno so opisana tudi
                    idejna načela in metode dela organizacij Orjunavit (Organizacija jugoslovanskih
                    nacionalistov v Italiji) in Fantovska zveza, ki sta Orjuni služili kot orodje za
                    delovanje na ozemlju Italije in Avstrije. Ekspanzionistične ideje, ki so bile
                    del Orjuninega ideološkega konstrukta in so se manifestirale z iredentističnimi
                    akcijami na ozemlju sosednjih držav, so bile globoko ukoreninjene v temeljnih
                    ideoloških načelih tega gibanja in posebnih zgodovinskih okoliščinah, v katerih
                    je nastalo. Orjunini ideologi so svoje ekspanzionistične načrte o ustanovitvi
                    Velike Jugoslavije, ki bi segala od Varne do Trsta in od Szegeda do Soluna,
                    predstavljali kot boj za ustanovitev enotnega in celovitega etničnega telesa
                    Južnih Slovanov.</hi>
                    <hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Vodstvo Orjune je na podlagi
                        imperativa ohranitve etnične identitete slovenskega prebivalstva v obmejnih
                        italijanskih in avstrijskih pokrajinah zagovarjalo sistematično uporabo
                        organiziranega nasilja kot osnovnega orodja v boju za uresničitev svojih ciljev.
                        Zmerna in legitimno usmerjena uradna zunanja politika jugoslovanskih oblasti ter
                        oboroženi odpor uradnih varnostnih sil in paravojaških organizacij Italije in
                        Avstrije sta vodstvu Orjune preprečila, da bi s terorizmom doseglo svoje
                        zunanjepolitične cilje. Po drugi strani pa so se ekspanzionistične ideje, ki so
                        bile ena od glavnih značilnosti ideologije Orjune, v medvojnem obdobju ohranile
                        kot del idejnih konceptov vseh skrajnih desničarskih gibanj za jugoslovanski
                        integralizem, ki so z manjšimi ali večjimi spremembami sprejela idejne
                        konstrukte Organizacije jugoslovanskih nacionalistov.</hi></p>
                <p><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Ključne besede: ekspanzionizem, Orjunavit
                    Slovenija, Organizacija jugoslovanskih nacionalistov, Trst, Istra, Koroška,
                    Fantovska zveza, Marko Kranjec</hi>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="abstract">
                <head>ABSTRACT</head>
                <p><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">This paper aims to examine and analyse the documentation available in the Slovenian Historical Archives and the Croatian State Archives as well as the strategic plans and projects described on the pages of the ORJUNA printed pamphlets and bulletins in order to determine the ideological tenets that formed the basis of the foreign policy as conceived by the Organisation of Yugoslav Nationalists (the ORJUNA). The focus of this paper will be on the irredentist actions taken by the Slovenian branch of the ORJUNA, carried out in the territories of Italy (Trieste, Gorizia, and Istria) and Austria (Carinthia). Special attention will be paid to the ORJUNAVIT (Organisation of Yugoslav Nationalists in Italy) and Fantovska zveza (Slovenian Boys Union) organisations, which were effectively the instruments of the ORJUNA, carrying out its activities in the territories of Italy and Austria. The expansionist ideas that were part of the ORJUNA ideological constructs and their implementation, as manifested through irredentist actions carried out in the territory of Yugoslavia’s neighbouring countries, were firmly rooted in the fundamental ideological foundations of this movement and the specific historical circumstances in which it emerged. The ORJUNA ideologists presented their expansionist agenda to create a Greater Yugoslavia, extending over a vast territory from Varna to Trieste and from Szeged to Thessaloniki, as the ultimate result of the struggle to create a unified and all-encompassing ethnic body of South Slavs. </hi><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Guided by the imperative of
                    preserving the ethnic identity of the Slovenian population in the provinces
                    bordering on Italy and Austria, the ORJUNA leadership promoted the systematic
                    use of organised violence as the basic tool in the struggle to achieve its
                    goals. Due to the restrained and legitimately-oriented official foreign policy
                    of the Yugoslav governments, as well as in light of the armed resistance of the
                    Italian and Austrian official security forces and paramilitaries, the leadership
                    of the ORJUNA failed to achieve its foreign-political goals through the use of
                    terror. On the other hand,
                    the</hi><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve"> expansionist ideas that were one of the essential tenets of the ORJUNA’s ideology remained a part of the ideological concepts embraced by all far-right movements for the Yugoslav integralism in the interwar period, which, with slight modifications, adopted the ideological constructs advocated by the ORJUNA.</hi></p>
                <p><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">Keywords: expansionism, ORJUNAVIT Slovenia, Organisation of Yugoslav Nationalists, Trieste, Istria, Carinthia, Fantovska zveza, Marko Kranjec </hi></p>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div><p>The Organisation of Yugoslav Nationalists (the
                    ORJUNA)<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn2" n="1">
                        Originally, the name of the organisation was the Yugoslav Progressive
                        Nationalist Youth (JNNO). In May 1922, having changed its articles of
                        association, a new name was adopted – i.e. the Organisation of Yugoslav
                        Nationalists – the ORJUNA. </note> was established on 23 March 1921 in Split. Its founders came from the pre-war Yugoslav Nationalist Youth, which was an umbrella organisation that brought together ideologically rather diverse groups, associations, and individuals that advocated the idea of an integral Yugoslav nation. The ORJUNA was created at the time when the newly-established Yugoslav state was facing many challenges, ranging from the territorial pretensions of its neighbours, separatist movements, and conflicts between the proponents of the centralist concept and those who favoured federalism. The ORJUNA organisation was conceived as a bulwark of national and state Unitarianism, keeper of territorial integrity, and champion of the Yugoslav ethnic population, which had, in the wake of the Treaty of Versailles, found itself outside the borders that demarcated the Kingdom of Serbs, Croats and Slovenes.
                <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn3" n="2"> Mladen Djordjević,
                        “Organizacija jugoslovenskih nacionalista (ORJUNA),” <hi rend="italic">NSPM,</hi> Vol. XII, No. 1–4 (2006): 188–93. </note>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">Guided by these principles and resorting to solutions
                    offered by the ideologically similar movements from abroad (the Italian Fascism
                    and German National Socialism), the ORJUNA leadership formulated a singular
                    ideological system and devised a specific political practice that had no paragon
                    in the Yugoslav region. In the period between 1921 and 1923, the ORJUNA
                    established a number of affiliates throughout the territory of the Kingdom of
                    Serbs, Croats and Slovenes. The movement had its strongholds mostly in Dalmatia,
                    Slovenia, and Vojvodina, while its organisational units in Croatia, Macedonia,
                    Bosnia-Herzegovina, and Serbia were less developed.</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn4" n="3"> Branislav Gligorijević,
                        “Organizacija jugoslovenskih nacionalista (ORJUNA),” <hi rend="italic">Istorija XX veka: Zbornik radova V</hi> (Beograd, 1963),
                    326–31.</note><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve"> The movement was organised through committees, established on the local and regional level. The organisation was headed by the Central/Chief Committee, whereas the role of its executive body was assigned to its Directorate, which consisted of seven members and had its head office in Split. The president of the Central Committee was simultaneously the head of the Directorate and the leader of the entire movement. Due to a number of circumstances, such organisational structure was never fully implemented. In reality, heads of regional (provincial) committees acted independently, on their own, paying little concern to the instructions given by the Central Committee and the Directorate. The most eminent figure in the ORJUNA was Ljubo Leontić, who was the president of the Directorate in the period from 1923 to 1927, and who was more a symbol of its unity than effectively its leader.</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn5" n="4"> Ibid., 333–38.
                    </note><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve"> After 1925, due to the turbulent historical events that occurred in the political arena and conflicts within the organisation itself, the process of the ORJUNA’s gradual disintegration began to take place. The altered internal political context, pressures from the government, and conflicts between the Directorate and heads of the local committees resulted in a severe loss of membership and dissolution of a significant number of the movement’s local branches. After Ljubo Leontić left the ORJUNA in 1927, the movement underwent organisational restructuring. The General Secretariat was therefore established, headed by Miodrag Dimitrijević, while the headquarters of the movement were moved to Belgrade.</hi>
                <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn6" n="5"> Djordjević,
                        “Organizacija jugoslovenskih nacionalista,” 202–07.</note><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve"> In the 1927–1929 period, the new leadership failed to impose its authority over the other strongholds of the movement (in Slovenia, Belgrade, and Southern Serbia). Hence, when the January 6</hi>
                <hi rend="superscript" style="font-size:12pt">th</hi>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">Decree was promulgated and the Yugoslav parliamentarism
                    was suspended, the ORJUNA found itself unprepared and subject to profound
                    ideological and organisational confusion. Even though the royal dictatorial
                    regime abolished all political organisations (paradoxically, it also quashed the
                    ORJUNA, which was the only political organisation that espoused the ideology of
                    Yugoslav integralism), the remaining cells of the ORJUNA organisation continued
                    to be active in the early 1930s. They mostly carried out irredentist and
                    terrorist actions, disguising themselves as legal organisations such as the
                    National Defence and establishing new political groups and organisations. In
                    1929, these ORJUNA cells in the territory of Slovenia were brought together
                    within the Association of Fighters of Yugoslavia,</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn7" n="6"> SI AS 1931, 935-600-12 document:
                        Materijal goričke kvesture o Orjuni (report of 26 January 1929). SI AS 1931,
                        935-600-12, document: Elaborat o ORJUNI. </note>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">whereas the ORJUNA members from Dalmatia, Slavonia, and
                    Serbia continued their activities within the Yugoslav Action movement.</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn8" n="7"> Branislav
                        Gligorijević, “Politički pokreti i grupe sa nacionalsocijalističkom
                        ideologijom i njihova fuzija u Ljotićevom Zboru,” <hi rend="italic">Istorijski glasnik</hi>, No. 4 (1965): 41–43.</note>
            </p>
            <p><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve">The expansionist ideas that were part of the ORJUNA ideological construct and their implementation, as manifested through the irredentist actions carried out in the territory of Yugoslavia’s neighbouring countries, were firmly rooted in the fundamental notions from the ideology of this movement and the specific historical circumstances in which this movement came into being. Claiming that it was the direct heir of the political legacy of the Yugoslav Nationalist Youth (JNO), the ORJUNA saw itself as the torchbearer in the struggle of all Yugoslavs who strived for national independence. Given that during World War I, the Yugoslavs, led by Serbia and Montenegro, together with their allies, actively participated in the destruction of the Austro-Hungarian Empire, the ideologists of the ORJUNA movement expected that the Entente Powers would allow the creation of the Yugoslav state, which would include all the territories populated by South Slavs. The provisions of the Versailles Peace Treaty were a major disappointment for the ORJUNA ideologists who – disregarding the fact that the Kingdom of Serbs, Croats and Slovenes was among those that profited the most in terms of territorial enlargement in the wake of World War I – believed that Yugoslav interests were, to a large extent, unsatisfied and even jeopardised by the order established by the Treaty of Versailles. When reading articles such as </hi>
                <hi rend="italic" style="font-size:12pt">Diplomatija iredentizma</hi>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">(Diplomacy of Irredentism)</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn9" n="8"> “Diplomatija iredentizma,” <hi rend="italic">Pobeda</hi>, I, No. 7, 24 September 1921.
                    </note><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve"> and </hi><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve">Iz rupe u rupu </hi><hi style="font-size:12pt">(From One Hole to Another),</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn10" n="9"> “Iz rupe u rupu,” <hi rend="italic">Vidovdan</hi>, VI, No. 377, 15 January 1927.</note>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">it becomes clear that the ORJUNA ideologists were
                    dissatisfied with the political map established under the Treaty of Versailles
                    and the organisation of the League of Nations, which served “to break the bones
                    of small nations in a nice way”.</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn11" n="10"> Ibid. </note>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">The negative stance taken by the ORJUNA regarding the
                    existing borders of the Kingdom of Serbs, Croats and Slovenes and its eagerness
                    to change them in accordance with its agenda was most evidently expressed in the
                    resolution adopted at the ORJUNA assembly that took place in Split on 1 December
                    1923. Among other things, this document claims: “Faithful to its ideal of an
                    integral Yugoslavia, the ORJUNA shall make every effort to rectify all those
                    international treaties that have separated us from hundreds of thousands of our
                    blood brethren and which have been brought about as a result of foreign
                    imperialist violence and our own discord”.</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn12" n="11"> Niko Bartulović, <hi rend="italic">Od
                            revolucionarne omladine do ORJUNE: Istorijat jugoslovenskog omladinskog
                            pokreta</hi> (Split: ORJUNA, 1925), 113. </note>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve">The ORJUNA ideologists presented their expansionist agenda to create a Greater Yugoslavia, which would spread over a vast territory from Varna to Trieste and from Szeged to Thessaloniki, as a struggle to create a unified and all-encompassing ethnic body of South Slavs. Such attitude was explicitly articulated in the article </hi><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:12pt">Naš
                    put</hi><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve"> (Our Path),</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn13" n="12"> “Naš put,” <hi rend="italic">Pobeda</hi>, I, No. 1, 28 June 1921.
                    </note><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve"> which was published on the front page of the first issue of the ORJUNA publication </hi><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:12pt">Pobeda</hi><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve"> (Victory). In this article, an anonymous author made a list of all the tasks that the newly-established state would have to face, highlighting that one of its principal goals was to expand the Yugoslav state to the extent that its borders would eventually be identical to the ethnic ones. Calling upon the right to incorporate all territories belonging to Yugoslav ethnic groups, the ideologists of ORJUNA demanded the inclusion of Trieste, Gorizia, Istria, Rijeka (Fiume), Zadar, Carinthia, Baranja, Aegean Macedonia, and Bulgaria into the Kingdom of Serbs, Croats and Slovenes, which would consequently be renamed as Great Yugoslavia. The ORJUNA ideologists claimed that a unified Yugoslav nation was the main protagonist in the struggle against the anachronistic social and economic forces, religious fanaticism, ignorance, and backwardness.</hi>
                <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn14" n="13"> Ivo Lahman,
                        “Kulturno Jugoslovenstvo,” <hi rend="italic">Pobeda</hi>, I, No. 7, 24
                        September 1921.</note>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">Based on the theory first espoused by Prvislav Grisogono
                    in his pamphlet titled</hi>
                <hi rend="italic" style="font-size:12pt">Savremena nacionalna
                    pitanja</hi><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve"> (Questions of Modern Nationalism) that Slavic tribes used to live in an autochthonous form of democracy,</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn15" n="14"> Prvislav Grisogono,
                            <hi rend="italic">Savremena nacionalna pitanja</hi> (Split: ORJUNA,
                        1923), 7. </note>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">the ORJUNA ideologists described the fall of the Slavic
                    tribes under the feudal yoke of the Habsburg and Ottoman Empires as a stage of
                    regression in the political, cultural, and economic development of the Yugoslav
                    nation. The Yugoslav revolution, which had led to the destruction of the
                    Austro-Hungarian and the Ottoman Empires during the Balkan Wars and World War I,
                    was perceived as a victory of the progressive Yugoslav forces that fought
                    against the reactionary and backward political, cultural, and economic phenomena
                    (absolutism, clericalism, and feudalism). The primary political objective of the
                    ORJUNA leadership was to incorporate the parts of the Yugoslav nation located
                    outside the territory of the Kingdom of Serbs, Croats and Slovenes into their
                    mother country, whereby the capacities of the Yugoslav nation to carry out its
                    cultural and historical mission would be enhanced.</hi>
                <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn16" n="15"> “Jugoslovenska
                        misija,” <hi rend="italic">Pobeda</hi>, I, No. 19, 24 December 1921.
                    </note><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve"> In the article titled </hi><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:12pt">Jugoslovenska misija</hi>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">(Yugoslav Mission), an anonymous author pointed out that
                    all great nations had a mission to accomplish so as to partake in the humanity,
                    and that the mission of the Yugoslav nation as such was primarily to complete
                    the process of its unification by means of war and to create a greater Yugoslav
                    state, trumpeting that “our Liberation has stemmed from blood. The liberation of
                    our misfortunate brethren who still languish in servitude … will not come to
                    pass in any other way. Their liberation must also stem from our blood…”</hi>
                <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn17" n="16">
                    Ibid.</note><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve"> The ORJUNA ideologists believed that once the ethnic borders of its territory were attained, the historical mission of the Yugoslav nation would be to lead the struggle for the unification of all Slavic nations.</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn18" n="17"> The ideologists of
                        the ORJUNA were not clear about the way in which the unification of Slavic
                        countries was to be accomplished. Given that Russia, as the biggest Slavic
                        country, was at the time under the Bolshevik regime, which denied its
                        nationhood, it makes sense to ask how Russia could become involved in such
                        unification process – that is, whether the ORJUNA ideologists had plans to
                        carry out an armed intervention to topple the Bolshevik regime in the USSR.
                    </note><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve"> They argued that the Slavic peoples were a young race with much unused cultural potential that was destined to contribute to the renewal of the decadent Europe.</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn19" n="18"> J. M. Silobrćić,
                        “Naša borba,” <hi rend="italic">Orjuna</hi> (Ljubljana), 25 March 1923.
                    </note>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve">The notion held by the ORJUNA ideologists – that by realising its historical mission through the unification of all Slavs, the Yugoslav nation would effectively deliver the decadent European civilisation – actually revealed a messiah complex of its architects, whom it also provided with a rational explanation of the expansionistic actions taken by their followers. In other words, the ideologists of the ORJUNA found a rational explanation for their aggressive course of actions in the field of foreign policy by depicting their expansionist plans as an (altruistically motivated) struggle for the cultural and political improvement of the European community of nations. Their expansionistic agenda was most explicitly set forth in articles such as </hi>
                <hi rend="italic" style="font-size:12pt">Govor Predsednika Direktorijuma brata
                    Leontića</hi><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve"> (Speech Delivered by the President of the Directorate, Brother Leontić),</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn20" n="19"> “Govor Predsednika
                        Direktorijuma brata Leontića,” <hi rend="italic">Pobeda</hi>, V, No. 40,
                        date illegible. </note>
                <hi rend="italic" style="font-size:12pt">Makedonstvujuščima</hi><hi style="font-size:12pt">,</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn21" n="20"> “Makedonstvujuščima,” <hi rend="italic">Jugoslavija</hi> (Skopje), I, No. 43 28 February 1927.
                    </note><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve"> and </hi><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:12pt">Bugarska i
                    Jugoslavija</hi><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve"> (Bulgaria and Yugoslavia).</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn22" n="21"> “Bugarska i
                        Jugoslavija,” <hi rend="italic">Jugoslavija</hi> (Skopje), I, No. 5, 27
                        March 1927.</note>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve">The newspapers of the ORJUNA published articles that openly advocated the annexation of territories belonging to the neighbouring countries, i.e. Italy, Austria, Hungary, Romania, Bulgaria, Greece, Turkey, and Albania. A characteristic example of this can be seen in the congratulations sent by the ORJUNA paper </hi><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:12pt">Vidovdan</hi>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">to the royal family on the occasion of the birth of the
                    crown prince, which ends with the exclamation: “Long live the future Yugoslav
                    Emperor, the only ruler of Istria, Gorizia, and the Adriatic”.</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn23" n="22">
                        <hi rend="italic">Vidovdan</hi>, II, No. 82, 8 September 1923, 1.
                    </note>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve">A map published on the front page of the newspaper </hi><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:12pt">Yugoslavia</hi><hi style="font-size:12pt">,
                    the bulletin of the Belgrade-based ORJUNA committee, provides the most obvious
                    example of the full scope of the territorial pretensions that the ORJUNA had in
                    the neighbouring countries. On this map, Great Yugoslavia is presented as also
                    including the regions of Skadar and Debar, Malesia, Dobruja, the Thracian coast,
                    and Eastern Thrace, in addition to the territories already mentioned.</hi>
                <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn24" n="23">
                        <hi rend="italic">Jugoslavija</hi> (Belgrade), I, No. 14, 1 December 1927,
                        1.</note>
            </p>
                <figure>
                    <head>Figure 1: A Map of Great Yugoslavia</head>
                    <graphic url="slika_1.jpg" height="600px"/>
                    <p style="text-align:center">Jugoslavija (Belgrade), I, No. 14, the National Library of Serbia</p>
                </figure>
            <p><hi style="font-size:12pt">The ORJUNA saw Italy as the main obstacle to the
                    full-blown integration of all territories belonging to the body of the Yugoslav
                    ethnic groups. Mussolini – who presented himself as the leader of the
                    interventionist block that supported Gabriele D’Annunzio in Rijeka and gathered
                    war veterans with the catchphrase “mutilated victory” – placed foreign policy in
                    the very centre of the fascist ideology. The main obstacle to the Italian foray
                    into the Balkans was the Kingdom of Serbs, Croats and Slovenes, which was the
                    centre of the pro-French alliance Little Entente and stood as a guarantor of the
                    order established under the Treaty of Versailles in Central and Southeast
                    Europe. Aiming to destabilise the Kingdom of Serbs, Croats and Slovenes, the
                    fascist regime applied a series of politically subversive measures and terrorist
                    methods which, nevertheless, had poor results. Even before the March on Rome,
                    the Kingdom of Italy endeavoured in every way to obstruct the process of the
                    creation of the Kingdom of Serbs, Croats and Slovenes. The Italian pre-fascist
                    governments occupied Dalmatia; encouraged the formation of the Albanian
                    separatist organisation Kosovo Committee; provided arms and training to the
                    Albanian kachaks</hi>
                <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn25" n="24"> J.R.B. Bosworth,
                            <hi rend="italic">Mussolini’s Italy: Life under the Dictatorship
                            1915–1945</hi> (London: Penguin Books, 2006), 283, 284. </note>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">and financed their political wing, i.e. the Jemiet
                    political party; incited the so-called Christmas Rebellion, a separatist
                    uprising in Montenegro that took place on 6 January 1919; provided financial
                    support for the organisation of the Montenegrin Army in exile</hi>
                <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn26" n="25"> Branislav
                        Gligorijević, <hi rend="italic">Kralj Aleksandar Karadjordjević:
                            Srpsko-hrvatski spor</hi> (Belgrade: Zavod za udzbenike i nastavna
                        sredstva, 2002), 160–65. </note><hi style="font-size:12pt">; supported
                    the Austrian Heimwehr in the undeclared war between Yugoslavia and Austria over
                    Carinthia; and provided a tacit support to D’Annunzio’s adventurous campaign in
                    Rijeka. This multinational coalition of anti-Yugoslav forces created by Italy
                    before the end of World War I continued to receive support from the new fascist
                    regime, and therefore it continued to carry out its activities throughout the
                    interwar period.</hi>
                <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn27" n="26"> Milorad Ekmečić,
                            <hi rend="italic">Stvaranje Jugoslavije 1790-1918 II</hi> (Belgrade:
                        Prosveta, 1989), 820–25, 827.
                    </note><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve"> In the wake of World War I, the fascist regime established close ties with the Austrian Heimwehr, </hi><hi rend="color(222222)" style="font-size:12pt">Gyula Gömbös</hi><hi style="font-size:12pt">’ Party of Racial Defense in Hungary, and the circles at
                    the Bulgarian Court.</hi>
                <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn28" n="27"> Bosworth,
                        <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Mussolini’s Italy, </hi>284.
                    </note><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve">. In that way, it besieged the Kingdom of Serbs, Croats and Slovenes, which became surrounded by revisionist states whose anti-Yugoslav actions were coordinated by the fascist government in Rome. The ORJUNA’s publications paid much attention to all aspects of the anti-Yugoslav actions taken by the Italian fascist government. In articles such as </hi>
                <hi rend="italic" style="font-size:12pt">Dve
                    metode</hi><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve"> (Two Methods),</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn29" n="28"> “Dve metode,” <hi rend="italic">Pobeda</hi>, I, No. 6, 17 September 1921. </note>
                <hi rend="italic" style="font-size:12pt">Sacro egoism,</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn30" n="29"> “Sacro egoismo,”
                        <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Jugoslavija </hi>(Belgrade), II, No.
                        26, date illegible (year 1928). </note>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve">and </hi><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:12pt">Italija i naše duhovno
                    jedinstvo</hi><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve"> (Italy and Our Spiritual Unity),</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn31" n="30"> “Italija i naše
                        duhovno jedinstvo,” <hi rend="italic">Pobeda</hi>, VII, No. 10, date
                        illegible (year 1927). </note>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve">the ORJUNA ideologists expressed their view of the Italian foreign policy as, essentially, a continuation of the imperialist legacy of the deceased Habsburg Monarchy, stressing that the same methods would be applied to settle accounts with Italy as was the case with the Austro-Hungarian Empire. In articles such as </hi>
                <hi rend="italic" style="font-size:12pt">Musolinijevi ljudi u Trstu pale
                    jugoslovenske domove</hi>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">(Mussolini’s Henchmen Setting Yugoslav Homes on Fire in
                    Trieste),</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn32" n="31">
                        “Musolinijevi ljudi u Trstu pale jugoslovenske domove,” <hi rend="italic">Pobeda</hi>, V, No. 72, date illegible (year 1925). </note>
                <hi rend="italic" style="font-size:12pt">Iz zemlje naše
                    tuge</hi><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve"> (From Our Country of Grief)</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn33" n="32"> “Iz zemlje naše
                        tuge,” <hi rend="italic">Orjuna</hi>, I, No. 30, 15 July 1923.</note>
                <hi rend="italic" style="font-size:12pt">Nova fašistička divljaštva u
                    Goričkoj</hi><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve"> (New Fascist Barbarism in Gorizia),</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn34" n="33"> “Nova fašistička
                        divljaštva u Goričkoj,” <hi rend="italic">Pobeda</hi> Vi, No. 66, date
                        illegible (year 1926).</note>
                <hi rend="italic" style="font-size:12pt">Crnim
                    košuljama</hi><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve"> (To the Blackshirts)</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn35" n="34"> “Crnim košuljama,”
                            <hi rend="italic">Jugoslavija</hi> (Skopje), I, No. 2, 20 February 1927.
                    </note><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve"> i </hi><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:12pt">Fašističko pokrštavanje</hi>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">(Fascist Evangelisation),</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn36" n="35"> “Fašističko pokrštavanje,” <hi rend="italic">Jugoslavija</hi> (Belgrade), II, No. 26, date illegible
                        (year 1928). </note>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">the authors called public attention to the brutal terror
                    and assimilation</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn37" n="36"> Boris Mlakar, “Radical nationalism and fascist
                        elements in political movements in Slovenia between the two world wars,” <hi rend="italic">Slovene studies</hi>, No. 1 (2009): 7.
                    </note><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve"> that the Yugoslav minority suffered under the fascist regime.</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn38" n="37"> Out of nine death
                        sentences pronounced by the fascist Special Court for State Defense, in
                        eight cases the sentences were passed against Slavic irredentists. (See:
                        Stanley G. Payne, <hi rend="italic">A History of Fascism 1914–1945</hi>
                        (Wisconsin: University of Wisconsin Press, 2003), 117).</note>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve">In the period from 1920 to 1922 only, the members of the fascist militia smashed and demolished the premises of more than 150 centres of cultural, educational, and economic organisations belonging to the Yugoslav ethnic minority in Italy. The most flagrant of these actions was the burning of the Trieste National Hall (13 July 1920) and the Trieste Workers Cultural Centre (10 February 1921) as well as the trashing and destruction of the premises of the editorial staff and printing stores of newspapers </hi>
                <hi rend="italic" style="font-size:12pt">Delo</hi><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve"> (10 February 1921)</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn39" n="38"> Tone Ferenc, Milica
                        Kacin-Wohinz and Tone Zorn, <hi rend="italic">Slovenci v zamejstvu: Pregled
                            zgodovine 1918–1945</hi> (Ljubljana: Državna založba Slovenije, 1974),
                        48–51.</note><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve"> and </hi><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:12pt">Edinost</hi><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve"> (13 July 1920).</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn40" n="39"> Milica Kacin-Wohinz,
                            <hi rend="italic">Primorski Slovenci pod Italijansko zasedbo</hi>
                        (Maribor, 1972), 313, 314.</note>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">Following the seizure of power by the fascist regime, the
                    entire state apparatus was employed to put even more pressure on the Yugoslav
                    population. Discriminatory laws were enforced that gradually pushed Slovenian
                    language out of education and public use until the regime finally managed to ban
                    and dismantle all cultural, educational, and economic organisations of the
                    Yugoslav minority in 1928.</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn41" n="40"> Milica Kacin-Wohinz, <hi rend="italic">Prvi
                            antifašizem v Evropi</hi> (Koper: Lipa, 1990), 24.</note>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve">Every day, the ORJUNA papers would publish news about the activities of the Italian government and the fascist party in Trieste, Istria, Gorizia, and Dalmatia. </hi>
            </p>
            <p><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve">In articles such as </hi><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve">Talijanski fašisti hoće da osnuju borbenu organizaciju u Splitu </hi><hi style="font-size:12pt">(Italian Fascists Want to Form a Military Organisation in
                    Split)</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn42" n="41">
                        “Talijanski fašisti hoće da osnuju borbenu organizaciju u Splitu,” <hi rend="italic">Pobeda,</hi> V, No. 69, date illegible (year 1926).
                    </note><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve"> and</hi>
                <hi rend="italic" style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve">Lega Nazionale u Šibeniku </hi><hi style="font-size:12pt">(Lega Nazionale in Šibenik),</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn43" n="42"> “Lega Nazionale u Šibeniku,” <hi rend="italic">Pobeda</hi>, VII, No. 4, 29 January 1927.
                    </note><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve"> the authors warned the general public about the subversive activities that the Fascist Party carried out among the members of the Italian ethnic minority in Dalmatia, calling upon the public authorities to take appropriate measures. The ORJUNA papers would also publish news about the many border incidents and incursions of the fascist militia into the territory of the Kingdom of Serbs, Croats and Slovenes. The ORJUNA papers stressed that its members were the only well-organised force that resisted such incursions and thus made great sacrifices for the Homeland.</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn44" n="43"> “Svesni orijunaši na
                        granici u službi Otadžbine,” <hi rend="italic">Pobeda</hi>, VI, No. 18, date
                        illegible (year 1926).
                    </note><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve"> In articles such as </hi><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:12pt">Hrvatski borac</hi>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">(Croatian Fighter),</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn45" n="44"> “Hrvatski borac,” <hi rend="italic">Budućnost,</hi> I, No. 3, 30 December 1922. </note>
                <hi rend="italic" style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve">Poslednji Mohikanci </hi><hi style="font-size:12pt">(The Last Mohicans)</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn46" n="45"> “Poslednji Mohikanci,” <hi rend="italic">Budućnost,</hi> I, No. 3, 30 December 1922.
                    </note><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve"> and </hi><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:12pt">Musolini izmišlja tako zvano Crnogorsko
                    pitanje</hi><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve"> (Mussolini Invents the so-called the Montenegro Question),</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn47" n="46"> “Musolini izmišlja
                        tako zvano Crnogorsko pitanje,” <hi rend="italic">Pobeda</hi>, VII, No. 3,
                        22 December
                    1927.</note><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve"> the authors accused the fascist government of supporting the separatist movements in Croatia and Montenegro. Articles such as </hi><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:12pt">Albansko pitanje</hi>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">(The Albanian Question),</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn48" n="47"> “Albansko pitanje,” <hi rend="italic">Pobeda</hi>, VII, No. 9, date illegible (approximately
                        February–March 1927). </note>
                <hi rend="italic" style="font-size:12pt">Pred Musolinijev podvig na Balkanu</hi>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">(Ahead of Mussolini’s Feat in the Balkans)</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn49" n="48"> “Pred Musolinijev
                        podvig na Balkanu,” <hi rend="italic">Pobeda</hi>, VII, No. 10, date
                        illegible (approximately February-March 1927).</note>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve">i </hi><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:12pt">Natezanje sa Musolinijem</hi>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">(Bickering with Mussolini)</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn50" n="49"> “Natezanje sa Musolinijem,” <hi rend="italic">Pobeda</hi>, VII, No. 29, 29 April 1927. </note>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve">make it clear that the ORJUNA papers paid close attention to the steps taken by the Italian government in Albania. The authors agreed in their opinions that the Tirana Pact served to strengthen the Italian influence in the Eastern Adriatic and that it posed a threat to the Kingdom of Serbs, Croats and Slovenes. The ORJUNA ideologists believed that Italy would use its newly-established influence in Albania to incite a rebellion of kachaks in the territory of Old Serbia (Kosovo and Metohija as well as Macedonia), which would provide them with an excuse to attack the Kingdom of Serbs, Croats and Slovenes. Many articles published in the ORJUNA papers – such as </hi>
                <hi rend="italic" style="font-size:12pt">Sloboda Jadranskog
                    mora</hi><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve"> (Freedom of the Adriatic Sea)</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn51" n="50"> Ljubo Leontić,
                        “Sloboda Jadranskog mora,” <hi rend="italic">Jugoslovenski Jadran</hi> – <hi rend="italic">a special ORJUNA publication published on the occasion of
                            its meeting in Dubrovnik on 23 and 24 March 1926</hi>.
                    </note><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve"> and </hi><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve">Italija na Sredozemnom moru </hi><hi style="font-size:12pt">(Italy in the Mediterranean Sea)</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn52" n="51"> “Italija na Sredozemnom moru,”
                            <hi rend="italic">Vidovdan</hi>, VI, No. 397, 22 May 1927. </note><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve"> – cautioned that Italy would sooner or later attack the Kingdom of Serbs, Croats and Slovenes with the aim of seizing the territories that had been promised to it under the Treaty of London. In articles such as </hi>
                <hi rend="italic" style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve">Musolinijeva agresivnost i naša spoljna politika </hi><hi style="font-size:12pt">(Mussolini’s Aggressiveness and Our Foreign
                    Policy),</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn53" n="52">
                        “Musolinijeva agresivnost i naša spoljna politika,” <hi rend="italic">Pobeda</hi>, VII, No. 28, 15 July 1927. </note><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve"> authors warned the public that the aggressive plotting of the fascist Italy was backed by Great Britain, while France remained indifferent to the Yugoslav-Italian conflict. The Kingdom of Serbs, Croats and Slovenes was therefore mostly left to its own devices. Notwithstanding such grim prospects, the ORJUNA members had no doubts about the outcome of an armed conflict between Italy and the Kingdom of Serbs, Croats and Slovenes. Their firm belief that they would be victorious in such a war was most explicitly expressed in the article </hi>
                <hi rend="italic" style="font-size:12pt">Naš prekomorski sused i mi</hi>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">(Our Overseas Neighbor and Ourselves),</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn54" n="53"> “Naš prekomorski
                        sused i mi,” <hi rend="italic">Pobeda</hi>, V, No. 31, date illegible (year
                        1925).</note><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve"> whose anonymous author states that in case of war, the mighty Italian fleet would surely seize the Yugoslav islands and destroy the coastal towns, but that the army of the Kingdom of Serbs, Croats and Slovenes would advance into the River Po valley and conquer large Italian cities, thus annulling the conquest made by the Italian naval forces. In its campaign aimed against the aggressive policies of the fascist Italy, the ORJUNA (itself strongly anti-communist) even employed a tactic of cooperating with the left-wing opposition to Mussolini’s regime.</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn55" n="54"> Boris Mlakar, “Zaton
                        Organizacije jugoslovanskih nacionalistov - Orjune pod budnim očesom
                        italjanskih fašističnih oblasti,” <hi rend="italic">Prispevki za novejšo
                            zgodovino</hi>, No. 2 (2013):
                    58.</note><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve"> A testimony to this can be found in the article </hi><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:12pt">Protiv rata sa
                    Jugoslavijom</hi><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve"> (Against the War with Yugoslavia),</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn56" n="55"> “Protiv rata sa
                        Jugoslavijom,” <hi rend="italic">Vidovdan</hi>, II, No. 90, 6 October 1923.
                    </note><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve"> a declaration made by the antifascist left-wing organisation Head Committee for Workers’ Defence against Fascism, published on the front page of the ORJUNA paper </hi>
                <hi rend="italic" style="font-size:12pt">Vidovdan</hi><hi style="font-size:12pt">.
                    Reacting to the provocations of Italian fascists in the border zone, the ORJUNA
                    action squads made various forays into the Italian territory, attacking Italian
                    military garrisons and fascist militia posts.</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn57" n="56"> Kacin-Wohinz, <hi rend="italic">Prvi antifašizem v Evropi</hi>, 51, 58, 60, 61.</note><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve"> In the early 1920s, the ORJUNA action squads came into conflicts with the Italian Army and fascist militia, mostly as a defensive reaction. Of these defensive actions, it is worth mentioning two events taking place in October 1922 and August 1923 respectively, when the ORJUNA drove out a fascist militia squad that tried to occupy Sušak and when the ORJUNA members clashed with the Italian Army on Mount Triglav.</hi>
                <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn58" n="57"> Gligorijević,
                        Organizacija jugoslovenskih nacionalista, 332, 349. </note>
            </p>
            <p><hi style="font-size:12pt">Reacting to such outright provocations of the fascist
                    Italy and the aggressive stance assumed by its satellites, in the mid-1920s, the
                    ORJUNA formed its secret organisations in the territories of Italy and Austria.
                    The key role in their establishment was played by the members of its Slovenian
                    branch (the local committees in Ljubljana and Maribor), namely Marko Kranjec,
                    Andrej Verbič, Anton Kukec, and Ivan Rehar. The most notable ORJUNA border-zone
                    organisation was ORJUNAVIT (abbreviation for the Organisation of Yugoslav
                    Nationalists in Italy), founded in 1925 in the Julian March. When ORJUNAVIT was
                    established, the ORJUNA members used the existing organisation called the TIGR
                    (abbreviation for Trieste-Istria-Gorizia-Rijeka), which had been founded in 1924
                    in Trieste,</hi>
                <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn59" n="58"> Milica
                        Kacin-Wohinz, <hi rend="italic">Narodnoobrambno gibanje primorskih Slovencev
                            v letih 1921–1928 II</hi> (Koper: Lipa; Trst: Založništvo tržaškega
                        tiska,1977),
                    431.</note><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve"> and brought together the members of the Slovenian and Croatian ethnic minorities living in the Italian territory.</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn60" n="59"> SI AS 1931,
                        935-600-12 document: <hi rend="italic">Materijal goričke kvestre o
                            Orjuni</hi> (report dated 10 August 1936). </note>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">Initially, this organisation, led by the lawyer Ivan
                    Marija Čok,</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn61" n="60"><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve"> The founder and leader of the Yugoslav irredentist organisation TIGR (abbreviation for Trieste-Istria-Gorizia-Rijeka) in Italy. In 1926, TIGR became a part of the ORJUNA border-zone terrorist organisation ORJUNAVIT. In 1931, during the period of dictatorship, Čok formed the organisation Alliance of Yugoslav Emigrant Associations in the Julian March. In the activities of this organisation, Čok relied on the support from Drago Marušić, Ban of the Drava Banovina, a former ORJUNA member and a protégé of the Association of Fighters of Yugoslavia BOJ. At the elections held in 1935, he ran on the electoral list of Bogoljub Jevtić. Due to his engagement in the Yugoslav National Party, the regime of Prime Minister Milan Stojadinović and the Cvetković-Maček government repressed the association of emigrants from the Julian March. </hi></note><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve"> was engaged primarily in cultural and educational activities aimed at the Slovenian and Croatian population in the Italian territory.</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn62" n="61"> SI AS 1931,
                        935-600-8 document: <hi rend="italic">Političke stranke na Primoriju</hi>.
                    </note>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">It did not have a clearly defined ideology. Instead, it
                    was a heterogeneous group of political and cultural cliques that had a wide
                    range of political views.</hi>
                <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn63" n="62"> Milica
                        Kacin-Wohinz, “Slovenci i Hrvati pod Fašističkom Italijom,” <hi rend="italic">Jugoslovenski istorijski časopis</hi>, No. 3, (1987): 90.
                    </note>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">According to the account given by Dorče Sardoč (one of
                    the activists of the TIGR organisation), the youth that gathered within the TIGR
                    and, later on, the ORJUNAVIT came from various political groups (ranging from
                    communists to Christian socialists and liberals). All of these groups emphasised
                    that their political differences were of secondary importance and that they all
                    subscribed to the ideal that they shared: to make Venezia Giulia a part of the
                    Yugoslav territory.</hi>
                <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn64" n="63"> Dorče Sardoč, <hi rend="italic">Tigrova sled: Pričevanje o uporu primorskih ljudi pod
                            fašizmom</hi> (Ljubljana, 1983).</note>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">This assertion was further confirmed by the fact that one
                    of the arrested activists claimed to the Italian authorities that he was a
                    member of the Italian Communist Party and the ORJUNA.</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn65" n="64"> Kacin-Wohinz, <hi rend="italic">Prvi antifašizem v Evropi</hi>, 254, 255.</note>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">Led by Marko Kranjec, the TIGR joined about 20 other
                    cultural and educational organisations of the Yugoslav ethnic minority, which
                    united in the ORJUNAVIT (abbreviation for the Organisation of Yugoslav
                    Nationalists in Italy) in December 1925.</hi>
                <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn66" n="65"> SI AS 1931,
                        935-600-12 document:
                        <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Materijal goričke kvestre o Orjuni </hi>(report
                        dated 10 August 1936).</note>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">The management board of this newly-established
                    organisation was formed by Kranjec and Verbič from the ORJUNA and by Gaberšek,
                    Rejec and Kocijančić as the representatives of the Yugoslav ethnic minority
                    organisations in Italy.</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn67" n="66"> Kacin-Wohinz, <hi rend="italic">Prvi antifašizem v
                            Evropi</hi>, 54, 55.</note>
            </p>
            <p><hi style="font-size:12pt">The ORJUNAVIT leadership divided the Julian March
                    territory into six operative zones and established an armed squad and an
                    intelligence network, managed by a commander, in each of them.</hi>
                <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn68" n="67"> SI AS 1931,
                        935-600-12 document:
                        <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Materijal goričke kvestre o Orjuni </hi>(report
                        dated 20 December 1927). </note><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve"> According to the information of the Italian government, an important role in the organisation of ORJUNAVIT activities in Italy was played by its Great Chief, the Chetnik military commander Ilija Trifunović Birčanin, who marshalled the Yugoslav irredentist actions in the Julian March based on his experience with the Chetnik actions carried out in Macedonia between 1903 and 1912.</hi>
                <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn69" n="68"> SI AS 1931,
                        935-600-12 document:
                        <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Materijal goričke kvestre o Orjuni </hi>(report
                        dated 10 August 1936). </note><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve"> Consequently, the ORJUNA members in Italy organised themselves in troikas that kept their activities top secret.</hi>
                <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn70" n="69"> SI AS 1931,
                        935-600-12 document:
                        <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Materijal goričke kvestre o Orjuni </hi>(report
                        dated 20 December 1927).  SI AS 1931, 935-600-12
                        document:
                        <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Materijal goričke kvestre o Orjuni </hi>(report
                        dated 10 August 1936).
                    </note><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve"> Recruited from the Yugoslav ethnic minority in Italy, Yugoslav refugees from the Julian March, and Italian antifascists, the ORJUNAVIT members spread antifascist propaganda, gathered intelligence and information of military and political importance, and sabotaged military posts and transport infrastructure.</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn71" n="70"> SI AS 1931,
                        935-600-12 document: <hi rend="italic">Elaborat o Orjuni</hi>. </note><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve"> According to the information of the Italian Ministry of Internal Affairs in the 1926–1930 period, the ORJUNAVIT carried out 99 acts of sabotage and terrorism.</hi>
                <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn72" n="71"> Kacin-Wohinz,
                        “Slovenci i Hrvati pod Fašističkom Italijom,” 91. SI AS 1931, 935-600-12
                        document: <hi rend="italic">Materijal goričke kvestre o Orjuni.</hi>
                    </note>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">Certain documents indicate that when carrying out such
                    tasks, the ORJUNAVIT cooperated with Andreas-Hofer-Bund, an illegal German
                    ethnic minority organisation affiliated with the Austrian fascist organisation
                    Heimwehr, which was active in South Tyrol.</hi>
                <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn73" n="72"> SI AS 1931,
                        935-600-12 document:
                        <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Materijal goričke kvestre o Orjuni </hi>(report
                        dated 1 March 1929). SI AS 1931, 935-600-12
                        document: <hi rend="italic">Predmet ORJUNA</hi>.</note>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">This fact is seemingly paradoxical, given that the ORJUNA
                    was openly antagonistic to Heimwehr with regard to the question of the Austrian
                    province of Carinthia. The biggest armed actions carried out by the ORJUNAVIT
                    included the assault on the printing shop of a local fascist paper in Trieste
                    and the assault on the Italian military garrison in Postojna.</hi>
                <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn74" n="73"> ARS, SI AS 1931,
                        935-600-12 document: <hi rend="italic">Predmet ORJUNA</hi>.</note>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">The first action, carried out by the Action Squad in the
                    Italian territory, was the assault in Prestranek. On 3 April 1926, a group of
                    five armed ORJUNA members crossed the border, broke into the ticket office at
                    the Prestranek railway station, threatened the Italian clerks with firearms, and
                    walked off with a sum of 246,000 lire. On the way back, before they entered the
                    Yugoslav territory, they were intercepted by a fascist militia troop. A shootout
                    ensued in which two ORJUNA members and two fascist militia members lost their
                    lives. The money stolen by the ORJUNA members was intended for the acquisition
                    of firearms for the ORJUNAVIT fighters operating in Italy.</hi>
                <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn75" n="74"> Robert Čop, ORJUNA
                        prototip političke organizacije (Graduation thesis defended at the Faculty
                        of Social Sciences in Ljubljana, 2006) 72. </note>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">Another significant armed action, carried out by the
                    ORJUNAVIT in Italy, was the assault on the National Home in Trieste, which was
                    the seat of the local branch of the Fascist Party and the editorial office of
                    the local fascist paper. On 8 March 1926, a small group of ORJUNAVIT activists
                    (Jakob Geržem i Herman Šolar)</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn76" n="75"> Kacin-Wohinz, <hi rend="italic">Prvi antifašizem v
                            Evropi</hi>,
                    58.</note><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve"> machine-gunned the façade of the building and threw a bomb at the editorial office premises.</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn77" n="76"> Čop, ORJUNA, 71.
                    </note>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">On 3 November 1926, the ORJUNA members planted an
                    explosive device in the army barracks of the fascist militia in Saint Peter in
                    Krain, killing three fascist militiamen. In the first half of 1927, the ORJUNA
                    members performed several armed attacks on the fascist militia border patrols,
                    killing several more fascist militiamen.</hi>
                <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn78" n="77"> Kacin-Wohinz, <hi rend="italic">Prvi antifašizem v Evropi</hi>, 60, 61.</note>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">In addition to terrorist actions, the ORJUNAVIT also
                    engaged in various military intelligence activities. When the ORJUNAVIT was
                    founded in 1926, the ORJUNA’s Great Chief Marko Kranjec established contacts
                    with the intelligence unit of the Drava Division Corps and the Ministry of
                    Defence, which provided financial resources to set up the ORJUNAVIT intelligence
                    network in Italy.</hi>
                <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn79" n="78"> SI AS 1931,
                        935-600-12 document:
                        <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Materijal goričke kvestre o Orjuni </hi>(report
                        dated 13 March 1929). </note>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">The ORJUNAVIT and the Yugoslav Army had close
                    connections, as attested to by the fact that the intelligence unit of this
                    organisation that covered the area stretching from Postojna to Vipava was headed
                    by Stanko Lavrenčić – an active-duty officer of the Yugoslav Army (as well as an
                    emigrant from Postojna).</hi>
                <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn80" n="79"> Kacin-Wohinz, <hi rend="italic">Prvi antifašizem v Evropi</hi>, 52.</note>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">A part of the intelligence obtained by the ORJUNAVIT was
                    also forwarded to the French Consulate,</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn81" n="80">
                        <hi rend="color(1D2228)" xml:space="preserve">Later on, during 1930s, the ORJUNA activists also cooperated with the British Secret Intelligence Service. In the wake of World War II, the former ORJUNA intelligence network in Italy and Austria was reorganised and became a part of the National Defense. It intensified its actions and carried out various intelligence tasks, acts of sabotage, and other actions for the British Intelligence Service. </hi>(Jerca
                        Vodušek Starič, <hi rend="italic">Slovenski špijoni in SOE 1938</hi>–<hi rend="italic">1942</hi> (Ljubljana: samozal., 2002), 111, 112, 143, 150,
                        161).</note><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve"> which, in return, partially funded the ORJUNA secret service in Italy.</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn82" n="81"> SI AS 1931,
                        935-600-12 document: <hi rend="italic">Predmet ORJUNA</hi>. </note>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">The ORJUNA agents obtained some of the information by
                    bribing Italian Army officers and fascist militia, while funds for that purpose
                    were provided through the Yugoslav Consulate in Trieste.</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn83" n="82"> SI AS 1931, 935-600-12 document:
                        <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Materijal goričke kvestre o Orjuni </hi>(report
                        dated 10 August 1936). </note>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">Many servicemen belonging to the Yugoslav ethnic minority
                    were among the ranks of the Italian Army and fascist militia, which made it
                    easier for the ORJUNAVIT to infiltrate these formations with the aim of setting
                    up its intelligence network within their ranks. With the help of such
                    collaborators, the ORJUNAVIT activists would, on many occasions, carry out their
                    subversive intelligence and sabotage activities dressed in the uniforms of the
                    fascist militia and the Italian Army.</hi>
                <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn84" n="83"> Kacin-Wohinz, <hi rend="italic">Prvi antifašizem v Evropi</hi>, 60.</note>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">The ORJUNA intelligence service was not active only in
                    the Italian territory, as its agents managed to gain long-term insight into the
                    official correspondence of the Italian Consulate in Ljubljana.</hi>
                <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn85" n="84"> SI AS 1931,
                        935-600-12 document: <hi rend="italic">Predmet ORJUNA</hi>.</note>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">At that point, the ORJUNA members uncovered information
                    indicating that a number of agents working for the Italian secret service had
                    infiltrated their ranks. This information led to a conflict within the ORJUNA
                    organisation itself. On Marko Kranjec’s orders, the ORJUNA members killed Eduard
                    Perić, a member of the organisation whose name was discovered on the list of the
                    Italian secret agents at the Italian Consulate in Ljubljana. Following this
                    assassination, Kranjec was arrested, together with his closest collaborators
                    Andrej Verbič and Anton Kukec.</hi>
                <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn86" n="85"> SI AS 1931,
                        935-600-12 document:
                        <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Materijal goričke kvestre o Orjuni </hi>(report
                        dated 12 December 1928). </note>
            </p>
            <p><hi style="font-size:12pt">The irredentist ORJUNA actions gained new momentum with
                    the events that took place on 18 June 1926. On that day, an ORJUNA unit in
                    Ljubljana organised a gathering of its members on the occasion of a flag
                    consecration ceremony, after which the members formed a procession that was
                    supposed to march through Ljubljana. Some 800 ORJUNA members headed toward the
                    centre of the city. There they came across police cordons that stopped them on
                    their way to the building of the Italian Consulate in the Prešernova ulica
                    street to prevent any possibility of anti-Italian protests. After a brief
                    argument with Leontić and Kranjec, who were leading the crowd, the police
                    commissioners directed the ORJUNA procession into the streets that go around the
                    Italian Consulate. A group of approximately 150 ORJUNA members became infuriated
                    with the police reaction, so they attacked the police cordon, trying to push
                    through it and get to the Italian Consulate. Following a ten-minute brawl, in
                    which the police used rubber truncheons and sabres, several ORJUNA members
                    opened fire at the police, which responded in kind. After the shooting, in which
                    more than 70 bullets were fired, the ORJUNA members ran off. Three people were
                    seriously wounded in the skirmish, while another six policemen and three ORJUNA
                    members suffered minor injuries. Following this incident, 68 ORJUNA members were
                    arrested and another 18 were taken into custody and charged with attacking
                    police officers. The ORJUNA leaders accused the police forces that they opened
                    fire first, claiming that the ORJUNA members merely reacted in self-defence. The
                    trial against the perpetrators of this incident did not result in any verdicts
                    due to the lack of evidence (as they fled, the ORJUNA members threw their guns
                    in the river Ljubljanica).</hi>
                <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn87" n="86"> АY, fund no. 63,
                        file no. 83/1926, Police report by Police Department in Ljubljana (2 July
                        1926).</note><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve"> Pressing charges against the ORJUNA unit in Ljubljana for endangering the public safety and order, the Government officially banned it on 29 June 1926. However, the members of the Slovenian ORJUNA continued to take actions regardless of the government prohibition, using their bulletins to ridicule the state authorities. Following this incident, the members of the Slovenian ORJUNA, led by Kranjec, reorganised themselves and continued resolutely to carry out their underground irredentist activities in Italy. In the first half of 1927, the ORJUNA organised its units in Trieste and initiated a series of field actions, of which the establishment of the clandestine paper </hi>
                <hi rend="italic" style="font-size:12pt">Borba</hi><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve"> should be pointed out.</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn88" n="87"> Kacin-Wohinz, <hi rend="italic">Prvi antifašizem v Evropi</hi>, 221–23.</note>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">In May 1927, the military authorities in Sušak warned
                    police officers that the local ORJUNA members were planning to take advantage of
                    Mussolini’s visit to Trieste on 24 May to assassinate him. As a result of that
                    timely information, the police managed to arrest the ringleaders behind this
                    plan, thus preventing a severe diplomatic incident.</hi>
                <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn89" n="88"> CSA, Režimske i
                        reakcionarne organizacije – grupa VII, document No. 858. </note>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">In November 1927, the Drava Division Corps command
                    informed the General Staff that the ORJUNA action squads had made an incursion
                    into the Italian territory and opened fire on the Italian Army, the police, and
                    the fascist militia. The command pointed out that the ORJUNA members stated they
                    carried out those actions following the orders of the military and underlined
                    the dangers of spreading such false news.</hi>
                <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn90" n="89"> CSA, Režimske i
                        reakcionarne organizacije – grupa VII, document No.
                    858.</note><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve"> During 1928, the best members of the ORJUNA action squads from Slovenia were assembled to form a special combat unit called Crni Vrazi (Black Devils), which was supposed to carry out terrorist actions in Italy.</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn91" n="90"> SI AS 1931,
                        935-600-12 document:
                        <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Materijal goričke kvestre o Orjuni </hi>(report
                        dated 5 June 1928). </note>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">In 1928, the ORJUNA squads, reorganised in that manner,
                    carried out a series of attacks on the fascist militia border patrols. The most
                    dramatic of these were the assault on 20 February (when three fascist militiamen
                    were wounded) and the one launched on 1 July (when two squad members were
                    killed). In both of these instances, the ORJUNA members went into hiding in the
                    territory of the Kingdom SHS after launching the attacks. The last of these
                    incidents provoked a reaction from the Italian authorities, which arrested a
                    large number of people suspected to be members of the ORJUNA border-zone
                    organisation.</hi>
                <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn92" n="91"> Kacin-Wohinz, <hi rend="italic">Prvi antifašizem v Evropi</hi>, 245, 246.</note>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">In June 1928, the Italian Ministry of the Internal
                    Affairs warned the Italian authorities in Dalmatia that a number of ORJUNA
                    groups, whose task was to set Italian schools on fire, had infiltrated the
                    region and ordered that the fascist militia should secure the school buildings
                    in Zadar.</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn93" n="92">
                        CSA, Režimske i reakcionarne organizacije – grupa VII, document No. 858.
                    </note>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">The intensified ORJUNA terrorist actions in Italy
                    eventually led to a conflict within the organisation. After the ORJUNA squads
                    had assaulted Prestranek in 1926, the TIGR left the ORJUNAVIT, believing that
                    Marko Kranjec was much too hot-tempered and prone to reckless actions.</hi>
                <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn94" n="93"> SI AS 1931,
                        935-600-12 document: <hi rend="italic">Kosec Lipe</hi>.</note>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">There are certain indications suggesting that the
                    cooperation between these two organisations in fact ended due to a conflict over
                    the division of loot taken in the assault on the railway station in Perestranka.
                    Namely, the leaders of the TIGR accused Marko Kranjec of using all of the
                    plunder for the ORJUNA’s needs in the Kingdom of SHS, while Kranjec claimed that
                    the looted money intended for the requirements of the organisation in Italy was
                    kept by Raiko Samso, who was among the raiders that launched the assault in
                    Perestranka. This question remained unresolved, and it was believed that Samso’s
                    murder in June 1929 was an act of revenge by Kranjec.</hi>
                <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn95" n="94"> Kacin-Wohinz,
                        <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Prvi antifašizem v Evropi, </hi>58,
                        59.</note></p>
            <p><hi style="font-size:12pt">Some of the ORJUNA members from Slovenia, led by Vladimir
                    Levstik, believed that armed actions in Italy were counterproductive and that
                    they would result in the dissolution of the movement. When Kranjec and his
                    closest collaborators were arrested in December 1928 for the murder of Eduard
                    Perić, Levstik was appointed by the ORJUNA Secretary-General Miodrag
                    Dimitrijević to take over the administration of the organisation in Slovenia and
                    tasked with putting an end to the practice of plotting terrorist actions in
                    Italy.</hi>
                <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn96" n="95"> SI AS 1931,
                        935-600-12 document:
                        <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Materijal goričke kvestre o Orjuni </hi>(report
                        dated 16 October 1928).
                    </note><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve"> The terrorist actions carried out by the ORJUNA and its affiliated organisation across the border in Italy played an important part in the dissolution of the organisation following the promulgation of the January 6</hi><hi rend="superscript" style="font-size:12pt">th</hi>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">Decree. In the words of Vladimir Levstik, one of the
                    leaders of the Slovenian ORJUNA, the terrorist actions plotted by Marko Kranjec
                    in the territories of Italy and Austria were the main reason why the regime made
                    ORJUNA illegal in the wake of the January 6</hi><hi rend="superscript" style="font-size:12pt">th</hi>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">Decree.</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn97" n="96"> SI AS 1931, 935-600-12 document:
                        <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Materijal goričke kvestre o Orjuni </hi>(report
                        dated 4 April 1929).</note>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">Once he was released from prison, Kranjec refused to
                    abide by the state decree that banned ORJUNA and its affiliated organisations
                    across the border and continued to plot terrorist actions in Italy,</hi>
                <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn98" n="97"> Kacin-Wohinz, <hi rend="italic">Prvi antifašizem v Evropi</hi>, 354.</note>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">which is telling enough and counters the assumption that
                    the ORJUNA was under the direct control of the Belgrade-based government and its
                    military command. Marko Kranjec was known to the Italian intelligence service,
                    which suspected that the ORJUNA continued its activities within the National
                    Defence. The information available to the Italian secret agents indicated that
                    Kranjec enjoyed the support of the Chetnik military commander Kosta Milovanović
                    Pećanac, an experienced guerrilla fighter who had plotted the incursions of the
                    ORJUNA squads into the Italian territory.</hi>
                <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn99" n="98"> SI AS 1931,
                        935-600-12 document:
                        <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Materijal goričke kvestre o Orjuni </hi>(report
                        dated 25 January 1929).
                    </note><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve"> In January 1929, Italian secret agents warned the Italian border authorities that the ORJUNA had issued a circular letter to its members announcing that a war between Italy and France was imminent, and that the Kingdom of Serbs, Croats and Slovenes would take part in it as France’s ally, while the role the ORJUNA had to play in that conflict was to incite riots in Dalmatia and Albania.</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn100" n="99"> SI AS 1931,
                        935-600-12 document:
                        <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Materijal goričke kvestre o Orjuni </hi>(report
                        dated 22 January 1929).</note>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">The Italian secret service particularly emphasised the
                    fact that the ORJUNA (which at that time operated under the cloak of the
                    National Defence) possessed 70,000 firearms that would be used against Italy in
                    the coming spring.</hi>
                <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn101" n="100"> SI AS 1931,
                        935-600-12 document:
                        <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Materijal goričke kvestre o Orjuni </hi>(report
                        dated 26 January 1929). </note>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">In February 1929, Kranjec formed an unarmed squad in
                    Sušak, which was supposed to make a foray into the Italian territory.</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn102" n="101"> SI AS 1931,
                        935-600-12 document:
                        <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Materijal goričke kvestre o Orjuni </hi>(report
                        dated 1 February 1929).</note><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve"> The Italian border authorities stressed that the members of the dissolved ORJUNA intensified their activities in March and April 1929. The Italian secret agents pointed out that the ORJUNA members from Ljubljana disseminated antifascist (communist) literature and leaflets in Italy.</hi>
                <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn103" n="102"> SI AS 1931,
                        935-600-12 document:
                        <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Materijal goričke kvestre o Orjuni </hi>(report
                        dated 29 March 1929).
                    </note><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve"> In March 1929, the Italian intelligence service reported that the ORJUNA members organised special groups intending to carry out a series of assassinations of high-ranked Fascist Party officials.</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn104" n="103"> SI AS 1931,
                        935-600-12 document:
                        <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Materijal goričke kvestre o Orjuni </hi>(report
                        dated 9 March 1929). </note><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve"> In early 1930, the ORJUNA members from Slovenia, led by Marko Kranjec, established ties with the Italian antifascist emigrants in Paris, who would join the fight against the fascist regime in Italy. These political émigrés were mostly members of the Italian Communist Party, and the Yugoslav authorities therefore feared that the former ORJUNA members would fall under the influence of Communist propaganda. These fears motivated the Yugoslav authorities to move Kranjec, considered to be the mastermind behind the irredentist actions, from the customs offices in Slovenia first to Skopje</hi>
                <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn105" n="104"> Due to the
                        repressive measures taken by the Italian authorities in reaction to the
                        armed attacks launched by the ORJUNA and TIGR in the period from 1922 to
                        1931, more than two thousand members of the Slovenian ethnic minority were
                        forced to leave Italy. In order to maintain good relations with Italy, the
                        Yugoslav government resettled most of these emigrants in the region of
                        Bistrenica in Macedonia, with the aim of preventing them from taking part in
                        any further armed actions of the ORJUNA. (Kacin-Wohinz, <hi rend="italic">Prvi antifašizem v Evropi</hi>, 280, 316, 317, 329,
                    230).</note><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve"> and then to Niš.</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn106" n="105"> SI AS 1931,
                        935-600-12 document:
                        <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Materijal goričke kvestre o Orjuni </hi>(report
                        dated 10 August 1936). </note>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">On Saturday, 2 September 1930, the ORJUNA organisation
                    across the border in Italy suffered a severe blow when Jože Kukec, one of the
                    most prominent activists in the movement, was killed in a skirmish with the
                    fascist militia.</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn107" n="106">
                        <hi rend="color(1D2228)" xml:space="preserve">Following Kukec’s death, the operational leadership of the irredentist ORJUNA organisation in Italy was taken over by Lipe Kosec. </hi>(Vodušek
                        Starič,
                        <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Slovenski špijoni in SOE, </hi>114).</note><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve"> The situation was additionally complicated by the fact that the Italian authorities found a number of compromising documents in Kukec’s possession, which endangered the very existence of the ORJUNA’s activist and intelligence network in Italy.</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn108" n="107"> Kacin-Wohinz, <hi rend="italic">Prvi antifašizem v Evropi</hi>, 301, 302.</note>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">In October 1930, when Kranjec left Slovenia, the ORJUNA
                    squads that carried out terrorist actions in Italy reorganised themselves within
                    the Propaganda Department on the Coast. The head commander of these squads was
                    General Rudolf Maister, who had played a prominent role in the war that
                    Yugoslavia had waged against Austria in 1918–1919 over Styria and Carinthia, and
                    who would later become the honorary president of the Association of Fighters of
                    Yugoslavia BOJ. Under his command, these squads stopped plotting terrorist
                    actions in Italy and instead focused their activities on patrolling the border
                    and taking in the fugitives from Italy.</hi>
                <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn109" n="108"> SI AS 1931,
                        935-600-12 document:
                        <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Materijal goričke kvestre o Orjuni </hi>(report
                        dated 12<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> October 1929). </note><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve"> Later on, most of the ORJUNA members from this organisation continued their activities in the Drava Banate within the National Defence,</hi>
                <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn110" n="109"> Kacin-Wohinz,
                            <hi rend="italic">Prvi antifašizem v Evropi</hi>,
                    356.</note><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve"> which was led by Josip Cepuder, a former leader of the ORJUNA branch in Ljubljana.</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn111" n="110"> SI AS 1931,
                        935-600-12 document: <hi rend="italic">Elaborat o ORJUNI</hi>. </note>
            </p>
            <p><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve">The ideologists of the ORJUNA were particularly mistrustful of Austria as the successor of the Austro-Hungarian Empire that kept pursuing the Habsburg pretensions in the Balkan Peninsula. This was most explicitly expressed in the article </hi>
                <hi rend="italic" style="font-size:12pt">Balkanske
                    stvari</hi><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve"> (Balkan Issues),</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn112" n="111"> “Balkanske
                        stvari,” <hi rend="italic">Vidovdan</hi>, V, No. 322, 28<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> February 1926. </note><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve"> whose anonymous author pinpointed Vienna as the epicentre of various anti-Yugoslav groups that freely gathered and operated there, ranging from the Croatian pro-Habsburg loyalists, organised under the command of Lieutenant Field Marshal Stjepan Sarkotić, to groups of clericalists and Hungarian nationalists, to Soviets who used their embassy to support the Communist Party in the Kingdom of Serbs, Croats and Slovenes. However, in the ORJUNA’s opinion, the Austrian province of Carinthia was the main point of dispute between the two neighbouring countries. This territorial dispute dated back to the final stage of World War I, when Slovenian nationalists, encouraged by the presence of the Serbian Army, undertook a large-scale action aiming to incorporate this province into the newly-formed Kingdom of Serbs, Croats and Slovenes. As a reaction to these challenges, units of volunteers were formed throughout Austria under the name of Heimwehr (Home Guard), intended to counter the incursions from the neighbouring countries. In this conflict, the Heimwehr forces (politically and financially supported by Italy and right-wing groups from Germany) were defeated, while the Slovenian volunteer units secured the cities of Maribor and Celovec (Klagenfurt).</hi>
                <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn113" n="112"> Ferenc,
                        Kacin-Wohinz in Zorn,
                        <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Slovenci v zamejstvu, </hi>139.</note>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">The Triple Entente decided that the dispute over these
                    territories would be settled by means of a plebiscite in 1920. At that point,
                    most of Carinthia remained a part of Austria, whereas Styria and the city of
                    Maribor were included into the Kingdom of Serbs, Croats and Slovenes.</hi>
                <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn114" n="113"> Jurij Perovšek,
                            <hi rend="italic">V zaželjeni deželi: Slovenska izkušnja s Kraljevino
                            SHS/Jugoslavijo 1918–1941</hi> (Ljubljana: Inštitut za novejšo
                        zgodovino, 2009), 72–74.</note><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve"> This undeclared war between the hostile volunteer units resulted in the ideological radicalisation on both sides of the newly-established border. In Austria, groups within the Heimwehr, which had previously not carried out joint operations, started to become aware that they had to cooperate with one another. The idea of Pan-Germanism was on the rise, whereas in the Slovenian regions within the Kingdom of Serbs, Croats and Slovenes the ideology of Yugoslav integralism was taking root together with the idea of Great Yugoslavia – a country that would eventually regain Carinthia and Styria, populated by Slovenians, from Austria. Many Slovenian members of the ORJUNA took part in this undeclared war, and the issue of Carinthia and its incorporation into Yugoslavia was argued for in many articles published in the ORJUNA newspapers, such as </hi>
                <hi rend="italic" style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve">Diplomacija iredentizma </hi><hi style="font-size:12pt">(Diplomacy of Irredentism),</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn115" n="114"> “Diplomacija iredentizma,” <hi rend="italic">Pobeda</hi>, I, No. 7, 24 September 1921. </note>
                <hi rend="italic" style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve">Beč i Beograd </hi><hi style="font-size:12pt">(Vienna and Belgrade),</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn116" n="115"> “Beč i Beograd,” <hi rend="italic">Budućnost</hi>, II, No. 9, 3 March 1923. </note>
                <hi rend="italic" style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve">Govor Predsednika Direktorijuma brata Leontića </hi><hi style="font-size:12pt">(Speech Delivered by the President of the Directorate,
                    Brother Leontić</hi><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:12pt">),</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn117" n="116"> Ljubo Leontić,
                        “Govor Predsednika Direktorijuma brata Leomtića,” <hi rend="italic">Pobeda</hi>, V, No. 40, date illegible. </note>
                <hi rend="italic" style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve">Koruška </hi><hi style="font-size:12pt">(Carinthia),</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn118" n="117"> “Koruška,” <hi rend="italic">Pobeda</hi>, V,
                        No. 66, date
                    illegible.</note><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve"> and </hi><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve">Orjunaši u Koruškoj </hi><hi style="font-size:12pt">(ORJUNA in Carinthia).</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn119" n="118"> “Orjunaši u Koruškoj,” <hi rend="italic">Pobeda</hi>, V, No. 78, date illegible. </note><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve"> The ORJUNA ideologists did not accept the results of the Carinthian plebiscite, believing that it was symptomatic of the repression that Slovenians in Carinthia were subjected to by the Heimwehr and the representatives of the Austrian authorities.</hi>
                <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn120" n="119"> “Obnavljanje
                        nemčurstva v severni Sloveniji,” <hi rend="italic">Orjuna</hi>, I, No. 30,
                        15 July 1923.</note>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">Consequently, the ORJUNA did not give up or abandon its
                    claim that this territory should become a part of the Yugoslav state</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn121" n="120"> France Flipič,
                        “Nekaterne značilnosti delavskega revolucionarnega gibanja v Mariboru in
                        njegovem zaledju v letih 1921–1925,” <hi rend="italic">Revolucionarno
                            delavsko gibanje v Sloveniji v letih 1921–1924: Referati z znanstvenega
                            posvetovanja v Ljubljani 6. in 7. junija 1974</hi> (Ljubljana, 1975),
                        151–73.</note><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve"> as soon as the international relations made such an outcome achievable.</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn122" n="121"> “Spominski shod za
                        Koroško u Mariboru,” <hi rend="italic">Orjuna</hi>, II, No. 51, 18 October
                        1924.</note>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">Just like in the case of Istria, Trieste, and Gorizia,
                    the ORJUNA took concrete steps with the aim of facilitating the incorporation of
                    Carinthia into the Kingdom of Serbs, Croats and Slovenes. In the 1920s, the
                    ORJUNA established its illegal organisation in the territory of Carinthia called
                    Fantovska zveza. Set up similarly as the ORJUNAVIT, the Fantovska zveza
                    organisation carried out armed attacks in Carinthia, assaulting the
                    representatives of the Austrian government and local Austrian nationalists. The
                    most prominent action carried out by the Fantovska zveza was the assault in
                    Celovec (Klagenfurt) in December 1925, on the occasion of the 6</hi>
                <hi rend="superscript" style="font-size:12pt">th</hi><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve"> anniversary of the Carinthian plebiscite. The police informers who had infiltrated the ORJUNA tipped off the gendarmerie corps in Ljubljana, informing them that the ORJUNA, in cooperation with the Action Squads from Maribor, was plotting to launch an attack on the Austrian border somewhere around Pliberk (Bleiburg), while the fighters from the Fantovska zveza, assisted by the Action Squads, would make a simultaneous attack on the attendees of the celebration in Celovec. The members of the Action Squads and the Fantovska zveza were armed with guns and bombs, and the latter had already planted infernal machines (time bombs) in the city centre of Celovec, where they would be detonated prior to the assault. The assault was supposed to be a reprisal for the persecution of the Slovenian population in Carinthia, for which the Heimwehr was responsible. Having received a timely warning, the gendarmerie corps in Ljubljana arrested the ringleaders behind this action, although some ORJUNA members managed to get away and cross over to the Austrian territory, where they were captured by the Austrian police.</hi>
                <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn123" n="122"> CSA, Režimske i
                        reakcionarne organizacije – grupa VII, document No. 855. </note>
            </p>
            <p><hi rend="color(212121)" style="font-size:12pt">Overall, the irredentist actions of
                    the Slovenian ORJUNA in Italy and Austria did not have a significant influence
                    on the foreign-political situation of that time. Their intensity and violent
                    character faithfully reflected the legacy of the ethnic conflicts in the
                    Habsburg Monarchy at the end of the 19</hi><hi rend="superscript color(212121)" style="font-size:12pt">th</hi><hi rend="color(212121)" style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve"> century as well as the reception of the modern political practice of the ideological system that came to power in Italy in 1922. Guided by the imperative of preserving the ethnic identity of the Slovenian population in the marginal provinces of Italy and Austria, the ORJUNА leadership promoted the systematic use of organised violence as a basic tool in the struggle to achieve its goals. Due to the restrained and legitimately oriented official foreign policy of the Yugoslav governments as well as because of the armed resistance provided by the official security forces and paramilitaries of Italy and Austria, the leadership of the ORJUNA failed to achieve its foreign-political goals through the use of terror. On the other hand,</hi>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve">the expansionist ideas that represented one of the essential tenets of the ORJUNA’s ideology would remain a part of the ideological concepts espoused by all far-right movements that supported the Yugoslav integralism in the interwar period, which, with slight modifications, adopted the ideological constructs advocated by the Organisation of Yugoslav Nationalists. In their political agendas and manifestos, the Yugoslav Action, Association of Fighters of Yugoslavia, and the Yugoslav National Movement Zbor would embrace and cherish the idea of the Greater Yugoslavia, whose borders would be more or less identical to the model established by the ORJUNA ideologists. The rise of revanchist states, restrictive security policies applied by the Yugoslav regimes, and rudimentary organisational forms of paramilitary militias in the 1930s were the factors that frustrated the leaderships of the far-right movements for Yugoslav integralism in their attempts to employ direct violent irredentist actions to further their expansionist agenda, thus restricting their activities to the field of culture and education, propaganda, and cooperation with the pro-Yugoslav elements in the neighbouring countries. </hi>
            </p></div>
        </body>
        <back>
    <div type="bibliography">
        <head>Sources and
                Literature</head>
            <list type="unordered">
                <head>Archival Sources</head>
                <item>AY – Archives of Yugoslavia:<list>
            
            <item>○ Ministarstvo pravde Kraljevine Jugoslavije (Fund No
                    63).</item></list></item>
            <item>CSA – Croatian State Archives:<list>
            
            <item>○Režimske i reakcionarne organizacije - grupa
                    VII.</item></list></item>
                <item>SI AS – The Archives of the Republic of Slovenia:<list>
            <item>○ SI AS 1931, Republiški secretariat za notranje zadeve
                SRS.
                </item></list></item>
            </list>
        
            <listBibl>
                <head>Newspaper Sources</head>
            <bibl><hi rend="italic">Budućnost</hi>, I, No. 3, 30<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> December 1922. “Hrvatski borac.”
            </bibl>
            <bibl><hi rend="italic">Budućnost</hi>, I, No. 3, 30<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> December 1922. “Poslednji Mohikanci.”</bibl>
            <bibl><hi rend="italic">Budućnost</hi>, II, No. 9, 3<hi rend="superscript">rd</hi> March 1923. “Beč i Beograd.”</bibl>
            <bibl><hi rend="italic">Jugoslavija</hi> (Belgrade), II, No. 26, date illegible (year 1928). “Fašističko pokrštavanje.”</bibl>
            <bibl><hi rend="italic">Jugoslavija</hi> (Belgrade), II, No. 26, date illegible (year 1928). “Sacro egoism.”</bibl>
            <bibl><hi rend="italic">Jugoslavija </hi>(Skopje), I, No. 2, 20<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> February 1927. “Crnim košuljama.”</bibl>
            <bibl><hi rend="italic">Jugoslavija</hi> (Skopje), I, No. 3, 28<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> February 1927. “Makedonstvujuščima.”</bibl>
            <bibl><hi rend="italic">Jugoslavija</hi> (Skopje), I, No. 5, 27<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> March 1927. “Bugarska i Jugoslavija.”</bibl>
            <bibl>Lahman, Ivo. “Kulturno Jugoslovenstvo.” <hi rend="italic">Pobeda</hi>, I, No. 7, 24<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> September 1921.</bibl>
            <bibl>Leontić, Ljubo. “Govor Predsednika Direktorijuma brata Leontića.” <hi rend="italic">Pobeda</hi>, V, No. 40, date illegible (year 1925).</bibl>
            <bibl>Leontić, Ljubo. “Sloboda Jadranskog mora.” <hi rend="italic">Jugoslovenski Jadran – special ORJUNA
                    publication published on the occasion of its meeting in
                    Dubrovnik,</hi> 23<hi rend="superscript">rd </hi>– 24<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> March 1926.</bibl>
            <bibl><hi rend="italic">Orjuna</hi>, I, No. 30, 15<hi rend="superscript">th </hi>July 1923. “Iz zemlje naše tuge.” </bibl>
            <bibl><hi rend="italic">Orjuna,</hi> I, No. 30, 15<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> July 1923. “Obnavljanje nemčurstva v severni Sloveniji.” </bibl>
            <bibl><hi rend="italic">Orjuna</hi>, II, No. 51, 18<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> October 1924. “Spominski shod za Koroško u Mariboru.”</bibl>
            <bibl><hi rend="italic">Pobeda</hi>, I, No. 1, 28<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> June 1921. “Naš put.”</bibl>
            <bibl><hi rend="italic">Pobeda</hi>, I, No. 6, 17<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> September 1921. “Dve metode.”</bibl>
            <bibl><hi rend="italic">Pobeda</hi>, No. 7, 24<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> September 1921. “Diplomatija iredentizma.”</bibl>
            <bibl><hi rend="italic">Pobeda</hi>, I, No. 19, 24<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> December 1921. “Jugoslovenska misija.”</bibl>
            <bibl><hi rend="italic">Pobeda</hi>, V, No. 31, date illegible (year 1925). “Naš prekomorski sused i mi.”</bibl>
            <bibl><hi rend="italic">Pobeda</hi>, V,
                No. 66, date illegible (year 1925). “Koruška.”</bibl>
            <bibl><hi rend="italic">Pobeda</hi>, V,
                No. 69, date illegible (year 1925). “Talijanski fašisti hoće da osnuju borbenu
                organizaciju u Splitu.”</bibl>
            <bibl><hi rend="italic">Pobeda</hi>, V,
                No. 72, date illegible (year 1925). “Musolinijevi ljudi u Trstu pale
                jugoslovenske domove.”</bibl>
            <bibl><hi rend="italic">Pobeda</hi>, V,
                No. 78, date illegible (year 1925). “Orjunaši u Koruškoj.”</bibl>
            <bibl><hi rend="italic">Pobeda</hi>, VI,
                No. 18, date illegible (year 1926). “Svesni orijunaši na granici u službi
                Otadžbine.”</bibl>
            <bibl><hi rend="italic">Pobeda</hi>, VI,
                No. 66, date illegible (year 1926). “Nova fašistička divljaštva u
                Goričkoj.”</bibl>
            <bibl><hi rend="italic">Pobeda</hi>, VII,
                No. 3, 22<hi rend="superscript">nd</hi> December 1927. “Musolini izmišlja tako zvano Crnogorsko pitanje.”</bibl>
            <bibl><hi rend="italic">Pobeda</hi>, VII,
                No. 4, 29<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>
                 January 1927. “Lega Nazionale u Šibeniku.”</bibl>
            <bibl><hi rend="italic">Pobeda</hi>, VII,
                No. 9, date illegible (approximately February-March 1927). “Albansko
                pitanje.”</bibl>
            <bibl><hi rend="italic">Pobeda</hi>, VII, No. 10, date illegible (year 1927). “Italija i naše duhovno jedinstvo.” </bibl>
            <bibl><hi rend="italic">Pobeda</hi>, VII,
                No. 10, date illegible (approximately February-March 1927). “Pred Musolinijev
                podvig na Balkanu.”</bibl>
            <bibl><hi rend="italic">Pobeda</hi>, VII,
                No 28, 15<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> July 1927. “Musolinijeva agresivnost i naša spoljna politika.”</bibl>
            <bibl><hi rend="italic">Pobeda,</hi>
                VII, No. 29, 29<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> April 1927. “Natezanje sa Musolinijem.”</bibl>
            <bibl>Silobrćić, J. M.. “Naša borba.” <hi rend="italic">Orjuna,</hi>
                II, No. illegible, 25<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> March 1923.</bibl>
            <bibl><hi rend="italic">Vidovdan</hi>,
                    II, No. 90, 6<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> October 1923. “Protiv rata sa Jugoslavijom.”</bibl>
            <bibl><hi rend="italic">Vidovdan</hi>, V,
                No. 322, 28<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> February 1926. “Balkanske stvari.“</bibl>
            <bibl><hi rend="italic">Vidovdan</hi>,
                VI, No. 377, 15<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> January 1927. “Iz rupe u rupu.”
            </bibl>
            <bibl><hi rend="italic">Vidovdan</hi>, VI, No. 397, 22<hi rend="superscript">nd</hi>
                May 1927. “Italija na Sredozemnom moru.”
            </bibl></listBibl>
         <listBibl>
             <head>Literature</head>
            <bibl>Bartulović, Niko. <hi rend="italic">Od revolucionarne omladine do ORJUNE: Istorijat jugoslovenskog omladinskog
                pokreta.</hi> Split: ORJUNA, 1925.</bibl>
            <bibl>Bosworth, J.R.B. <hi rend="italic">Mussolini’s Italy: Life under the
                    Dictatorship 19151945.</hi> London: Penguin Books, 2006.</bibl>
             <bibl>Čop, Robert. ORJUNA prototip političke organizacije. Graduation thesis defended at the Faculty of
                Social Sciences in Ljubljana, 2006.</bibl>
            <bibl>Djordjević, Mladen. “Organizacija jugoslovenskih nacionalista (ORJUNA).” <hi rend="italic">NSPM</hi>, Vol. XII, No. 1-4
                (2006). </bibl>
            <bibl>Ekmečić, Milorad. <hi rend="italic">Stvaranje Jugoslavije 1790-1918
                    II.</hi> Belgrade: Prosveta, 1989.</bibl>
            <bibl>Ferenc, Tone, Kacin-Wohinz, Milica in Tone Zorn. <hi rend="italic">Slovenci v zamejstvu: Pregled zgodovine 1918-1945</hi>. Ljubljana: Državna
                založba Slovenije, 1974.</bibl>
            <bibl>Flipič, France. „Nekaterne značilnosti delavskega revolucionarnega gibanja v Mariboru in
                njegovem zaleđu v letih 1921–1925.“
                <hi rend="italic" >Revolucionarno delavsko gibanje v Sloveniji v letih 1921-1924: Referati z znanstvenega posvetovanja v Ljubljani 6. in 7.  junija 1974, </hi>151-173. Ljubljana, 1975.</bibl>
            <bibl>Gligorijević,
                    Branislav. „Organizacija jugoslovenskih nacionalista (Orjuna).“ <hi rend="italic">Istorija XX veka: zbornik radova</hi> (1962).</bibl>
            <bibl>Gligorijević, Branislav. „Politički pokreti i grupe sa nacionalsocijalističkom ideologijom i
                njihova fuzija u Ljotićevom Zboru.“ <hi rend="italic">Istorijski glasnik</hi>, No. 4 (1965).</bibl>
            <bibl>Gligorijević, Branislav. <hi rend="italic">Kralj Aleksandar Karadjordjević:
                    Srpsko-hrvatski spor.</hi> Belgrade: Zavod za
                udzbenike i nastavna sredstva, 2002.</bibl>
            <bibl>Grisogono,
                    Prvislav. <hi rend="italic">Savremena nacionalna pitanja</hi>. Split: ORJUNA, 1923.</bibl>
            <bibl>Kacin-Wohinz, Milica. <hi rend="italic">Narodnoobrambno gibanje primorskih Slovencev v letih 1921-1928 II</hi>. Koper: Lipa;
                Trst: Založništvo tržaškega tiska, 1977.</bibl>
            <bibl>Kacin-Wohinz, Milica. „Slovenci i Hrvati pod Fašističkom Italijom.“<hi rend="italic"> Jugoslovenski istorijski časopis</hi>, No. 3 (1987). </bibl>
            <bibl>Kacin-Wohinz, Milica. <hi rend="italic">Prvi antifašizem v Evropi</hi>. Koper: Lipa, 1990.</bibl>
            <bibl>Mlakar, Boris. „Radical nationalism and fascist elements in political movements in Slovenia between
                the two world wars.“ <hi rend="italic">Slovene studies</hi>, No. 1 (2009).</bibl>
            <bibl>Mlakar, Boris. „Zaton Organizacije jugoslovanskih nacionalistov - Orjune pod budnim očesom italjanskih fašističnih oblasti.“ <hi rend="italic">Prispevki za novejšo
                zgodovino</hi>, No. 2 </bibl>
            <bibl>Payne, Stanley G. <hi rend="italic">A History of Fascism 1914-1945</hi>. Wisconsin: University of Wisconsin Press,
                2003.</bibl>
            <bibl>Perovšek, Jurij. <hi rend="italic">V zaželjeni deželi: Slovenska izkušnja s Kraljevino SHS/Jugoslavijo 1918-1941</hi>. Ljubljana: Inštitut za novejšo
                zgodovino, 2009.</bibl>
            <bibl>Vodušek Starič, Jerca. <hi rend="italic">Slovenski špijoni in SOE 1936-1942</hi>. Ljubljana: samozal., 2002.</bibl>
         </listBibl></div>
            <div type="summary" xml:lang="sl">
                <docAuthor>Vasilije
                Dragosavljević</docAuthor>
            <head>IREDENTISTIČNE AKCIJE SLOVENSKE
                ORGANIZACIJE JUGOSLOVANSKIH NACIONALISTOV (ORJUNE) V ITALIJI IN AVSTRIJI
                (1922–1930)</head>
            <head>POVZETEK</head>
            <p>V prispevku so predstavljeni konceptualni okviri
                zunanjepolitičnih idej Organizacije jugoslovanskih nacionalistov (Orjune). V
                uvodnem delu članka sta tako opisana kratka zgodovina Orjune in proces razvoja
                njene ideologije s poudarkom na ekspanzionistični ideji. Ekspanzionistični
                načrti vodilnih Orjuninih ideologov, utelešeni v načrtu Velike Jugoslavije, ki
                bi segala od Varne do Trsta in od Szegeda do Soluna, so bili neločljivo povezani
                s teorijo jugoslovanskega integralizma, v skladu s katero naj bi na tem ozemlju
                živeli izključno jugoslovanski prebivalci. Orjunini ideologi so bili prepričani,
                da mora biti enotnost Jugoslovanov najpomembnejša vodilna ideja jugoslovanske
                zunanje politike. Vodstvo Orjune je na podlagi imperativa ohranitve etnične
                identitete slovenskega prebivalstva v pokrajinah ob meji z Italijo in Avstrijo
                zagovarjalo sistematično uporabo organiziranega nasilja kot osnovnega orodja v
                boju za uresničitev svojih ciljev. Posebna pozornost je posvečena
                iredentističnim akcijam, ki jih je slovenska veja Orjune opravila na ozemlju
                Italije (Trst, Gorica in Istra) in Avstrije (Koroška). Izpostavljeni sta tudi
                organizaciji Orjunavit in Fantovska zveza, ki sta Orjuni služili kot orodje za
                delovanje na ozemlju Italije in Avstrije. Zmerna in legitimno usmerjena uradna
                zunanja politika jugoslovanskih oblasti ter oboroženi odpor uradnih varnostnih
                sil in paravojaških organizacij Italije in Avstrije sta vodstvu Orjune
                preprečila, da bi s terorizmom doseglo svoje zunanjepolitične cilje.
                Ekspanzionistične ideje kot ena glavnih značilnosti Orjunine ideologije so se v
                medvojnem obdobju ohranile v okviru idejnih konceptov vseh skrajnih desničarskih
                gibanj za jugoslovanski integralizem. Ta so z manjšimi ali večjimi spremembami
                sprejela ideološke konstrukte, ki jih je zagovarjala Orjuna.
            </p></div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>