<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Smart Big Data: Use of Slovenian Parliamentary Papers in Digital History</title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename>Andrej</forename>
                        <surname>Pančur</surname>
                        <roleName>PhD.</roleName>
                        <roleName>Research associate</roleName>
                        <affiliation>Institute of Contemporary History</affiliation>
                        <address>
                            <addrLine>Kongresni trg 1</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>SI-1000 Ljubljana</addrLine>
                        </address>
                        <email>andrej.pancur@inz.si</email>
                    </name>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename>Mojca</forename>
                        <surname>Šorn</surname>
                        <roleName>PhD.</roleName>
                        <roleName>Research associate</roleName>
                        <affiliation>Institute of Contemporary History</affiliation>
                        <address>
                            <addrLine>Kongresni trg 1</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>SI-1000 Ljubljana</addrLine>
                        </address>
                        <email>mojca.sorn@inz.si</email>
                    </name>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>2016-11-02</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>
                    <orgName xml:lang="sl">Inštitut za novejšo zgodovino</orgName>
                    <orgName xml:lang="en">Institute of Contemporary History</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Kongresni trg 1</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>SI-1000 Ljubljana</addrLine>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>http://ojs.inz.si/pnz/article/view/193</pubPlace>
                <date>2016</date>
                <availability status="free">
                    <licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title xml:lang="sl">Prispevki za novejšo zgodovino</title>
                <title xml:lang="en">Contributions to Contemporary History</title>
                <biblScope unit="volume">56</biblScope>
                <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
                <idno type="ISSN">2463-7807</idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source, born digital.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc xml:lang="en">
                <p>Contributions to Contemporary History is one of the central Slovenian scientific
                    historiographic journals, dedicated to publishing articles from the field of
                    contemporary history (the 19th and 20th century).</p>
                <p>The journal is published three times per year in Slovenian and in the following
                    foreign languages: English, German, Serbian, Croatian, Bosnian, Italian, Slovak
                    and Czech. The articles are all published with abstracts in English and
                    Slovenian as well as summaries in English.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <projectDesc xml:lang="sl">
                <p>Prispevki za novejšo zgodovino je ena osrednjih slovenskih znanstvenih
                    zgodovinopisnih revij, ki objavlja teme s področja novejše zgodovine (19. in 20.
                    stoletje).</p>
                <p>Revija izide trikrat letno v slovenskem jeziku in v naslednjih tujih jezikih:
                    angleščina, nemščina, srbščina, hrvaščina, bosanščina, italijanščina, slovaščina
                    in češčina. Članki izhajajo z izvlečki v angleščini in slovenščini ter povzetki
                    v angleščini.</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="sl"/>
                <language ident="en"/>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords xml:lang="en">
                    <term>digital humanities</term>
                    <term>digital history</term>
                    <term>Slovenia</term>
                    <term>parliament</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords xml:lang="sl">
                    <term>digitalna humanistika</term>
                    <term>Slovenija</term>
                    <term>digitalna zgodovina</term>
                    <term>parlament</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change>
                    <date>2016-11-07</date>
                    <name>Neja Blaj Hribar</name>
                    <desc>Pretvorba iz DOCX v TEI, dodatno kodiranje</desc>
                </change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <docAuthor>Andrej Pančur<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn0" n="*"><hi rend="bold">Research associate, PhD, Institute of Contemporary History, Kongresni trg 1, SI-1000 Ljubljana, Slovenia, <ref target="mailto:andrej.pancur@inz.si">andrej.pancur@inz.si</ref></hi></note></docAuthor>
            <docAuthor>Mojca Šorn<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn00" n="**"><hi rend="bold">Research associate, PhD, Institute of Contemporary History, Kongresni trg 1, SI-1000 Ljubljana, Slovenia, <ref target="mailto:mojca.sorn@inz.si">mojca.sorn@inz.si</ref></hi></note></docAuthor>
            <docImprint>
                <idno type="cobissType">Cobiss type: 1.01</idno>
                <idno type="UDC">UDC: </idno>
                </docImprint>
            <div type="abstract" xml:lang="sl">
                <head type="main">IZVLEČEK</head>
                <head>PAMETNI MASIVNI PODATKI: UPORABA SLOVENSKIH PARLAMENTARNIH
                    DOKUMENTOV V DIGITALNI ZGODOVINI</head>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Avtorja v prispevku opozorita na problem velikih količin digitalnih
                    zgodovinskih virov, s katerim se bodo srečavali raziskovalci sodobne zgodovine.
                    Bolj nadrobno predstavita slovenske parlamentarne dokumente kot primer pametnih
                    masivnih podatkov. Avtorja menita, da velikih količin tega digitalnega gradiva
                    zgodovinarji ne bodo mogli obdelovati samo z uporabo klasičnih zgodovinskih
                    metod, temveč bodo morali začeti uporabljati še metode in orodja, ki jih razvija
                    digitalna zgodovina, digitalna humanistika in tudi jezikoslovne
                    tehnologije.</hi></p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Ključne besede: digitalna humanistika, digitalna zgodovina,
                    Slovenija, parlament</hi></p>
            </div>
            <div type="abstract">
                <head>ABSTRACT</head>
                <p><hi rend="italic">The paper calls attention to the problem of massive amounts of
                    digital historical sources that will eventually be faced by researchers of
                    contemporary history. Slovenian parliamentary papers are then presented in
                    detail as an example of smart big data. The authors believe that historians will
                    be unable to process massive amounts of such digital materials using only
                    standard historiographical methods and will be forced to start using methods and
                    tools developed by digital history, digital humanities and also language
                    technologies.</hi></p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Keywords: digital humanities, digital history, Slovenia,
                    parliament</hi></p>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div>
            <head>Big Data</head>
            <p><hi rend="italic">Big data</hi> is the buzzword of the decade. However, the very
                ubiquity of the term both in the industry, the media as well as in the academic
                community has led to big data being defined in various ways. Furthermore, big data
                in the humanities is not the same as big data in natural sciences.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn3" n="2"> Christof Schöch, “Big? Smart?
                        Clean? Messy? Data in the Humanities,” <hi rend="italic">Journal of Digital
                            Humanities</hi> 2, no. 3 (2013), accessed on 25 September 2016, <ref target="http://journalofdigitalhumanities.org/2-3/big-smart-clean-messy-data-in-the-humanities/">http://journalofdigitalhumanities.org/2-3/big-smart-clean-messy-data-in-the-humanities/</ref>.</note>
                This paper uses the definition according to which historical big data is described
                as follows;</p>
            <list type="unordered">
                <item>large volumes of data, particularly texts that cannot be read within a
                    reasonable time frame, and</item>
                <item>information that only allows us to reach new conclusions through the use of
                    digital methods.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn4" n="3">
                            Shawn Graham, Ian Milligan and Scott Weingart, <hi rend="italic">Exploring Big Historical Data. The Historian’s Macroscope</hi>
                            (London: Imperial College Press, 2015), accessed on 28 September 2016.
                                <ref target="http://www.themacroscope.org">http://www.themacroscope.org</ref>.</note></item>
            </list>
            <p>Large amounts of computer-readable data are gradually becoming the reality of modern
                historiography. The late Roy Rosenzweig, one of the pioneers of digital history,
                warned as early as 2003 that historiography, instead of working within the scarcity
                paradigm of historical records, will have to start facing the problem of an excess
                of resources.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn5" n="4"> Roy
                        Rosenzwig, “Scarcity or Abundance? Preserving the Past in a Digital Era,”
                            <hi rend="italic">American Historical Review</hi> 108, no. 3 (2003):
                        735–62.</note> Up to now, historiography has mostly had to deal with the
                lack of resources, their incompleteness and often also with high costs of acquiring
                additional sources. Today, on the other hand, historians can access new digitized
                and digital sources quickly and effectively. Although a lion’s share of analogue
                materials has not been and is unlikely to be digitized within reasonable time,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn6" n="5"> Gerben Zaagsma, “On
                        Digital
                        History,”<hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve"> BMGN – Low Countries Historical Review</hi>
                        128, no. 4 (2013): 19–23.</note> the materials emerging today are
                increasingly created in the digital form. This is the reason why, for example, the
                Slovenian archives are currently working hard on establishing a Slovenian electronic
                archive – e-ARH.si.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn7" n="6">
                        Tatjana Hajtnik, “Strategija razvoja slovenskega javnega elektronskega
                        arhiva ’e-ARH.si’,” <hi rend="italic">Knjižnica</hi> 55, no. 1 (2011):
                        40–41, 44. Bojan Cvelfar et al., <hi rend="italic">Strategija in izvedbeni
                            načrt razvoja slovenskega elektronskega arhiva 2016–2020</hi>
                        (Ljubljana: Archives of the Republic of Slovenia, 2016), 10.</note>
                Consequently, the problem of (over)abundance of historical resources is also
                emerging in the studies of contemporary history,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn8" n="7"> Peter Haber, “Zeitgeschichte und Digital
                        Humanities,” in: <hi rend="italic">Zeitgeschichte – Konzepte und
                            Methoden</hi>, eds. Frank Bösch and Danyel Jürgen (Göttingen:
                        Vandenhoeck &amp; Ruprecht, 2012), 47–66.</note> including the history
                of the Republic of Slovenia after 1991.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn9" n="8"> Jure Gašparič, “Pisati politično zgodovino Republike
                        Slovenije,” in: <hi rend="italic">Četrt stoletja Republike Slovenije –
                            izzivi, dileme, pričakovanja</hi>, eds. Jure Gašparič and Mojca Šorn
                        (Ljubljana: Institute of Contemporary History, 2016), 30.</note></p>
            <p>The massive amount of digital materials has spurred the creation and spreading of
                digital humanities, which use digital methods and tools to address new research
                    questions.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn10" n="9"> Sandra Collins et al.,
                            <hi rend="italic">ALLEA E-Humanities Working Group Report. Going
                            Digital: Creating Change in the Humanities</hi> (Berlin: All European
                        Academies, 2015), 9, accessed 19 July 2016, <ref target="http://www.allea.org/Content/ALLEA/WG%20E%20Humanities/Going%20Digital_digital%20version.pdf">http://www.allea.org/Content/ALLEA/WG%20E%20Humanities/Going%20Digital_digital%20version.pdf</ref>.
                        Devon Elliot, Robert MacDougall and William J. Turkel, “New Old Things.
                        Fabrication, Physical Computing, and Experiment in Historical Practice,” <hi rend="italic">Canadian Journal of Communication</hi> 37 (2012): 122,
                        accessed 19 July 2016, <ref target="http://www.cjc-online.ca/index.php/journal/article/view/2506">http://www.cjc-online.ca/index.php/journal/article/view/2506</ref>.</note>
                In the following sections, the paper uses the example of Slovenian parliamentary
                papers to present the advantages and drawbacks of the digital historiography methods
                in the analysis of big historical data. In this context, the digital history is
                understood as part of the digital humanities, which is primarily concerned with
                online distribution and presentation of historical sources using various computer
                tools, especially for mapping, network software and, last but not least, text
                    analysis.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn11" n="10">
                        Stephen Robertson, “The Differences between Digital Humanities and Digital
                        History,” in: <hi rend="italic">Debates in Digital Humanities 2016</hi>,
                        eds. Matthew K. Gold and Lauren F. Klein (Minneapolis and London: University
                        of Minnesota Press, 2016).</note> The paper focuses mainly on the
                possibilities for the use of text analysis methods and tools.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
            <head>Slovenian Parliamentary Papers</head>
            <p>Parliamentary papers are a rich source of data used by different academic disciplines
                including historiography. In some European countries, a large part of these papers
                is already accessible in digital form, mostly in PDF format.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn12" n="11"> Agiatis Benardou, Alastair
                        Dunning, Martin Schaller and Nephelie Chatzi Chatzidiakou. <hi rend="italic">Research Themes for Aggregating Digital Content. Parliamentary Papers
                            in Europe</hi> (Europeana Cloud, 2015), 6.</note></p>
            <p rend="LREC main body text">Both researchers and the public can avail themselves of
                the materials from parliamentary institutions located within today’s Slovenia and
                from parliamentary institutions whose members once included representatives from
                Slovenia. While it is true that most of the materials are currently only available
                in analogue form, an increasing amount has already been digitized and made available
                to the public:</p>
            <list type="unordered">
                <item>Austrian National Assembly (1861–1918);<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn13" n="12"> “Parlamentaria,” <hi rend="italic">ALEX –
                                Historische Rechts- und Gesetzestexte</hi>, accessed on 30 September
                            2016, <ref target="http://alex.onb.ac.at/sachlichegliederung.htm">http://alex.onb.ac.at/sachlichegliederung.htm</ref>.</note>
                </item>
                <item>Styrian Provincial Assembly (1848–1914);<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn14" n="13"> “Landtag Steiermark – stenographische
                            Sitzungsberichte,” <hi rend="italic">Das Land Steiermark</hi>, accessed
                            on 30 September 2016, <ref target="http://www.landesarchiv.steiermark.at/cms/ziel/111284715">http://www.landesarchiv.steiermark.at/cms/ziel/111284715</ref>.</note></item>
                <item>Carniolan Provincial Assembly (1861–1869);<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn15" n="14"> “Provincial Assembly of Carniola 1861–1918,”
                                <hi rend="italic">SIstory – History of Slovenia</hi>, accessed on 30
                            September 2016, <ref target="http://hdl.handle.net/11686/menu719">http://hdl.handle.net/11686/menu719</ref>.</note></item>
                <item>Yugoslav legislative bodies 1919–1939, 1942–1953;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn16" n="15"> “Stenographical minutes of
                            the executive and legislative bodies, Yugoslavia,” <hi rend="italic">SIstory – History of Slovenia</hi>, accessed on 30 September 2016,
                                <ref target="http://hdl.handle.net/11686/menu396">http://hdl.handle.net/11686/menu396</ref>.</note></item>
                <item>People’s Assembly of the People’s Republic of Slovenia (1947–1963);<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn17" n="16"> “Shorthand
                            minutes of the People’s Assembly of the People’s Republic of Slovenia
                            (1947–1963),” <hi rend="italic">SIstory – History of Slovenia</hi>,
                            accessed on 30 September 2016, <ref target="http://hdl.handle.net/11686/menu407">http://hdl.handle.net/11686/menu407</ref>.</note></item>
                <item>Assembly of the Socialist Republic of Slovenia (1963–1990);<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn18" n="17"> “Assembly of the Socialist
                            Republic of Slovenia (1963–1990),” <hi rend="italic">SIstory – History
                                of Slovenia</hi>, accessed on 30 September 2016, <ref target="http://hdl.handle.net/11686/menu408">http://hdl.handle.net/11686/menu408</ref>.</note></item>
                <item>National Assembly of the Republic of Slovenia, from 1990 until today.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn19" n="18"> “Seje Državnega
                            zbora – Po datumu,” <hi rend="italic">Republic of Slovenia: National
                                Assembly</hi>, accessed on 30 September 2016, <ref target="https://www.dz-rs.si/wps/portal/Home/deloDZ/seje/sejeDrzavnegaZbora/PoDatumuSeje/">https://www.dz-rs.si/wps/portal/Home/deloDZ/seje/sejeDrzavnegaZbora/PoDatumuSeje/</ref>.</note></item>
            </list>
            <p rend="LREC main body text">With the exception of the documents from the National
                Assembly, which are being published in the HTML format, all documents have been
                published in PDF.</p>
            <p>Chart 1 shows the number of words contained in parliamentary speeches for each
                parliamentary term of the Slovenian parliament which are archived in PDF at the
                History of Slovenia – SIstory portal (36 million words) and in HTML at the National
                Assembly website (69 million words). Up until 1974, minutes of the sessions also
                included extensive attachments (10.5 million words), which were later published in a
                special serial publication titled <hi rend="italic">Poročevalec</hi>. From 2010
                onward, <hi rend="italic">Poročevalec</hi> has been regularly accessible at the
                National Assembly website,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn20" n="19"> “Gradivo DZ,” <hi rend="italic">Republic of Slovenia:
                            National Assembly</hi>, accessed on 30 September 2016, <ref target="https://www.dz-rs.si/wps/portal/Home/deloDZ/Porocevalec/GradivaDZ">https://www.dz-rs.si/wps/portal/Home/deloDZ/Porocevalec/GradivaDZ</ref>.
                    </note> where visitors can also look through archived issues from 2006 to
                    2010.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn21" n="20"> “Arhiv
                        Poročevalec od 14.4.2006 do 15.7.2010,” <hi rend="italic">Republic of
                            Slovenia: National Assembly</hi>, accessed on 30 September 2016, <ref target="https://www.dz-rs.si/wps/portal/Home/deloDZ/Porocevalec/arhivPorocevalec">https://www.dz-rs.si/wps/portal/Home/deloDZ/Porocevalec/arhivPorocevalec</ref>.</note>
                Other issues of <hi rend="italic">Poročevalec</hi> (1974–2006) are going to be
                digitized within three years by the Institute of Contemporary History that manages
                the History of Slovenia – SIstory portal. As of this moment, the Institute has
                already managed to digitize issues of <hi rend="italic">Poročevalec</hi> from 1974
                to 1996, which together contain almost 37 million words (see Chart 1).</p>
            <p>#file: Chart1.xlsx</p>
            <p>Chart 1: Number of words in parliamentary speeches (1947–1990), attachments
                (1947–1974) and <hi rend="italic">Poročevalec</hi> (1974–1996) at the History of
                Slovenia – SIstory portal and the number of words in parliamentary speeches at the
                National Assembly website (1990–2011); in millions of words per parliamentary
                term.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
            <head>Searching</head>
            <p>It is clear that no researcher is able to read that much text in its entirety.
                Researchers thus only read those parts that they consider relevant for their
                research. In doing so, they read the selected parts of the text carefully, from word
                to word, or quickly skim over the pages looking for relevant parts of the text.
                However, such research is generally based on the assumption that the researchers
                will find what they are looking for in the text. Researchers thus determine the text
                they are looking for, as well as the context of their research, in advance. In doing
                so, they necessarily lean on their previous comprehensive or inadequate knowledge of
                the area of study.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn22" n="21">
                        Federico Nanni, Hiram Kumper, and Simone Paolo Ponzetto, “Semi-Supervised
                        Textual Analysis and Historical Research Helping Each Other. Some Thoughts
                        and Observations,” <hi rend="italic">International Journal of Humanities and
                            Arts Computing</hi> 10, no. 1 (2016): 73–74.</note></p>
            <p>In history as well as in other humanities, such methods are of course completely
                acceptable and often yield useful results. A number of good studies has been created
                in such a manner using materials from the National Assembly of the Republic of
                    Slovenia.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn23" n="22"> Jure
                        Gašparič, <hi rend="italic">Državni zbor 1992–2012. O slovenskem
                            parlamentarizmu</hi> (Ljubljana: Institute of Contemporary History,
                        2012). Jure Gašparič, <hi rend="italic">Slovenski parlament.
                            Politično-zgodovinski pregled od začetka prvega do konca šestega
                            mandata (1992–2014)</hi> (Ljubljana: Institute of Contemporary History,
                        2014). Rosvita Pesek, <hi rend="italic">Osamosvojitev Slovenije</hi>
                        (Ljubljana: Nova revija, 2007).</note> Most researchers in the
                humanities thus primarily understand digital materials in terms of easier and
                quicker access to desired information.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn24" n="23"> Lisa Spiro, “Access, Explore, Converse: The Impact
                        (and Potential Impact) of the Digital Humanities on Scholarship,” in: <hi rend="italic">Keys for architectural history research in the digital
                            era</hi>, eds. <hi rend="Strong"><seg rend="normalweight" xml:space="preserve">Juliette </seg></hi><hi rend="familyname">Hueber</hi><hi rend="Strong"><seg rend="normalweight" xml:space="preserve"> and Antonio </seg></hi><hi rend="familyname">Mendes da Silva 3</hi> (2014). </note> In the case
                of materials from the National Assembly, researchers can make use of a search engine
                that allows them to filter their results according to search modules. In a similar
                manner, researchers can search for older parliamentary materials at the History of
                Slovenia – SIstory portal.</p>
            <p>Most researchers in the humanities first use search engines to identify sources and
                then do a full text keyword search. This means that studies are no longer conducted
                only vertically, from top to bottom, where a researcher only reads canonical texts
                and browses previously organized data collections. Rather, studies are being
                conducted in a bottom-up manner, with researchers looking for parts of text
                pertinent to their research that they would otherwise not have read. However, this
                research method has its limitations. The researcher must know the search queries in
                advance, and these can differ from modern thought patterns. Inasmuch as the
                researcher does not carefully examine every search result, the results are always
                lacking proper context.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn25" n="24"> Robertson, “The Differences between Digital Humanities
                        and Digital History.” Bob Nicholson, “The Digital Turn. Exploring the
                        methodological possibilities of digital newspaper archives,” <hi rend="italic">Media History</hi> 19, no. 1 (2013): 66–67.</note></p>
            <p>Despite these limitations, a full text keyword search can yield very useful results.
                A good example of such research is the article <hi rend="italic">War in Parliament:
                    What a Digital Approach Can Add to the Study of Parliamentary History</hi> whose
                authors used carefully selected search queries and a search engine to systematically
                check to which extent the Boerenpartij (Farmers’ Party) was described as “wrong” in
                all Dutch parliamentary debates between 1958 and 1982.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn26" n="25"> Hinke Piersma et al., “War in
                        Parliament. What a Digital Approach Can Add to the Study of Parliamentary
                        History,” <hi rend="italic">DHQ: Digital Humanities Quarterly</hi> 8, no. 1
                        (2014).</note> The article was written as part of the <hi rend="italic">War in Parliament</hi> project. The results of this project clearly showed that
                satisfactory research results can only be obtained if we are familiar not only with
                the advantages but also with the shortcomings of digital research methods.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn27" n="26"> Hinke Piersma and
                        Kees Ribbens, “Digital Historical Research. Context, Concept and the Need
                        for Reflection,” <hi rend="italic">BMGN – Low Countries Historical
                            Review</hi> 128, no. 4 (2013): 87–90, 100–01.</note></p>
            </div>
            <div>
            <head>Smart Big Data</head>
            <p>One of the prerequisites for the <hi rend="italic">War in Parliament</hi> project to
                be successful was the use of partly structured data in the XML format, which allowed
                for the search results to be filtered by speaker’s name, by party, by time period,
                structure of the text, etc.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn28" n="27"> “War in Parliament,” <hi rend="italic">NIOD</hi>,
                        accessed on 30 September 2016, <ref target="http://www.niod.nl/en/projects/war-parliament">http://www.niod.nl/en/projects/war-parliament</ref>.</note> What
                was used was thus not big data in the form of plain text, but rather smart data.
                Smart data may be structured or partly structured, and compared to implicit big
                data, smart data is explicit, marked, enriched and described by metadata. The
                creation of smart data is often a labour-intensive process that requires human
                    intervention.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn29" n="28">
                        Schöch, “Big? Smart? Clean? Messy? Data in the Humanities,”
                4.</note></p>
            <p>As we have seen, parliamentary papers represent extremely extensive data collections.
                We thus cannot expect to be able to reveal their explicit content merely through
                precise manual annotation. The dilemma necessarily encountered by researchers in the
                use of digital parliamentary papers was succinctly stated by Christof Schöch:</p>
            <p rend="Quote">“I believe the most interesting challenge for the next years when it
                comes to dealing with data in the humanities will be to actually transgress this
                opposition of smart and big data. What we need is bigger smart data or smarter big
                data, and to create and use it, we need to make use of new methods. So, how can we
                enrich big data sufficiently to make more intelligent queries possible? How can we
                speed up the process of creating smart data so that we can produce larger volumes of
                    it?”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn30" n="29"> Ibid.,
                        10.</note></p>
            <p>At the same time, Schöch calls our attention to two possible ways of making big data
                smarter: through automatic annotation and through crowdsourcing. In practice,
                parliamentary papers proved very suitable for automatic annotation. In particular,
                parliamentary debates were written down in a format that has changed very little
                with time.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn31" n="30"> Maarten
                        Marx, “Advanced Information Access to Parliamentary Debates,” <hi rend="italic">Texas Digital Library</hi> 10, no. 6 (2009):
                    2–3.</note> This is one of the reasons why various research projects often
                annotate parliamentary debates using the XML markup language. Among others, sessions
                of the British parliament (Hansard) from 1803,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn32" n="31"> “Hansard archive (digitised debates from 1803),”
                            <hi rend="italic">www.parliament.uk</hi>, accessed on 30 September 2016,
                            <ref target="http://www.hansard-archive.parliament.uk/">http://www.hansard-archive.parliament.uk/</ref>.</note> the Dutch
                parliament from 1803,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn33" n="32"> Maarten Marx and Anne Schuth, “DutchParl. The
                        Parliamentary Documents in Dutch,” in: <hi rend="italic">Proceedings of the
                            International Conference on Language Resources and Evaluation</hi>, eds.
                        Nicoletta Calzolari et al. (Valetta: LREC, 2010), 3670–77.</note> the
                Spanish parliament from 1977,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn34" n="33"> Carlos Martin-Dancausa and Maarten Marx.
                        “Parliamentary documents from Spain,” in: <hi rend="italic">Proceedings of
                            the International Conference on Language Resources and Evaluation</hi>,
                        eds. Nicoletta Calzolari et al. (Valetta: LREC, 2010).</note> the Czech
                parliament from 1993<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn35" n="34"> Miloš Jakubíček and Vojtěch Kovář. CzechParl, “Corpus of Stenographic
                        Protocols from Czech Parliament,” in: <hi rend="italic">Proceedings of
                            Recent Advances in Slavonic Natural Language Processing, RASLAN
                            2010</hi>, eds. Petr Sojka and Aleš Horák (Tribun EU, 2010),
                    41–46.</note> and the Polish parliament from 1993<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn36" n="35"> Maciej Ogrodniczuk, “The Polish
                        Sejm Corpus,” in: <hi rend="italic">LREC 2010, Eight International
                            Conference on Language Resources and Evaluation</hi>, eds. Nicoletta
                        Calzolari et al. (Istanbul, 2012), 2219–23.</note> are all available in
                the XML format.</p>
            <p>The following sections of this article will present the use of Slovenian
                parliamentary papers, particularly the minutes of parliamentary debates, in digital
                history. A number of cases will be presented to illustrate the huge potential of
                smart big data in contemporary history studies. As an example, 2.7 million words of
                the minutes of parliamentary debates in the Chamber of Associated Labour of the
                Assembly of the Republic of Slovenia from 1990 to 1992 have been annotated using the
                XML format.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn37" n="36">
                        “SlovParl,” <hi rend="italic">GitHub</hi>, accessed on 30 September 2016,
                            <ref target="https://github.com/SIstory/SlovParl">https://github.com/SIstory/SlovParl</ref>.</note> In doing so, it
                was decided that the Text Encoding Initiative (TEI) Guidelines should be used,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn38" n="37"> TEI Consortium, <hi rend="italic">TEI P5: Guidelines for Electronic Text Encoding and
                            Interchange</hi> (Text Encoding Initiative Consortium, 2016).</note>
                as these are the <hi rend="italic">de facto</hi> standard for the encoding of texts
                in digital humanities.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn39" n="38"> For example, the German Research Community (Deutsche
                        Forschungsgemeinschaft) demands that any texts being digitized be encoded
                        using the TEI guidelines, if at all possible. Deutsche
                        Forschungsgemeinschaft, <hi rend="italic">DFG Practical Guidelines on
                            Digitisation</hi> (Bonn: Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft, 2013), 31.
                    </note>
            </p>
            <p>Automatic conversions were carried out using XSL stylesheets created specifically for
                the project. However, annotation was also carried out by hand, not just
                automatically. The reason for this was that automatic conversions can also contain
                annotation errors. Attempts were made to find these errors and remove them through
                an upgrade of XSL stylesheets. There were also some parts of text that could only be
                annotated manually. Using such semi-automatic annotation, brief sessions could be
                marked up in 30 minutes, while those of medium length usually took up to two hours
                and the longest (over 200,000 words) up to four hours. Speeches were marked in
                accordance with the TEI module for performance texts (speech, speaker, stage
                direction). Other annotations included the structure of the assemblies and type of
                sessions, individual sessions, topics of individual sessions and dates and duration
                of sessions. Links were created to tables of contents and lists of speakers.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn40" n="39"> Andrej Pančur,
                        “Označevanje zbirke zapisnikov sej slovenskega parlamenta s smernicami TEI,”
                        in: <hi rend="italic">Zbornik konference Jezikovne tehnologije in digitalna
                            humanistika</hi>, eds. Tomaž Erjavec and Darja Fišer (Ljubljana:
                        Znanstvena založba Filozofske fakultete v Ljubljani, 2016),
                    142–48.</note></p>
            <p>Based on such annotated minutes of sessions, researchers can carry out various types
                of fundamental analyses.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn41" n="40"> Jure Gašparič, “Slovenian Socialist Parliament on the
                        Eve of the Dissolution of the Yugoslav Federation. A feeble “ratification
                        body” or important political decision-maker?,” <hi rend="italic">Prispevki
                            za novejšo zgodovino</hi> 55, no. 3 (2015): 54.</note> Over 2.7
                million words were thus spoken in 13,894 speeches at 54 sessions. At the longest,
                36th session, which lasted eight days, the total duration of speeches was 29 hours
                and 3 minutes, and the session was adjourned no less than 21 times. On the other
                hand, the total duration of speeches at the briefest, 9th session was only one hour.
                The longest uninterrupted span was 460 minutes, while the average (median) duration
                of speeches between two interruptions was 90 minutes.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
            <head>Connection to External Data</head>
            <p>However, TEI documents annotated in such a manner also have some shortcomings that
                preclude precise analysis of the speeches. Initial analyses of the speeches of
                various speakers were carried out based on their first and last names. A single
                person, whose name might be written differently in other cases, is thus treated as
                two or more different people. On the other hand, people with identical first and
                last names are automatically considered the same person. Various historical records
                were thus used to manually verify and sanitize the lists of MPs, ministers and other
                invited speakers. These data are contained in a separate TEI document. </p>
            <p>#file: Chart2.xlsx</p>
            <p>Chart 2: Number of words spoken in the Chamber of Associated Labour of the Assembly
                of the Republic of Slovenia (1990/92) by organization membership; in %.</p>
            <p>Data connected in such a manner can, for example, be used to determine the provenance
                of speakers in the Chamber of Associated Labour (see Chart 2). In doing so, we find
                that almost 20% of the words were spoken by various representatives of the
                Government and other rapporteurs associated with the legislation that was being
                passed by the Assembly. As President and Vice-President of the Chamber of Associated
                Labour, Jože Zupančič (President, 735,166 words) and Bogo Rogina (Vice-President,
                114,418 words) together spoke as much as 38.3% of all words spoken by the MPs of the
                Chamber of Associated Labour. Among other MPs of the Assembly, Jože Arzenšek
                (106,000 words), Roman Jakič (69,111 words) and Andrej Šter (67,005) were the most
                verbose. Then there was the silent Jože Košak who only managed to say 14 words
                during his term.</p>
            <p>Speeches of the MPs can obviously also be analysed according to the parties they
                belonged to (see Table 1). MPs who were, at the start of their term, members of the
                DEMOS coalition thus spoke 21.5% of all words, opposition MPs spoke 23.3%, while the
                numerous independent MPs (including the President of the Chamber) spoke as much as
                half of all words.</p>
            <p>#file: Table1.xlsx</p>
            <p>Table 1: Number of words spoken by members of political party; Chamber of Associated
                Labour of the Assembly of the Republic of Slovenia (1990/92)</p>
            <p>Lists of MPs, members of the Government and other speakers can also be used to
                formulate research questions connected to additional variables: first and last name,
                gender, date and place of birth, date and place of death, education, profession,
                residence, organization membership.</p>
            <p>Answers to complicated research questions are possible in part thanks to the newly
                created TEI file that includes a thematic index of the topics dealt with by the
                Chamber. The creation of this table of contents used data from existing topics and
                tables of contents, which were then annotated according to the new scheme. The data
                was first categorized in accordance with the Rules of Procedure of the National
                Assembly (see Chart 3).<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn42" n="41"> “Rules of Procedure of the National Assembly
                        (PoDZ-1),” <hi rend="italic">Republic of Slovenia: National Assembly</hi>,
                        accessed on 30 September 2016, <ref target="https://www.dz-rs.si/wps/portal/en/Home/ODrzavnemZboru/PristojnostiInFunkcije/RulesoftheProcedureText">https://www.dz-rs.si/wps/portal/en/Home/ODrzavnemZboru/PristojnostiInFunkcije/RulesoftheProcedureText</ref>.
                    </note></p>
            <p>#file: Chart3.xlsx</p>
            <p>Chart 3: Thematic index of the speeches in the Chamber of Associated Labour of the
                Assembly of the Republic of Slovenia (1990/92); No. of words by topic as per the
                categorization in the Rules of Procedure of the National Assembly.</p>
            <p>The largest category, <hi rend="italic">Acts and Procedures,</hi> was classified in
                accordance with the thematic index of the Legal Information System of the Republic
                of Slovenia.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn43" n="42">
                        “Tematsko kazalo” [Thematic Index], <hi rend="italic">PIS:
                            Pravno-informacijski sistem</hi> [PIS: Legal Information System],
                        accessed on 30 September 2016, <ref target="http://www.pisrs.si/Pis.web/pravniRedRSDrzavniNivoKazalaTematskoKazalo">http://www.pisrs.si/Pis.web/pravniRedRSDrzavniNivoKazalaTematskoKazalo</ref>.</note>
                Based on data annotated in such a manner, it is easily determined that over a fifth
                of all speeches were associated with the legislation pertaining to the
                constitutional arrangements in the Republic of Slovenia (see Table 2).</p>
            <p>#file: Table2.xlsx</p>
            <p>Table 2: Main topic categories within Acts and Procedures as per the thematic index
                of the Legal Information System of the Republic of Slovenia.</p>
            <p>The greatest amount of discussion was stirred up by the Ownership Transformation of
                Companies Act, which resulted in 520 speeches containing over 100,000 words (see
                Table 3). On the other hand, debate regarding the Act Ratifying the Agreement
                between the Government of the Republic of Slovenia and the Federal Council of the
                Swiss Confederation on the Abolishment of Visas was extremely brief, consisting of
                only 46 words.</p>
            <p>#file: Table3.xlsx</p>
            <p>Table 3: Longest discussions on individual topics (in the category of Acts and
                Procedures)</p>
            </div>
            <div>
            <head>Data Enrichment: Natural Language Processing (NLP)</head>
            <p>Another extremely extensive category was the category named <hi rend="italic">Initiatives, Suggestions and Questions from the MPs</hi> (102,858 words).
                However, the category is too broad to allow any conclusions about its actual content
                based solely on the title. Natural language processing technologies can be of some
                help in this regard. For example, the topic modelling method can be used to search
                for word patterns in the text, which can in turn assist with determining the
                semantic meaning of various parts of the text. One of the most popular (among
                historians as well as other researchers)<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn44" n="43"> Shawn Graham, Scott Weingart and Ian Milligan,
                        “Getting Started with Topic Modeling and MALLET,” <hi rend="italic">Programming Historian</hi> (2 September 2012).</note> tools used in
                such analyses is MALLET.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn45" n="44"> Andrew McCallum, <hi rend="italic">MALLET</hi>: <hi rend="italic">A Machine Learning for Language Toolkit</hi>
                    (2002).</note> Although the results were incomplete, MALLET was nonetheless
                successfully used to discern a number of topics within the
                <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Initiatives, suggestions and questions </hi>category:
                customs duties, healthcare, the environment, strikes, banks, etc.</p>
            <p>A tool that searched the text for named entities (people, places and organizations)
                yielded much better results. Named entity recognition was carried out using the
                Stanford NER for the Slovenian language.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn46" n="45"> Nikola Ljubešić et al., “Combining Available Datasets
                        for Building Named Entity Recognition Models of Croatian and Slovene,” <hi rend="italic">Slovenščina 2.0</hi> 1, no. 2 (2013): 35–57.</note> It
                should come as no surprise that those who were most often named in the speeches of
                MPs were the other MPs. It is also unsurprising that the place name used most often
                by speakers in the Slovenian parliament was Slovenia. Table 4 thus shows that the
                Stanford NER for the Slovenian language recognized 11,378 place names in
                parliamentary speeches, 45% of which were identifiable as Slovenia or the Republic
                of Slovenia. However, a detailed look at the table quickly reveals that the place
                names identified by Stanford NER for the Slovenian language also included names of
                organizations (Assembly, Commission, DEMOS) and other names (Poročevalec).</p>
            <p>#file: Table4.xlsx</p>
            <p>Table 4: List of the 30 most common place names in speeches in the Chamber of
                Associated Labour of the Assembly of the Republic of Slovenia (1990/92) as
                identified by the Stanford NER for the Slovenian language.</p>
            <p>These results clearly indicate that history researchers should never simply copy the
                results of natural language processing (NLP) technologies. At its current level of
                development, the technology is far from infallible. For example, the Stanford NER
                for the Slovenian language has 85% precision when annotating persons, while its
                precision is below 80% when it comes to places.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn47" n="46"> Ljubešić, “Combining Available Datasets for
                        Building Named Entity Recognition Models of Croatian and Slovene,”
                    48.</note> The following warning must thus truly be taken to heart:</p>
            <p rend="Quote">“Historians need to be aware that, in addition to verifying reliability
                of sources as is common in their field, they also need to take the reliability of
                NLP methods into account when working with automatically extracted
                    information.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn48" n="47">
                        Antske Fokkens et al., “BiographyNet: Methodological issues when NLP
                        supports historical research,” in: <hi rend="italic">Proceedings of the
                            Ninth International Conference on Language Resources and Evaluation
                            (LREC’14)</hi>, eds. Nicoletta Calzolari et al. (Reykjavik: European
                        Language Resources Association (ELRA), 2014), 3734.</note></p>
            <p rend="LREC main body text">The authors of this paper are certain that the most
                effective way to achieve this would be through close collaboration with
                computational linguists. The existing TEI documents that had been encoded in
                accordance with the TEI module used for performance texts were thus subsequently
                converted into TEI documents wherein the text was annotated in accordance with the
                speech transcription TEI module. Such documents can then be furnished with
                linguistic annotations at a later time. Computational linguists have thus already
                provided part-of-speech tagging for the text of the speeches. The corpus has been
                imported into the No Sketch Engine concordance base<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn49" n="48"> “SlovParl (parlament RS 1990–1992),” <hi rend="italic">NoSketch Engine</hi>, accessed on 30 September 2016, <ref target="http://nl.ijs.si/noske/all.cgi/corp_info?corpname=slovparl">http://nl.ijs.si/noske/all.cgi/corp_info?corpname=slovparl</ref>. Tomaž
                        Erjavec, “Korpusi in konkordančniki na strežniku nl.ijs.si,” <hi rend="italic">Slovenščina 2.0</hi> 1, no. 1 (2013): 24–49.</note>
                and all TEI documents are accessible at the CLARIN.SI repository.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn50" n="49"> Tomaž Erjavec, Jan Jona Javoršek
                        and Simon Krek, “Raziskovalna infrastruktura CLARIN.SI,” in: <hi rend="italic">Proceedings of the 17th International Multiconference
                            Information Society – IS 2014: Language Technologies</hi>, eds. Tomaž
                        Erjavec and Jerneja Žganec Gros (Ljubljana: IJS, 2014), 19–24. Andrej
                        Pančur, Mojca Šorn and Tomaž Erjavec, <hi rend="italic">Slovenian
                            parliamentary corpus SlovParl 1.0</hi> (2016), distributed by Slovenian
                        language resource repository CLARIN.SI, <ref target="http://hdl.handle.net/11356/1075">http://hdl.handle.net/11356/1075</ref>.</note></p>
            </div>
            <div>
            <head>Conclusion</head>
            <p>This article has attempted to show, based on a number of fundamental analyses of the
                minutes of the sessions of the Chamber of Associated Labour of the Assembly of the
                Republic of Slovenia (1990/92), that future historians will be unable to process the
                increasing amounts of digital materials using standard historiographical methods and
                will be forced to start supplementing these with methods and tools developed by
                digital humanities. In doing so, most historians will still rely on various tools
                developed by digital historians in order to simplify the work of their colleagues
                who are unfamiliar with digital humanities. At the same time, digital historians
                will also have to be aware of the limitations of the use of tools developed by other
                fields, including language technologies. On the other hand, historians who have
                started learning the basics of programming languages are increasingly establishing
                themselves in the field.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn51" n="50"> Nanni et al., “Semi-Supervised Textual Analysis and
                        Historical Research Helping Each Other,” 63–68. Graham et al., <hi rend="italic">Exploring Big Historical Data: The Historian’s
                            Macroscope</hi>.</note> The reason for this is that this is the only
                way to extract additional useful research results from existing digital sources.
                This is also the manner in which most of the analyses presented by this paper were
                carried out. At the same time, the authors of this article are well aware that in
                addition to new knowledge supplied by digital history, it remains indispensable for
                researchers to be very familiar with research domain. It can thus be anticipated
                that future research of contemporary history will take place through fruitful
                collaboration of experts from a multitude of different fields.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="bibliography">
            <head>Sources and Literature</head>
            <listBibl>
            <head>Dataset:</head>
                <bibl>Pančur, Andrej, Mojca Šorn and Tomaž Erjavec. <hi rend="italic">Slovenian
                    parliamentary corpus SlovParl 1.0</hi> (2016). Distributed by Slovenian
                    language resource repository CLARIN.SI. <ref target="http://hdl.handle.net/11356/1075">http://hdl.handle.net/11356/1075</ref>.</bibl>
            </listBibl>
            <listBibl>
                <head>Literature:</head>
                <bibl>Benardou, Agiatis, Alastair Dunning, Martin Schaller and Nephelie
                    Chatzidiakou. <hi rend="italic">Research Themes for Aggregating Digital Content.
                        Parliamentary Papers in Europe</hi>. Europeana Cloud, 2015. Accessed 28
                    September 2016. <ref target="http://pro.europeana.eu/files/Europeana_Professional/Projects/Project_list/Europeana_Cloud/WP1%20Research%20Needs/research-themes-for-aggregating-digital-content-parliamentary-papers.pdf">http://pro.europeana.eu/files/Europeana_Professional/Projects/Project_list/Europeana_Cloud/WP1%20Research%20Needs/research-themes-for-aggregating-digital-content-parliamentary-papers.pdf</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl>Collins, Sandra, Natalie Harrower, Dag Trygve Truslew Haug, Beat Immenhauser,
                    Gerhard Lauer, Tito Orlandi, Laurent Romary and Eveline Wandl-Vogt. <hi rend="italic">ALLEA E-Humanities Working Group Report. Going Digital:
                        Creating Change in the Humanities</hi>. Berlin: All European Academies,
                    2015. Accessed 19 July 2016. <ref target="http://www.allea.org/Content/ALLEA/WG%20E%20Humanities/Going%20Digital_digital%20version.pdf">http://www.allea.org/Content/ALLEA/WG%20E%20Humanities/Going%20Digital_digital%20version.pdf</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl>Cvelfar, Bojan, Tatjana Hajtnik, Miroslav Novak, Nada Čibej and Drago Trpin.
                    <hi rend="italic">Strategija in izvedbeni načrt razvoja slovenskega
                        elektronskega arhiva 2016 – 2020.</hi> Ljubljana: Arhiv Republike Slovenije,
                    2016.</bibl>
                <bibl>Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft. <hi rend="italic">DFG Practical Guidelines on
                    Digitisation.</hi> Bonn: Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft, 2013. Accessed 19
                    July 2016. <ref target="http://www.dfg.de/formulare/12_151/12_151_en.pdf">http://www.dfg.de/formulare/12_151/12_151_en.pdf</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl>Elliot, Devon, Robert MacDougall and William J. Turkel. “New Old Things:
                    Fabrication, Physical Computing, and Experiment in Historical Practice.” <hi rend="italic">Canadian Journal of Communication</hi> 37 (2012): 122.
                    Accessed 19 July 2016. <ref target="http://www.cjc-online.ca/index.php/journal/article/view/2506">http://www.cjc-online.ca/index.php/journal/article/view/2506</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl>Erjavec, Tomaž, Jan Jona Javoršek and Simon Krek. ”Raziskovalna infrastruktura
                    CLARIN.SI.” In: <hi rend="italic">Proceedings of the 17th International
                        Multiconference Information Society – IS 2014: Language Technologies</hi>,
                    eds. Tomaž Erjavec and Jerneja Žganec Gros, 19<hi rend="italic">–</hi>24.
                    Ljubljana: IJS, 2014. Accessed 30 September 2016. <ref target="http://nl.ijs.si/isjt14/proceedings/isjt2014_03.pdf">http://nl.ijs.si/isjt14/proceedings/isjt2014_03.pdf</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl>Erjavec, Tomaž. ”Korpusi in konkordančniki na strežniku nl.ijs.si.” <hi rend="italic">Slovenščina 2.0</hi> 1, no. 1 (2013): 24-49. Accessed 19 July
                    2016. <ref target="http://slovenscina2.0.trojina.si/arhiv/2013/1/Slo2.0_2013_1_03.pdf">http://slovenscina2.0.trojina.si/arhiv/2013/1/Slo2.0_2013_1_03.pdf</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl>Fokkens, Antske, Serge ter Braake, Niels Ockeloen, Piek Vossen, Susan Legêne
                    and Guus Schreiber. ”BiographyNet: Methodological issues when NLP supports
                    historical research.” In: <hi rend="italic">Proceedings of the Ninth
                        International Conference on Language Resources and Evaluation
                        (LREC'14)</hi>, eds. Nicoletta Calzolari, Khalid Choukri, Thierry Declerck,
                    Hrafn Loftsson, Bente Maegaard, Joseph Mariani, Asuncion Moreno, Jan Odijk and
                    Stelios Piperidis, 3728<hi rend="italic">–</hi>35. Reykjavik: European Language
                    Resources Association (ELRA), 2014. Accessed 30 September 2016. <ref target="http://www.lrec-conf.org/proceedings/lrec2014/pdf/1103_Paper.pdf">http://www.lrec-conf.org/proceedings/lrec2014/pdf/1103_Paper.pdf</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl>Gašparič, Jure. “Slovenian Socialist Parliament on the Eve of the Dissolution
                    of the Yugoslav Federation. A feeble ”ratification body” or important political
                    decision-maker?.” <hi rend="italic">Prispevki za novejšo zgodovino</hi> 55, no.
                    3 (2015): 41<hi rend="italic">–</hi>59. Accessed 19 July 2016. <ref target="http://ojs.inz.si/pnz/article/view/123">http://ojs.inz.si/pnz/article/view/123</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl>Gašparič, Jure. ”Pisati politično zgodovino Republike Slovenije.” In: <hi rend="italic">Četrt stoletja Republike Slovenije – izzivi, dileme,
                    pričakovanja</hi>, eds. Jure Gašparič and Mojca Šorn, 27<hi rend="italic">–</hi>37. Ljubljana: Institute of Contemporary History Institute of
                    Contemporary History, 2016.</bibl>
                <bibl>Gašparič, Jure. <hi rend="italic">Državni zbor 1992 – 2012. O slovenskem
                    parlamentarizmu</hi>. Ljubljana: Institute of Contemporary History,
                    2012.</bibl>
                <bibl>Gašparič, Jure. <hi rend="italic">Slovenski parlament: politično-zgodovinski
                    pregled od začetka prvega do konca šestega mandata (1992-2014)</hi>.
                    Ljubljana: Institute of Contemporary History, 2014. Accessed 19 July 2016. <ref target="http://hdl.handle.net/11686/26950">http://hdl.handle.net/11686/26950</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl>Graham, Shawn, Ian Milligan and Scott Weingart. <hi rend="italic">Exploring
                    Big Historical Data: The Historian’s Macroscope</hi>. London: Imperial
                    College Press, 2015. Accessed 28 September 2016. <ref target="http://www.themacroscope.org">http://www.themacroscope.org</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl>Graham, Shawn, Scott Weingart and Ian Milligan. ”Getting Started with Topic
                    Modeling and MALLET.” <hi rend="italic">Programming Historian</hi> (2 September
                    2012). Accessed 19 July 2016. <ref target="http://programminghistorian.org/lessons/topic-modeling-and-mallet">http://programminghistorian.org/lessons/topic-modeling-and-mallet</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl>Haber, Peter. “Zeitgeschichte und Digital Humanities.” In: <hi rend="italic">Zeitgeschichte – Konzepte und Methoden</hi>, eds. Frank Bösch and Danyel
                    Jürgen, 47<hi rend="italic">–</hi>66. Göttingen: Vandenhoeck &amp; Ruprecht,
                    2012. Accessed 19 July 2016. <ref target="http://dx.doi.org/10.14765/zzf.dok.2.269.v1">http://dx.doi.org/10.14765/zzf.dok.2.269.v1</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl>Hajtnik, Tatjana. ”Strategija razvoja slovenskega javnega elektronskega arhiva
                    ’e-ARH.si’.” <hi rend="italic">Knjižnica</hi> 55, no. 1 (2011): 39<hi rend="italic">–</hi>56. <ref target="http://revija-knjiznica.zbds-zveza.si/Izvodi/K1101/Hajtnik.pdf">http://revija-knjiznica.zbds-zveza.si/Izvodi/K1101/Hajtnik.pdf</ref>
                </bibl>
                <bibl>Jakubíček, Miloš and Vojtěch Kovář. CzechParl. “Corpus of Stenographic
                    Protocols from Czech Parliament.” In: <hi rend="italic">Proceedings of Recent
                        Advances in Slavonic Natural Language Processing, RASLAN 2010</hi>, eds.
                    Petr Sojka and Aleš Horák, 41<hi rend="italic">–</hi>46. Tribun EU, 2010.
                    Accessed 19 July 2016. <ref target="http://www.muni.cz/research/publications/914313">http://www.muni.cz/research/publications/914313</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl>Ljubešić, Nikola, Marija Stupar, Tereza Jurić and Željko Agić. “Combining
                    Available Datasets for Building Named Entity Recognition Models of Croatian and
                    Slovene.” <hi rend="italic">Slovenščina 2.0</hi> 1, no. 2 (2013): 35<hi rend="italic">–</hi>57.</bibl>
                <bibl>Martin-Dancausa, Carlos and Maarten Marx. “Parliamentary documents from
                    Spain.” In: <hi rend="italic">Proceedings of the International Conference on
                        Language Resources and Evaluation</hi>, eds. Nicoletta Calzolari, Khalid
                    Choukri, Bente Maegaard, Joseph Mariani, Jan Odijk, Stelios Piperidis, Mike
                    Rosner and Daniel Tapias. Valetta: LREC, 2010. Accessed 19 July 2016. <ref target="https://www.researchgate.net/publication/239585911">https://www.researchgate.net/publication/239585911</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl>Marx, Maarten and Anne Schuth. “DutchParl. The Parliamentary Documents in
                    Dutch.” In: <hi rend="italic">Proceedings of the International Conference on
                        Language Resources and Evaluation</hi>, eds. Nicoletta Calzolari, Khalid
                    Choukri, Bente Maegaard, Joseph Mariani, Jan Odijk, Stelios Piperidis, Mike
                    Rosner and Daniel Tapias, 3670<hi rend="italic">–</hi>77. Valetta: LREC, 2010.
                    Accessed 19 July 2016. <ref target="http://www.lrec-conf.org/proceedings/lrec2010/pdf/263_Paper.pdf">http://www.lrec-conf.org/proceedings/lrec2010/pdf/263_Paper.pdf</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl>Marx, Maarten. ”Advanced Information Access to Parliamentary Debates.” <hi rend="italic">Texas Digital Library</hi> 10, no. 6 (2009): 1<hi rend="italic">–</hi>11. Accessed 19 July 2016. <ref target="https://journals.tdl.org/jodi/index.php/jodi/article/view/668">https://journals.tdl.org/jodi/index.php/jodi/article/view/668</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl>McCallum, Andrew Kachites. <hi rend="italic">MALLET</hi>: <hi rend="italic">A
                    Machine Learning for Language Toolkit</hi>. 2002. Accessed 19 July 2016.
                    <ref target="http://mallet.cs.umass.edu/">http://mallet.cs.umass.edu/</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl>Nanni, Federico, Hiram Kumper and Simone Paolo Ponzetto. “Semi-Supervised
                    Textual Analysis and Historical Research Helping Each Other: Some Thoughts and
                    Observations.” <hi rend="italic">International Journal of Humanities and Arts
                        Computing</hi> 10, no. 1 (2016): 63<hi rend="italic">–</hi>77. Accessed 19
                    July 2016. <ref target="http://dx.doi.org/10.3366/ijhac.2016.0160">http://dx.doi.org/10.3366/ijhac.2016.0160</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl>Nicholson, Bob. “The Digital Turn: Exploring the methodological possibilities
                    of digital newspaper archives.” <hi rend="italic">Media History</hi> 19, no. 1
                    (2013): 59<hi rend="italic">–</hi>73. Accessed 30 September 2016. <ref target="http://dx.doi.org/10.1080/13688804.2012.752963">http://dx.doi.org/10.1080/13688804.2012.752963</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl>Ogrodniczuk, Maciej. “The Polish Sejm Corpus.” In: <hi rend="italic">LREC
                    2010, Eight International Conference on Language Resources and
                    Evaluation</hi>, eds. Nicoletta Calzolari, Khalid Choukri, Thierry Declerck,
                    Mehmet Uğur Doğan, Bente Maegaard, Joseph Mariani, Asuncion Moreno, Jan Odijk
                    and Stelios Piperidis, 2219<hi rend="italic">–</hi>23. Istanbul, 2012. Accessed
                    19 July 2016. <ref target="http://www.lrec-conf.org/proceedings/lrec2012/pdf/653_Paper.pdf">http://www.lrec-conf.org/proceedings/lrec2012/pdf/653_Paper.pdf</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl>Pančur, Andrej. ”Označevanje zbirke zapisnikov sej slovenskega parlamenta s
                    smernicami TEI” [Encoding the Slovenian Parliament Session Minutes in Line with
                    the TEI Guidelines]. In:
                    <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Zbornik konference Jezikovne tehnologije in digitalna humanistika </hi>[Proceedings
                    of the Conference on Language Technologies &amp; Digital Humanities], eds. Tomaž
                    Erjavec and Darja Fišer, 142<hi rend="italic">–</hi>48. Ljubljana: Znanstvena
                    založba Filozofske fakultete v Ljubljani, 2016. Accessed 5 October 2016. <ref target="http://nl.ijs.si/isjt16/proceedings-en.html">http://nl.ijs.si/isjt16/proceedings-en.html</ref>. </bibl>
                <bibl>Pesek, Rosvita. <hi rend="italic">Osamosvojitev Slovenije</hi>. Ljubljana:
                    Nova revija, 2007.</bibl>
                <bibl>Piersma, Hinke and Kees Ribbens. ”Digital Historical Research: Context,
                    Concept and the Need for Reflection.” <hi rend="italic">BMGN – Low Countries
                        Historical Review</hi> 128, no. 4 (2013): 78<hi rend="italic">–</hi>102.</bibl>
                <bibl>Piersma, Hinke, Ismee Tames, Lars Buitinck and Maarten Marx. ”War in
                    Parliament. What a Digital Approach Can Add to the Study of Parliamentary
                    History.” <hi rend="italic">DHQ: Digital Humanities Quarterly</hi> 8, no. 1
                    (2014). Accessed 30 September 2016. <ref target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/8/1/000176/000176.html">http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/8/1/000176/000176.html</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl>Robertson, Stephen. “The Differences between Digital Humanities and Digital
                    History.” In: <hi rend="italic">Debates in Digital Humanities 2016</hi>, eds.
                    Matthew K. Gold and Lauren F. Klein. Minneapolis and London: University of
                    Minnesota Press, 2016. Accessed 25 September 2016. <ref target="http://dhdebates.gc.cuny.edu/debates/text/76">http://dhdebates.gc.cuny.edu/debates/text/76</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl>Rosenzwig, Roy. “Scarcity or Abundance? Preserving the Past in a Digital Era.”
                    <hi rend="italic">American Historical Review</hi> 108, no. 3 (2003): 735<hi rend="italic">–</hi>62.</bibl>
                <bibl>Schöch, Christof. ”Big? Smart? Clean? Messy? Data in the Humanities.” <hi rend="italic">Journal of Digital Humanities</hi> 2, no. 3 (2013). Accessed
                    25 September 2016. <ref target="http://journalofdigitalhumanities.org/2-3/big-smart-clean-messy-data-in-the-humanities/">http://journalofdigitalhumanities.org/2-3/big-smart-clean-messy-data-in-the-humanities/</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl>Spiro, Lisa. “Access, Explore, Converse. The Impact (and Potential Impact) of
                    the Digital Humanities on Scholarship.” In: <hi rend="italic">Keys for
                        architectural history research in the digital era</hi>, eds. <hi rend="Strong"><seg rend="normalweight">Juliette</seg>
                        </hi><hi rend="familyname">Hueber</hi><hi rend="Strong"><seg rend="normalweight" xml:space="preserve"> and Antonio </seg></hi><hi rend="familyname">Mendes da Silva.</hi> 2014. Accessed 25 September 2016.
                    <ref target="https://inha.revues.org/4925">https://inha.revues.org/4925</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl>TEI Consortium. <hi rend="italic">TEI P5: Guidelines for Electronic Text
                    Encoding and Interchange</hi>, Text Encoding Initiative Consortium, 2016.
                    Accessed 19 July 2016. <ref target="http://www.tei-c.org/Guidelines/P5/">http://www.tei-c.org/Guidelines/P5/</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl>Zaagsma, Gerben. ”On Digital History.” <hi rend="italic">BMGN – Low Countries
                    Historical Review</hi> 128, no. 4 (2013): 3<hi rend="italic">–</hi>29. <ref target="http://www.bmgn-lchr.nl/articles/10.18352/bmgn-lchr.9344/">http://www.bmgn-lchr.nl/articles/10.18352/bmgn-lchr.9344/</ref>.</bibl>
            </listBibl>
        </div>
            <div type="summary" xml:lang="sl">
                <head type="main">PAMETNI MASIVNI PODATKI: UPORABA SLOVENSKIH PARLAMENTARNIH DOKUMENTOV V DIGITALNI
                    ZGODOVINI</head>
                <head>POVZETEK</head>
                
                <docAuthor>Andrej Pančur</docAuthor>
                <docAuthor>Mojca Šorn</docAuthor>
            <p>Avtorja v uvodu opozoriva na dejstvo, da velika količina računalniško berljivih
                podatkov postaja stvarnost in neizogibno dejstvo tudi v zgodovinopisju, pri čemer
                poudariva, da je prav ta fenomen spodbudil nastanek in uveljavitev digitalne
                humanistike, ki s pomočjo digitalnih metod in orodij odgovarja na nova raziskovalna
                vprašanja<hi rend="italic">.</hi></p>
            <p>Ker so parlamentarni dokumenti bogat vir podatkov, ki ga uporabljajo različne
                discipline v humanistiki, med drugim tudi v zgodovinopisju, avtorja v nadaljevanju
                predstaviva primer uporabe parlamentarnih debat v digitalni zgodovini. Predstavljeni
                primeri so ilustrativni vzorci, s pomočjo katerih hočeva prikazati ogromen
                potencial, ki ga lahko imajo pametni množični podatki v raziskavah sodobne
                zgodovine. Vzorčno sva v XML formatu označila 2,7 milijona besed parlamentarnih
                debat v Zboru združenega dela Skupščine Republike Slovenije v letih 1990–1992. Pri
                tem sva se odločila uporabiti Smernice Text Encoding Initiative (TEI), ki so v
                digitalni humanistiki <hi rend="italic">de facto</hi> standard za kodiranje
                tekstovnih besedil. Avtomatske pretvorbe sva izvajala s pomočjo XSLT stilov,
                napisanih posebej za ta projekt. Ker avtomatske pretvorbe lahko vsebujejo tudi
                napačne označbe, je označevanje potekalo delno tudi ročno. S tem delno avtomatskim
                označevanjem sva krajše seje lahko označila v pol ure, za daljše seje sva po navadi
                porabila do dve uri, za najdaljše (več kot 200000 besed) pa do štiri ure. Govore sva
                označila v skladu s TEI modulom za dramska besedila (govor, govorec, didaskalija).
                Označila sva še strukturo zborov in vrste sej, posameznih sej, vsebinskih sklopov
                posameznih sej, datumov in časovnega poteka sej. Naredila sva povezave na kazala
                vsebine in sezname govorcev.</p>
            <p>Na podlagi tako označenih zapisnikov sej lahko raziskovalci naredijo različne vrste
                osnovnih analiz. V 13894 govorih je bilo na 54 sejah tako skupaj izgovorjenih več
                kot 2,7 milijonov besed. Na najdaljši – 36. seji – so v osmih dnevih skupaj govorili
                29 ur in 3 minute, pri čemer so sejo kar enaindvajsetkrat prekinili. Na najkrajši –
                9. seji – pa so nasprotno skupaj govorili samo eno uro. Največ so neprekinjeno
                govorili 460 minut, v povprečju (mediana) pa so neprekinjeno govorili uro in
                pol.</p>
            <p>Osnovne analize zapisnikov torej pokažejo, da v prihodnosti zgodovinarji vedno večjih
                količin digitalnega gradiva ne bodo več mogli obdelovati samo z uporabo klasičnih
                zgodovinskih metod, temveč bodo morali začeti uporabljati metode in orodja, ki jih
                razvija digitalna humanistika. Večina zgodovinarjev se bo pri tem (še naprej)
                zanašala na različna orodja, ki jih razvijajo digitalni zgodovinarji z namenom, da
                olajšajo delo svojim kolegom, ki se ne ukvarjajo z digitalno humanistiko. Pri tem pa
                bodo digitalni zgodovinarji morali poznati omejitve, ki jih prinaša uporaba orodij,
                razvitih v okrilju drugih disciplin, med drugim tudi jezikovne tehnologije. Avtorja
                prispevka se dobro zavedava, da je za kakovostne analize poleg novih znanj, ki jih
                prinaša digitalna zgodovina, neobhodno potrebno tudi temeljito poznavanje
                raziskovalne domene. Zato lahko predvidimo, da bo raziskovanje sodobne zgodovine
                potekalo v znamenju plodnega sodelovanja strokovnjakov iz različnih področij.</p>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>