<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>An Emperor by a Different Name: School Commemoration in Habsburg
                    Austria and the Second Austrian Republic</title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename>Scott O.</forename>
                        <surname>Moore</surname>
                        <roleName>Assistant Professor of History</roleName>
                        <roleName>PhD</roleName>
                        <affiliation>Eastern Connecticut State University</affiliation>
                        <address>
                            <addrLine>United States</addrLine>
                        </address>
                        <email>mooresc@easternct.edu</email>
                    </name>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>2017-05-22</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>
                    <orgName xml:lang="sl">Inštitut za novejšo zgodovino</orgName>
                    <orgName xml:lang="en">Institute of Contemporary History</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Kongresni trg 1</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>SI-1000 Ljubljana</addrLine>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>http://ojs.inz.si/pnz/article/view/226</pubPlace>
                <date>2017</date>
                <availability status="free">
                    <licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title xml:lang="sl">Prispevki za novejšo zgodovino</title>
                <title xml:lang="en">Contributions to Contemporary History</title>
                <biblScope unit="volume">57</biblScope>
                <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
                <idno type="ISSN">2463-7807</idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source, born digital.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc xml:lang="en">
                <p>Contributions to Contemporary History is one of the central Slovenian scientific
                    historiographic journals, dedicated to publishing articles from the field of
                    contemporary history (the 19th and 20th century).</p>
                <p>The journal is published three times per year in Slovenian and in the following
                    foreign languages: English, German, Serbian, Croatian, Bosnian, Italian, Slovak
                    and Czech. The articles are all published with abstracts in English and
                    Slovenian as well as summaries in English.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <projectDesc xml:lang="sl">
                <p>Prispevki za novejšo zgodovino je ena osrednjih slovenskih znanstvenih
                    zgodovinopisnih revij, ki objavlja teme s področja novejše zgodovine (19. in 20.
                    stoletje).</p>
                <p>Revija izide trikrat letno v slovenskem jeziku in v naslednjih tujih jezikih:
                    angleščina, nemščina, srbščina, hrvaščina, bosanščina, italijanščina, slovaščina
                    in češčina. Članki izhajajo z izvlečki v angleščini in slovenščini ter povzetki
                    v angleščini.</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="sl"/>
                <language ident="en"/>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords xml:lang="en">
                    <term>Habsburg Austria</term>
                    <term>Second Austrian Republic</term>
                    <term>school commemorations</term>
                    <term>Emperor</term>
                    <term>President</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords xml:lang="sl">
                    <term>Habsburška Avstrija</term>
                    <term>druga avstrijska republika</term>
                    <term>šolske proslave</term>
                    <term>cesar</term>
                    <term>predsednik</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change>
                    <date>2017-11-20</date>
                    <name>Neja Blaj Hribar</name>
                    <desc>Pretvorba iz DOCX v TEI, dodatno kodiranje</desc>
                </change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <docAuthor>Scott O. Moore<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn1" n="*">
                    <hi rend="bold" xml:space="preserve">Assistant Professor of History, PhD, Eastern Connecticut State University, United States, </hi><ref target="mailto:mooresc@easternct.edu"><hi rend="bold">mooresc@easternct.edu</hi></ref>
                </note>
            </docAuthor>
            <docImprint>
                <idno type="cobissType">Cobiss type: 1.01</idno>
                <idno type="UDC">UDC: 394.4:373(436)"1918/1945"</idno>
            </docImprint>
            <div type="abstract" xml:lang="sl">
                <head>IZVLEČEK</head>
                <head>CESAR Z DRUGAČNIM IMENOM: ŠOLSKE SLOVESNOSTI V HABSBURŠKI AVSTRIJI
                    IN DRUGI AVSTRIJSKI REPUBLIKI</head>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Članek proučuje povezavo med šolskimi proslavami, s katerimi so v
                        poznem obdobju habsburške Avstrije izražali domoljubje, in podobnimi proslavami
                        v drugi avstrijski republiki.  Podobno kot v drugih državah je bilo javno
                        šolstvo tudi v habsburški Avstriji sredstvo za domoljubno vzgojo.  Eden
                        najočitnejših primerov je bila vsakoletna slovesnost ob cesarjevem rojstnem
                        dnevu. Med takimi slovesnostmi so morali učenci šol v Habsburški monarhiji
                        recitirati domoljubno poezijo, prepevati domoljubne pesmi in poslušati govore o
                        vrlinah svojega monarha. Čeprav teh slovesnosti po koncu monarhije ni bilo več,
                        članek razkriva, da so se v povojni Avstriji pojavile v drugačni, nekoliko
                        posebni obliki.</hi></p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Čeprav je Avstrija po padcu monarhije poskušala
                    ustvariti identiteto, ki bi bila neodvisna od imperialne preteklosti, je
                    zapuščina imperialističnih slovesnosti in državotvornih dejavnosti še naprej
                    vplivala na avstrijsko dojemanje domoljubnih proslav. Ta zapuščina je bila močna
                    zlasti po drugi svetovni vojni. V prispevku je z doslej neraziskanimi govori,
                    programi in organizacijskimi gradivi z avstrijskih šolskih proslav po letu 1945
                    in podobnimi viri iz habsburškega obdobja prikazano, da so avstrijske šole po
                    vojni za spodbujanje domoljubja pri učencih uporabljale programe, enake tistim
                    iz habsburškega obdobja. Ta pregled ponazarja vpliv imperialne birokracije na
                    njeno zapuščino in moč nezavednega birokratskega spomina, ki se lahko tudi po
                    premikih mej in razpadih držav ohrani skozi generacije. To nam pomaga pri
                    razumevanju mejnega spomina v Srednji Evropi in izboljša naše razumevanje
                    spomina v državah po spremembah ustave in obsega ozemlja.</hi></p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Ključne besede: Habsburška Avstrija, druga avstrijska republika,
                    šolske proslave, cesar, predsednik</hi></p></div>
            <div type="abstract"><head>ABSTRACT</head>
                <p><hi rend="italic">This paper examines the connections between
                    patriotic school celebrations in late-Habsburg Austria and similar celebrations
                    in the Second Austrian Republic. Similar to other states, Habsburg Austria
                    utilized public schools as a vehicle for patriotic education. One of the most
                    obvious examples of this fact were the annual commemorations of the emperor’s
                    birth. During these commemorations, schools across the Habsburg Monarchy would
                    have students recite patriotic poems, sing patriotic songs, and listen to
                    speeches detailing the virtues of their monarch. While these commemorations
                    ended with the Monarchy, this paper illustrates that these events experienced a
                    curious afterlife in postwar Austria.</hi></p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Even though Austria attempted to craft an identity
                    independent of its former imperial past when the Monarchy collapsed, the legacy
                    of imperial commemoration and state-building continued to influence the way
                    Austria conceptualized patriotic celebration. This legacy was especially strong
                    after World War II. Using previously unexamined speeches, programs, and
                    organizational materials from Austrian school celebrations after 1945, along
                    with similar sources from the Habsburg period, this paper will show that postwar
                    Austrian schools used programs identical to those from the Habsburg period to
                    develop the patriotism of students. This examination illustrates the legacy of
                    the imperial administration on its remnants and the power of unconscious
                    bureaucratic memory which can survive generations after border change and state
                    collapse. As a result, it helps to develop our understanding of border memory in
                    Central Europe and enhances our understanding of memory in states after changes
                    to its constitution and lands.</hi></p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Key words: Habsburg Austria, Second Austrian Republic, school
                    commemorations, Emperor, President</hi></p></div>
        </front>
        <body>
           <p>In its final decades, the Dual Monarchy of Austria-Hungary crafted a series of public
                commemorations and celebrations aimed at enhancing the patriotism of its citizens.
                These events took several forms, including parades, the construction of monuments
                honoring Austrian historical figures, and the celebration of anniversaries and state
                holidays. Often, these events occurred in schools or with the participation from
                schoolchildren, a practice common throughout Europe and the United States. As public
                education became a standard feature of the modern state in the nineteenth century,
                governments quickly realized that schools could do more than simply educate
                children. They could also be used to shape how children conceptualized their
                government, their state, and their culture. In Austria-Hungary, these school events
                sought to create a sense of cohesion and belonging among the Monarchy’s diverse
                population. In order to accomplish this task, Habsburg civic education relied
                heavily on teaching the history of the Monarchy in a way that emphasized the shared
                sacrifices and struggles of its peoples and by crafting an Austrian identity that
                was supranational and imperial in nature. This identity asserted that anyone who
                lived in and was loyal to the Habsburg Monarchy could rightful consider himself as
                Austrian.</p>
            <p> Efforts of this kind were an essential part of patriotic development in the
                Monarchy, aimed at stressing the unity and cohesion of the multinational state,
                arguing that its diversity was a strength, not a weakness. The works of Pieter
                Judson and Tara Zahra make clear that nationalists attempted to use education as a
                tool of nationalization, while also demonstrating that national identity was not as
                rigidly formed as earlier scholarship assumed. Instead, there was a substantial
                amount of ambivalence and indifference toward national identity.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn2" n="1"> Pieter M. Judson, <hi rend="italic">Guardians of the Nation: Activists on the Language Frontiers of
                            Imperial Austria</hi> (Cambridge: Harvard University Press, 2006),
                        19–65. Tara Zahra, <hi rend="italic">Kidnapped Souls: National Indifference
                            and the Battle for Children in the Bohemian Lands, 1900</hi>–<hi rend="italic">1948</hi> (Ithaca, NY: Cornell University Press, 2008),
                        13–79. For further discussion of this national indifference and the efforts
                        of nationalists, see Jeremy King, <hi rend="italic">Budweisers into Czechs
                            and Germans: A Local History of Bohemian Politics,
                        1848-1948 </hi>(Princeton:
                        Princeton University Press, 2002). Keely Stauter-Halsted, <hi rend="italic">The Nation in the Village: The Genesis of Peasant National Identity in
                            Austrian Poland, 1848</hi>–<hi rend="italic">1914</hi> (Ithaca, NY:
                        Cornell University Press, 2001). </note> The fluidity of identity meant
                that there was space for the Habsburg state to develop the loyalty of its subjects,
                and as Judson recently argued, Habsburg officials aggressively crafted and developed
                their image in an effort to accomplish this task.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn3" n="2"> Pieter M. Judson,
                        <hi rend="italic">The Habsburg Empire: A New History </hi>(Cambridge:
                        The Belknap Press, 2016), 4–8.</note> As a result of these conditions,
                it is natural that these officials would use public schools to develop an Austrian
                identity that could transcend national division.</p>
            <p> Obviously, loyalty to the monarch, Franz Joseph, was essential to this identity. He,
                and the Habsburg dynasty as a whole, provided the connective thread which bound the
                state together. Because of this, Habsburg schools utilized every opportunity to
                celebrate the monarch and commemorate his achievements. One of the most common ways
                by which schools accomplished this goal was through school events held in the
                emperor’s honor. As the Upper Austrian Provincial schoolboard noted throughout its
                reports in the 1880s, these events provided an ideal opportunity to strengthen “the
                loyalty, unbreakable attachment, and love of the fatherland and exalted
                    dynasty.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn4" n="3"> OÖLA,
                        LSR, box 22, <hi rend="italic">Jahreshauptbericht für Mittelschulen in
                            Oberösterreich, 1884</hi>. OÖLA, LSR, box 23, <hi rend="italic">Jahreshauptbericht für Mittelschulen in Oberösterreich,
                    1887</hi>.</note> Celebrations honoring Franz Joseph were held in every
                school across the Monarchy, regardless of region or the nationality of its students
                and in spite of the Monarchy’s federalized education system, the format of these
                events were similar throughout the Austrian half of the state.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn5" n="4"> For more on the organization of
                        Austrian schools, see Peter Urbanitsch, “Österreichs Schulen:
                        Organisatorischer und struktureller Wandel 1848 bis 1914,” in: <hi rend="italic">Kindheit und Schule im Ersten Weltkrieg</hi>, Hannes
                        Stekl, Christa Hämmerle, Ernst Bruckmüller, eds. (Vienna: New Academic
                        Press, 2016), 45–73.</note> The consistency of these celebrations
                resulted from the guidance provided by the Ministry of Religion and Education, which
                supervised Austrian schools, as well as a general consensus regarding the structure
                of school ceremonies.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn6" n="5">
                        Comparing the celebrations described by the school boards of Upper Austria,
                        Lower Austria, Styria, Moravia, and Bohemia reflects this consistency. For
                        such a comparison, see <hi rend="italic">Jahresbericht über das k.k.
                            akademisches Gymnasium in Wien für das Schuljahr 1868</hi>–<hi rend="italic">1869</hi> (Vienna: Verlag des k.k. akademischen
                        Gymnasiums, 1869), 50. OÖLA, LSR, box 76, doc. 1599, discussing schools in
                        Perg. OÖLA, LSR, box 76, <hi rend="italic">Jahreshauptbericht über die
                            allgemeinen Volks- und Bürgerschulen und die Bildungsanstalten für
                            Lehrer- und Lehrerinnen in Steiermark</hi>, 1906;
                        <hi rend="italic">Programm des kaiserl. königl. Gymnasiums in Olmütz am Schlusse des Schuljahres 1901 </hi>(Olmütz:
                        Franz Slawiks Buchdruckerei, 1901), 59. AHMP, SVZ, NAD 1042, Německá škola
                        chlapeckă v Karlíně, Palackého 33 Karton: Kronika, 1877, October 4,
                        1877.</note> The commemorations of Franz Joseph and his contributions to
                Austria-Hungary sought to create a sense of unity among a diverse state. They also
                provided a template for the future Austrian Republic to follow decades after the
                Monarchy collapsed.</p>
            <p> As Austrians emerged from the carnage of the Second World War, desperate to develop
                an Austrian identity that would allow them to distance themselves from the war,
                Nazism, and radical German nationalism, Austrian schools began to celebrate the
                presidents of the new (Second) Austrian Republic. The structure of these
                celebrations possessed a surprising degree of similarity to the commemorations of
                the Habsburg emperor half a century earlier. The continuity of such events speaks to
                the potentially unconscious legacy of Habsburg commemoration in postwar Austria and
                illustrates the power of administrative memory even after states collapse.</p>
            <p> Before continuing, it is important to discuss the parameters of this paper.
                Considering the size and diversity of the Habsburg Monarchy, it would be impossible
                to provide a comprehensive discussion of school events in all of Austria-Hungary.
                The nature of the Compromise of 1867, which created the Dual Monarchy contribute to
                this constraint. Since the Compromise divided the Habsburg Monarchy into two nearly
                sovereign states, education policy differed in Austria and Hungary. Because of this
                fact, and due to this paper’s interest in the influence of school events on the
                Austrian Republic, I will only be discussing schools from the parts of the Dual
                Monarchy that became the Austrian Republic. Additionally, in exploring the legacy of
                Habsburg school celebrations, this paper will look specifically at the early years
                of the Second Republic. It will rely on existing scholarship when discussing the
                First Republic and the period of the <hi rend="italic">Anschluss</hi>.</p>
            <p> Beginning in the last quarter of the nineteenth century, Austrian schools held
                several events commemorating Franz Joseph and the Monarchy throughout the year. The
                nature of these celebrations varied from year to year, marking the anniversary of
                significant events in the state’s history or celebrating major milestones of the
                monarch or dynasty. Such commemorations included the 600th anniversary of Rudolf I’s
                acquisition of Austria, the centennial of Joseph II’s birth, or the centennial of
                the victories over Napoleon.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn7" n="6"> For example WStLA, SSR, 2.2.2.3.101.B51, <hi rend="italic">Schulchronik – Schule St. Stefan</hi>, entry for April 24,
                        1879. WStLA, SSR, 2.2.2.3.203.B51, <hi rend="italic">Schulchronik –
                            Holzhausergasse</hi>, entry for December 27, 1881. WStLA, SSR,
                        2.2.2.3.506.B51, <hi rend="italic">Schulchronik – Einsiedlergasse</hi>,
                        entry for May 26, 1909.</note> Each year, schools would have at least
                two patriotic celebrations, one for the emperor’s name day and another for the
                empresses’ name day. By the end of Franz Joseph’s reign, it was also common for
                schools to commemorate the anniversary of his ascension to the throne on December 2,
                1848. The decision to honor the monarchs on their name day, which corresponded to
                the feast day of the saint sharing their name, rather than the monarch’s birthday,
                resulted from logistical realities. Franz Joseph was born on August 18, Empress
                Elisabeth on December 24. Since schools were not in session on either of these
                dates, it was difficult to organize school events at these times.</p>
            <p> The Ministry of Religion and Education, responsible for crafting Austrian
                educational policy, established the general guidelines for school celebrations,
                deciding how many events would be held in the school year and setting the dates for
                each. Local and provincial school boards were then responsible for facilitating
                their implementation.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn8" n="7">
                        For example ÖStA, AVA, MKU, f. 4189, memorandum from the Ministry of
                        Religion and Education, 6196-1886. Plans developed by the Vienna city
                        council for celebrations of Franz Joseph’s seventieth birthday further
                        illustrate this coordination. Municipal and Provincial Archives of Vienna,
                        3.1.5.5.A62.2, 70. Geburtstag Kaiser FJ I 1900 0818, <hi rend="italic">Fest-Ordnung</hi>, 6944/1900.</note> Individual schools then
                organized their events, which took place during normal school hours. While the
                school boards provided general guidelines for organizing such commemorations, each
                school created its own programs. Reflecting the continued influence of religion over
                Austrian society, each celebration began with a religious service. Considering
                Austria’s protection of religious tolerance, students attended this service at their
                individual house of worship. Catholics attended mass at their parish church,
                Protestants had services at the church of their denomination, and Jews either
                attended a synagogue or went to the home of their rabbi if their local Jewish
                population was too small to have a synagogue.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn9" n="8"> AStL, B0019, <hi rend="italic">Disziplinar-Vorschriften für die Schüler des k.k. Staats-Gymnasiums
                            Linz</hi>, 1872, 14, 15; <hi rend="italic">Disziplinar-Vorschriften für
                            die Schüler des k.k. Staats-Gymnasiums Linz</hi>, 1881, 15,
                    16.</note></p>
            <p> After these services, students met in the main hall or gymnasium of the school. The
                room would be decorated with at least the Austrian flag and a picture or bust of the
                emperor. Typically schools would also use flowers, bunting, and other decorations to
                create a “festive” environment. <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn10" n="9"> When writing about the various school celebrations,
                        most year-end reports from schools made some comment about the room being
                        “festively decorated,” often with detailed descriptions of those
                        decorations. See for example AStL, B0027, <hi rend="italic">Dreizehnter
                            Jahresbericht des bischöflichen Privat-Gymnasiums am “Collegium
                            Petrinum,”</hi> 1910, 43. WStLA, Stadtschulrat, SSR, 2.2.2.3.1601, <hi rend="italic">Schulchronik – Abelegasse</hi>, entry for October 4,
                        1900.</note> Often these decorations could be quite elaborate. For
                example, in an event honoring Franz Joseph’s visit to Linz in 1903, the Collegium
                Petrinum Gymnasium lined the road to the school with the black and yellow flags of
                the Habsburg dynasty and decorated the school’s main hall with oil paintings of
                every Habsburg emperor from Rudolf I to Joseph I, complete with the individual
                mottos of each ruler.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn11" n="10"> AStL, B0027, Kollegium Petrinum (1898–1918), <hi rend="italic">Sechster Jahresbericht des bischöflichen Privat-Gymnasiums
                            am “Collegium Petrinum” in Urfahr für das Schuljahr 1902/03</hi>, 4-6.
                    </note> Besides students, these events included the faculty of the school
                and parents. Local, provincial, and sometimes state-level dignitaries joined the
                celebration, by invitation, and typically offered speeches. These speeches were
                given along with student readings of patriotic poems and the singing of patriotic
                songs. The event ended with the signing of the Austrian <hi rend="italic">Volkshymne</hi> and well-wishes offered in the name of the emperor.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn12" n="11"> WStLA, SSR,
                        2.2.2.3.402, <hi rend="italic">Schulchronik - Hauptschule für Mädchen,
                            Vierter Bezirk, Graf Starhemberggasse</hi>, entries for November 11,
                        1887; May 12, 1888; January 15, 1891; July 14, 1900. 2.2.2.3.203.B51, <hi rend="italic">Schulchronik – Holzhausergasse</hi>, entries for November
                        10, 1877; November 30, 1880; December 27, 1882; July 14, 1900; SSR,
                        2.2.2.3.506.B51, <hi rend="italic">Schulchronik – Einsiedlergasse</hi>,
                        entry for October 4, 1910.</note></p>
            <p> Speakers at these events had control over their individual speeches, but they always
                reflected on the importance of the day and reinforced the value of patriotism and
                loyalty. The consistency of speeches from school to school and from speaker to
                speaker reflects the existence of a general consensus regarding the history of
                Austria-Hungary and the qualities of Franz Joseph. This consistency also reflected
                the fact that local leaders often received suggested themes for their speeches. For
                example, in 1908, for Franz Joseph’s sixtieth jubilee, Mayor Karl Lueger of Vienna
                distributed sample speeches for his representatives to give. It was clear he only
                intended for minor changes to be made to these remarks.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn13" n="12"> WStLA, KBK, 3.1.5.5.A63.4, Sample
                        speech distributed by Mayor Karl Lueger, Document 16500.</note></p>
            <p> In general, the speeches honoring Franz Joseph asserted that the emperor was a model
                of ideal leadership. They praised him for his piety and virtue, offering examples
                from his life as proof of these qualities. In particular, speeches often described
                “his faith and sense of duty,” along with his tireless work ethic and
                    dedication.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn14" n="13">
                        WStLA, SSR, Materialien-Schulveranstaltungen (uncollected materials), <hi rend="italic">Festrede</hi> by Franziska Wolf.</note> This
                dedication gained even more resonance as speakers reflected on the personal
                tragedies Franz Joseph suffered. They lamented the execution of his brother,
                Maximilian, in Mexico; the death of his son Rudolph; and the assassination of his
                wife, Elisabeth. Yet in spite of these personal challenges, Franz Joseph focused
                only on the welfare of Austria.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn15" n="14"> WStLA, SSR, 2.2.2.3.203.B51, <hi rend="italic">Schulchronik – Holzhausergasse</hi>, entry for December 2,
                    1898.</note> Considering these remarks were given in schools, speakers often
                used Franz Joseph’s support for education as evidence of this concern. They rarely
                missed an opportunity to describe his patronage of schools and his support for the
                arts and sciences.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn16" n="15">
                        <hi rend="italic">Jahresbericht über das k.k. akademisches Gymnasium in Wien
                            für das Schuljahr 1870</hi>–<hi rend="italic">1871</hi> (Vienna: Verlag
                        des k.k. akademischen Gymnasiums, 1871), 82.</note></p>
            <p> By reflecting on his devotion to his family, as well as his country, Franz Joseph
                embodied the paternalistic ideal of nineteenth century kingship. He became, in the
                words of one teacher, a “faithful father to all of his subjects.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn17" n="16"> WStLA, SSR, 2.2.2.3.102.B51, <hi rend="italic">Schulchronik – Pfarrhauptschule Heiligenkreuzerhof</hi>,
                        Band 1, entry for December 2, 1873.</note> Another speech given in 1900
                at a Viennese elementary school developed this concept further, describing Franz
                Joseph as a noble “father of his country (<hi rend="italic">Landesvater</hi>)” who
                “over the long years always showed concern for the welfare and happiness of his
                peoples.” This concern earned the “complete love and steadfast (<hi rend="italic">unerschütterlich</hi>) loyalty” of his peoples. As evidence of this concern,
                one only need look to his deep concern for the poor, his patronage of schools and
                hospitals, and his tireless efforts to reform the Austrian government. It also
                reminded listeners of the shared moments of “happiness and joy as well as grief and
                sorrow” which bound the monarch and the peoples of Austria.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn18" n="17"> WStLA, SSR, 2.2.2.3.907.B51, <hi rend="italic">Schulchronik – Liechtensteinstrasse</hi>, Band 1, entry
                        for July 14, 1900.</note></p>
            <p> The speeches given at these celebrations were reinforced through other media in
                Austrian society. Individuals could purchase the same pictures and busts schools
                displayed, biographies of Franz Joseph written to commemorate jubilees and
                anniversaries reiterated the themes of the speeches given in schools, and as Daniel
                Unowsky points out, individuals could even buy marzipan likenesses of the
                    emperor.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn19" n="18"> Daniel
                        L. Unowsky, <hi rend="italic">The Pomp and Politics of Patriotism: Imperial
                            Celebrations in Habsburg Austria,
                        1848-1916 </hi>(West Lafayette,
                        IN: Purdue University Press, 2005), 105–44.</note> By the end of his
                life, Franz Joseph became a symbol of unity, piety, devotion and good leadership.
                The commemoration of the monarch continued after Franz Joseph’s death, but obviously
                ended when the Monarchy collapsed in 1918.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn20" n="19"> For examples of the celebrations of Emperor Karl
                        I, see WStLA, SSR, 2.2.2.3.604.B51, <hi rend="italic">Schulchronik –
                            Sonnenuhrgasse</hi>, Band 2, entry for November 3, 1917; Municipal and
                        Provincial Archives of Vienna, SSR, 2.2.2.3.1601.B51, <hi rend="italic">Schulchronik – Abelegasse</hi>, Entries for November 3, 1917, November
                        21, 1917.</note> As the new Austrian state transcended from being part
                of a large, multinational empire into an independent republic, it had to reconcile
                its imperial past and craft a new sense of identity. This process was long and
                difficult.</p>
            <p> During the interwar period, Austrian identity remained in flux and poorly formed.
                Considering the state’s imperial legacy, this is hardly surprising. As nationalism
                developed in Central Europe in the late nineteenth century, few argued that an
                Austrian nation existed. Austrian identity was, by necessity, supranational and
                imperial. One was Austrian because one lived in the Habsburg Monarchy. By this
                logic, a Czech-speaker living in Bohemia was just as Austrian as a German-speaker
                living in Styria.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn21" n="20">
                        Albert F. Reiterer,
                        <hi rend="italic">Nation und Nationalbewusstsein in Österreich </hi>(Vienna:
                        VWGÖ, 1988), 36.</note> As a result, most Austrians
                who lived in the Austrian Republic after World War I considered themselves to be
                members of the German nation, though not members of the German nation-state. The
                fact that many called the new state the Republic of German-Austria (much to the
                frustration of the Allied powers), and the fact that there was strong support for
                eventual union with Germany reflects this reality.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn22" n="21"> Franz Mathis, “1,000 Years of Austria and
                        Austrian Identity: Founding Myths,” in: <hi rend="italic">Austrian
                            Historical Memory and National Identity</hi>, Günter Bischof and Anton
                        Pelinka, eds. (New Brunswick: Transaction Publishers, 1997),
                22.</note></p>
            <p> While many of Austria’s interwar leaders supported the possibility of joining
                Germany, the treaties which ended World War I made this an impossibility. As a
                result, as Heidemarie Uhl and Albert Reiterer note, the First Republic was “the
                state no one wanted”, lacking broad support from the general population and even
                among its own leaders.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn23" n="22"> Heidemarie Uhl, <hi rend="italic">Zwischen Versöhnung
                            und Verstörung: Eine Kontroverse um Österreichs historische Identität
                            fünfzig Jahre nach dem Anschluß</hi> (Vienna: Böhlau Verlag, 1988), 52.
                        Reiterer, <hi rend="italic">Nation und Nationalbewusstsein in
                            Österreich</hi>, 56.</note> Not only did many Austrians doubt the
                economic vitality of the new state, few considered themselves to be members of an
                Austrian nation. As a result, the new republic was left to try to create an Austrian
                national identity among lingering questions of Austria’s German character.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn24" n="23"> Uhl, <hi rend="italic">Zwischen Versöhnung und Verstörung</hi>,
                46.</note></p>
            <p> Austrian leaders attempted to achieve this goal by distancing Austria from its
                Habsburg past. In the early years of the republic, the commemorations and
                celebrations typical to the Monarchy gave way to a state eager to align society to a
                mindset that reflected the socialist and democratic principles of the republic’s
                    founders.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn25" n="24"> For
                        an overview of these efforts, see Douglas Patrick Campbell, “The Shadow of
                        the Habsburgs: Memory and National Identity in Austrian Politics and
                        Education, 1918–1955” (Ph.D. diss., The University of Maryland, College
                        Park, 2006), 1–201. While the new Austrian state sought to distance itself
                        from its Habsburg past, it nevertheless maintained much of the governmental
                        structure and bureaucracy that existed in Habsburg Austria. This
                        bureaucratic legacy was typical to the monarchy’s successor states. See
                        Pieter M. Judson, “'Where Our Commonality is Necessary…': Rethinking the End
                        of the Habsburg Monarchy,” <hi rend="italic">Austrian History Yearbook</hi>
                        48 (April 2017): 12.</note> Furthermore, in recognition of the fact that
                most Austrians identified as members of the German nation, the leaders of the First
                Republic attempted to forge a sense of “Austrianess” that embraced German national
                culture while simultaneously emphasizing Austria’s unique contribution to that
                    culture.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn26" n="25">
                        Reiterer, <hi rend="italic">Nation und Nationalbewusstsein in
                            Österreich</hi>, 37.</note></p>
            <p> These efforts intensified as the republic fell under the conservative, authoritarian
                control of Engelbert Dollfuß. Even though Dollfuß’ regime vigorously supported
                Austria’s independence from Germany, it continued to distance Austrian identity from
                its imperial history. Rather than relying on Austria’s Habsburg legacy, Dollfuß
                promoted an Austrian identity based on the fusion of traditional German culture and
                Catholic Christianity. Under Dollfuß, educators presented the Austrian nation as the
                final “bulwark” of German culture, its only defense against the barbarizing
                influence of the Prussian dominated German state.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn27" n="26"> Walter Wiltschegg, <hi rend="italic">Österreich
                            – der Zweite Deutsche Staat? Der nationale Gedanke in der Ersten
                            Republik</hi> (Graz: Leopold Stockerverlag, 1992), 152–56.</note>
                Whole school celebrations utilized images from the Habsburg past, they became
                symbols of Austria’s contribution to German culture, not a celebration of its
                imperial legacy.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn28" n="27">
                            Ibid<hi rend="italic">.,</hi> 213, 214.</note></p>
            <p> The Austrian national identity promoted by Dollfuß’ regime put it in direct conflict
                with the radical, pro-union German nationalism of the National Socialists who were
                becoming a strong voice in Austrian politics. When the Nazi regime in Germany
                engineered the annexation of Austria in 1938, it was obviously this latter group
                that became the dominant voice in Austrian political culture. Once union was
                achieved, the Nazi regime made every effort to expunge Austria’s sense of cultural
                and political distinction within German speaking Europe.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn29" n="28"> For more on the development of
                        this struggle, see John C. Swanson, <hi rend="italic">The Remnants of the
                            Habsburg Monarchy: The Shaping of Modern Austria and Hungary,
                        1918-1922 </hi>(New York: East
                        European Monographs, 2001), 13–41. For more on the impact of World War II on
                        shaping Austrian national identity after 1938, see Bruce F. Pauley,
                        <hi rend="italic">Hitler and the Forgotten Nazis: A History of Austrian National Socialism </hi>(Chapel
                        Hill: University of North Carolina Press, 1981), 216–29. Evan Burr Bukey,
                            <hi rend="italic">Hitler’s Austria: Popular Sentiment in the Nazi Era,
                            1938-1945 </hi>(Chapel Hill:
                        University of North Carolina Press, 2000), 155–234.</note> This new
                government even went so far as to change the name of the former Austrian state to
                    <hi rend="italic">Ostmark</hi>, a vague connection to Austria’s medieval
                origins, and all public commemorations and celebrations honored Adolf Hitler, the
                Nazi regime, and the German nation. Germany’s defeat in the Second World War
                provided a second attempt for Austria to craft a unique national identity.</p>
            <p> As scholars like Heidemarie Uhl have long noted, the desire to obscure the role of
                many Austrians in the Third Reich helped bolster the establishment of an Austrian
                national identity distinct from German nationalism. In Uhl’s words, the Second
                Austrian Republic was founded as “the antithesis to the <hi rend="italic">Anschluß</hi> and to National Socialism.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn30" n="29"> Uhl, <hi rend="italic">Zwischen Versöhnung und
                            Verstörung</hi>, 81. A similar notion is made in Reiterer, <hi rend="italic">Nation und Nationalbewusstsein in Österreich</hi>, 57.
                        Anton Pelinka, “Taboos and Self-Deception: The Second Republic’s
                        Reconstruction of History,” in: <hi rend="italic">Austrian Historical Memory
                            and National Identity</hi>, Günter Bischof and Anton Pelinka, eds. (New
                        Brunswick: Transaction Publishers, 1997), 96–101. </note> Embracing its
                Habsburg past, though detached from its imperial connotations and without any desire
                for a Habsburg restoration, helped in this process. After the Second World War,
                Austria’s political and cultural leaders began promoting the artists, musicians, and
                historical figures from the Habsburg past in order to craft an Austria identity
                separate and distinct from German national culture.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn31" n="30"> Reiterer, <hi rend="italic">Nation und
                            Nationalbewusstsein in Österreich</hi>, 55. See also, Campbell, “The
                        Shadow of the Habsburgs: Memory and National Identity in Austrian Politics
                        and Education, 1918-1955,” 413–601. Peter Thaler, <hi rend="italic">The
                            Ambivalence of Identity: The Austrian Experience of Nation-Building in a
                            Modern Society</hi> (West Lafayette, IN: Purdue University Press,
                        2001).</note> This allowed for the legacy of imperial celebration to
                resurface in the years following the Second World War, and established a curious
                continuity between civic education in Habsburg Austria and that of Austria in the
                Second Republic. It appears that school events for Franz Joseph created a template
                for celebrating the republic and its leaders.</p>
            <p> School celebrations held in 1950 to honor President Karl Renner mirrored those held
                half a century earlier for Emperor Franz Joseph. Renner had been a major figure in
                Austrian politics for decades. Before the First World War, he was a leader of the
                Social Democratic Party and he became Austria’s first chancellor when the Monarchy
                collapsed. In 1945, he established a provisional government and became the first
                president of the Second Republic. Both contemporaries and historians credit Renner
                for helping to ensure Austria’s relatively benign treatment by the Allies. These
                celebrations reflected the important role that Renner played in Austrian
                society.</p>
            <p> The itinerary of the celebrations were almost identical to those held for Franz
                Joseph, even including some of the same patriotic songs and poems.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn32" n="31">
                        <hi rend="italic">Renner-Feier, November 27, 1950</hi>, WStLA, SSR,
                        Materialien-Schulveranstaltungen (uncollected materials).</note> As with
                celebrations for the emperor, those for Karl Renner included speeches about his life
                and his service to Austria. The descriptions of Renner and his life offer striking
                and obvious parallels with those of Franz Joseph. Speakers described Renner as a
                consummate statesman, dedicated to the peace and stability of Europe. They reflected
                on Renner’s tireless service to Austria and credited him with “the reestablishment
                of Austria” after World War II. They also praised Renner’s dedication to the arts
                and sciences.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn33" n="32">
                        Ibid.<hi rend="italic"> Renner-Feier</hi>, Allg.
                        Öffentliche Volks- und Hauptschule für Mädchen, 18. Bezirk, WStLA, SSR,
                        Materialien-Schulveranstaltungen (uncollected materials).</note> As with
                Franz Joseph, Karl Renner embodied the ideal of good governance. In many ways the
                only major difference between the celebrations was the fact that events to honor
                Renner ended with a signing of the <hi rend="italic">Bundeshymne</hi>, the national
                anthem of the Austrian republic, rather than the <hi rend="italic">Volkshymne</hi>.</p>
            <p> On June 21, 1951, schools held an almost identical celebration for President Theodor
                Körner’s birthday.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn34" n="33">
                        Theodor Körner was the second president of the Second Republic, serving from
                        1951 until he died in 1957. He was also the first post-war mayor of Vienna,
                        serving from 1945-1950. All contents of this footnote is said in the text,
                        this note should be deleted.</note> Körner was the second president of
                the Second Republic, serving from 1951 until he died in 1957. He was also the first
                post-war mayor of Vienna, serving from 1945-1950, responsible for supervising the
                capital’s postwar recovery. Speeches honoring Körner utilized familiar themes:
                drawing attention to his military service during World War I and praising his
                efforts to rebuild Austria when he was elected mayor of Vienna in 1945. Speakers
                also reflected on Körner’s deep interest in improving the lives of the citizens of
                Vienna, evidenced by the schools, parks, and youth organizations established when he
                was mayor. Similar to those honoring Franz Joseph, speakers also discussed Körner’s
                personal life, especially his devotion to his home and his family. This dedication
                not only reflected his personal virtue, it also provided a foundation for his
                dedication to the people of Austria.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn35" n="34">
                        <hi rend="italic">Feier für Theodor Körners Angelobung</hi>, WStLA, SSR,
                        Materialien-Schulveranstaltungen (uncollected materials).</note></p>
            <p> The parallels between these speeches and those honoring Franz Joseph are obvious.
                Speakers wanted to emphasize the fact that Austria was a state led by pious,
                dedicated leaders who devoted their lives to the state and to the people of Austria.
                This emphasis speaks to the unconscious legacy of Habsburg commemoration. The notion
                that Habsburg leaders were stewards of the state and benevolent rulers was essential
                to Austrian civic education before the First World War, and these leadership tropes
                persisted in the Second Republic. As Austria emerged from the carnage of the Second
                World War, the biographies of its postwar presidents helped to create an image of a
                state led by similar stewards. Such celebrations reflected the assertion that
                Austria’s new republic had the good fortune to be led by just, honorable leaders,
                interested only in peace and in the development of the state, just like the Monarchy
                in the time of the Habsburgs. These celebrations formed a crucial bridge between
                Austria’s past and present as it transitioned to the Second Republic.</p>
            <p> Ultimately, celebrations of Austria’s presidents tapered off in favor of explicitly
                republican national holidays after the signing of the state treaty of 1955. The
                state treaty ended Allied occupation of Austria and established an Austrian state
                neutral in the Cold War competition between the United States and the Soviet Union.
                As Austria developed a prosperous democratic society, schools celebrated Austria’s
                new role in the world. These efforts included commemorating the state treaty itself
                as well as Austrian Flag Day.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn36" n="35"> Mementos and programs for these events can be found
                        throughout the WStLA, SSR, Materialien-Schulveranstaltungen (uncollected
                        materials).</note> In spite of these changes, the initial commemoration
                of Austria’s postwar presidents speak to the power of administrative legacies, which
                can provide a template for notions of patriotism, civic education, and sense of self
                that can persist even after states collapse. It would be interesting to see if
                similar legacies exist in other parts of the former Habsburg Monarchy and to see how
                such ideas shaped these successor states as well.</p>
            
        </body>
        <back>
<div type="bibliography">
            <head>Sources and References</head>
            <list type="unordered">
                <head>Archival Sources:</head>
                <item>AHMP – Archiv hlavního města Prahy [Prague City
                    Archives]:<list>
                        <item>SVZ – Sbirka vyroenich zprav.</item></list></item>
                <item>AStL – Archiv der Stadt Linz [Archives of the City of Linz].</item>
                <item>OÖLA – Oberösterreichisches Landesarchiv, Linz [Upper Austrian Provincial
                    Archives, Linz]:<list>
                        <item>LSR – Landesschulrat.</item></list></item>
                <item>ÖStA – Österreichisches Staatsarchiv [Austrian
                    State Archives]:<list>
                <item>AVA: MKU, Allgemeines Verwaltungsarchiv: Ministerium für Kultus und
                    Unterricht.</item></list></item>
                <item>WStLA – Wiener Stadt- und Landesarchiv [Municipal and Provincial Archives of
                    Vienna]:<list>
                <item>KBK – Kleine Bestände: Kaiserhaus.</item>
                        <item>SSR – Stadtschulrat.</item></list></item>
            </list>
            <listBibl>
                <head>Printed School Reports:</head>
                <bibl><hi rend="italic">Jahresbericht über das k.k. akademisches Gymnasium in Wien
                    für das Schuljahr 1870-1871.</hi> Vienna: Verlag des
                    k.k. akademischen Gymnasiums, 1871.</bibl>
            </listBibl>
            <listBibl>
                <head>Secondary Literature:</head>
                <bibl>Bukey, Evan Burr. <hi rend="italic">Hitler’s Austria: Popular Sentiment in the
                    Nazi Era, 1938</hi>–<hi rend="italic">1945</hi>. Chapel Hill: University of
                    North Carolina Press, 2000.</bibl>
                <bibl>Campbell, Douglas Patrick. “The Shadow of the Habsburgs: Memory and National
                    Identity in Austrian Politics and Education, 1918–1955.” Ph.D. diss., The
                    University of Maryland, College Park, 2006.</bibl>
                <bibl>Judson, Pieter M. <hi rend="italic">Guardians of the Nation: Activists on the
                    Language Frontiers of Imperial Austria</hi>. Cambridge: Harvard University
                    Press, 2006.</bibl>
                <bibl>Judson, Pieter M. <hi rend="italic">The Habsburg Empire: A New History</hi>.
                    Cambridge: The Belknap Press, 2016.</bibl>
                <bibl>Judson, Pieter M. “'Where Our Commonality is Necessary…': Rethinking the End
                    of the Habsburg Monarchy.” <hi rend="italic">Austrian History Yearbook</hi> 48
                    (April 2017): 1–21.</bibl>
                <bibl>King, Jeremy. <hi rend="italic">Budweisers into Czechs and Germans: A Local
                    History of Bohemian Politics, 1848</hi>–<hi rend="italic">1948</hi>.
                    Princeton: Princeton University Press, 2002.</bibl>
                <bibl>Mathis, Franz. “1,000 Years of Austria and Austrian Identity: Founding Myths.”
                    In: <hi rend="italic">Austrian Historical Memory and National Identity</hi>,
                    edited by Günter Bischof and Anton Pelinka. New Brunswick: Transaction
                    Publishers, 1997.</bibl>
                <bibl>Pauley, Bruce F. <hi rend="italic">Hitler and the Forgotten Nazis: A History
                    of Austrian National Socialism</hi>. Chapel Hill: University of North
                    Carolina Press, 1981.</bibl>
                <bibl>Pelinka, Anton. “Taboos and Self-Deception: The Second Republic’s
                    Reconstruction of History.” In: <hi rend="italic">Austrian Historical Memory and
                        National Identity</hi>, edited by Günter Bischof and Anton Pelinka. New
                    Brunswick: Transaction Publishers, 1997.</bibl>
                <bibl>Reiterer, Albert F. <hi rend="italic">Nation und Nationalbewusstsein in
                    Österreich</hi>. Vienna: VWGÖ, 1988.</bibl>
                <bibl>Stauter-Halsted, Keely. <hi rend="italic">The Nation in the Village: The
                    Genesis of Peasant National Identity in Austrian Poland, 1848-1914</hi>. Ithaca, NY: Cornell University Press, 2001.</bibl>
                <bibl>Swanson, John C. <hi rend="italic">The Remnants of the Habsburg Monarchy: The
                    Shaping of Modern Austria and Hungary, 1918</hi>–<hi rend="italic">1922</hi>. New York: East European Monographs, 2001.</bibl>
                <bibl>Thaler, Peter. <hi rend="italic">The Ambivalence of Identity: The Austrian
                    Experience of Nation-Building in a Modern Society</hi>. West Lafayette, IN:
                    Purdue University Press, 2001.</bibl>
                <bibl>Uhl, Heidemarie. <hi rend="italic">Zwischen Versöhnung und Verstörung: Eine
                    Kontroverse um Österreichs historische Identität fünfzig Jahre nach dem
                    Anschluß.</hi> Vienna: Böhlau Verlag, 1988.</bibl>
                <bibl>Unowsky, Daniel L. <hi rend="italic">The Pomp and Politics of Patriotism:
                    Imperial Celebrations in Habsburg Austria, 1848</hi>–<hi rend="italic">1916</hi>. West Lafayette, IN: Purdue University Press, 2005.</bibl>
                <bibl>Urbanitsch, Peter. “Österreichs Schulen: Organisatorischer und struktureller
                    Wandel 1848 bis 1914.” In: <hi rend="italic">Kindheit und Schule im Ersten
                        Weltkrieg</hi>, edited by Hannes Stekl, Christa Hämmerle, Ernst Bruckmüller.
                    Vienna: New Academic Press, 2016.</bibl>
                <bibl>Wiltschegg, Walter. <hi rend="italic">Österreich – der Zweite Deutsche Staat?
                    Der nationale Gedanke in der Ersten Republik</hi>. Graz: Leopold
                    Stockerverlag, 1992.</bibl>
                <bibl>Zahra, Tara. <hi rend="italic">Kidnapped Souls: National Indifference and the
                    Battle for Children in the Bohemian Lands, 1900-1948</hi>. Ithaca: Cornell University Press, 2008.</bibl>
            </listBibl></div>
            <div type="summary" xml:lang="sl">
                <docAuthor>Scott O. Moore</docAuthor>
            <head>CESAR Z DRUGAČNIM IMENOM: ŠOLSKE SLOVESNOSTI V HABSBURŠKI AVSTRIJI IN DRUGI
                AVSTRIJSKI REPUBLIKI</head>
            <head>POVZETEK</head>
            <p>Domoljubne proslave so bile ob koncu devetnajstega stoletja v avstrijskih šolah
                pomemben del javnega izobraževanja. Habsburški uradniki so upali, da bodo pri
                državljanih spodbudile lojalnost in oblikovale skupen pogled na preteklost
                Habsburške monarhije. Ključni del teh prizadevanja so bili dogodki, ki so
                obeleževali življenje habsburškega cesarja. Desetletja po padcu monarhije so šole
                organizirale podobne dogodke v čast avstrijskih predsednikov, ki so delovali v prvi
                dekadi po drugi svetovni vojni. Podobnosti med temi dogodki pričajo o moči
                birokratske zapuščine, ki lahko preživi padce vlad in razpade držav.</p>
            <p> Konec devetnajstega in začetek dvajsetega stoletja je cislajtanijsko (tj.
                avstrijsko) ministrstvo za religijo in šolstvo določilo parametre za proslave v
                avstrijskih šolah, pokrajinska in lokalna šolska vodstva pa so določila strukturo
                teh dogodkov. Navkljub tej decentralizirani ureditvi so si bili dogodki v avstrijski
                polovici Avstro-Ogrske med seboj osupljivo podobni. Proslave so se začele z verskim
                obredom, ki so mu sledili petje domoljubnih pesmi, recitiranje domoljubne poezije in
                govori, ki so poudarjali pomembnost dogodka. Cesarja Franca Jožefa so govorniki
                počastili tako, da so ga predstavili kot utelešenje dobrega vladarja ter ga hvalili
                kot zvestega zaščitnika monarhije in ljudstva. Po smrti Franca Jožefa leta 1916 so
                šole podobne dogodke prirejale za Cesarja Karla I vse do razpada monarhije leta
                1918.</p>
            <p> Konec monarhije in nastanek (prve) avstrijske republike sta spremenila značaj javnih
                slovesnosti v Avstriji. Zaradi želje po ločitvi prve republike od Habsburške
                monarhije so želeli avstrijski voditelji poudariti socialistične in demokratične
                ideale njenih snovalcev. Ko je kancler Engelbert Dollfuß leta 1933 postal
                avtokratski vladar Avstrije, so šolske proslave znova prilagodili in v njih
                poudarjali tradicionalno nemško, katoliško kulturo, ki jo je podpiral nov režim. Po
                priključitvi Avstrije k Nemčiji marca 1938 so šole častile Hitlerja in nacistično
                vizijo nemškega naroda.</p>
            <p> Povojna vlada je nato zaradi burnih in uničujočih dogodkov v Avstriji med letoma
                1918 in 1945 želela razviti in izraziti avstrijsko identiteto, ki bi Avstrijo in
                Avstrijce odmaknila od omenjenih izkustev. Šolske proslave v čast avstrijskega
                predsednika so neposredno po koncu druge svetovne vojne postale orodje, s katerim je
                država skušala doseči tovrstne cilje. Pri načrtovanju takih dogodkov so se šole
                vrnile k organizaciji proslav, kot so jih v Habsburški monarhiji prirejali v čast
                Francu Jožefu. Z uporabo strukture, enake tisti s proslav v imperiju, so želele
                poudariti vodstvene sposobnosti predsednika Karla Rennerja in predsednika Theodorja
                Körnerja, tako da so oba slavile kot utelešenje dobrega vladanja in močnega vodstva.
                Jezik teh prireditev je popolnoma spominjal na tistega, ki so ga uporabljali za
                opisovanje Cesarja Franca Jožefa. Čeprav so se dogodki v čast avstrijskega
                predsednika sčasoma umaknili novim državnim praznikom, se zdi, da je bil v obdobju
                tik po vojni institucionalni spomin javnih slovesnosti za Avstrijo sredstvo
                spoprijemanja s posledicami vojne in vzpostavljanja povojne avstrijske
                identitete.</p></div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>