<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Introductory explanation</title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename>Jure</forename>
                        <surname>Gašparič</surname>
                    </name>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename>Jure</forename>
                        <surname>Perovšek</surname>
                    </name>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>2018-05-14</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>
                    <orgName xml:lang="sl">Inštitut za novejšo zgodovino</orgName>
                    <orgName xml:lang="en">Institute of Contemporary History</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Kongresni trg 1</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>SI-1000 Ljubljana</addrLine>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>http://ojs.inz.si/pnz/article/view/277</pubPlace>
                <date>2018</date>
                <availability status="free">
                    <licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title xml:lang="sl">Prispevki za novejšo zgodovino</title>
                <title xml:lang="en">Contributions to Contemporary History</title>
                <biblScope unit="volume">58</biblScope>
                <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
                <idno type="ISSN">2463-7807</idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source, born digital.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc xml:lang="en">
                <p>Contributions to Contemporary History is one of the central Slovenian scientific
                    historiographic journals, dedicated to publishing articles from the field of
                    contemporary history (the 19th and 20th century).</p>
                <p>The journal is published three times per year in Slovenian and in the following
                    foreign languages: English, German, Serbian, Croatian, Bosnian, Italian, Slovak
                    and Czech. The articles are all published with abstracts in English and
                    Slovenian as well as summaries in English.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <projectDesc xml:lang="sl">
                <p>Prispevki za novejšo zgodovino je ena osrednjih slovenskih znanstvenih
                    zgodovinopisnih revij, ki objavlja teme s področja novejše zgodovine (19. in 20.
                    stoletje).</p>
                <p>Revija izide trikrat letno v slovenskem jeziku in v naslednjih tujih jezikih:
                    angleščina, nemščina, srbščina, hrvaščina, bosanščina, italijanščina, slovaščina
                    in češčina. Članki izhajajo z izvlečki v angleščini in slovenščini ter povzetki
                    v angleščini.</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change>
                    <date>2018-05-21</date>
                    <name>Neja Blaj Hribar</name>
                    <desc>Pretvorba iz DOCX v TEI, dodatno kodiranje</desc>
                </change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <docAuthor>
                <name>
                    <forename>Jure</forename>
                    <surname>Gašparič</surname>
                    <roleName>Editor-in-Chief of the <hi rend="italic">Prispevki
                        za novejšo zgodovino</hi> publication</roleName>
                </name> </docAuthor>
            <docAuthor>
                <name>
                    <forename>Jure</forename>
                    <surname>Perovšek</surname>
                    <roleName>Leader of the <hi rend="italic">Idejnopolitični in
                        kulturni pluralizem in monizem na Slovenskem v 20. stoletju</hi>
                        research programme</roleName>
                </name> 
                </docAuthor>
        </front>
        <body>
            <p>Among the turning points that have shaped the historical image of the world, the 1917
                October Revolution with its long-lasting social, economic, and political
                consequences has for a long time attracted the attention of historiographers all
                around the world as well as in Slovenia, influencing the policy-making and spurring
                the interest of the general public. At the time of the Revolution, the established
                political order was shaken: a "global revolution of rising expectations" broke out
                that eventually reached the furthest ends of the globe. The recent World War,
                national movements, as well as social and class discontent were simultaneously
                disintegrative and creative, opening new opportunities, inspiring new ways of
                thinking, and shaping new mental worlds. The historical importance of these events
                was also amply demonstrated by the radical ideological and political movements
                stemming from the Modernity, which saw the October Revolution in Petrograd as either
                the origin or an emphasised purpose of their activities. The one hundredth
                anniversary of these events provided us with a marvellous opportunity to discuss new
                findings and evaluate the existing ones, resulting from the research endeavours
                focusing on this specific issue. Last year, the Institute of Contemporary History
                therefore decided to organise a round table dedicated to the October Revolution in
                order to contemplate the various questions that still surround this issue after a
                century. On 24 October 2017, Slovenian and international contemporary history
                researchers gathered at the Institute at the conference entitled <hi rend="italic"
                    >Thinking about the Revolution: 100 Years Later</hi> in order to analyse the
                issues and present the current outlooks on the Revolution, as expressed by the
                international and Slovenian historiography.</p>
            <p> The present issue of the <hi rend="italic">Prispevki za novejšo zgodovino
                    (Contributions to Contemporary History)</hi> publication includes the scientific
                research encouraged by the last year's round table. The authors of the
                contributions, included in this publication – Andreas Schulz, Anton Bebler, Jure
                Gašparič, Jurij Perovšek, Vida Deželak Barič, Bojan Godeša, Zdenko Čepič, Avgust
                Lešnik, Jerzy Wiatr, and Janko Prunk – shed light on the various aspects of the
                October historical phenomenon and its development; its internal dynamics; its
                ideological, conceptual, philosophical, socio-economic and political character; as
                well as on its consequences for the Slovenian and international environment. The
                outline of the October Revolution, presented in such a manner and in a single
                publication, has been envisioned by the Institute's associates in charge of the
                implementation of the research programme entitled <hi rend="italic">Idejnopolitični
                    in kulturni pluralizem in monizem na Slovenskem v 20. Stoletju
                    (Ideological-Political and Cultural Pluralism and Monism in Slovenia in the 20th
                    Century)</hi>. </p>
            <p>The presentation of the Revolution in front of you focuses on the following issues:
                the October Revolution itself as an ideological heir to the European revolutionary
                passions that gave rise to the Bolshevik revolutionary voluntarism; the key problems
                and dilemmas involved in the socio-economic and political development of the Soviet
                Russia or the Union of Soviet Socialist Republics in the first two decades after the
                takeover of power; the emigration from the post-revolutionary Russia and the
                position of the Russian emigrants in Europe; the global geopolitical consequences of
                the Revolution as well as its evaluation until the end of the 1980s and in the times
                of the post-bipolar division of the world; as well as on the incentives and
                challenges of the Russian experience for the Western capitalism. Furthermore, the
                authors have provided in-depth analyses of the responses to the Revolution in the
                Slovenian bourgeois politics and its ideological internalisation by the Slovenian
                revolutionary communist movement until its rise to power; the common points and
                differences between the implementation of the October Revolution and the Yugoslav
                Revolution; and of the question of introducing the October revolutionary elements in
                the Yugoslav and Slovenian social and political practices after 1945. </p>
            <p>We hereby invite the readers to familiarise themselves with the aforementioned
                analyses, hoping that they can contribute to further clarification of the Russian
                revolutionary October of 1917 and its perception in Slovenia.</p>
           </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
