<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Changing View of the 1917 Russian Revolution – Slovenia in the Global
                        Perspective<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn3" n="*"> The author acknowledges
                        the financial support from the Slovenian Research Agency (research core
                        funding No. P6-0281).</note></title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename>Jure</forename>
                        <surname>Gašparič</surname>
                    </name>
                    <roleName>Dr.</roleName>
                    <roleName>višji znanstveni sodelavec</roleName>
                    <affiliation>Inštitut za novejšo zgodovino</affiliation>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Kongresni trg 1</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>SI – 1000 Ljubljana</addrLine>
                    </address>
                    <email>jure.gasparic@inz.si</email>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>2018-02-20</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>
                    <orgName xml:lang="sl">Inštitut za novejšo zgodovino</orgName>
                    <orgName xml:lang="en">Institute of Contemporary History</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Kongresni trg 1</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>SI-1000 Ljubljana</addrLine>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>http://ojs.inz.si/pnz/article/view/255</pubPlace>
                <date>2018</date>
                <availability status="free">
                    <licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title xml:lang="sl">Prispevki za novejšo zgodovino</title>
                <title xml:lang="en">Contributions to Contemporary History</title>
                <biblScope unit="volume">58</biblScope>
                <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
                <idno type="ISSN">2463-7807</idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source, born digital.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc xml:lang="en">
                <p>Contributions to Contemporary History is one of the central Slovenian scientific
                    historiographic journals, dedicated to publishing articles from the field of
                    contemporary history (the 19th and 20th century).</p>
                <p>The journal is published three times per year in Slovenian and in the following
                    foreign languages: English, German, Serbian, Croatian, Bosnian, Italian, Slovak
                    and Czech. The articles are all published with abstracts in English and
                    Slovenian as well as summaries in English.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <projectDesc xml:lang="sl">
                <p>Prispevki za novejšo zgodovino je ena osrednjih slovenskih znanstvenih
                    zgodovinopisnih revij, ki objavlja teme s področja novejše zgodovine (19. in 20.
                    stoletje).</p>
                <p>Revija izide trikrat letno v slovenskem jeziku in v naslednjih tujih jezikih:
                    angleščina, nemščina, srbščina, hrvaščina, bosanščina, italijanščina, slovaščina
                    in češčina. Članki izhajajo z izvlečki v angleščini in slovenščini ter povzetki
                    v angleščini.</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="sl"/>
                <language ident="en"/>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords xml:lang="en">
                    <term>October Revolution</term>
                    <term>Russia</term>
                    <term>100th anniversary</term>
                    <term>20th century</term>
                    <term>Slovenia</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords xml:lang="sl">
                    <term>Oktobrska revolucija</term>
                    <term>Rusija</term>
                    <term>stota obletnica</term>
                    <term>20. stoletje</term>
                    <term>Slovenija</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change>
                    <date>2018-02-22</date>
                    <name>Neja Blaj Hribar</name>
                    <desc>Pretvorba iz DOCX v TEI, dodatno kodiranje</desc>
                </change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <docAuthor>Jure Gašparič<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn2" n="**"> Senior researcher, PhD,
                    Institute of Contemporary History, Kongresni trg 1, SI-1000 Ljubljana, Slovenia,
                        <ref target="mailto:jure.gasparic@inz.si"
                >jure.gasparic@inz.si</ref></note></docAuthor>
            <docImprint>
                <idno type="cobissType">Cobiss type: 1.01</idno>
                <idno type="UDC">UDC: </idno>
            </docImprint>
            <div type="abstract" xml:lang="sl">
                <head>IZVLEČEK</head>
                <head>SPREMINJAJOČ POGLED NA RUSKO REVOLUCIJO – SLOVENIJA V GLOBALNI
                    PERSPEKTIVI</head>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Letos mineva 100 let od ruskih revolucij leta 1917 (februarja
                        in oktobra), ki so s svojimi daljnosežnimi posledicami pretresle svet. Del
                        zgodovine revolucije je nedvomno tudi spreminjajoč pogled nanjo, zato si ga
                        velja podrobneje pogledati, saj bomo le tako bolje razumeli njene globalne
                        učinke in osmišljali današnja in prihodnja politična stališča. V prispevku
                        je pregledno predstavljena spreminjajoča se globalna perspektiva ruskih
                        revolucij v kratkem dvajsetem stoletju, v katero je umeščen slovenski
                        prostor.</hi></p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Ključne besede: Oktobrska revolucija, Rusija, stota obletnica,
                        20. stoletje, Slovenija</hi></p>
            </div>
            <div type="abstract" xml:lang="en">
                <head>ABSTRACT</head>
                <head>THE CHANGING VIEW OF THE 1917 RUSSIAN REVOLUTION – SLOVENIA IN THE GLOBAL
                    PERSPECTIVE</head>
                <p><hi rend="italic">This year we celebrate the 100th anniversary of the Russian
                        Revolutions (of February and October), which shook the world with their
                        far-reaching consequences. The changing outlook on the Revolution by all
                        means represents a part of its history, and therefore it has to be examined
                        more closely, as this is the only way to understand the Revolution's global
                        impact as well as give meaning to the current and future political
                        standpoints. The contribution presents an overview of the changing global
                        perspective of the Russian Revolutions in the short 20th century and the
                        Slovenian space within it.</hi></p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Keywords: October Revolution, Russia, 100th anniversary, 20th
                        century, Slovenia</hi></p>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div><p> In 1967 one of the most influential European weekly newspapers – the German <hi
                    rend="italic">Spiegel</hi> – published a lengthy article entitled <hi
                    rend="italic">Ein halbes Jahrhundert nach Bronsteins
                    Geburtstags-Putch</hi>.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn4" n="1"> "Ein halbes
                    Jahrhundert nach Bronsteins Geburtstags-Putsch,"<hi rend="italic"> Spiegel</hi>,
                    Nr. 43 (1967), 153–56.</note> The article opened in the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Spiegel's</hi> characteristic style: "A German cavalry officer (<hi
                    rend="italic">Rittmeister</hi>) lined up the Russian emigrants at the border
                with Switzerland. They were counted at the railway platform in Gottmadingen. There
                were 32 men. In April 1917 they rode a special train through Germany to Sassnitz and
                through Sweden and Finland to Petrograd." In the continuation the article also
                presented the now already legendary story of Lenin's journey home as well as the
                subsequent events, which had already been put into words countless times by then
                (including in the literary form, for example by Stefan Zweig).<note place="foot"
                    xml:id="ftn5" n="2"> Stefan Zweig, „Plombirani vlak,“
                    in:<hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve"> Zvezdni trenutki človeštva</hi>
                    (Celovec: Mohorjeva, 2004), 187–96. Original: Stefan Zweig, „The Miniature Der
                    Versiegelte Zug,“
                    in:<hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve"> Sternstunden der Menscheit</hi>.</note>
                The <hi rend="italic">Spiegel</hi> wrote: "This was the 'Great Socialist October
                Revolution'. In the communist countries – today these amount to one third of
                humankind – this implies the birth of a new, better world and a new, better man...
                When the Red Army soldiers erected their flag among the ruins of the Berlin
                Reichstag, Russia became a global superpower, second to none other but the United
                States of America. Nobody followed Karl Marx's teachings. The worker's democracy was
                not established, and communism remained utopic. However, what did take shape was a
                self-confident and ideologically-convinced industrial nation. The illiteracy and
                mass poverty of the tsarist era were overcome. Millions of university graduates
                built the new state-founding elite."</p>
            <p>The revolution and the development of the Soviet empire at the time were
                    upsetting...<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn6" n="3"> The celebration of the 50th
                    anniversary of the Revolution in Moscow was attended by 1000 foreign
                    journalists, and the event was broadcast by the Eurovision network. – "Za
                    50-letnico revolucije nad sto tujih
                    delegacij,"<hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve"> Delo</hi>, 29. 10.
                    1967.</note> Fifty years later it was obvious all around the world that the
                symbolic embarking on the train in Switzerland had shaken the global political,
                economic, and cultural architecture. For the first time after the revolution broke
                out in the territory of the Soviet Union, at that time the American <hi
                    rend="italic">New York Times</hi> deployed a special group of journalists, who
                would travel around the enormous country for weeks and write about the consequences
                of October 1917.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn7" n="4"> Edward Crankshaw, "The Coup
                    That Changed the World (Cont.) Lenin had invoked the masses; now he brought them
                    to heel," <hi rend="italic">The New York Times</hi>, 19. 2. 1967, 235.
                </note></p>
            <p>Simultaneously, the Slovenian historiography prepared a large-scale symposium
                entitled The 50th Anniversary of the October Revolution and the 30th Anniversary of
                the Inaugural Congress of the Communist Party of Slovenia. The event was prominent
                and prestigious in terms of its expert as well as political aspects, and the main
                lectures were given by Boris Ziherl, Dušan Kermavner, and Janko Pleterski.<note
                    place="foot" xml:id="ftn8" n="5"> The discussions and considerations were
                    published in a special topical issue of the <hi rend="italic">Prispevki za
                        zgodovino delavskega gibanja</hi> publication [Contributions to the History
                    of the Workers' Movement] (today <hi rend="italic">Prispevki za novejšo
                        zgodovino</hi> [Contributions to Contemporary History]. <hi rend="italic"
                        >Prispevki za zgodovino delavskega gibanja</hi> VII, Nr. 1-2 (1967): <hi
                        rend="italic">Zbornik razprav in obravnav znanstvenega posvetovanja Ob 50.
                        obletnici oktobrske revolucije in ob 30. obletnici ustanovnega kongresa
                        Komunistične partije Slovenije v Ljubljani od 2. do 4. novembra
                    1967</hi>.</note> Ziherl, the "revolutionary-scientist" who was deemed as
                Zhdanov's follower, underlined the following initial thoughts about the October in
                the introduction: first he established, as expected, that the October Revolution
                was, at the time, "the most important event of our century, a revolutionary act of
                the vast Russia's working masses, which shook the world fifty years ago, gave rise
                to the general crisis of the capitalist social system, and announced the beginning
                of a new era in the history of all humankind: the era of socialism." In the
                continuation, Ziherl reflected upon the Revolution's heritage and immediately
                tackled the issue regarding the "model" of socialism – a question which had troubled
                him for a long time. Could the Russian October represent a model for all socialist
                revolutions around the world? Some people, especially in the West, argued against
                the revolutionary character of October, claiming that the economic landscape of the
                old Russia made it impossible as such, while others "absolutised" it and strove to
                implement it in the exact same manner, especially after 1945. Ziherl, referring to
                Lenin, believed that the Revolution could only be victorious as a dialectic thought
                and not as a solid model. Nevertheless, Ziherl remarked: "The Great October
                Revolution and the revolutionary turmoil in a number of European and non-European
                countries that accompanied and strengthened it also confirmed the international
                reaction in the conviction that stems from every revolutionary situation: that the
                old ways are <hi rend="italic">no longer feasible.</hi>"<note place="foot"
                    xml:id="ftn9" n="6"> Boris Ziherl, "Dve obletnici," <hi rend="italic">Prispevki
                        za zgodovino delavskega gibanja</hi> VII, Nr. 1-2 (1967): 9-19.</note></p>
            <p><hi rend="None">On that occasion, one of the parks in the Slovenian capital of
                    Ljubljana was named after Lenin, and special honour was paid to the 95
                    participants of the Russian Revolutions from Slovenia who were still alive at
                    the time.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn10" n="7"> "Ljubljana je počastila
                        petdesetletnico Oktobra;" "Sprejem za udeležence Oktobra," <hi rend="italic"
                            >Delo</hi>, 7. 11. 1967.</note> The principal Slovenian newspaper Delo
                    assessed the message of the October with the following humanist motto: striving
                    for "a higher degree of prosperity and freedom".<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn11" n="8"> Dušan Dolinar, "Pet desetletij Oktobra," <hi
                            rend="italic">Delo</hi>, 7. 11. 1967.</note></hi></p>
            <p>In 1967, the global outlook on the Russian October definitely varied greatly
                (understandably depending on the political and bloc structure of the world).
                However, it had a few important common points: nobody denied or disregarded the
                significance of the event that had taken place fifty years earlier. The Russian
                Revolution captured the attention of states, intellectuals, and the public. The
                conviction that Russia and a part of the world had no longer been the same after
                October 1917 prevailed: the "old ways" had in fact become untenable. </p></div>
            <div><ab type="milestone" style="text-align:center">* * *</ab>
            <p> Let us now first move (almost) fifty years back, to the time (immediately) after the
                revolution, and then fifty years forward, to today's time. In these one hundred
                years the world has changed thoroughly, also because of the Revolution, and together
                with the world the outlook on the Revolution has changed as well. <hi rend="bold">As
                    it is, the changing outlook on the October Revolution by all means represents a
                    part of the history of the Revolution, and therefore it has to be examined more
                    closely, as this is the only way to understand the Revolution's global impact as
                    well as to give meaning to the current and future political
                standpoints.</hi></p>
            <p>In 1924 – in the year of Lenin's death – contributions, commentaries, essays, and
                discussions on the extraordinary role of this man and even more so on the global
                importance of the developments taking place well over six years earlier, which Lenin
                had famously organised, kept being published all around the world. The Viennese
                    newspapers<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn12" n="9"> "Der Tod Lenins," <hi
                        rend="italic">Neue Freie Presse</hi>, 23. 1. 1924, 1. "Lenin," <hi
                        rend="italic">Arbeiterwille</hi>, 23. 1. 1924, 1.</note> asked themselves
                who Lenin and his role had been, and assessed the historical importance of the
                events at the same time as the American press. "Lenin is dead and Trotsky is no
                longer at the head of the Red Army. Lenin had been away from the helm of Russian
                affairs for some time, while Trotsky was but recently eliminated from the inner
                councils of the Soviets. How will Soviet Russia fare without these master minds of
                the Bolshevist revolution?" one of newspapers wrote, and stated: "Communism Now
                Faces Its Greatest Crisis -- Leaders Struggle for the Mantle of Lenin".<note
                    place="foot" xml:id="ftn13" n="10"> Herman Bernstein, "Russia after Lenin --
                    will soviet survive?," <hi rend="italic">The New York Times</hi>, 27. 1. 1924,
                    XX3.</note> A few years earlier, in the period between 1917 and 1919, the New
                York Times search engine returns as many as 1979 hits for the query "Russian
                Revolution". Not even a single day passed in March 1917 that the events taking place
                in Russia were not reported on.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn14" n="11">
                    <hi rend="italic">Newspapers.com</hi>, accesed 5 July 2017, <ref
                        target="lnd=1&amp;query=russian+revolution&amp;dr_year=1917-1919&amp;t=395"
                            ><hi rend="Hyperlink.0">
                            https://www.newspapers.com/search/#lnd=1&amp;query=russian+revolution&amp;dr_year=1917-1919&amp;t=395</hi></ref><hi
                        rend="None">.</hi></note><hi rend="None"> The press would mostly establish
                    that "No statesman has ever had such an occasion to become a great benefactor of
                    his country as Lenin had, yet he left Russia in far worse condition than she was
                    when he became her absolute dictator."<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn15" n="12">
                        Peter J. Popoff, "Lenin's Great Experiment; He Failed, and No One Else Is
                        Likely to Try Again," <hi rend="italic">The New York Times</hi>, 25. 1.
                        1924, 16.</note></hi></p>
            <p>Numerous authors from the Slovenian territory contributed to the
                    massive collection of assessments as well. None of the political camps (neither
                    the liberal, Catholic, nor the Marxist side),<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn16"
                        n="13"> See: Jurij Perovšek, "Ruski begunci in pogledi slovenske politike na
                        Lenina ob njegovi smrti," <hi rend="italic">Monitor ISH XVIII</hi>, Nr. 1
                        (2016): 7-31.</note> political groups, or barely any newspapers could resist
                    the urge to give their own assessments of the leading revolutionary (this is
                    discussed in more detail in this volume by <seg rend="color(FF0000)">Jurij
                        Perovšek, Vida Deželak-Barič, and Bojan Godeša</seg>). </p>
            <p>Why this was the case was already explained in the 1920s by one of
                    the most influential Yugoslav writers (and members of the forbidden Yugoslav
                    Communist Party), the Croatian Miroslav Krleža, who visited Russia in 1924. As
                    he deliberated on the importance of the Revolution, he pointed out a simple
                    fact: "The significance of the Revolution stems from its invaluable practical
                    importance. From numerous theoretical debates in the context of the First and
                    Second International and the First of May philistine social democratic
                    declamations that accompanied a mug of beer, and through the conflicts within
                    the Party and its fractions, the path towards an organised state government has
                    been long and hard." However, all these debates and theories suddenly had to
                    face the USSR as the proof that socialism had transcended theory and had been
                    put into practice. "On the basis of the speeches in the Assembly, the evening
                    Marxist school, and the newspaper editorial ... a reality had emerged,
                    consisting of coins, armoured warships, artillery, modern aviation, and
                    international diplomatic relations."<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn17" n="14">
                        Miroslav Krleža, <hi rend="italic">Izlet u Rusiju</hi> (Zagreb: Novi Liber,
                        2013), 260, 261.</note></p>
            <p>Of the Slovenian authors, Franc Terseglav, a representative of the
                    Christian socialists, asserted himself with his insightfulness and the synthetic
                    character of his reasoning. He wrote two lengthy texts about Lenin and the
                    Revolution. In the conclusion of the second text he presented an assessment
                    which can be deemed as an approximate common denominator of the Slovenian
                    opinions about the Russian Revolution. In Terseglav's view, Lenin "hastened the
                    end of the global massacre with the Brest-Litovsk peace treaty and motto War on
                    War! ... as well as set the basic guidelines for the future global development
                    by creating the will to achieve the future republic of all humankind, federation
                    of free nations, and parliament of all humanity. Without Lenin's powerful
                    thrust, Asia would never have come forward with the demand for
                    self-determination of its subjugated nations; Kemal's Turkey would not have
                    risen; and neither would the white man's slaves from the Pacific Ocean and
                    Mongolian steppes to the African deserts and American prairies have stood up and
                    demanded their freedom". He concluded his evaluation of Lenin and the Revolution
                    extremely optimistically, as he wrote that Lenin's pivotal role was not "to
                    bring about communism as a system – the embodiment of this German
                    intellectualist theory is what is in fact the least important: it is the least
                    durable and is purely experimental. Especially for Russia, Lenin has been most
                    important as a teacher of an entirely new generation."<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn18" n="15"> Perovšek, "Ruski begunci in pogledi slovenske
                        politike na Lenina," 28, 29.</note>
                </p>
            <p>At that time the Revolution had nothing to do with communism at all,
                    they would write, but rather involved much more: the alteration (transformation)
                    of humankind. It had opened unprecedented possibilities. In Slovenia, the
                    Revolution was still seen as heralding a better future, while the American as
                    well as many other media had already established that Lenin and his comrades had
                    failed.</p>
            <p>Such a position strengthened itself even further in the following
                    decade. At the tenth anniversary of the Russian October, the <seg rend="italic"
                        >Time</seg> magazine published a detailed and fair portrait of Russia, only
                    to conclude it with Alexander Kerensky's offended words from his book <seg
                        rend="italic">The Catastrophe</seg>: "In the struggle for liberation Russia
                    must inevitably return to the road of popular, national, democratic government,
                    the road upon which the Russian people embarked – hesitatingly and with
                    uncertain steps – in March, 1917."<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn19" n="16">
                        "Russia," <hi rend="italic">Time</hi>, 21. 11. 1927, 15–18. </note></p>
            <p>In Slovenia, on the other hand, the following was established: "Under
                    the ingenious leadership of the diplomat Chicherin, Russia expanded its former
                    tsarist imperialism. Russia has introduced a novelty in the European diplomacy –
                    its diplomats are not merely its official representatives, but also
                    disseminators of Bolshevik ideas and protectors of local supporters. Through
                    Bolshevism, Russia undermined the world and incited revolutions in Bulgaria,
                    Hungary, Germany, Czechoslovakia, and partly also in Italy."<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn20" n="17"> "7. XI. 1917 – 7. XI. 1927 (Editorial)," <hi
                            rend="italic">Slovenec</hi>, 8. 11. 1927.</note></p>
            <p>However, only a decade later the assessment of the events taking
                    place in Russia became much more critical – also in Slovenia. Towards the end of
                    the 1930s, the press established that communism was "merely utopic" and that the
                    Marxist doctrine was "unfeasible".<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn21" n="18">
                        "Dvajset let boljševiške Rusije," <hi rend="italic">Jutro</hi>, 9. 11.
                        1937.</note> The Slovenian Catholic political camp, which was becoming
                    increasingly radical, wrote the following: "What was built in blood is now
                    maintained in blood, and it will be destroyed in blood as well. The red paradise
                    on Earth is truly completely red – from all the bloodshed."<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn22" n="19"> "Dvajsetletnica sovjetov (Drin.)," <hi rend="italic"
                            >Slovenec</hi>, 7. 11. 1937.</note></p></div>
            <div><ab type="milestone" style="text-align:center">* * *</ab>
            <p>After World War II, the assessment of the Russian October in Slovenia
                    and in the rest of Yugoslavia changed significantly. If before 1945 one could
                    follow numerous critical as well as positive evaluations of the Revolution, the
                    critical could no longer be found afterwards. The first period after the end of
                    the war was characterised exclusively by panegyrical praises and uncritical
                    glorifications. A partial change quite understandably took place after the 1948
                    Cominform dispute, although this, in its essence, had nothing to do with the
                    ideological aspects of the Russian October. Namely, the Yugoslav state and Party
                    ideology did not renounce the October Revolution. Quite the opposite: it
                    remained one of the fundamental elements of the system; it was presented in the
                    brightest possible light in the school textbooks;<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn23" n="20"> Pupils would often write essays and deliberations on
                        the October, which reflect the spirit of the times and the perception of
                        Russia and the Revolution. A student from the Poljane grammar school (at the
                        time the Vida Janežič secondary school for social sciences and general
                        culture) wrote elatedly about "the typical emotional-political or
                        moral-political relations" between Slovenians and Russia.</note> and the
                    celebrations dedicated to October would be organised in some school facilities
                    until as late as the 1980s (the author of this paper himself participated in a
                    few of them).<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn24" n="21"> At the time one could
                        read many jokes on account of Russia and particularly Stalin in the
                        satirical press. In one of the most famous jokes, Stalin wanted to know what
                        the simple folk thought about him, so he disguised himself and stepped into
                        a tavern in Moscow. There he started chatting with a worker: he asked him
                        quietly what the man thought about comrade Stalin. The frightened worker
                        looked around and whispered: "I have to admit that I still support him!" –
                            <hi rend="italic">Toti list</hi>, 1. 3. 1952, 2.</note>
                </p>
            <p>The Cominform dispute was perhaps most evidently reflected in
                    historiography, which was not seriously interested in studying the 1917
                        events.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn25" n="22"> Janko Prunk, "Jugoslovanska
                        historiografija o oktobrski revoluciji," <hi rend="italic">Prispevki za
                            novejšo zgodovino</hi> XXVII, Nr. 1-2 (1987) : 3–6.</note> In Slovenia
                    and Yugoslavia in general, only a single historian dedicated himself to this
                    topic: Professor Marjan Britovšek, whose work is
                        <seg rend="color(FF0000)" xml:space="preserve">explored in this </seg><seg
                        rend="color(FF0000)">v</seg><seg rend="color(FF0000)">olume by Avgust
                        Lešnik</seg>.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn26" n="23">Marjan Britovšek, <hi
                            rend="italic">Revolucionarni idejni preobrat med prvo svetovno vojno.
                            Lenin v boju za tretjo internacionalo</hi> (Ljubljana: Cankarjeva
                        založba, 1969). <hi rend="italic">Boj za Leninovo dediščino</hi> (Ljubljana:
                        Mladinska knjiga, 1976). <hi rend="italic">Carizem, revolucija, stalinizem.
                            Družbeni razvoj v Rusiji in perspektive socializma</hi> (Ljubljana:
                        Cankarjeva založba, 1980). <hi rend="italic">Korenine stalinizma in
                            negativne posledice kulta osebnosti</hi> (Ljubljana: Zavod SR Slovenije
                        za šolstvo,1980). <hi rend="italic">Stalinov termidor</hi> (Ljubljana:
                        Cankarjeva založba, 1984).</note> In fact, the only significant exception
                    with regard to the studying of the October Revolution was the 1967 symposium,
                    mentioned in the introduction, and the memorial collection of texts, published
                    by the Belgrade Institute of Contemporary History on the sixtieth anniversary of
                    the Revolution. It contains memorial records of 152 Yugoslav citizens who
                    participated in the October Revolution and the subsequent civil war. One of the
                    texts was contributed by the legendary Yugoslav leader Josip Broz Tito.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn27" n="24"> Josip Broz Tito, "Moja doživetja v
                        Rusiji med oktobrsko revolucijo in državljansko vojno," <hi rend="italic"
                            >Delo – Sobotna priloga</hi>, 5. 11. 1977.</note>
                </p>
            <p>Naturally, the Yugoslav and Slovenian optics were completely
                    different from that in the West and in the United States of America, where the
                        <seg rend="italic">Time</seg> wrote in 1947: "Thirty years ago a stooped man
                    with hollow cheeks and a potbelly came out from behind the bookstacks, where he
                    had spent most of his life, and kidnapped a state. Never before or after did he
                    fire a gun or throw a bomb or raise his slim-fingered hands to strike a blow. In
                    his name, nevertheless, more men have been slaughtered than in Attila's. His
                    name was Lenin."<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn28" n="25">"Russia. The Root &amp;
                        the Flower," <hi rend="italic">Time</hi>, 17. 11. 1947, 33.</note></p>
            <p>We can only guess what opinion the Slovenian people had of the
                    October Revolution, but judging from the fact that the basic elements of the
                    Russian October were also ingrained in the narrative of the Yugoslav Revolution
                        (<seg rend="color(FF0000)" xml:space="preserve">which is discussed by Zdenko Čepič in this </seg><seg
                        rend="color(FF0000)">v</seg><seg rend="color(FF0000)">olume</seg>), we can
                    safely claim that it was favourable. In the public opinion polls, carried out in
                    Slovenia since 1968 (which was a unique case in the European East),<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn29" n="26">About the public opinion pools in
                        Slovenia in this period see: Jure Gašparič, "Slovensko dojemanje druge
                        Jugoslavije," in: <hi rend="italic">Slovenija v Jugoslaviji</hi>, ed. Zdenko
                        Čepič (Ljubljana: Inštitut za novejšo zgodovino, 2015), 87–104.</note> this
                    question was not asked, but it is very telling that the Soviet Union as a state
                    always ranked high (compared to other states) in terms of its characteristics
                    and popularity.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn30" n="27">Niko Toš et al., <hi
                            rend="italic">Slovensko javno mnenje 1968</hi>. [datoteka podatkov].
                        Ljubljana: Univerza v Ljubljani, Visoka šola za politične vede, Center za
                        raziskovanje javnega mnenja in množičnih komunikacij [izdelava], 1968
                        (Ljubljana: Univerza v Ljubljani, Fakulteta za družbene vede, Arhiv
                        družboslovnih podatkov [distribucija], 1999). Available at: <hi
                            rend="italic">Podatki o raziskavi Slovensko javno mnenje 1991/2</hi>,
                            <ref target="http://www.adp.fdv.uni-lj.si/opisi/sjm912.xml"
                            >http://www.adp.fdv.uni-lj.si/opisi/sjm912.xml</ref>.</note>
                </p>
            <p><seg rend="bold" xml:space="preserve">Which country has advantages in a specific field in comparison with the others? (SJM 1968) </seg></p>
            <table rend="rules">
                <row>
                    <cell/>
                    <cell>Yugo-slavia</cell>
                    <cell>Soviet Union</cell>
                    <cell>United States</cell>
                    <cell>Italy</cell>
                    <cell>Austria</cell>
                    <cell>Germany</cell>
                    <cell>Scandi-navian count-ries</cell>
                    <cell>Switz-erland</cell>
                    <cell>Other socialist countries</cell>
                    <cell>Other Western countries</cell>
                    <cell>None</cell>
                    <cell>I don't know</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell><hi rend="None">1</hi></cell>
                    <cell><hi rend="None"><seg rend="bold">47.1</seg></hi></cell>
                    <cell><hi rend="None">2.3</hi></cell>
                    <cell><hi rend="None">4.6</hi></cell>
                    <cell><hi rend="None">0.5</hi></cell>
                    <cell><hi rend="None">0.7</hi></cell>
                    <cell><hi rend="None">4.2</hi></cell>
                    <cell><hi rend="None">1.9</hi></cell>
                    <cell><hi rend="None">1.5</hi></cell>
                    <cell><hi rend="None">0.3</hi></cell>
                    <cell><hi rend="None">1.3</hi></cell>
                    <cell><hi rend="None">1.1</hi></cell>
                    <cell><hi rend="None">34.4</hi></cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell><hi rend="None">2</hi></cell>
                    <cell><hi rend="None"><seg rend="bold">56.7</seg></hi></cell>
                    <cell><hi rend="None">7</hi></cell>
                    <cell><hi rend="None">1.5</hi></cell>
                    <cell><hi rend="None">0</hi></cell>
                    <cell><hi rend="None">0.2</hi></cell>
                    <cell><hi rend="None">1.3</hi></cell>
                    <cell><hi rend="None">1.1</hi></cell>
                    <cell><hi rend="None">0.5</hi></cell>
                    <cell><hi rend="None">0.2</hi></cell>
                    <cell><hi rend="None">1.6</hi></cell>
                    <cell><hi rend="None">0.6</hi></cell>
                    <cell><hi rend="None">29.9</hi></cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell><hi rend="None">3</hi></cell>
                    <cell><hi rend="None"><seg rend="bold">36.3</seg></hi></cell>
                    <cell><hi rend="None">4.6</hi></cell>
                    <cell><hi rend="None">1.9</hi></cell>
                    <cell><hi rend="None">2.1</hi></cell>
                    <cell><hi rend="None">0.5</hi></cell>
                    <cell><hi rend="None">2.2</hi></cell>
                    <cell><hi rend="None">1.3</hi></cell>
                    <cell><hi rend="None">0.4</hi></cell>
                    <cell><hi rend="None">0.4</hi></cell>
                    <cell><hi rend="None">4.7</hi></cell>
                    <cell><hi rend="None">1.1</hi></cell>
                    <cell><hi rend="None"><seg rend="bold">44.4</seg></hi></cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell><hi rend="None">4</hi></cell>
                    <cell><hi rend="None"><seg rend="bold">56.9</seg></hi></cell>
                    <cell><hi rend="None">1.5</hi></cell>
                    <cell><hi rend="None">1.7</hi></cell>
                    <cell><hi rend="None">0.4</hi></cell>
                    <cell><hi rend="None">0.8</hi></cell>
                    <cell><hi rend="None">1.3</hi></cell>
                    <cell><hi rend="None">3.4</hi></cell>
                    <cell><hi rend="None">0.7</hi></cell>
                    <cell><hi rend="None">0.3</hi></cell>
                    <cell><hi rend="None">1.4</hi></cell>
                    <cell><hi rend="None">2.3</hi></cell>
                    <cell><hi rend="None">29.3</hi></cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell><hi rend="None">5</hi></cell>
                    <cell><hi rend="None"><seg rend="bold">48.3</seg></hi></cell>
                    <cell><hi rend="None">0.1</hi></cell>
                    <cell><hi rend="None">1.8</hi></cell>
                    <cell><hi rend="None">12.7</hi></cell>
                    <cell><hi rend="None">1.7</hi></cell>
                    <cell><hi rend="None">1.2</hi></cell>
                    <cell><hi rend="None">0.2</hi></cell>
                    <cell><hi rend="None">0.3</hi></cell>
                    <cell><hi rend="None">0.1</hi></cell>
                    <cell><hi rend="None">1.4</hi></cell>
                    <cell><hi rend="None">1.1</hi></cell>
                    <cell><hi rend="None">31.1</hi></cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell><hi rend="None">6</hi></cell>
                    <cell><hi rend="None">24.8</hi></cell>
                    <cell><hi rend="None">3.6</hi></cell>
                    <cell><hi rend="None">9.4</hi></cell>
                    <cell><hi rend="None">1.1</hi></cell>
                    <cell><hi rend="None">0</hi></cell>
                    <cell><hi rend="None">13.5</hi></cell>
                    <cell><hi rend="None">5.2</hi></cell>
                    <cell><hi rend="None">3.8</hi></cell>
                    <cell><hi rend="None">0.2</hi></cell>
                    <cell><hi rend="None">4.3</hi></cell>
                    <cell><hi rend="None">1.1</hi></cell>
                    <cell><hi rend="None"><seg rend="bold">32</seg></hi></cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell><hi rend="None">7</hi></cell>
                    <cell><hi rend="None"><seg rend="bold">75.6</seg></hi></cell>
                    <cell><hi rend="None">1.1</hi></cell>
                    <cell><hi rend="None">0.3</hi></cell>
                    <cell><hi rend="None">0.2</hi></cell>
                    <cell><hi rend="None">0.1</hi></cell>
                    <cell><hi rend="None">0</hi></cell>
                    <cell><hi rend="None">0.8</hi></cell>
                    <cell><hi rend="None">2.1</hi></cell>
                    <cell><hi rend="None">0.4</hi></cell>
                    <cell><hi rend="None">0.8</hi></cell>
                    <cell><hi rend="None">0.7</hi></cell>
                    <cell><hi rend="None">17.8</hi></cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell><hi rend="None">8</hi></cell>
                    <cell><hi rend="None">23.9</hi></cell>
                    <cell><hi rend="None"><seg rend="bold">24</seg></hi></cell>
                    <cell><hi rend="None">8.6</hi></cell>
                    <cell><hi rend="None">0.5</hi></cell>
                    <cell><hi rend="None">0.1</hi></cell>
                    <cell><hi rend="None">9.6</hi></cell>
                    <cell><hi rend="None">0.9</hi></cell>
                    <cell><hi rend="None">0.4</hi></cell>
                    <cell><hi rend="None">0.2</hi></cell>
                    <cell><hi rend="None">4.1</hi></cell>
                    <cell><hi rend="None">0.5</hi></cell>
                    <cell><hi rend="None"><seg rend="bold">27.1</seg></hi></cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell><hi rend="None">9</hi></cell>
                    <cell><hi rend="None"><seg rend="bold">68.5</seg></hi></cell>
                    <cell><hi rend="None">0.1</hi></cell>
                    <cell><hi rend="None">0.1</hi></cell>
                    <cell><hi rend="None">2.4</hi></cell>
                    <cell><hi rend="None">0.4</hi></cell>
                    <cell><hi rend="None">0.5</hi></cell>
                    <cell><hi rend="None">0.4</hi></cell>
                    <cell><hi rend="None">5.7</hi></cell>
                    <cell><hi rend="None">0.2</hi></cell>
                    <cell><hi rend="None">2.0</hi></cell>
                    <cell><hi rend="None">0.2</hi></cell>
                    <cell><hi rend="None">19.6</hi></cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell><hi rend="None">10</hi></cell>
                    <cell><hi rend="None"><seg rend="bold">48.5</seg></hi></cell>
                    <cell><hi rend="None">0.9</hi></cell>
                    <cell><hi rend="None">0.5</hi></cell>
                    <cell><hi rend="None">0.5</hi></cell>
                    <cell><hi rend="None">0.2</hi></cell>
                    <cell><hi rend="None">0.3</hi></cell>
                    <cell><hi rend="None">0.4</hi></cell>
                    <cell><hi rend="None">0.4</hi></cell>
                    <cell><hi rend="None">0.2</hi></cell>
                    <cell><hi rend="None">1.5</hi></cell>
                    <cell><hi rend="None">2.6</hi></cell>
                    <cell><hi rend="None"><seg rend="bold">43.9</seg></hi></cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell><hi rend="None">11</hi></cell>
                    <cell><hi rend="None"><seg rend="bold">51.4</seg></hi></cell>
                    <cell><hi rend="None">3.1</hi></cell>
                    <cell><hi rend="None">0.3</hi></cell>
                    <cell><hi rend="None">0.2</hi></cell>
                    <cell><hi rend="None">0.2</hi></cell>
                    <cell><hi rend="None">0.7</hi></cell>
                    <cell><hi rend="None">1.1</hi></cell>
                    <cell><hi rend="None">0.3</hi></cell>
                    <cell><hi rend="None">0.5</hi></cell>
                    <cell><hi rend="None">0.4</hi></cell>
                    <cell><hi rend="None">6.3</hi></cell>
                    <cell><hi rend="None">35.5</hi></cell>
                </row>
            </table>
            <list type="unordered">
                <item>advancement possibilities </item>
                <item>education possibilities</item>
                <item>highly developed culture life</item>
                <item>care for the sick and unemployed </item>
                <item>position of religion and relations between the Church and the state</item>
                <item>good economy (country's economic progress)</item>
                <item>pacifist policy and reputation in the world</item>
                <item>swift development of science and technology</item>
                <item>natural beauties</item>
                <item>possibilities of the majority of the people to influence social
                    decisions</item>
                <item>camaraderie and equality between the people</item>
            </list>
            </div>
            <div>
            <ab type="milestone" style="text-align:center">* * *</ab>
            <p>Major changes in the attitude towards the Russian October on the global as well as
                the Slovenian level took place towards the end of the 1980s, when the bipolar global
                system became unstable. At the seventieth anniversary of the Revolution in 1987, a
                big parade was organised in Moscow, as always. On this occasion the first man in the
                state would traditionally speak, and this time it was the reformist Mikhail
                Gorbachev who gave the speech. "The October Revolution is truly the shining hour of
                humanity, its radiant dawn," Gorbachev said. "The October Revolution is a revolution
                of the people and for the people, for every individual, for his emancipation and
                development." However, in the continuation he did not forget to add: "The changes
                taking place in the country today probably constitute the biggest step in developing
                socialist democracy since the October revolution."<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn31"
                    n="28">"Gorbachev on History; Revolution's Road From 1917 to Now: The Leader
                    Takes Stock," <hi rend="italic">The New York Times</hi>, 3. 11. 1987.</note> Not
                long after that – only three years later – almost all politicians and media
                worldwide agreed with this assessment.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn32" n="29"> In
                    1987, after Gorbachev's speech, the Slovenian newspaper Komunist saw Perestroika
                    as the continuation of the October. - Sava Živanov, "Perestrojka kot
                    nadaljevanje Oktobra," <seg rend="italic">Komunist</seg>, 6. 11. 1987, 18,
                    19.</note> 1990 was unanimously declared as The Year of the People – as the most
                pivotal year in the Russian or Soviet history after 1917.<note place="foot"
                    xml:id="ftn33" n="30">"Undoing Lenin's Legacy," <hi rend="italic">Time</hi>, 19.
                    2. 1990.</note></p>
            <p>It seems that this – the year 1990 – was the last year when the Russian October still
                enjoyed the reputation of a globally-important and epochal event. Afterwards its
                provocative power started waning. Today the Russian October thus appears to be
                "outdated", an ancient event whose consequences have already dissipated. In Slovenia
                and in the former Yugoslav countries barely anyone researches this event or even has
                an opinion about it.</p>
            <p>How about Russia? At the symposium, organised by the Institute of Contemporary
                History on the occasion of the 100th anniversary of the October Revolution on 26
                October 2017 in Ljubljana, Alexander Semyonov, the director of the Centre for
                Historical Research at St. Petersburg School of Social Sciences and Humanities,
                commented mischievously: "Russian Government today is anti-revolutionary". Sam
                Greene, the director of the Russia Institute at King's College London, expressed a
                similar opinion: "The Russian government won't mark the 100th anniversary," he said.
                "They are trying to construct a narrative of uninterrupted power and stability. So
                something like 1917 is an uncomfortable fact that doesn't fit in with that."<note
                    place="foot" xml:id="ftn34" n="31">Angela Dewan and Darya Tarasova, "Russian
                    Revolution: An awkward moment for Putin 100 years on," <hi rend="italic"
                        >CNN</hi>, 18 January 2018, <ref
                        target="http://edition.cnn.com/2017/03/08/europe/russian-revolution-100-years-putin/index.html"
                        >http://edition.cnn.com/2017/03/08/europe/russian-revolution-100-years-putin/index.html</ref>.</note>
                Another historian stated for the Guardian: "There’s no official line from the
                Kremlin – they can’t identify themselves with Lenin, because he was a revolutionary,
                and they can’t identify with Nicholas II because he was a weak leader."<note
                    place="foot" xml:id="ftn35" n="32">Shaun Walker, "Tragedy or triumph? Russians
                    agonise over how to mark 1917 revolutions," <hi rend="italic">The Guardian</hi>,
                    17. 12. 2016,
                    https://www.theguardian.com/world/2016/dec/17/russia-1917-revolutions-legacy-lenin-putin.</note></p>
            <p>While Europe was capable of coming together in order to commemorate the anniversary
                of World War II and the beginning of World War I, the 1917 events remain
                "forgotten". We can establish that the attitude towards the events that took place a
                century ago is certainly overshadowed by the current political developments, as it
                has, after all, always been – yet with one crucial difference: until the 1990s, the
                Revolution was everywhere seen as the beginning of something important (and great).
                This says a lot about the times we live in – as if the great opportunities, provided
                by the Revolution in the opinion of many of its observers, were finally exhausted in
                1990. </p>
            <p>If we were not historians but futurologists instead, we could assume that the time
                will come when the fascination with the 1989, 1990 and 1991 events will eventually
                disappear as well. All we have to wait for is the next Year of the People. After
                all, at the beginning of the 1990s the bipolar global system crumbled, which was
                something that many people in the West disliked; it was the time when the Soviet
                empire disintegrated, which was something that many people in the East disliked; and
                it was also when the Yugoslav socialist experiment came to an end, which is
                something that many people disliked (and still do) in Slovenia. </p>
            <p>On the other hand, in Russia as well as in many places in the Western hemisphere,
                historians are still interested in the October Revolution,<note place="foot"
                    xml:id="ftn36" n="33">The collection of literature about the Russian
                    Revolutions, published in the recent years, is truly vast. Even Slovenian
                    translations of a few works have been published, including the following
                    prominent works: Orlando Figes, <hi rend="italic">Tragedija ljudstva. Ruska
                        revolucija 1891–1924</hi> (Ljubljana: Modrijan, 2013). Original: <seg
                        rend="italic">A People’s Tragedy. The Russian Revolution 1891-1924</seg>.
                    Alexander Rabinowitch, <seg rend="italic">Boljševiki prihajajo na oblast</seg>
                    (Ljubljana: Sophia, 2017). Original: <seg rend="italic">The Bolsheviks Come to
                        Power. The Revolution of 1917 in Petrograd</seg>. </note> with the only
                distinction that the focus of interest has changed along with the spatial and
                temporal context.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn37" n="34">In this regard see the
                    booklet of abstracts, published during the international conference at the
                    Institute of Contemporary History: <hi rend="italic">Misliti o revoluciji: 100
                        let pozneje / Thinking About the Revolution: 100 Years Later. Povzetki /
                        Abstracts</hi>, ed. Mojca Šorn (Ljubljana: Inštitut za novejšo zgodovino,
                    2017).</note> Nowadays not many people pay attention to the <seg rend="italic"
                    >Ten Days That Shook the World</seg> (as the American journalist John Reed
                entitled his outstanding report on these events),<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn38"
                    n="35">John Reed, <hi rend="italic">Deset dni, ki so pretresli svet</hi>
                    (Ljubljana: Cankarjeva založba, 1951). Original: <hi rend="italic">Ten Days That
                        Shook the World</hi>.</note> as it is necessary to study the late Russian
                empire at least from the end of the 19th century and the revolutionary echo until
                the present moment in order to understand the process. Thus, modern historiography
                currently focuses on the role of Duma, the national circumstances in the late
                Russian empire, the questions of autonomy and federalism… The term "Revolution" is
                progressively disappearing from the interpretative repertoire, and the expression
                "imperial breakup" or "transformation" is asserting itself instead.<note
                    place="foot" xml:id="ftn39" n="36">Alexander M. Semyonov, "Revolucija ali razpad
                    imperija? Leto 1917 kot primer preoblikovanja imperijev / Revolution or Imperial
                    Breakup? 1917 as a Case of Imperial Transformations," in: <hi rend="italic"
                        >Misliti o revoluciji: 100 let pozneje / Thinking About the Revolution: 100
                        Years Later. Povzetki / Abstracts</hi>, ed. Mojca Šorn (Ljubljana: Inštitut
                    za novejšo zgodovino, 2017), 7–10.</note> Similarly, German historiography is
                expanding the range of topics, approaches and the temporal frame of studying the Red
                    October<seg rend="color(FF0000)" xml:space="preserve"> (Andreas Schulz focuses on this subject more closely in his contribution to this </seg><seg
                    rend="color(FF0000)">volume</seg><seg rend="color(FF0000)">).</seg> German
                historiographers are establishing that the Revolution had long-term consequences on
                at least three levels – the political, demographic, and socio-economic. Due to the
                massive relocations of the population and numerous refugees, the population
                structure changed significantly. The Russian experience stimulated the improvement
                of the social legislation, while the German industrial Soviets, organised in the
                factories, have survived until this very day and still represent the institutional
                pillar of the German social market economy system (the so-called Paritätische
                    Mitbestimmung).<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn40" n="37">Andreas Schulz, "Vplivi
                    ruske revolucije na weimarsko Nemčijo / Impacts of the Russian Revolution on
                    Weimar Germany," in: <hi rend="italic">Misliti o revoluciji: 100 let pozneje /
                        Thinking About the Revolution: 100 Years Later. Povzetki / Abstracts</hi>,
                    ed. Mojca Šorn (Ljubljana: Inštitut za novejšo zgodovino, 2017), 11–16.</note>
                The German constitution, adopted after World War I (the Weimar Constitution),
                contained a whole section dedicated to the socio-economic issues which was a great
                novelty at the time. Under the influence of this section of the Weimar Constitution,
                a few years later (in 1921) the Yugoslav Constitutional Assembly also adopted such a
                constitution (the St. Vitus' Day Constitution), which regulated the workers' rights
                in a very similar (sometimes literally identical) manner.<note place="foot"
                    xml:id="ftn41" n="38">Jure Gašparič, "Od Sv. Jakoba do Lenina. Ustavodajni
                    proces v Kraljevini SHS in njegov evropski kontekst," in: <seg rend="italic"
                        >Nečakov zbornik</seg> (Ljubljana: Filozofska fakulteta, 2018),
                    115-30.</note> The indirect influence of the Russian Revolution definitely
                reached far across space as well as time. </p></div>
            <div><ab type="milestone" style="text-align:center">* * *</ab>
            <p>I prepared this discussion in the early autumn of 2017 in the context of the
                preparations for the conference Thinking about the Revolution: 100 Years After,
                organised by the Institute of Contemporary History. At that time it appeared that
                the anniversary of the Revolution would slip unnoticed by the Slovenian public and
                (partly) also historiography, but as it turned out, numerous Slovenian media and
                institutions nevertheless brought the anniversary of the Revolution to the public
                attention. Quite a few academic events took place – conferences of various scopes
                and levels (including the ones organised by the Institute of Contemporary History on
                24 October in Ljubljana; by the University Library of Maribor and the Research
                Centre of the Slovenian Academy of Sciences and Arts on 7 November 2017 in Maribor;
                and by Alma Mater Europaea – Institutum Studiorum Humanitatis in cooperation with
                the
                <hi rend="None" xml:space="preserve"> Russian Centre for Science and Culture on 19 October 2017 in Ljubljana).</hi></p>
            <p>Furthermore, in the autumn of 2017 a few discussions (for example by the Study Centre
                for National Reconciliation on 6 November 2017) and various round tables (for
                example by the Slovenia-Russia Society and the Miran Jarc library in Novo mesto on 8
                November 2017) were organised. A new translation of Lenin's work <seg rend="italic"
                    >The State and Revolution</seg><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn42" n="39">
                    Vladimir Iljič Lenin, <hi rend="italic">Država in revolucija in drugi spisi iz
                        leta 1917</hi> (Ljubljana: Studia Humanitatis, 2017). </note><hi rend="None"
                    > was published, the Institute of Contemporary History digitised John Reed's
                    book <seg rend="italic">Ten Days That Shook the World</seg>,</hi><note
                    place="foot" xml:id="ftn43" n="40"> John Reed, <hi rend="italic">Deset dni, ki
                        so pretresli svet</hi>, available at:
                    <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Zgodovina Slovenije – SIstory, </hi>22
                    January 2018, http://www.sistory.si/11686/37829.</note><hi rend="None"> and the
                    Slovenian Cinematheque prepared a special Soviet film retrospective, which
                    opened with the projection of Sergei Eisenstein's 1925 film <seg rend="italic"
                        >Battleship Potemkin</seg>. The printed and electronic media published
                    several interviews, discussions,</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn44" n="41">
                    E.g., "Oktobrska revolucija, najpomembnejši dogodek 20. stoletja," <hi
                        rend="italic">Oddaja Intelekta</hi>, 7. 11. 2017. Available at: <hi
                        rend="italic">RTV SLO</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Radio Prvi</hi>, <hi
                        rend="allcaps">http://4d.rtvslo.si/arhiv/intelekta/174500787.</hi></note><hi
                    rend="None"> commentaries and presentations. <seg rend="italic"
                    >Mladina</seg>,</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn45" n="42">
                    <hi rend="italic">Mladina</hi>, Oktobrska revolucija 1917-2017 (Special Issue,
                    November 2017).</note><hi rend="None"> a leftist weekly magazine, dedicated a
                    special issue to the anniversary; <seg rend="italic">Slovenski čas</seg> (a
                    Catholic magazine and supplement of the <seg rend="italic">Družina</seg>
                    weekly)</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn46" n="43">
                    <hi rend="italic">Slovenski čas (Priloga tednika Družina)</hi> 90, October
                    2017.</note><hi rend="None" xml:space="preserve"> wrote about the anniversary in various articles; and topical issues of the Borec magazine for history, anthropology and literature (Oktober 1917–2017)</hi><note
                    place="foot" xml:id="ftn47" n="44">
                    <hi rend="italic">Borec</hi> LXIX, Nr. 739-741 (2017) (Oktober
                    1917-2017).</note><hi rend="None"> as well as of the <seg rend="italic"
                        >Časopis</seg><seg rend="italic" xml:space="preserve"> za kritiko znanosti</seg>
                    journal (Mislimo revolucije) were published.</hi><note place="foot"
                    xml:id="ftn48" n="45">
                    <hi rend="italic">Časopis za kritiko znanosti</hi> 269 (2017) (Mislimo
                    revolucije).</note><hi rend="None" xml:space="preserve"> </hi></p>
            <p>Perhaps we can thus establish that the Russian October is still capable of attracting
                people's attention. The number of events and celebrations was actually not
                negligible at all, especially considering the fact that some anniversaries were
                completely overlooked in 2017 – for example the 110th anniversary of the universal
                suffrage in Austria (1907) and the anniversary of the strike in one of the largest
                Slovenian companies in the socialist period, Litostroj (1987), which played a
                pivotal role in the contemporaneous democratisation processes and led to the
                creation of a political party – the Social Democratic Party of Slovenia. </p>
            <p>However, if we compare the public events and publications dedicated to the Russian
                October with other historiographic subjects, we can confidently claim that the
                anniversary was not one of the central historical topics in 2017. More importance
                was given to the topics from the recent national history, especially the 100th
                anniversary of the May Declaration (the declaration of the Yugoslav parliamentary
                group in the Vienna parliament, which contained a demand to establish an independent
                state body under the rule of the Habsburg dynasty). At the celebration that followed
                the symposium, President of the Republic Borut Pahor gave a speech and Cardinal
                Franc Rode held a mass. Furthermore, a documentary film was made about the
                declaration and the president of the Yugoslav parliamentary group Anton
                    Korošec.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn49" n="46">"Majniška deklaracija 1917,"
                        <hi rend="italic">Sledi časa</hi>, 18. 6. 2017, available at:
                    <seg rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">RTV SLO, </seg>http://4d.rtvslo.si/arhiv/sledi/174477695.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Other more publicly renowned historical events also included the 100th anniversary of
                the death of one of the most prominent Slovenian politicians, thinkers and public
                workers Janez Evangelist Krek, who was also called "the red socialist in a black
                robe" due to his social programme and actions (the national television dedicated a
                lengthy and partly live-action documentary film to him)<note place="foot"
                    xml:id="ftn50" n="47">"Revolucionar v talarju: Janez Evangelist Krek," <hi
                        rend="italic">RTV SLO</hi>, 8. 10. 2017, <ref
                        target="http://4d.rtvslo.si/arhiv/dokumentarni-filmi-in-oddaje-kulturno-umetniski-program/174495515"
                        >http://4d.rtvslo.si/arhiv/dokumentarni-filmi-in-oddaje-kulturno-umetniski-program/174495515</ref>.</note>;
                and – traditionally – the topics of World War II, collaboration, and the Slovenian
                revolution, which never cease to fascinate the media. None of the Slovenian museums
                organised an exhibition dedicated to the anniversary of the Revolution.<note
                    place="foot" xml:id="ftn51" n="48"> On the other hand, the German Historical
                    Museum (Deutsches Historisches Museum) in Berlin prepared an extensive
                    exhibition, also described by Andreas Schulz in his discussion, published in
                    this volume.</note></p>
            <p>Nevertheless it seems that the October Revolution no longer represents such a
                socially-momentous event as it used to. This fact is confirmed by the contributions
                of the aforementioned media – some of them merely summarised the events of that
                period, while others simply emphasised certain selected issues, for example the
                revolutionary violence. Only academic journals and events were – as expected –
                capable of offering a more comprehensive reflexion. With a tinge of cynicism we
                could perhaps conclude that the October Revolution has become a completely ordinary
                historical topic in Slovenia.</p></div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="bibliography">
                <head>Sources and Literature</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Newspapers and Magazines</head>
                    <bibl><seg rend="italic">Arbeiterwille</seg>.</bibl>
                    <bibl><seg rend="italic">Delo.</seg></bibl>
                    <bibl><seg rend="italic">Der Spiegel.</seg></bibl>
                    <bibl><seg rend="italic">Jutro.</seg></bibl>
                    <bibl><seg rend="italic">Komunist.</seg></bibl>
                    <bibl><seg rend="italic">Mladina.</seg></bibl>
                    <bibl><seg rend="italic">Neue Freie Presse</seg>.</bibl>
                    <bibl><seg rend="italic">Slovenec.</seg></bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="italic">Slovenski čas (Priloga tednika Družina)</hi></bibl>
                    <bibl><seg rend="italic">The Guardian.</seg></bibl>
                    <bibl><seg rend="italic">The New York Times.</seg></bibl>
                    <bibl><seg rend="italic">Time.</seg></bibl>
                    <bibl><seg rend="italic">Toti list.</seg></bibl>
                </listBibl>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Literature</head>
                    <bibl>Bernstein, Herman. "Russia after Lenin -- will soviet survive?." <hi
                            rend="italic">The New York Times</hi>, 27. 1. 1924.</bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="italic">Borec</hi> LXIX, Nr. 739-741 (2017) (Oktober
                        1917-2017).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Britovšek, Marjan. <seg rend="italic">Revolucionarni idejni preobrat med
                            prvo svetovno vojno. Lenin v boju za tretjo internacionalo</seg>.
                        Ljubljana: Cankarjeva založba, 1969.</bibl>
                    <bibl>-. <seg rend="italic">Boj za Leninovo dediščino</seg>. Ljubljana:
                        Mladinska knjiga, 1976.</bibl>
                    <bibl>-. <seg rend="italic">Carizem, revolucija, stalinizem. Družbeni razvoj v
                            Rusiji in perspektive socializma</seg>. Ljubljana: Cankarjeva založba,
                        1980.</bibl>
                    <bibl>-.
                        <seg rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Korenine stalinizma in negativne posledice kulta </seg>osebnosti.
                        Ljubljana: Zavod SR Slovenije za šolstvo, 1980.</bibl>
                    <bibl>-. <seg rend="italic">Stalinov termidor</seg>. Ljubljana: Cankarjeva
                        založba, 1984.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Crankshaw, Edward. "The Coup That Changed the
                        World."<hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve"> The New York Times</hi>, 19.
                        2. 1967.</bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="italic">Časopis za kritiko znanosti</hi> 269 (2017) (Mislimo
                        revolucije).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Dolinar, Dušan. "Pet desetletij Oktobra." <hi rend="italic">Delo</hi>, 7.
                        11. 1967.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Figes, Orlando. <seg rend="italic">Tragedija ljudstva. Ruska revolucija
                            1891-1924</seg>. Ljubljana: Modrijan, 2013 [Original: Figes, Orlando,
                            <seg rend="italic">A People’s Tragedy. The Russian Revolution
                            1891-1924</seg>].</bibl>
                    <bibl>Gašparič, Jure. "Slovensko dojemanje druge Jugoslavije." In: <seg
                            rend="italic">Slovenija v Jugoslaviji</seg>, edited by Zdenko Čepič,
                        87-104. Ljubljana: Inštitut za novejšo zgodovino, 2015.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Gašparič, Jure. "Od Sv. Jakoba do Lenina. Ustavodajni proces v Kraljevini
                        SHS in njegov evropski kontekst." In:<hi rend="None">
                            <seg rend="italic">Nečakov zbornik</seg>, 115-130. Ljubljana: Filozofska
                            fakulteta, 2018.</hi></bibl>
                    <bibl>Krleža, Miroslav. <seg rend="italic">Izlet u Rusiju</seg>. Zagreb: Novi
                        Liber, 2013.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Lenin, Vladimir Iljič. <hi rend="italic">Država in revolucija in drugi
                            spisi iz leta 1917</hi>. Ljubljana: Studia Humanitatis, 2017.</bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="None"><seg rend="italic">Misliti o revoluciji: 100 let pozneje
                                /</seg><seg rend="italic" xml:space="preserve"> Thinking About the Revolution: 100 Years Later</seg><seg
                                rend="italic">. Povzetki / Abstracts</seg>,
                        </hi>edited<hi rend="None" xml:space="preserve"> by Mojca Šorn. Ljubljana: Inštitut za novejšo zgodovino, 2017.</hi></bibl>
                    <bibl>Perovšek, Jurij. "Ruski beguncu in pogledi slovenske politike na Lenina ob
                        njegovi smrti." <seg rend="italic">Monitor ISH</seg> XVIII, Nr. 1 (2016):
                        7-31.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Popoff, Peter J. "Lenin's Great
                        Experiment."<seg rend="italic" xml:space="preserve"> The New York Times</seg>,
                        25. 1. 1924.</bibl>
                    <bibl><seg rend="italic">Prispevki za zgodovino delavskega gibanja</seg> 1967
                        VII, Nr. 1-2, Zbornik razprav in obravnav znanstvenega posvetovanja Ob 50.
                        obletnici oktobrske revolucije in ob 30. obletnici ustanovnega kongresa
                        Komunistične partije Slovenije v Ljubljani od 2. do 4. novembra 1967.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Prunk, Janko. "Jugoslovanska historiografija o oktobrski revoluciji."
                            <seg rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Prispevki za </seg><seg
                            rend="italic">novejšo zgodovino</seg> XXVII (1987): 3-6.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Rabinowitch,
                        Alexander.<seg rend="italic" xml:space="preserve"> Boljševiki prihajajo na oblast</seg>.
                        Ljubljana: Sophia, 2017 [Original: Rabinowitch, Alexander. <seg
                            rend="italic">The Bolsheviks Come to Power. The Revolution of 1917 in
                            Petrograd</seg>].</bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="None">Reed, John. <seg rend="italic">Deset dni, ki so pretresli
                                svet</seg>. Ljubljana: Cankarjeva založba, 1951 [Original: Reed,
                            John. <seg rend="italic">Ten Days That Shook the
                        World</seg>].</hi></bibl>
                    <bibl>Schulz, Andreas. "Vplivi ruske revolucije na weimarsko Nemčijo / Impacts
                        of the Russian Revolution on Weimar Germany." In:
                            <seg rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Misliti o revoluciji: 100 let pozneje / </seg><seg
                            rend="italic">Thinking About the Revolution: 100 Years Later</seg>. <seg
                            rend="italic">Povzetki / Abstracts</seg>, edited by Mojca Šorn, 11-16.
                        Ljubljana: Inštitut za novejšo zgodovino, 2017.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Semyonov, Alexander M. "Revolucija ali razpad imperija? Leto 1917 kot
                        primer preoblikovanja imperijev / Revolution or Imperial Breakup? 1917 as a
                        Case of Imperial Transformations." In:
                            <seg rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Misliti o revoluciji: 100 let pozneje </seg><seg
                            rend="italic">/ Thinking About the Revolution: 100 Years Later</seg><seg
                            rend="italic"
                        >.</seg><seg rend="italic" xml:space="preserve"> Povzetki / Abstracts</seg>,
                        edited by Mojca Šorn, 7-10. Ljubljana: Inštitut za novejšo zgodovino,
                        2017.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Tito, Josip Broz. "Moja doživetja v Rusiji med oktobrsko revolucijo in
                        državljansko vojno." <hi rend="italic">Delo – Sobotna priloga</hi>, 5. 11.
                        1977.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Toš, Niko et al. <hi rend="italic">Slovensko javno mnenje 1968</hi>.
                        [datoteka podatkov]. Ljubljana: Univerza v Ljubljani, Visoka šola za
                        politične vede, Center za raziskovanje javnega mnenja in množičnih
                        komunikacij [izdelava], 1968. Ljubljana: Univerza v Ljubljani, Fakulteta za
                        družbene vede, Arhiv družboslovnih podatkov [distribucija], 1999 (Arhiv
                        družboslovnih podatkov: <ref
                            target="http://www.adp.fdv.uni-lj.si/opisi/sjm912.xml"
                            >http://www.adp.fdv.uni-lj.si/opisi/sjm912.xml</ref>).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Ziherl, Boris. "Dve obletnici," <hi rend="italic">Prispevki za zgodovino
                            delavskega gibanja</hi> VII, Nr. 1-2 (1967): 9-19.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Zweig, Stefan. <seg rend="italic">Zvezdni trenutki človeštva</seg> (zgodba
                        Plombirani vlak). Celovec: Mohorjeva, 2004 [Original: Zweig, Stefan.
                        <seg rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Sternstunden der Menscheit </seg>(the
                        Miniature Der Versiegelte Zug)].</bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="None">Živanov, Sava. "Perestrojka kot nadaljevanje Oktobra."
                                <seg rend="italic">Komunist</seg>, 6. 11. 1987, 18, 19.</hi></bibl>
                </listBibl>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>E-Sources</head>
                    <bibl><hi rend="None">Dewan, Angela and Darya Tarasova. "Russian Revolution: An
                            awkward moment for Putin 100 years on."
                            <seg rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">CNN </seg></hi>Accesed 18
                        January 2018. <ref
                            target="http://edition.cnn.com/2017/03/08/europe/russian-revolution-100-years-putin/index.html"
                            >http://edition.cnn.com/2017/03/08/europe/russian-revolution-100-years-putin/index.html</ref><hi
                            rend="None">.</hi></bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="italic">Newspapers.com</hi>. Accesed 5 July 2017. <ref
                            target="lnd=1&amp;query=russian+revolution&amp;dr_year=1917-1919&amp;t=395"
                                ><hi rend="Hyperlink.0"
                                >https://www.newspapers.com/search/#lnd=1&amp;query=russian+revolution&amp;dr_year=1917-1919&amp;t=395</hi></ref></bibl>
                    <bibl>Reed,
                        John.<hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve"> Deset dni, ki so pretresli svet</hi>.
                        Available at: <ref target="http://www.sistory.si/11686/37829"
                            >http://www.sistory.si/11686/37829</ref>.</bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="italic">RTV SLO</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Radio Prvi</hi>.
                        "Oktobrska revolucija, najpomembnejši dogodek 20. stoletja." Oddaja
                        Intelekta,<hi rend="allcaps" xml:space="preserve"> 7. 11. 2017. </hi>Available
                        at: <ref target="http://4d.rtvslo.si/arhiv/intelekta/174500787"><hi
                                rend="allcaps"
                            >http://4d.rtvslo.si/arhiv/intelekta/174500787</hi></ref><hi
                            rend="allcaps">.</hi></bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="None"><seg rend="italic">RTV SLO.</seg> "Majniška deklaracija
                            1917 (Sledi časa)," 18. 6. 2017. </hi>Available
                            at:<hi rend="None" xml:space="preserve"> </hi><ref
                            target="http://4d.rtvslo.si/arhiv/sledi/174477695"
                            >http://4d.rtvslo.si/arhiv/sledi/174477695</ref><hi rend="None"
                        >.</hi></bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="None"><seg rend="italic">RTV SLO</seg>. "Revolucionar v talarju:
                            Janez Evangelist Krek," 8. 10. 2017. </hi>Available
                            at:<hi rend="None" xml:space="preserve"> </hi><ref
                            target="http://4d.rtvslo.si/arhiv/dokumentarni-filmi-in-oddaje-kulturno-umetniski-program/174495515"
                            >http://4d.rtvslo.si/arhiv/dokumentarni-filmi-in-oddaje-kulturno-umetniski-program/174495515</ref><hi
                            rend="None">.</hi></bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="None">Walker, Shaun.</hi> "Tragedy or triumph? Russians agonise
                        over how to mark 1917 revolutions." <hi rend="italic">The Guardian</hi>, 17.
                        12. 2016. Available at: <ref
                            target="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2016/dec/17/russia-1917-revolutions-legacy-lenin-putin"
                            >https://www.theguardian.com/world/2016/dec/17/russia-1917-revolutions-legacy-lenin-putin</ref>.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
            <div type="summary" xml:lang="sl">
                <docAuthor>Jure Gašparič</docAuthor>
                <head>SPREMINJAJOČ POGLED NA RUSKO REVOLUCIJO – SLOVENIJA V GLOBALNI
                        PERSPEKTIVI</head>
                <head>POVZETEK</head>
                <p>Med letoma 1917 in 1924 so po skoraj vsej zemeljski obli izhajali
                        podlistki in komentarji o svetovnem pomenu dogajanja v Rusiji. Množičnemu
                        ocenjevanju so se pridružili tudi številni pisci s slovenskega ozemlja.
                        Želji, podati svojo oceno, se niso mogli upreti v nobenem političnem taboru
                        (ne liberalnem, ne katoliškem, ne marksističnem), pri nobeni politični
                        skupini. Tedaj sploh ni šlo za komunizem, so pisali, marveč za veliko več,
                        za prekrajanje (preoblikovanje) človeka. Revolucija je odprla neslutene
                        možnosti. Na Slovenskem so nanjo sprva zrli v pričakovanju boljšega (četudi
                        zavedajoč se nevarnosti), konec tridesetih let pa se je ocena zaostrila.
                        Časniki so ugotavljali, da je komunizem "le utopija", v slovenskem
                        katoliškem političnem taboru so zapisali: "Rdeči paradiž na zemlji je v
                        resnici ves rdeč – od prelite človeške krvi."</p>
                <p>Po drugi svetovni vojni se je ocenjevanje ruskega oktobra v Sloveniji in nasploh v Jugoslaviji precej spremenilo. Če je pred letom 1945 opazovalec lahko spremljal številne kritične, a tudi pozitivne ocene revolucije, prvih odtlej ni bilo več najti. V prvem obdobju po koncu vojne so prevladovale le panegirične hvalnice in nekritični hvalospevi. Po sporu z Informbirojem leta 1948 je nato razumljivo prišlo do delnega preobrata, ki pa v bistvu ni zadeval idejnih prvin ruskega Oktobra. Jugoslovanska državna in partijska ideologija se namreč oktobrski revoluciji nista odrekli. Ta je ostajala eden od fundamentov sistema. </p>
                <p>Do večjih sprememb v odnosu do ruskega Oktobra tako na globalni kot na slovenski ravni je prišlo konec osemdesetih let, ko se je zamajala bipolarna ureditev sveta. </p>
                <p>Njegova izzivalna moč je nato začela zginevati. Ruski oktober danes tako deluje "včerajšnje", kot daven dogodek, čigar posledice so se že razblinile. Kakor da so se velike možnosti, ki jih je po mnenju številnih opazovalcev odprla revolucija, z letom 1990 dokončno izčrpale. </p>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
