<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Unwanted Heritage? Historiographic Discourse about (Second)
                    Yugoslavia</title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename>Jurij</forename>
                        <surname>Hadalin</surname>
                        <roleName>dr.</roleName>
                        <roleName>znanstveni sodelavec</roleName>
                        <affiliation>Inštitut za novejšo zgodovino</affiliation>
                        <address>
                            <addrLine> Kongresni trg 1</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>SI-1000 Ljubljana</addrLine>
                        </address>
                        <email>jurij.hadalin@inz.si</email>
                    </name>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>2016-09-27</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>
                    <orgName xml:lang="sl">Inštitut za novejšo zgodovino</orgName>
                    <orgName xml:lang="en">Institute of Contemporary History</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Kongresni trg 1</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>SI-1000 Ljubljana</addrLine>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>http://ojs.inz.si/pnz/article/view/177</pubPlace>
                <date>2016</date>
                <availability status="free">
                    <licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title xml:lang="sl">Prispevki za novejšo zgodovino</title>
                <title xml:lang="en">Contributions to Contemporary History</title>
                <biblScope unit="volume">56</biblScope>
                <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
                <idno type="ISSN">2463-7807</idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source, born digital.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc xml:lang="en">
                <p>Contributions to Contemporary History is one of the central Slovenian scientific
                    historiographic journals, dedicated to publishing articles from the field of
                    contemporary history (the 19th and 20th century).</p>
                <p>The journal is published three times per year in Slovenian and in the following
                    foreign languages: English, German, Serbian, Croatian, Bosnian, Italian, Slovak
                    and Czech. The articles are all published with abstracts in English and
                    Slovenian as well as summaries in English.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <projectDesc xml:lang="sl">
                <p>Prispevki za novejšo zgodovino je ena osrednjih slovenskih znanstvenih
                    zgodovinopisnih revij, ki objavlja teme s področja novejše zgodovine (19. in 20.
                    stoletje).</p>
                <p>Revija izide trikrat letno v slovenskem jeziku in v naslednjih tujih jezikih:
                    angleščina, nemščina, srbščina, hrvaščina, bosanščina, italijanščina, slovaščina
                    in češčina. Članki izhajajo z izvlečki v angleščini in slovenščini ter povzetki
                    v angleščini.</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="sl"/>
                <language ident="en"/>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords xml:lang="en">
                    <term>Yugoslavia</term>
                    <term>history</term>
                    <term>historiography</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords xml:lang="sl">
                    <term>Jugoslavija</term>
                    <term>zgodovina</term>
                    <term>zgodovinopisje</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change>
                    <date>2016-10-06</date>
                    <name>Neja Blaj Hribar</name>
                    <desc>Pretvorba iz DOCX v TEI, dodatno kodiranje</desc>
                </change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <docAuthor>Jurij Hadalin <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn1" n="*"><hi rend="bold">dr.,
                        znanstveni sodelavec, Inštitut za novejšo zgodovino, Kongresni trg 1,
                        SI-1000 Ljubljana, <ref target="mailto:jurij.hadalin@inz.si"
                            >jurij.hadalin@inz.si</ref></hi></note></docAuthor>
            <docImprint>
                <idno type="cobissType">Cobiss tip: 1.01</idno>
                <idno type="UDC">UDK: </idno>
                <date>Prejeto 27. 9. 2016</date>
            </docImprint>
            <div type="abstract" xml:lang="sl">
                <head type="main">IZVLEČEK</head>
                <head>NEZAŽELENA DEDIŠČINA? HISTORIOGRAFSKI DISKURZ O (DRUGI) JUGOSLAVIJI</head>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Avtor poskuša v kratkem pregledu predstaviti dojemanje druge
                        jugoslovanske države v slovenskem zgodovinopisju in družbi, saj ostaja
                        jugoslovanska zgodovina v Sloveniji predvsem politična in ne toliko
                        strokovna tema. Vprašanje, kdaj se bo uspela odlepiti od tega, ostaja
                        neodgovorjeno, kljub temu pa ocenjuje, da je potrebno na procese, ki so v
                        preteklosti bili obravnavani izven širšega konteksta, včasih pogledati tudi
                        z nekoliko drugačne perspektive.</hi></p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Ključne besede: Jugoslavija, zgodovina, zgodovinopisje</hi></p>
            </div>
            <div type="abstract">
                <head>ABSTRACT</head>
                <p><hi rend="italic">In a short overview the author attempts to present the attitude
                        towards the second Yugoslav state in the Slovenian historiography and
                        society, as in Slovenia the Yugoslav history remains above all a political
                        rather than expert topic. The question when this flaw will be overcome
                        remains unanswered. Nevertheless, the author estimates that the processes,
                        seen outside of the broader context in the past, should sometimes be viewed
                        from a somewhat different perspective.</hi></p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Keywords: Yugoslavia, history, historiography</hi></p>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <p>In this article I shall discuss a historical phenomenon called Yugoslavia. It is a
                country that no longer exists, and allegedly we are all well-aware of this. However,
                one could ask a direct witness about it: the singer-songwriter Andrej Šifrer, who
                used to sing at the time of its demise: “Kdo bo za pijačo dal, ko umrla bo država?
                [Who will buy drinks when the state is dead?]”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn2" n="1"
                    > Andrej Šifrer, “Država,” on: <hi rend="italic">Hiti počasi</hi> (Ljubljana:
                    ZKP RTVLJ, 1990). The song was a big hit in the period before the Slovenian
                    independence. More about the circumstances surrounding the creation of this
                    song: “Hiti počasi,”
                    <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Hiti počasi ‒ Wikipedija, prosta enciklopedija, </hi>accesed
                    20 June 2016, <ref target="https://sl.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hiti_po%C4%8Dasi"
                        >https://sl.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hiti_po%C4%8Dasi</ref>. </note></p>
            <p>After all, that is why we are celebrating the 25<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>
                anniversary of the independent Slovenian state this year. Nevertheless, Yugoslavia
                still lives its virtual life, perhaps mostly because it does not actually exist in
                the political geography; it does not have only a single successor or pretender to
                its universal heritage; nor does it have a “nation” (neither tripartite, nor from
                the ranks of the nations and nationalities); although fifteen years ago almost
                328,000 Yugoslavs were counted in the United States.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn3"
                    n="2"> In the population census of 2000, 328,547 people declared the Yugoslav,
                    374,241 Croatian, 140,337 Serbian and 176,691 Slovenian ancestry. See: “United
                    States Census Bureau, American Fact Finder, Ancestry (Total Categories Tallied)
                    for People with One or More Ancestry Categories Reported,”
                    <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">American FactFinder – Results, </hi>accesed
                    20 June 2016, <ref
                        target="http://factfinder.census.gov/faces/tableservices/jsf/pages/productview.xhtml?pid=DEC_00_SF3_PCT018&amp;prodType=table"
                        >http://factfinder.census.gov/faces/tableservices/jsf/pages/productview.xhtml?pid=DEC_00_SF3_PCT018&amp;prodType=table</ref>.</note>
                On the basis of the same source (a lecture by Tomasz Kamusella at the Faculty of
                Arts in Ljubljana<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn4" n="3"> Tomasz Kamusella, <hi
                        rend="italic">The Forgotten 1989 Ethnic Cleansing of Bulgaria’s Turks. A
                        Yugoslav Connection?</hi> (lecture) (Ljubljana: Faculty of Arts and
                    Institute of Contemporary History, 7 June 2016). </note>) we can add that even
                its unique language has been preserved in the virtual world, as the largest
                Wikipedia from our territories has been written in what is today the non-existent
                Serbo-Croatian language.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn5" n="4"> The Serbo-Croatian
                    version includes 433,561 articles, Serbian 336,321 articles, Croatian 166,093
                    articles and Slovenian 151,768 articles. See:
                    <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">List of Wikipedias – Meta, </hi>accesed
                    20 June 2016, <ref target="All_Wikipedias_ordered_by_number_of_articles"
                        >https://meta.wikimedia.org/wiki/List_of_Wikipedias#All_Wikipedias_ordered_by_number_of_articles</ref>.
                </note> At this point let me also mention the Yugoslav leader Josip Broz Tito, who
                is often – in the general as well as professional public – presented as synonymous
                with the word Yugoslavia. Even he “has lived his virtual life” since as early as
                1997, when he started disturbing the public from the servers of the Jožef Stefan
                    Institute.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn6" n="5">
                    <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Tito's Home Page, </hi><ref
                        target="http://www.titoville.com">www.titoville.com</ref><hi
                        rend="Hyperlink">. Website currently unavailable.</hi>
                </note> Thus he lives regardless of reality and not always merely due to the concept
                of “Yugo-nostalgia”, which has in the recent years acquired an increasingly
                pejorative connotation, especially in the segment of the society which sees the
                second Yugoslav state especially on the basis of the traumatic events at the time of
                its establishment. However, perhaps these people can seek solace in the fact that
                “Yugo-nostalgia” is a typical example of retroutopia,<note place="foot"
                    xml:id="ftn7" n="6"> Jela Krečič,
                    <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Miglena Nikolčina: Treba je tvegati in si zamisliti utopijo </hi>[We
                    Have to Take a Risk and Imagine an Utopia]. Accesed 1 September 2016, <ref
                        target="http://m.delo.si/sobotna/miglena-nikolcina-treba-je-tvegati-in-si-zamisliti-utopijo.html"
                        >http://m.delo.si/sobotna/miglena-nikolcina-treba-je-tvegati-in-si-zamisliti-utopijo.html</ref>.
                </note> i.e. nostalgia for something that has in fact never existed, at least not in
                the idolised form that might be painted today. We could also use the term
                retronostalgia; however, that is something completely different, as the Radio
                Student show with the same title underlines with its slogan: “We record, describe
                and deconstruct selected objects from our consumer past. Unfortunately, however, we
                cannot deny them.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn8" n="7">
                    <hi rend="italic">Retrostalgija</hi>
                    [Retronostalgia]<hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve"> | Radio Študent</hi>,
                        <ref target="http://radiostudent.si/dru%C5%BEba/retrostalgija"
                        >http://radiostudent.si/dru%C5%BEba/retrostalgija</ref>. </note>
            </p>
            <p>Many people associate this nostalgia merely with the political system, and we have to
                acknowledge, from what is today already a sufficient temporal distance, that it was
                unique and utopic in its complexity. However, also in terms of geography and culture
                we have been determined by Yugoslavia to the degree where we cannot simply overlook
                it on the occasion of the 25<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> anniversary of the
                independent Slovenian state. Dejan Novačić is the curator of this non-existent
                state: he described the Socialist Federal Republic of Yugoslavia in his well-known
                work SFRJ za ponavljače (SFRY for Repeaters, in the Slovenian translation SFRJ –
                moja dežela, or SFRY – My Country)<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn9" n="8"> Dejan
                    Novačić,
                    <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">SFRJ za ponavljače. Turistički vodič </hi>[SFRY
                    for Repeaters. A Tourist Guide] (Beograd: Moć knjige, 2003).</note>, while he
                developed the Yugoslav mental heritage in the book Emigrantska kuharica<note
                    place="foot" xml:id="ftn10" n="9"> Dejan Novačić,
                    <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Emigrantski kuvar. Sve što ste oduvek hteli da znate o jugoslovenskoj kuhinji, ali nemate više koga da pitate </hi>[Emigrant
                    Cookbook. What You’ve Always Wanted to Know About the Yugoslav Kitchen, But
                    There’s No One Left to Ask] (Novi Sad: Stylos Art, 2009).</note> (Emigrant
                Cookbook, which explains how the aforementioned 328,000 Yugoslavs have been
                preserving their culture). In the introduction to the aforementioned “lexicographic
                study” Miha Avanzo asks himself: “Where do dead countries end up?”<note place="foot"
                    xml:id="ftn11" n="10"> Miha Avanzo, “Kje končajo mrtve države?,” [Where do Dead
                    Countries End Up] in: Dejan Novačić, <hi rend="italic">SFRJ – moja dežela.
                        Turistični vodnik</hi> (Ljubljana: Orbis, 2003), 4.</note> The answer is
                provided by Dubravka Ugrešić, who says: “that Novačić’s book is a humorous
                deconstruction of flowery words, and therefore it has a twofold effect. As we are
                reading it, we can calmly come to terms with our own past and at the same time
                forgive it with relief.” She also adds: “The value of this book lies in the fact
                that it is one of the first works to open the space for the revaluation of the past,
                and not the official past – that is up to historians – but the past of our own
                    lives.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn12" n="11"> Dubrovka Ugrešić, “Leksikon
                    izmišljene dežele,” [Lexicon of an Imaginary Country] in: Dejan Novaćić, <hi
                        rend="italic">SFRJ – moja dežela. Turistični vodič</hi> (Ljubljana: Orbis,
                    2003), 5‒6.</note> And at this point I can think of two things: </p>
            <list type="ordered">
                <item>In the last 25 years, in Slovenia the orphan Yugoslavia has lived in a
                    tumultuous atmosphere, as our former/current actors have been unable to carry
                    out this revaluation in a relaxed-enough spirit. Let me just refer to the recent
                    interview with Stane Granda. “The journalist asked him how it is possible that
                    the youth today – those who were born after the disintegration of Yugoslavia –
                    talk about the fallen state with such a positive attitude. Granda answered that
                    one of the reasons was the false upbringing that perpetuated a myriad of lies
                    and half-truths. One of such lies is that once upon a time everybody had jobs.
                    ‘Of course we all had jobs, but people often had nothing to do there,’ Granda
                    refuted one of the most frequent blunders. He also reminded everyone to the
                    hilarious processes involved in buying cars and a seriously limited freedom of
                    speech. ‘These rights, whose acquisition represents a significant turning
                    point... They do not mean anything to them, as they were born to this, this is
                    their life. When they hear that jobs and apartments existed, it is naturally
                    that they complain – even though I, for one, have never received an apartment,
                    and I nevertheless had to contribute money to the housing fund.’ The historian
                    claims that many lies remain, in judiciary as well as in the education system.
                    In schools the lies are reflected in the selected topics. Granda illustrated
                    this with the lessons in history, where the pupils learn when people in Slovenia
                    started wearing jeans, but they do not find out that jeans had to be smuggled
                    from abroad. ‘The former system was based on lies, and many of these lies remain
                    present in the society,’ he stated and added that the various Yugo-nostalgic
                    celebrations in the primary and secondary schools are also the result of the
                    advanced age of the teachers, who are therefore perhaps also slightly
                        demented.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn13" n="12"> Stane Granda,
                        “Zaklinjanje Titu je znak razpadanja uma in demence,” [Swearing by Tito is a
                        Sign of Disintegrating Minds and Dementia] <hi rend="italic">Nova24tv</hi>,
                        accesed <hi rend="Hyperlink" xml:space="preserve">20 June 2016, </hi><ref
                            target="http://nova24tv.si/slovenija/ljudje/stane-granda-zaklinjanje-titu-je-znak-razpadanja-uma-in-demence/"
                            >http://nova24tv.si/slovenija/ljudje/stane-granda-zaklinjanje-titu-je-znak-razpadanja-uma-in-demence/</ref><hi
                            rend="Hyperlink">.</hi></note></item>
                <item>Yugoslavia no longer exists and it should be the subject of historians. That
                    is what my colleague Zdenko Čepič<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn14" n="13"> E.g.
                        Zdenko Čepič, “Misli in dejstva: izhodišča,” [Thoughts and Facts: Starting
                        Points] in: <hi rend="italic">Slovenija v Jugoslaviji,</hi> ed. Zdenko Čepič
                        (Ljubljana: Inštitut za novejšo zgodovino, 2015), 5‒19.</note> has
                    frequently said in the recent years, and it is time that we actually get on with
                    it – soberly and using the standard historiographic methodology. However, we
                    have more or less intensively been doing this also in the last 25 years. And
                    that, actually, is what I wanted to discuss.</item>
            </list>
            <p>In the time of the Second Yugoslavia and its permanent reforms not very many truly
                Yugoslav/common things were created, despite significant efforts. If we can describe
                the Yugoslav social reality with precisely three truly common denominators – Tito,
                Yugoslav People’s Army and the blue team – than it is clear that Yugoslav
                historiography in the classic sense of the word did not exist. Large-scale common
                project did exist – from the History of the Communist Party of Yugoslavia/League of
                Communists of Yugoslavia to the Encyclopaedia of Yugoslavia – but we can
                nevertheless not talk about a common “Yugoslav historiography”.<note place="foot"
                    xml:id="ftn15" n="14"> Mateja Režek, “Usmerjena preteklost. Mehanizmi ideološke
                    in politične 'kontaminacije' zgodovinopisja v socialistični Sloveniji in
                    Jugoslaviji,” [Directed Past: Mechanisms of Ideological and Political
                    'Contamination' of Historiography in the Socialist Slovenia and Yugoslavia], <hi
                        rend="italic">Acta Histriae</hi> 22, No. 4 (2014): 971‒92 and 977.</note>
                Extensive joint projects, where their contributors “nearly perished due to excessive
                workload” (I am quoting Zdenko Čepič, who would often tell an anecdote about a
                leader of one of the projects, Dušan Bilandžić), remained unrealised, “while the
                exploration of the Yugoslav nations” past started moving more and more often into
                the realm of journalism, artistic works and especially ‘pure politics”,<note
                    place="foot" xml:id="ftn16" n="15"> Božo Repe, “Zgodovina, zgodovinopisje in
                    etika,” [History, Historiography and Ethics] in:
                    <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Etika v slovenskem jeziku, literaturi in kulturi. Zbornik predavanj / 49. seminar slovenskega jezika, literature in kulture, [Ljubljana], 1 – 12 July 2013, </hi>ed.
                    Aleksander Bjelčević (Ljubljana: Znanstvena založba Filozofske fakultete,
                    Ljubljana: 2013), 82‒83.</note> as Božo Repe wrote. Sadly, most often that was
                where it remained. For the purposes of this contribution I have reviewed quite a
                collection of scientific publications, and under keyword “Yugoslavia” I have found
                quite a few peculiar ways in which this concept was used (sort of in the style of
                the permanent exhibition of the military museum at Kalamegdan, where the
                presentation of the Yugoslav military history started somewhere in the Iron Age). I
                have nevertheless found that in the middle of the 1980s a few reviews were written
                that may have partly opposed each other in their interpretations, but they still
                represent the basis for serious studies of the Yugoslav history (History of SFRY by
                    Bilandžić,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn17" n="16"> The book was first published
                    in 1979, in the Slovenian language in 1980, but here I am referring to the
                    third, extended edition from the middle of the 1980s. – Dušan Bilandžić, <hi
                        rend="italic">Historija Socijalističke Federativne Republike Jugoslavije.
                        Glavni procesi</hi> [History of the Socialist Federal Republic of
                    Yugoslavia. The Main Processes: 1918‒1985] (Zagreb: Školska knjiga,
                    1985).</note> Yugoslavia 1918‒1984 by Petranović‒Zečević,<note place="foot"
                    xml:id="ftn18" n="17"> The publication was then re-published and extended to
                    include the period until 1988, and the authors continued writing about this
                    topic in the 1990s. – Branko Petranović and Momčilo Zečević,
                    <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Jugoslavija 1918‒1984 </hi>[Yugoslavia
                    1918‒1984] (Beograd: Rad, 1985).</note> and Nations, Yugoslavia, Revolution by
                Janko Pleterski<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn19" n="18"> Janko Pleterski, <hi
                        rend="italic">Nacije, Jugoslavija, revolucija</hi> [Nations, Yugoslavia,
                    Revolution] (Beograd: Komunist, 1985). Slovenian edition Janko Pleterski, <hi
                        rend="italic">Narodi, Jugoslavija, revolucija</hi> (Ljubljana: Komunist and
                    Državna založba, 1986).</note>). Despite the differences, the common
                historiographic space did exist. In the Contributions to Contemporary History
                (Prispevki za novejšo zgodovino) scientific journal we can thus follow reviews of
                works from the territory of the former state until around the end of 1992 (due to
                the relatively long delay in publication). In the same year three works focusing on
                the Slovenian history also in the Yugoslav context were published (Assumption of
                Power by Jera Vodušek Starič,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn20" n="19"> Jerca Vodušek
                    Starič,
                    <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Prevzem oblasti 1944‒1946 </hi>[Assumption
                    of Power 1944‒1946] (Ljubljana: Cankarjeva založba, 1992).</note> Slovenian
                Industry in the Clutches of Yugoslavia by Jože Prinčič,<note place="foot"
                    xml:id="ftn21" n="20"> Jože Prinčič, <hi rend="italic">Slovenska industrija v
                        jugoslovanskem primežu</hi> [Slovenian Industry in the Clutches of
                    Yugoslavia] (Novo mesto: Dolenjska založba, 1992).</note> and Liberalism by Božo
                    Repe<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn22" n="21"> Božo Repe,
                    <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">“Liberalizem” v Sloveniji </hi>[“Liberalism”
                    in Slovenia] (Ljubljana: RO ZZB NOV Slovenije, 1992).</note>). These were
                followed by quite a lengthy silence and we could say that the “republican
                historiography” with the purpose of strengthening the new state reality once again
                came to the forefront. However, the study programmes at the Department of History at
                the Faculty of Arts in Ljubljana managed to avoid this focus somehow. There we, the
                students, were still able to listen to lectures on the former common space, albeit
                under somewhat altered titles: for example, in 1991 the term “History of Yugoslav
                nations” was replaced by the collocation “History of South-East Europe”.<note
                    place="foot" xml:id="ftn23" n="22"> Janez Mlinar, <hi rend="italic">Oddelek za
                        zgodovino</hi>. <hi rend="italic">Zgodovina oddelka</hi> [Departmen of
                    History. History of the Department], accesed 1 September 2016, <ref
                        target="http://www.zgodovina-ff-uni-lj.net/index.php?option=com_content&amp;task=view&amp;id=20&amp;Itemid=42"
                        >http://www.zgodovina-ff-uni-lj.net/index.php?option=com_content&amp;task=view&amp;id=20&amp;Itemid=42</ref>.</note></p>
            <p>In the time of its dissolution and throughout of the 1990s Yugoslavia was at the
                centre of the international attention, especially due to the Yugoslav Wars. At this
                moment a turning point took place in Slovenia, and after the significant growth in
                the 1980s the Slovenian-centric historiography was in full swing. After all, the
                flood of exclusively foreign works about Yugoslavia and its neuralgic former
                component parts led to the fact that my colleague and I, when we researched this
                issue years ago, would refer to the works of foreign (English-speaking) and Serbian
                authors much more often than the few Slovenian and Croatian authors. The publication
                of Pirjevec’s Yugoslavia in 1995, more than half of which is dedicated to the Second
                Yugoslavia, was an important reference point.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn24"
                    n="23"> Jože Prijevec,
                    <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Jugoslavija 1918‒1992. Nastanek, razvoj ter razpad Karadjordjevićeve in Titove Jugoslavije </hi>[Yugoslavia
                    1918‒1992. Origin, Development and Disintegration of Karađorđević’s and Tito's
                    Yugoslavia] (Koper: Lipa, 1995).</note> However, even this book was initially
                written for the Italian market, and only afterwards it was successfully published
                and well-received in Slovenia as well. Afterwards Jože Pirjevec wrote further works
                about the Yugoslav Wars and later also Tito. These were released in ideal publishing
                circumstances, but they did not transcend the importance of his book Yugoslavia,
                which therefore remains unsurpassed as the only synthetic work of this kind by a
                Slovenian author. In the words of Branko Goropevšek, “It is currently one of the few
                works written in the language of a small nation living under the Alps, whose
                contents do not stir up emotions in its readers and it is also not subject to
                sensationalism, which can often be claimed of similar political thrillers of this
                    sort.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn25" n="24"> Branko Goropevšek, “Kot
                    steklenica piva na smetišču,” [Like a Beer Bottle in the Dump] <hi rend="italic"
                        >Zgodovina za vse</hi> 3, No. 1 (1996): 87‒88.</note> Such thrillers are
                still in ample supply today. However, as I browse through the works of Slovenian
                historians I can establish that in Slovenia the new era of interest in the Yugoslav
                history in its broader context started after 2000 and after the change of the regime
                in the contemporaneous Federal Republic of Yugoslavia or Serbia. Slovenian
                historians finally regained access to archive sources, and in the interim a sort of
                a competitive spirit was formed, as in Serbia the Yugoslav history had been
                intensively dealt with, focused on in temporal and substantive stages, and often
                interpreted in a way which did not necessarily correspond to the Slovenian outlook
                on this period.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn26" n="25"> Here we should mention an
                    interesting fact that in the last 25 years the First Yugoslavia has acquired a
                    markedly better reputation in the Slovenian historiography. This does not only
                    mean a more lenient view of its political regime, which simply was not seen
                    positively in the second Yugoslav state, but also the outlook on the position of
                    Slovenians in this state. This, for example, is not comparable with the other
                    former Yugoslav historiographies, where the image of the First Yugoslavia has
                    remained more similar to the former views. This is especially true of Serbia. I
                    would like to thank Peter Vodopivec for this note. </note> Since my active
                engagement in research, the Second Yugoslavia has become increasingly important.
                Symposiums were organised on occasions of major anniversaries of the Yugoslav state;
                a research project dedicated to this very issue took place at the Institute of
                Contemporary History (Položaj in vloga Slovenije v jugoslovanski državi po drugi
                svetovni vojni 1945‒1991 – Position and Role of Slovenia in the Yugoslav State after
                World War II 1945‒1991); several collections of scientific texts have been
                published; individual researchers have placed their works into a broader context;
                and the exchange of visits and confrontation of opinions with the researchers from
                other former Yugoslav territories has gradually become a constant. </p>
            <p>The second issue involves the evaluation of the Yugoslav experience and is discussed
                in the third part of this contribution. Many people have focused on Yugoslavia in
                various contexts and times. Their evaluations differed and were sometimes even
                conflicting, so that the readers sometimes even felt that these assessments were
                made under the influence of the constant requirements of daily politics, as the
                events from the times of Yugoslavia and its disintegration are still present not
                only in the parliamentary discussions, but also in the main TV news programmes and
                lately even in the crime sections in the press. Perhaps this indicates that we, as a
                society, have still not got over the dissolution of the “marriage”. Many authors
                were also quite unoriginal. For example, if we look at one of the formulations from
                the conclusion in Silvo Kranjec’s book Kako smo se zedinili (How We Have United) of
                1928, we can soon establish that a formula exists for a successful ending of every
                text about the Slovenian national decisions: “Thus our unification was acknowledged
                and confirmed in the international agreements, where we Slovenians were mentioned
                for the first time. After long centuries of foreign yoke we have joined the family
                of free nations as an equal member... /...This very formation of our current state
                teaches us that it is impossible to vanquish an educated and honest nation and <hi
                    rend="underline">that no man can permanently separate what God has joined
                    together</hi>.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn27" n="26"> Silvo Kranjec, <hi
                        rend="italic">Kako smo se zedinili</hi> [How We Have United] (Celje: Družba
                    sv. Mohorja, 1928), 142.</note> (underlined by J. H.) From a myriad of opinions
                I have extracted the records of three Slovenian historians who wrote about this
                topic constantly and through a lengthy time period: Janko Pleterski, Božo Repe and
                Dušan Nećak. </p>
            <p>The following quote from Dušan Nećak’s article 70 let Jugoslavije – obletnice in
                prelomnice (70 Years of Yugoslavia – Anniversaries and Turning Points) of 1989,
                written on a similar occasion as we are celebrating today, shows how thoughts depend
                on the circumstances and how much easier it is to observe the historical
                circumstances from an all-knowing position thirty years later.<note place="foot"
                    xml:id="ftn28" n="27"> The seventy-year anniversary of the establishment of the
                    first Yugoslav state.</note> “In 1988 the ‘point zero!’ of the general Yugoslav
                development was reached. Only through domination of rationality over emotions and, I
                hope, because of the realisations stemming from historical experience – that only a
                democratic Yugoslavia is a homeland of all nations and nationalities under the
                condition that everyone in it feels nationally and socially safe and equal and that
                it is strong only in so far as its constituent parts are strong – an explosion has,
                for now, not taken place. If we can keep learning from historical experience, it
                shall also never happen”.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn29" n="28"> Dušan Nećak, “70
                    let Jugoslavije ‒ obletnice in prelomnice,” [70 Years of Yugoslavia –
                    Anniversaries and Turning Points] <hi rend="italic">Časopis za zgodovino in
                        narodopisje</hi> 60, No. 1 (1989), 31‒32.</note> The same author appeared at
                a very interesting colloquium entitled Jugoslavija – zgodovinska nuja ali zmota
                (Yugoslavia – a Historical Necessity or Mistake), which indicates that the question
                of evaluating the Slovenian experience in the former state despite the professed
                historiographical love or the need for temporal distance was an important social
                issue. Here, well over five years later, Nećak said: “From all of the above it is
                nevertheless clear that Yugoslavia was a historical necessity also for the Slovenian
                nation. It was an unavoidable historical transference in which the Slovenian nation
                had matured to the degree where it was able to undertake the formation of its own
                sovereign state. With its own nation Slovenians received an opportunity to decide
                independently about its own destiny and future. We must also assume the
                responsibility for every decision about the potential new, old, or ancient
                    integrations.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn30" n="29"> Dušan Nećak,
                    “Jugoslavija, historična nujnost ali napaka?,” [Yugoslavia, a Historical
                    Exigency or a Mistake?] <hi rend="italic">Časopis za zgodovino in
                        narodopisje</hi> 65, No. 1 (1994): 70‒71.</note> The very title of the
                symposium attests to the spirit of the times. Božo Repe stated: “We historians
                focused on Yugoslavia from the viewpoint of a done fact. It is simply our job. We
                were looking for traces of logical developments from the Yugoslav idea until the
                creation and functioning of the state.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn31" n="30">
                    Božo Repe<hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">, </hi>“Jugoslavija –
                    zgodovinska nuja ali zgodovinska zmota,” [Yugoslavia: A Historical Necessity or
                    a Historical Mistake?] <hi rend="italic">Časopis za zgodovino in
                        narodopisje</hi> 65, No. 1 (1994): 73.</note> Quite a few years later he
                went on to add: “The today’s Slovenian outlook on Yugoslavia, especially the
                political outlook – and this is partly true also of historians – stems from the
                theory that Yugoslavism was a kind of a provisional solution, something that helped
                Slovenians overcome the difficult times until they were able to return where they
                belonged: to the so-called ‘Europe’.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn32" n="31"> Božo
                    Repe, “Zakaj so Slovenci vstopili v Jugoslavijo in zakaj so iz nje odšli?,” [Why
                    Slovenians Entered Yugoslavia and Why They Left It], in:
                    <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Jugoslavija v času. Devetdeset let od nastanka prve jugoslovanske države, </hi>[Yugoslavia
                    in Time. Ninety Years from the Formation of First Yugoslav State] ed. Bojan
                    Balkovec (Ljubljana: Oddelek za zgodovino Filozofske fakultete, 2009),
                    23.</note> From the today’s distance, when we have been dwelling in the
                so-called Europe for quite a while and when this historical goal has been achieved,
                this issue is not at the forefront anymore. Especially if we think of what is today
                a very popular (and populist) comparison between the mastodonically bureaucratic but
                politically weak European Union, whose members include states on very different
                levels of development, and Yugoslavia. At this point we can refer to the well-known
                thought of the last Yugoslav President of the Government (or President of the
                Federal Executive Council) Ante Marković, who saw Yugoslavia as a convoy of ships in
                which the last ship, i.e. Kosovo, was seven times slower than the rest. Thus Božo
                Repe removes Europe from the forefront in a university textbook: “Circumstances have
                forced Slovenia to leave Yugoslavia: the increasing gap between Yugoslavia and the
                developed countries, but primarily the inability of Yugoslavia to democratise and
                modernise itself as well as ensure the national rights to its nations. It was this
                combination of liberal ideas and national feelings that created enough mass energy
                in Slovenia to allow for the envisioned goals to be carried out.”<note place="foot"
                    xml:id="ftn33" n="32"> Božo Repe, <hi rend="italic">Jugoslovanstvo kot ideja in
                        kot praksa</hi> [Yugoslavism as Idea and Practice] (Ljubljana: Filozofska
                    Fakulteta‒Oddelek za zgodovino, 2016), 148, accesed 1 September 2016, <ref
                        target="http://www.zgodovina-ff-uni-lj.net/index.php?option=com_remository&amp;Itemid=26&amp;func=startdown&amp;id=67"
                        >http://www.zgodovina-ff-uni-lj.net/index.php?option=com_remository&amp;Itemid=26&amp;func=startdown&amp;id=67</ref>.</note>
                Naturally, he also adds the international context that made this possible. To the
                following empty phrase – the so-called thousand-year dream – we should also add the
                following finding from the aforementioned textbook: “Despite its constant
                dissatisfaction Slovenia believed in the Yugoslav state. It invested extraordinary
                amounts of energy in its existence and its system, and the Slovenian political and
                economic elites had significant influence in the state leadership already in the
                First, but even more so in the Second Yugoslavia. Therefore nobody thought of
                seeking any solutions outside of Yugoslavia until the very end of the 1980s.” When I
                said something similar in a radio broadcast on the occasion of the referendum about
                the independence of Slovenia, the journalist just gaped at me in wonder.<note
                    place="foot" xml:id="ftn34" n="33"> Filip Čuček, Jurij Hadalin, Jure Gašparič
                    and Ivan Merljak, “Strta pričakovanja (Sledi časa),” [Broken Expectations
                    (Traces of Time)] <hi rend="italic">Radio Slovenija, programme I</hi> (23
                    December 2012), accesed 1 September 2016, <ref
                        target="http://tvslo.si/predvajaj/strta-pricakovanja/ava2.153826307/"
                        >http://tvslo.si/predvajaj/strta-pricakovanja/ava2.153826307/</ref>.</note></p>
            <p>However, the point of this contribution lies elsewhere: not so much in the
                interpretations, but rather in the context in which this chapter of the Slovenian
                history should be explored. Already Janko Pleterski discussed this at the Maribor
                symposium, where he talked about the plundering of history<note place="foot"
                    xml:id="ftn35" n="34"> The plundering of history has been characteristic of the
                    former Eastern Bloc countries. I see it as reaching into a cookie jar and taking
                    only what you find useful, while leaving and discarding the rest. </note>: “Only
                a comprehensive, unplundered history can be the proverbial bough on which one can
                sit. No matter whether the tree from which this bough grows was once called the
                Habsburg Empire, yesterday Yugoslavia, or today simply Europe.”<note place="foot"
                    xml:id="ftn36" n="35"> Janko Pleterski, “Jugoslavija v slovenski zgodovini,”
                    [Yugoslavia in the Slovenian History] <hi rend="italic">Časopis za zgodovino in
                        narodopisje</hi> 65, No. 1 (1994): 45.</note></p>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="bibliography">
            <head>Sources and Literature</head>
                <listBibl>
            <head>Literature:</head>
              <bibl> “Hiti počasi.” <hi rend="italic">Hiti počasi ‒ Wikipedija, prosta
                        enciklopedija</hi>. Accesed 20 June 2016. <ref
                        target="https://sl.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hiti_po%C4%8Dasi"
                        >https://sl.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hiti_po%C4%8Dasi</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl>Avanzo, Miha. “Kje končajo mrtve države?.” [Where Do Dead Countries End Up]
                    In: Dejan Novačić, <hi rend="italic">SFRJ – moja dežela: turistični vodnik</hi>,
                    4. Ljubljana: Orbis, 2003.</bibl>
                <bibl>Bilandžić, Dušan. <hi rend="italic">Historija Socijalističke Federativne
                        Republike Jugoslavije. Glavni procesi: 1918‒1985</hi> [History of the
                    Socialist Federal Republic of Yugoslavia: the Main Processes: 1918‒1985].
                    Zagreb: Školska knjiga, 1985.</bibl>
                <bibl>Čepič, Zdenko. “Misli in dejstva. Izhodišča.” [Thoughts and Facts: Starting
                    Points] In: <hi rend="italic">Slovenija v Jugoslaviji,</hi> ed. Zdenko Čepič,
                    5‒19. Ljubljana: Inštitut za novejšo zgodovino, 2015.</bibl>
                <bibl>Čuček, Filip, Jurij Hadalin, Jure Gašparič and Ivan Merljak. “Strta
                    pričakovanja (Sledi časa).” [Broken Expectations (Traces of Time)] <hi
                        rend="italic">Radio Slovenija, programme I</hi> (23 December 2012). Accesed
                    1 September 2016. <ref
                        target="http://tvslo.si/predvajaj/strta-pricakovanja/ava2.153826307/"
                        >http://tvslo.si/predvajaj/strta-pricakovanja/ava2.153826307/</ref>. </bibl>
                <bibl>Goropevšek, Branko. “Kot steklenica piva na smetišču.” [Like a Beer Bottle in
                    the Dump] <hi rend="italic">Zgodovina za vse</hi> 3, No. 1 (1996): 85‒88.</bibl>
                <bibl>Granda, Stane. “Zaklinjanje Titu je znak razpadanja uma in demence.” [Swearing
                    by Tito is a Sign of Disintegrating Minds and Dementia] <hi rend="italic"
                        >Nova24tv</hi>. Accesed 20 June 2016. <ref
                        target="http://nova24tv.si/slovenija/ljudje/stane-granda-zaklinjanje-titu-je-znak-razpadanja-uma-in-demence/"
                        >http://nova24tv.si/slovenija/ljudje/stane-granda-zaklinjanje-titu-je-znak-razpadanja-uma-in-demence/</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl>Kamusella, Tomasz. <hi rend="italic">The Forgotten 1989 Ethnic Cleansing of
                        Bulgaria’s Turks. A Yugoslav Connection?</hi> (lecture). Ljubljana: Faculty
                    of Arts and Institute of Contemporary History, 7 June 2016. </bibl>
                <bibl>Kranjec, Silvo. <hi rend="italic">Kako smo se zedinili. [How We Have
                        United]</hi> Celje: Družba sv. Mohorja, 1928.</bibl>
                <bibl>Krečič, Jela. <hi rend="italic">Miglena Nikolčina: Treba je tvegati in si
                        zamisliti utopijo</hi> [We Have to Take a Risk and Imagine an Utopia]<hi
                        rend="italic">.</hi> Accesed 1 September 2016. <ref
                        target="http://m.delo.si/sobotna/miglena-nikolcina-treba-je-tvegati-in-si-zamisliti-utopijo.html"
                        >http://m.delo.si/sobotna/miglena-nikolcina-treba-je-tvegati-in-si-zamisliti-utopijo.html</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl><hi rend="italic">List of Wikipedias- Meta</hi>. Accesed 20 June 2016<hi
                        rend="italic">.</hi>
                    <ref
                        target="https://meta.wikimedia.org/wiki/List_of_Wikipedias%23All_Wikipedias_ordered_by_number_of_articles"
                        >https://meta.wikimedia.org/wiki/List_of_Wikipedias#All_Wikipedias_ordered_by_number_of_articles</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl>Mlinar, Janez. <hi rend="italic">Oddelek za zgodovino. Zgodovina oddelka.</hi>
                    [Department of History. History of the Department] Accesed 1 September 2016.
                        <ref
                        target="http://www.zgodovina-ff-uni-lj.net/index.php?option=com_content&amp;task=view&amp;id=20&amp;biblid=42"
                        >http://www.zgodovina-ff-uni-lj.net/index.php?option=com_content&amp;task=view&amp;id=20&amp;biblid=42</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl>Nećak, Dušan. “70 let Jugoslavije ‒ obletnice in prelomnice.” [70 Years of
                    Yugoslavia – Anniversaries and Turning Points] <hi rend="italic">Časopis za
                        zgodovino in narodopisje</hi> 60, No. 1 (1989): 15‒32.</bibl>
                <bibl>Nećak, Dušan. “Jugoslavija, historična nujnost ali napaka?.” [Yugoslavia, a
                    Historical Exigency or a Mistake?] <hi rend="italic">Časopis za zgodovino in
                        narodopisje</hi> 65, No. 1 (1994): 67‒71.</bibl>
                <bibl>Novačić, Dejan.
                    <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Emigrantski kuvar. Sve što ste oduvek hteli da znate o jugoslovenskoj kuhinji, ali nemate više koga da pitate </hi>[Emigrant
                    Cookbook. What You’ve Always Wanted to Know About the Yugoslav Kitchen, But
                    There’s No One Left to Ask] Novi Sad: Stylos Art, 2009. </bibl>
                <bibl>Novačić, Dejan. <hi rend="italic">SFRJ – moja dežela. Turistični vodič.</hi>
                    [SFRY – My Country. A Tourist Guide] Ljubljana: Orbis, 2003.</bibl>
                <bibl>Novačić, Dejan.
                    <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">SFRJ za ponavljače. Turistički vodič. </hi>[SFRY
                    for Repeaters. A Tourist Guide] Beograd: Moć knjige, 2003.</bibl>
                <bibl>Petranović, Branko and Momčilo Zečević. <hi rend="italic">Jugoslavija
                        1918‒1984. Zbirka dokumenata.</hi> [Yugoslavia 1918‒1984. Collection of
                    Documents] Beograd: Rad, 1985.</bibl>
                <bibl>Pirjevec, Jože. <hi rend="italic">Jugoslavija 1918‒1992. Nastanek, razvoj ter
                        razpad Karadjordjevićeve in Titove Jugoslavije.</hi> [Yugoslavia 1918‒1992.
                    Origin, Development and Disintegration of Karađorđević’s and Tito's Yugoslavia]
                    Koper: Lipa, 1995.</bibl>
                <bibl>Pleterski, Janko. “Jugoslavija v slovenski zgodovini.” [Yugoslavia in the
                    Slovenian History] <hi rend="italic">Časopis za zgodovino in narodopisje</hi>
                    65, No. 1 (1994): 40‒46.</bibl>
                <bibl>Pleterski, Janko. <hi rend="italic">Nacije, Jugoslavija, revolucija.</hi>
                    [Nations, Yugoslavia, Revolution] Beograd: Komunist, 1985. </bibl>
                <bibl>Pleterski, Janko. <hi rend="italic">Narodi, Jugoslavija, revolucija.</hi>
                    [Nations, Yugoslavia, Revolution] Ljubljana: Komunist and Državna založba
                    Slovenije, 1986. </bibl>
                <bibl>Prinčič, Jože. <hi rend="italic">Slovenska industrija v jugoslovanskem
                        primežu. Kapitalna, ključna kapitalna in temeljna investicijska izgradnja v
                        Sloveniji: 1945‒1956.</hi> [Slovenian Industry in the Clutches of
                    Yugoslavia. Capital, Key Capital and Basic Investment Development in Slovenia:
                    1945‒1956] Novo Mesto: Dolenjska založba, 1992.</bibl>
                <bibl>Repe, Božo. <hi rend="italic">'Liberalizem' v Sloveniji. ['Liberalism' in
                        Slovenia]</hi> Ljubljana: RO ZZB NOV Slovenije, 1992.</bibl>
                <bibl>Repe, Božo. “Jugoslavija — zgodovinska nuja ali zgodovinska zmota.”
                    [Yugoslavia: A Historical Necessity or a Historical Mistake?] <hi rend="italic"
                        >Časopis za zgodovino in narodopisje</hi> 65, No. 1, (1994): 72‒76.</bibl>
                <bibl>Repe, Božo. <hi rend="italic">Jugoslovanstvo kot ideja in kot praksa.</hi>
                    [Yugoslavism as Idea and Practice] Ljubljana: Filozofska Fakulteta‒Oddelek za
                    zgodovino, 2016. Accesed 1 September 2016. <ref
                        target="http://www.zgodovina-ff-uni-lj.net/index.php?option=com_remository&amp;biblid=26&amp;func=startdown&amp;id=67"
                        >http://www.zgodovina-ff-uni-lj.net/index.php?option=com_remository&amp;biblid=26&amp;func=startdown&amp;id=67</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl>Repe, Božo. “Zakaj so Slovenci vstopili v Jugoslavijo in zakaj so iz nje
                    odšli?.” [Why Slovenians Entered Yugoslavia and Why They Left It] In: <hi
                        rend="italic">Jugoslavija v času. Devetdeset let od nastanka prve
                        jugoslovanske države,</hi> [Yugoslavia in Time. Ninety Years from the
                    Formation of First Yugoslav State] ed. Bojan Balkovec, 21‒46. Ljubljana: Oddelek
                    za zgodovino Filozofske fakultete, 2009.</bibl>
                <bibl>Repe, Božo. “Zgodovina, zgodovinopisje in etika.” [History, Historiography and
                    Ethics] In:
                    <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Etika v slovenskem jeziku, literaturi in kulturi. Zbornik predavanj / 49. seminar slovenskega jezika, literature in kulture, [Ljubljana], 1 – 12 July 2013, </hi>ed.
                    Aleksander Bjelčević, 81‒88. Ljubljana: Znanstvena založba Filozofske fakultete,
                    Ljubljana, 2013.</bibl>
                <bibl><hi rend="italic">Retrostalgija</hi> [Retronostalgia] | <hi rend="italic"
                        >Radio Študent</hi>. Accesed 1 September 2016. <ref
                        target="http://radiostudent.si/dru%C5%BEba/retrostalgija"
                        >http://radiostudent.si/dru%C5%BEba/retrostalgija</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl>Režek, Mateja. “Usmerjena preteklost: Mehanizmi ideološke in politične
                    'kontaminacije' zgodovinopisja v socialistični Sloveniji in Jugoslaviji.”
                    [Directed Past: Mechanisms of Ideological and Political “Contamination” of
                    Historiography in the Socialist Slovenia and Yugoslavia] <hi rend="italic">Acta
                        Histriae</hi> 22, No. 4 (2014): 971‒92.</bibl>
                <bibl>Šifrer, Andrej. “Država”. <hi rend="italic">Hiti počasi</hi>. Ljubljana: ZKP
                    RTVLJ, 1990. </bibl>
                <bibl><hi rend="italic">Tito's Home Page</hi>. At: <ref
                        target="file:///C:\((---GOOGLE%20DRIVE---))\SPROTNO%20DELO%20-%20BORUT\INZ%20-%200%2013-6-2015-27\www.titoville.com"
                        >www.titoville.com</ref>. Website currently unavailable. </bibl>
                <bibl>Ugrešić, Dubravka. “Leksikon izmišljene dežele.” [Lexicon of an Imaginary
                    Country]. In: Dejan Novaćić, <hi rend="italic">SFRJ – moja dežela. Turistični
                        vodič</hi>, 5‒6. Ljubljana: Orbis, 2003. </bibl>
                <bibl>“United States Census Bureau, American Fact Finder, Ancestry (Total Categories
                    Tallied) for People with One or More Ancestry Categories Reported.” <hi
                        rend="italic">American FactFinder – Results.</hi> Accesed 20 June 2016. <ref
                        target="http://factfinder.census.gov/faces/tableservices/jsf/pages/productview.xhtml?pid=DEC_00_SF3_PCT018&amp;prodType=table"
                        >http://factfinder.census.gov/faces/tableservices/jsf/pages/productview.xhtml?pid=DEC_00_SF3_PCT018&amp;prodType=table</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl>Vodušek Starič, Jera. <hi rend="italic">Prevzem oblasti 1944‒1946.</hi>
                    [Assumption of Power 1944-1946] Ljubljana: Cankarjeva založba, 1992.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
            <div type="summary" xml:lang="sl">
            <docAuthor>Jurij Hadalin</docAuthor>
            <head type="main">NEZAŽELENA DEDIŠČINA? HISTORIOGRAFSKI DISKURZ O (DRUGI) JUGOSLAVIJI</head>
            <p>POVZETEK</p>
            <p>O drugi jugoslovanski državi so v različnih kontekstih in časovnih razmakih
                razmišljali mnogi. Postavili so različne ocene, ki se med seboj včasih tudi bijejo,
                tako da ima bralec včasih občutek, da so nastale predvsem pod vplivom nenehnih
                potreb dnevne politike, saj je dogajanje iz časov Jugoslavije in njenega konca še
                vedno prisotno ne le v parlamentarni razpravi, ampak je izpostavljeno v osrednjih
                informativnih oddajah in zadnje čase celo črnih kronikah. Kar morda kaže, da konca
                »zakonskega razmerja« kot družba še vedno nismo preboleli. Bolečih oz. perečih tem
                se navadno ob praznovanjih ogibamo, a politično, zemljepisno in tudi kulturno nas je
                Jugoslavija determinirala do te mere, da ob 25. obletnici samostojne slovenske
                države preprosto ne moremo mimo nje.</p>
            <p>Avtor je pod drobnogled vzel tri povezane tematike. V prvem delu razprave najprej
                opravi s fenomenom t. i. “jugonostalgije”, ki je danes v družbi precejšen kamen
                spotike, pomembno pa prispeva tudi k ugledu in pomenu druge jugoslovanske države v
                širši javnosti. V drugem delu sestavka se posveti vprašanju obstoja jugoslovanske
                historiografije in odnosu slovenskega zgodovinopisja do druge Jugoslavije. V tretjem
                delu članka nato na podlagi zapisov treh uveljavljenih slovenskih zgodovinarjev iz
                različnih obdobij zadnjega tridesetletja poskuša predstaviti še spremembe v
                vrednotenju jugoslovanske izkušnje. </p>
            <p>Razprava ni namenjena temu, da bi na enem mestu in z obširno analizo poskušali rešiti
                zgoraj navedena vprašanja, predstavlja zgolj kritični preblisk in želi doseči
                nekoliko širšo obravnavo problema, upoštevajoč širše kontekste, ki v današnjem
                zgodovinopisju še vedno občasno umanjkajo. </p>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
