<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Maks Samec and His Adapting to Academic Standards After World War II</title>
            <author>
                <name>
                    <forename>Željko</forename>
                    <surname>Oset</surname>
                    <roleName>Assistant Professor</roleName>
                    <roleName>PhD</roleName>
                    <affiliation>School of Humanities of the University of Nova Gorica</affiliation>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Vipavska cesta 13</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>SI-5000 Nova Gorica</addrLine>
                    </address>
                    <email>zeljko.oset@ung.si</email>
                </name>
            </author>
        </titleStmt>
        <editionStmt>
            <edition><date>2017-09-26</date></edition>
        </editionStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
                <orgName xml:lang="sl">Inštitut za novejšo zgodovino</orgName>
                <orgName xml:lang="en">Institute of Contemporary History</orgName>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Kongresni trg 1</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>SI-1000 Ljubljana</addrLine>
                </address>
            </publisher>
            <pubPlace>http://ojs.inz.si/pnz/article/view/296</pubPlace>
            <date>2018</date>
            <availability status="free">
                <licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</licence>
            </availability>
        </publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title xml:lang="sl">Prispevki za novejšo zgodovino</title>
            <title xml:lang="en">Contributions to Contemporary History</title>
            <biblScope unit="volume">58</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
            <idno type="ISSN">2463-7807</idno>
        </seriesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <p>No source, born digital.</p>
        </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc xml:lang="en">
                <p>Contributions to Contemporary History is one of the central Slovenian scientific
                    historiographic journals, dedicated to publishing articles from the field of
                    contemporary history (the 19th and 20th century).</p>
                <p>The journal is published three times per year in Slovenian and in the following
                    foreign languages: English, German, Serbian, Croatian, Bosnian, Italian, Slovak
                    and Czech. The articles are all published with abstracts in English and
                    Slovenian as well as summaries in English.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <projectDesc xml:lang="sl">
                <p>Prispevki za novejšo zgodovino je ena osrednjih slovenskih znanstvenih
                    zgodovinopisnih revij, ki objavlja teme s področja novejše zgodovine (19. in 20.
                    stoletje).</p>
                <p>Revija izide trikrat letno v slovenskem jeziku in v naslednjih tujih jezikih:
                    angleščina, nemščina, srbščina, hrvaščina, bosanščina, italijanščina, slovaščina
                    in češčina. Članki izhajajo z izvlečki v angleščini in slovenščini ter povzetki
                    v angleščini.</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="sl"/>
                <language ident="en"/>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords xml:lang="en">
                    <term>&gt;Maks Samec</term>
                    <term>Institute of Chemistry</term>
                    <term>academic freedom</term>
                    <term>Slovenian Academy of Sciences and Arts</term>
                    <term>University of Ljubljana</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords xml:lang="sl">
                    <term>Maks Samec</term>
                    <term>Inštitut za kemijo</term>
                    <term>akademska svoboda</term>
                    <term>Slovenska akademija znanosti in umetnosti</term>
                    <term>Univerza v Ljubljani</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change>
                    <date>2017-12-27</date>
                    <name>Neja Blaj Hribar</name>
                    <desc>Pretvorba iz DOCX v TEI, dodatno kodiranje</desc>
                </change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <docAuthor>Željko Oset<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn1" n="*">
                    <hi rend="bold" xml:space="preserve">Assistant Professor, PhD, School of Humanities of the University of Nova Gorica, Vipavska cesta 13, Nova Gorica, </hi><ref target="mailto:zeljko.oset@ung.si"><hi rend="bold">zeljko.oset@ung.si</hi></ref></note></docAuthor>
                <docImprint>
                    <idno type="cobissType">Cobiss type: 1.01</idno>
                    <idno type="UDC">UDC: 929Samec M:001.891(497.4Ljubljana)"1945/1964"</idno>
                </docImprint>
                <div type="abstract" xml:lang="sl">
                    <head>IZVLEČEK</head>
                    <head><hi rend="allcaps" style="font-size:12pt">Maks Samec in
                        njegovo prilagajanje akademskim standardom po drugi svetovni vojni</hi></head>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="italic" style="font-size:12pt">Prispevek obravnava akademsko kariero Maksa
                            Samca (1881–1964) po drugi svetovni vojni. Čeprav je Samec po »čistki« na
                            Univerzi v Ljubljani avgusta 1945 izgubil habilitacijo, so mu kot
                            nenadomestljivemu znanstveniku ponudili drugo priložnost – postal je
                            ustanovitelj novoustanovljenega Kemijskega inštituta pri Slovenski akademiji
                            znanosti in umetnosti (SAZU). Za svoje delo si je prislužil številna priznanja
                            in državna odlikovanja. Na inštitutu si je prizadeval za uporabo svojih
                            akademskih standardov, vendar pri tem ni bil povsem uspešen, kar je bila tudi
                            posledica upravnih reform in sprememb v raziskovalni politiki v petdesetih letih
                            20. stoletja.</hi></p>
                    <p><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:12pt"> Ključne besede: Maks Samec, Inštitut za
                        kemijo, akademska svoboda, Slovenska akademija znanosti in umetnosti, Univerza v
                        Ljubljani</hi></p></div>
                <div type="abstract" xml:lang="en">
                <head>ABSTRACT</head>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic" style="font-size:12pt">The paper at hand deals with the academic
                        career of Maks Samec (1881–1964) after World War II. Samec lost his habilitation
                        upon the “purge” at the University of Ljubljana in August of 1945, but was
                        offered a second chance as an irreplaceable scientist – he became the founder of
                        the newly established Institute of Chemistry at the Slovenian Academy of
                        Sciences and Arts (SASA). He has earned numerous recognitions and state
                        decorations for his work. At the institute, he strived to apply his academic
                        standards, but was not entirely successful, which was also a consequence of
                        administrative reforms and changes to research policy in the 1950s.</hi></p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic" style="font-size:12pt">Keywords</hi><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve">: </hi><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:12pt">Maks Samec, Institute of Chemistry,
                            academic freedom, Slovenian Academy of Sciences and Arts, University of
                            Ljubljana</hi></p></div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div><head>Transformation of
                    Slovenian Academic Community After World War II</head>
            <p>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">The academic community in Slovenia changed essentially
                    after World War II, mainly due to a stronger state role and an altered status of
                    science. The state assumed the role of society modernizer, and science –
                    especially technical – was perceived as an important tool of modernization.
                    Therefore, the new authority allocated more funds for science and the number of
                    research positions rose, both in the frame of University of Ljubljana as well as
                    SASA.</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn2" n="1"> Aleš
                        Gabrič, “Znanstvena politika v Sloveniji po drugi svetovni vojni in vloga
                        Antona Peterlina,” in: <hi rend="italic">Anton Peterlin 1908 – 1993:
                            življenje in delo</hi>, eds. Vili Bukošek et al. (Ljubljana: Slovenska
                        akademija znanosti in umetnosti and Institut Jožef Stefan, 2008), 300–05.
                        France Kidrič, “V novi Jugoslaviji,” in: <hi rend="italic">Letopis Akademije
                            znanosti in umetnosti v Ljubljani: druga knjiga: 1943–1947</hi>
                        (Ljubljana: Akademija znanosti in umetnosti v Ljubljani, 1947), 5–7. David
                        Movrin, “The Anatomy of a Revolution: Classics at the University of
                        Ljubljana after 1945,” in: <hi rend="italic">Classics and Communism: Greek
                            and Latin behind the Iron Curtain,</hi> eds. György Karsai et al.
                        (Ljubljana: Znanstvena založba Filozofske fakultete Univerze v Ljubljani;
                        Budapest: Collegium Budapest Institute for Advanced Study; Warsaw: The
                        Faculty of ‘Artes Liberales,’ University of Warsaw, 2013.),
                    141–68.</note>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">Proportionally to stronger state role, the autonomy of
                    institutions decreased. Despite all the changes and reforms, senior scientists
                    preserved their influence and advocated autonomy, becoming a disturbing element
                    in the political authority’s hold on scientific institutions. After completing
                    their mission, i.e. the education of scientific offspring, a group of senior
                    scientists was retired in the years from 1957 to 1959. These have contributed
                    decisively in the institutionalization of Slovenian science, as well as set an
                    example of scientific conduct that was not fully followed by younger scientists.
                    A conflict between the senior and the ambitious younger scientists was
                    deliberately constructed or at least instigated, where the younger scientists
                    have as a rule enjoyed political support.</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn3" n="2"> Aleš Gabrič, “Reforma visokega šolstva 1954–1961
                        ali kako uničiti ljubljansko Univerzo,” in: <hi rend="italic">Nova
                            revija</hi>, 1994, No. 149, 115–20. Željko Oset, <hi rend="italic">Zgodovina Slovenske akademije znanosti in umetnosti: razvoj najvišje
                            znanstvene in umetniške ustanove, 1945–1992</hi> (Ljubljana: Slovenska
                        akademija znanosti in umetnosti, 2017), 57–83.</note></p>
            <p>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">By focusing on pure research before World War II,
                    Slovenian scientists have contributed in the treasury of world knowledge, thus
                    working for the good of humankind.</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn4" n="3"> See also Florian Bieber and Harald Heppner, eds., <hi rend="t41"><seg rend="italic">Universities and Elite Formation in
                                Central, Eastern and South Eastern Europe</seg> (Wien, Zürich,
                            Münster: LIT, 2015),
                    1–10.</hi></note><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve"> After World War II, however, their focus was redirected towards the benefit of people’s community and with the local participators.</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn5" n="4"> Prim. Gabrič,
                        “Znanstvena politika,” 300–05.</note>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">In the West, a rise in cooperation of research sphere
                    with the industry has been also present, both in producing technology for dual
                    (military, civil) or an entirely military purpose, but a commitment to
                    fundamental research work and free choice of research questions is
                    preserved.</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn6" n="5">
                        John Krige, <hi rend="italic">American Hegemony and the Postwar
                            Reconstruction of Science in Europe</hi> (Cambridge, Massachusetts: MIT
                        Press, 2014), 30–39.</note>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">In Slovenia – at least in the building of two institutes:
                    the SASA Institute of Physics/Jožef Stefan Institute and Institute of Chemistry
                    Boris Kidrič – the authority “determined” a priority research field which it was
                    ready to finance substantially, a novelty at the time.</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn7" n="6"> Gabrič, “Znanstvena politika,”
                        300–05. Željko Oset, “Kemični inštitut (Borisa Kidriča) v letih med 1946 in
                        1959,” in: <hi rend="italic">Maks Samec (1881–1964): življenje in delo:
                            zbornik ob 50-letnici smrti</hi>, eds. Branko Stanovnik et al.
                        (Ljubljana: Slovenska akademija znanosti in umetnosti and Slovensko kemijsko
                        društvo, 2015), 183–88.</note></p>
            <p>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">The new era was marked by getting used to scientists
                    being more dependent on authority, new rules of decision-making, lesser autonomy
                    in determining research questions, and limitations in collaboration abroad.
                    Scientists had to accept their loss of status as opinion leaders who publicly
                    and quite freely discussed socially important political issues. These were still
                    discussed in private meetings and expert gatherings, but their views were not
                    made public.</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn8" n="7">
                        SI AS 1931, II, 26, 50279.</note></p>
            <p>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">Because of this, senior scientists criticized the
                    authority’s measures in private parties, ridiculed the rulers, complained about
                    the changes and warned about too small investments in science.</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn9" n="8"> Ibid.,
                        50248.</note>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">But they were still proud of their reputation, so they
                    wanted to remain perceived in Slovenian science as self-dependent, independent
                    from authority.</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn10" n="9"> France Kidrič emphasized, in the elections of Josip
                        Broz for honorary member in August 1948, that SASA had decided by its own
                        inclination for the election, and that it is not a Party or Party-dependent
                        institution. Similar warnings were given by the president France Kidrič in
                        October 1949 before the elections of new members. It was then that the legal
                        provision on the authority confirming an academician's election was applied
                        for the first time. The president warned that this must not arouse an
                        appearance of SASA's subordination in public, so SASA asked the Slovenian
                        authority's opinion on the candidates before the elections. – Oset, <hi rend="italic">Zgodovina Slovenske akademije</hi>, 201–03.</note>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">At the same time, they also wanted to preserve the
                    influence in their research groups.</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn11" n="10"> SI AS 223, b. 498, Uradna zabeležka o odstopu dr.
                        Franceta Avčina kot predsednika sveta Inštituta za elektriško
                        gospodarstvo.</note></p></div>
           <div> <head>Slovenian Academic
                    Community’s Transformation as a Research Question</head>
            <p>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">Problems of transforming the Slovenian academic community
                    after World War II were discussed in the beginning of 1990s within the scope of
                    an in-depth research of the takeover of power and its subsystems by the
                    Communist Party after World War II. On one hand, researching was encouraged
                    importantly through democratization and the related procedure of rectification
                    of the wrongs committed during communism, especially in the early stage, and on
                    the other hand, it is part of a broader researching of the historical period
                    upon setting the historical distance and using comparative approach, which,
                    after entering European Union, is in part encouraged through EU priority
                    research goals.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">Important work was done by the commission of Slovenian
                    historians that prepared, upon request by the Slovenian parliament, the
                    Elaborate on key characteristics of Slovenian politics between 1929–1955
                    (Ključne značilnosti slovenske politike v letih 1929–1955, znanstveno poročilo –
                    written only in Slovenian language), published in 1995. Its focal point is in
                    reviewing the political development and lines of force, i.e. “breaking points
                    that are crucial to understanding and explaining the reasons for the ‘schism’ in
                    Slovenian society”.</hi>
                <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn12" n="11"> Zdenko Čepič et
                        al., <hi rend="italic">Ključne značilnosti slovenske politike v letih
                            1929–1955: znanstveno poročilo</hi> (Ljubljana: Inštitut za novejšo
                        zgodovino, 1995).</note>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">The University of Ljubljana and the Slovenian Academy of
                    Sciences and Arts have subsequently founded their own commissions, wanting to
                    research their history in the first years after the communist takeover of power.
                    The goal was essentially a rectification of wrongs and rehabilitation of
                    professors, collaborators and academicians who were wronged, while a more
                    wholesome valorization of the historical period has established itself
                    simultaneously.</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn13" n="12">
                       Aleš Gabrič and Peter Vodopivec, eds., <hi rend="italic">Politični pritiski in izključevanja
                            učiteljev in sodelavcev z Univerze v Ljubljani: poročilo Komisije za
                            rehabilitacijo univerzitetnih učiteljev in sodelavcev</hi> (Ljubljana: Univerza v Ljubljani, 2000). France Bernik, “Iz zgodovine SAZU,” in:
                        <hi rend="italic">Letopis Slovenske akademije
                            znanosti in umetnosti: 46. knjiga:
                            1995</hi> (Ljubljana: Slovenska akademija znanosti in umetnosti, 1996), 147–50. Oset, <hi rend="italic">Zgodovina Slovenske
                            akademije</hi>, 215, 216.</note></p>
            <p>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">New researches, a new research approach and documentation
                    of material collections have contributed to partial rectification of wrongs, a
                    better understanding of the historical period, and a new scholarship has formed.
                    Important consequence of the discussion is a profound interest in selected
                    scientists, resulting in the recent period in a large number of monographs and
                    articles on scientists and cultural workers who have importantly marked
                    Slovenian science, but too little was known about them.</hi>
                <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn14" n="13"> Bukošek et al.,
                            <hi rend="italic">Anton Peterlin 1908–1993</hi>. Anton Suhadolc, <hi rend="italic">Profesor Rihard Zupančič</hi> (Ljubljana: A. Suhadolc,
                        2011). Stanovnik et al., <hi rend="italic">Maks Samec (1881–1964).</hi>
                        Alenka Puhar, <hi rend="italic">Izidor Cankar, Mojster dobro zasukanih
                            stavkov: življenje in delo Izidorja Cankarja, 1886–1958</hi> (Ljubljana:
                        Mladinska knjiga, 2016).</note>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">Maks Samec, a chemist, university professor at University
                    of Ljubljana and the manager of Institute of Chemistry Boris Kidrič, can be
                    qualified among such scientists who have marked the institutionalization of
                    Slovenian science.</hi></p></div>
            <div><head>Academic Career of Maks Samec Until 1945</head>
            <p>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">Samec made a successful academic career before World War
                    II (articles, books, patents), became the dean of Technical faculty twice and
                    head of University of Ljubljana (1935–1937). However, the focus of his work was
                    the university chemistry institute. He received numerous recognitions and
                    decorations, was named a regular member of SASA, the Yugoslavian Academy of
                    Sciences and Arts, and the Academy of Sciences Leopoldina.</hi>
                <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn15" n="14"> Tatjana Peterlin
                        Neumaier, “Življenjepis Maksa Samca,” in: Stanovnik et al., <hi rend="italic">Maks Samec (1881–1964),</hi> 39–51.</note>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">He was, in short, one of the most respected professors of
                    the Ljubljana University, but obtained some powerful opponents when running for
                    its head position in February 1935.</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn16" n="15"> Željko Oset, “Gradnja kemičnega inštituta Univerze
                        kralja Aleksandra I.,” in: Stanovnik et al., <hi rend="italic">Maks Samec
                            (1881–1964)</hi>, 138–40.</note>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">Because of defending strict academic standards and
                    insisting on an outdated code of behavior, as well as modest job opportunities
                    for young graduates, he fell out of favor with some of his younger colleagues,
                    among them such who would become decision-makers after World War II.</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn17" n="16"> Peterlin Neumaier,
                        “Življenjepis Maksa Samca,” 52, 53.</note></p>
            <p>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">Maks Samec kept good relations with German scientists,
                    particularly during 1930s, when the results of his research on food persistence
                    were published. Due to successful research, good acquaintanceships among
                    scientists, as well as support of the German consul in Ljubljana, he was elected
                    for the correspondent member of Academy of Sciences Leopoldina in 1940, and also
                    received a high Third Reich national award (an order of the German Eagle, 1</hi>
                <hi rend="superscript" style="font-size:12pt">st</hi>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">grade). He was highly recommended for both German
                    decorations by the German consul in Ljubljana, who wrote in February 1940 in a
                    report to German embassy in Belgrade that Samec, through “his research work,
                    conducted in close collaboration with the German scientists, is one of Germany’s
                    best friends”. In lobbying for the state recognition, he even characterized
                    Samec as “unserer Mensch an der Universität”. Therefore, it is no surprise that
                    Samec received an offer in autumn of 1941 to move together with
                    “volksdeutschers” from Ljubljana province to Germany. Samec did not decide for
                    this step, but wanted to preserve good relations with the German authorities. He
                    also declined the position of Mayor of Ljubljana, offered by the German
                    occupying authorities.</hi>
                <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn18" n="17"> SI AS 1931, VIII,
                        5, 7680–7686.</note></p></div>
            <div><head>The Post-war Purge
                    and Irreplaceable Experts</head>
            <p>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">At the post-war purge at the Ljubljana University, he was
                    detached, removing his habilitation, but received a pay and a liability on
                    support of his research. Samec obtained the status of irreplaceable scientist
                    who can contribute to the realization of planned measures of the new people’s
                    power and educate an adequately qualified generation of younger
                    experts.</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn19" n="18">
                        Oset, “Kemični inštitut (Borisa Kidriča),” 183–86.</note></p>
            <p><hi style="font-size:12pt">Removal of Maks Samec’s habilitation – and the wider purge
                    at the Ljubljana University – achieved its goal of intimidating scientists who
                    thus became aware of their dependence on the authority, especially in the
                    breaking period. It is the period which Anton Peterlin characterized as the
                    period of partisan freedom.</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn20" n="19">
                        Archives’ of family Peterlin, Notes of Anton Peterlin; Library of the Slovenian Academy of Sciences and Arts, R 46/III-138. David Movrin, Fran Bradač, Anton Sovre, Milan Grošelj, Jože Košar and Fran Petre, “Latinščina in grščina na ljubljanski univerzi v prvem desetletju po vojni,” in: <hi rend="italic">Keria: studia Latina et
                            Graeca</hi> 15, No. 2 (2013): 147–79. Puhar, <hi rend="italic">Izidor Cankar</hi>, 88–105.</note>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">In this time, obtaining support and protection from
                    visible representatives of the new authority was required for deciding on
                    guerilla collecting of aparatures in the field,</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn21" n="20"> Gabrič, “Znanstvena politika,”
                        303–05.</note>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">valorizing one’s inter-war activity, or continuing a
                    scientific career.</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn22" n="21"> Milan Vidmar, <hi rend="italic">Spomini: II.</hi>
                        (Maribor: Založba Obzorja, 1964), 238, 239.</note></p>
            <p>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">In the summer of 1945, Samec experienced a feeling of
                    isolation and endangerment; information circulated about his ejection to Austria
                    as part of deportation of the German minority from Slovenia. His younger
                    colleagues spread rumors about his favor for Germans, a strong Germany and his
                    displaying of the German high state decoration during World War II. He was also
                    accused of a life of comfort before and during the war, but acknowledged at the
                    same time his scientific excellence. By gaining support of the president of
                    Slovenian government, he was personally “protected”, so his adversaries
                    retaliated against his supporting members at the University’s chemistry
                    institute: doc. dr. Marta Blinc</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn23" n="22"> Marta Blinc, seen as Samec's protegee and a personal
                        friend, lost her habilitation in the purge, her assets were nationalized,
                        and she as a German was exiled from Ljubljana to Austria. She was only
                        allowed to return in autumn 1947, when SASA arranged for her return on
                        Samec's demand. – SI AS 1931, Lm, 105, 208927.</note>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">and prof. dr. Marius Rebek.</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn24" n="23"> Rebek was exiled from Yugoslavia together with his wife on the pretext that she, as a German, was a hostile element, even though they had both collaborated with partisans during the war. Rebek claimed in his letters to colleagues, and also to the president of government, that Samec was irreplaceable, even more so in the new times, when development of technical branches was planned. – Anton Peterlin, “O slovenskem kemiku dr. Mariusu Rebeku,” in: 
                        <hi rend="italic">Ameriška domovina/American home </hi>(Cleveland, Ohio), 25. 2.
                1983.</note></p></div>
            <div><head>New Research Policy
                    and Irreplaceable “Cadres”</head>
            <p>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">The new Slovenian authority’s research policy was vaguely
                    defined – perhaps the most thoughtful was the field of human resources, but the
                    authority had to consider the scarcity of Slovenian academic community and a
                    somewhat modest influence of younger scientists who were ideologically in its
                    favor. Due to this scarcity, a group of irreplaceable scientists was formed,
                    among which we can undoubtedly place the founders of big natural institutes at
                    SASA (Maks Samec: Institute of Chemistry/Boris Kidrič/; Milan Vidmar: Institute
                    for electrical economy; Anton Kuhelj: Institute for turbine machines; Anton
                    Peterlin: Institute of Physics/Institute Jožef Stefan). Their interests varied:
                    some wanted to connect the research work with the pedagogy process at the
                    university (Peterlin),</hi>
                <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn25" n="24"> Gabrič,
                        “Znanstvena politika,” 309.</note>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">others to found their institute anywhere in Slovenia, if
                    provided with sufficient state support (Vidmar, Kuhelj),</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn26" n="25"> Oset, “Zgodovina Slovenske
                        akademije,” 81–83.</note>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">and Samec simply wanted to continue his research work
                    after his habilitation was removed.</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn27" n="26"> Peterlin Neumaier, “Življenjepis Maksa Samca,”
                        52–55.</note></p>
            <p>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">In the post-war period, it held good for Samec, in the
                    words of Slovenian government’s president Boris Kidrič, spoken at SASA’s request
                    for the employment of Jakob Šolar, “for pedagogical work, no, for scientific
                    work, do make use of him”.</hi>
                <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn28" n="27"> Archives of SASA,
                        Predsedstvo 1938–1952, folder 14, Zapisnik seje predsedstva SAZU (11. 10.
                        1952).</note></p>
            <p>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">His younger colleagues presented him as an ideological
                    opponent, and his disorderly attendance in the people’s-front-organs only
                    hardened the suspicions. Of course, regular visiting of all
                    people’s-front-sessions would in no way essentially change his position. Later,
                    as Samec was working intensely in the field of enriching coal, for entire days
                    and also during weekends, his rare visits of people’s-front-sessions were no
                    longer paid particular attention. Even more, his absence was proof that he is
                    devoted to solving an important research problem, the solution of which was
                    expected much of by the authority.</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn29" n="28"> Oset, “Kemični inštitut (Borisa Kidriča),”
                        168–72.</note></p>
            <p>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">Maks Samec was, first of all, a researcher-workaholic who
                    wanted to “do” as much as possible. Yet he was constantly accompanied by a sense
                    of lost time from his Vienna period and the period of Kingdom of SHS/Yugoslavia,
                    when he had to struggle to ensure appropriate working conditions.</hi>
                <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn30" n="29"> Peterlin Neumaier,
                        “Življenjepis Maksa Samca,” 45, 46, 64–66.</note></p>
            <p>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">Samec pointed out several times in 1945 and 1946 that he
                    only wanted to continue his scientific work, and the Slovenian authority
                    (particularly Boris Kidrič) wanted an important scientific center to be formed
                    in Slovenia. In early 1946, Boris Kidrič invited Samec to a meeting and
                    suggested him to think about founding a large chemistry institute at SASA that
                    would be home to chemists of Yugoslavia. The purpose of the institute would be
                    to solve the fundamental problems of Yugoslavian economy in the field of
                    chemistry, as well as educating the young generation, and international
                    collaboration would be enabled.</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn31" n="30"> “Pot do moderne znanstvene ustanove,” in: <hi rend="italic">Slovenski poročevalec</hi> 15, 1954, No.
                140.</note></p>
            <p>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">Maks Samec, who remained in the field of colloid
                    chemistry (food persistence), a less interesting economic question for a
                    predominantly agricultural country, accepted the proposal by the president of
                    Slovenian government. Despite this, he pointed out the research of food
                    persistence as the central research question in his first work program in
                    February 1946, whereas in the future, he intended to research the possibility
                    for raising a culture to produce penicillin.</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn32" n="31"> Archives of SASA, Razna pošta, b.
                        7 (1946), No. 33/46.</note>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">His proposal did not appease the expectations of the
                    Slovenian authority, so he sent another proposal of the new institute’s research
                    plan two months later. Samec suggested as the central research question the
                    studying of the process of making metallurgical coke from domestic coals. In
                    this, he pointed out that he had already conducted his preliminary research in
                    the years 1928–1931 for Trbovlje coal mining company. He made it clear that the
                    research results were encouraging in laboratory phase, however, the client then
                    did not decide for test production due to it being unrewarding, since such coke
                    was 25 per cent more expensive than imported one.</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn33" n="32"> Ibid., No. 141/46.</note></p>
            <p>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">Samec’s research of enriching coals was a research field
                    the authority was willing to financially support. SASA passed the new research
                    program proposal to the Ministry of industry and mining that positively
                    evaluated the proposal, since it was exceptionally important in the concept of
                    Yugoslavian key economy development.</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn34" n="33"> Ibid., No. 184/46. Jože Prinčič, “Razvoj gospodarstva do sredine petdesetih let,” in: <hi rend="italic">Slovenska novejša zgodovina: od
                            programa Zedinjene Slovenije do mednarodnega priznanja Republike
                            Slovenije: 2</hi>, eds. Jasna Fischer et al.
                            (Ljubljana: Inštitut za novejšo zgodovino; Mladinska knjiga, 2005),
                            965–68.</note></p>
            <p>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">The proposal was officially endorsed in October 1946,
                    therefore the head secretary of SASA prepared a statute, and SASA officially
                    employed Samec, whereas the statute of the Institute of Chemistry was passed in
                    December 1947 at SASA assembly. This changed Samec’s position which he used to
                    set up a laboratory, but he also managed to have his former close colleague
                    Marta Blinc repatriated.</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn35" n="34"> SI AS 1931, VIII, 28, 7832, 7833.</note></p>
            <p>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">With successful running of the institute and encouraging
                    research results, political scruples ceased to obstruct his re-election as SASA
                    member; he was re-elected in December 1949 as member of SASA,</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn36" n="35"> Željko Oset, “Samec
                        vnovič postane član Slovenske akademije znanosti in umetnosti,” in:
                        Stanovnik et al., <hi rend="italic">Maks Samec (1881–1964)</hi>,
                    168–72.</note>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">and three years later again as correspondent member of
                    the Yugoslavian Academy of Sciences and Arts in Zagreb.</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn37" n="36"> Samec belongs in a group of
                        pre-war members of Yugoslavian academy of sciences and arts whose
                        memberships were not returned on academy's revival in autumn 1947. – Ibid., 166.</note></p>
            <p>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">But he was also publicly promoted as a top home
                    scientist. This strengthened patriotism and most of all the view that the
                    authority was able by domestic knowledge to carry out industrialization, or
                    broader, a transition to a socialist society. An important aspect for the
                    Slovenian authority was the fact that Samec managed to do this as a Slovenian
                    scientist who was more successful than the Serbian scientist Božo Popović, a
                    former student of Samec, who was conducting coal enrichment for the Serbian
                    academy of sciences. Therefore, it is no surprise that Samec was even awarded
                    two Prešeren awards in 1949 and 1950. First one was for scientific results,
                    important for reaching the five-year plan, while next year, the award was for
                    successful work to produce metallurgic coke from domestic coal.</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn38" n="37"> Ibid., 167, 168.
                        Peterlin Neumaier, “Življenjepis Maksa Samca,” 59, 60.</note></p></div>
            <div><head>Maks Samec Under
                    Surveillance</head>
            <p>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">The main research project by the Institute of Chemistry
                    was extremely important, the key cause for UDBA’s</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn39" n="38"> The State Security Administration (Uprava Državne Bezbednosti) was the secret police organization of Yugoslavia, and it was best known at all times simply by the acronym UDBA.</note><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve"> operative supervision of Samec in summer of 1948. Before, UDBA mostly gathered rumors about Samec, circulating among university professors, and extracts from documents, especially the German consulate in Ljubljana. But since Samec was very retained in public, while his social network was narrow, UDBA failed to obtain quality information on him.</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn40" n="39"> SI AS 1931, VIII, 5,
                        7611.</note>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">Decision for his methodical supervision was made after
                    the so-called Dachau trials, a mock political trial against former internees in
                    German concentration camps, where much of technical intelligence was
                    interrogated and eventually sentenced, even pre-war communists. Interesting to
                    UDBA regarding Samec were the interrogations of Boris Fakin and Boris Krajnc, a
                    graduate and doctorate candidate of Samec. UDBA was mainly interested in his
                    relation toward German scientists and his international contacts.</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn41" n="40"> Ibid.,
                        7610, 7611.</note></p>
            <p>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">Even though the mentioned two made critical remarks about
                    Samec, the reason of supervision was in the mere importance of the project for
                    economic development. Samec was also aware of this, writing in a letter to the
                    president of SASA in May 1948 how he was aware that he was under “a very strict
                    supervision, like everyone who worked in an industrial facility”.</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn42" n="41"> Archives of SASA, Kemijski inštitut, 1948, Maks Samec's letter to France Kidrič (17. 5. 1948).</note>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">Interrogation of Fakin and Kranjc thus “merely” sped up
                    the procedure of establishing operative supervision over Samec, beginning in
                    summer of 1948, when the Slovenian authority assigned a Ford automobile to the
                    Institute of Chemistry, with a chauffeur who, under the alias “Ford Jože”,
                    became the first UDBA collaborator and watched Samec.</hi>
                <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn43" n="42"> SI AS 1931, LM,
                        105, 208930.</note></p>
            <p><seg xml:space="preserve">           </seg><hi style="font-size:12pt">UDBA began with
                    detailed supervision in October 1948, after Samec became the chief of the group
                    for chemistry in the Federal commission for the progress of production, and the
                    federal ministry of economy called Samec and Božo Popović, head of competitive
                    group in the Serbian academy of sciences, to an advocacy in order to clear up a
                    (supposed) sabotage. Namely, the ministry did not appropriately evidence the
                    memos that the scientists were sending. Even though an obvious miscommunication
                    had taken place, UDBA decided to supervise Samec more closely.</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn44" n="43"> SI AS 1931, VIII, 5,
                        7619, 8075, 8076.</note></p>
            <p>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">Even concealing research results was sabotage. Samec
                    faced a grave danger in the decision-makers’ incomprehension of the problem.
                    This, that is, incomprehension, was not supposed to happen in Ljubljana, since
                    the surveillance was coordinated by Milan Osredkar, also head of Ljubljana
                    branch of the Federal commission for progress of production. Osredkar thus
                    controlled Samec during work and in his free time.</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn45" n="44"> Ibid., 7753,
                        7754.</note></p>
            <p>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">Samec, too, was very afraid of sabotage, and called all
                    collaborators of the Institute of Chemistry to discretion in using research
                    results, also in contacts with journalists, who he suspected to be UDBA agents.
                    Samec feared UDBA would send a “provoker” to obtain information on the research,
                    only to use it in a process against him. But Samec already suspected in summer
                    1949 that UDBA managed to “thrash” one of the employees at the Institute of
                    Chemistry, which he was very offended with.</hi>
                <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn46" n="45"> Ibid., 7730, 8013–15.</note></p>
            <p>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">What worried UDBA was mainly Samec’s poor family
                    situation – health issues of his wife. Her condition, already bad before the
                    war, deteriorated further after the war. Unbearable family situation also
                    effected Samec’s health and, as a consequence, success of his scientific work.
                    In summer of 1949, after the construction of the new building of the Institute
                    of Chemistry started, Samec believed he would not live to see it
                    built.</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn47" n="46"> SI
                        AS 1931, Lm, 105, 208930, 208931,
                    208933–38.</note><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve"> Osredkar and France Kidrič first convinced Samec into hospital treatment of his wife, but then a decision was made for her to “move” to Austria. Because of reduced stress in his private life, Samec functioned as if reborn, the early 1950s thus being among his most successful research years.</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn48" n="47"> Peterlin Neumaier,
                        “Življenjepis Maksa Samca,” 57–59.</note></p></div>
            <div><head>“Fight” with
                    Reforms</head>
            <p>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">Due to the success of the parade research project – the
                    research of producing metallurgic coke – other research groups were able to form
                    at the institute, among them for studying colloid chemistry. In 1950s, the
                    institute’s financial dependence on a single project has proven to be an
                    exceptional challenge for long-term stability. First serious blow was the
                    abolishment of the Federal commission for the progress of production – the main
                    financer of the institute – in autumn 1952 – and employment of the commission’s
                    collaborators at the institute. An even graver blow was introducing a new
                    funding model to the institute: self-maintenance. Until then, the institute
                    received almost all its funds from the state, but now, it had to acquire the
                    resources for its function on the market. By this, the authority wanted to
                    strengthen collaboration of research institutes with the economy, but there was
                    little demand for research favors of the institute. And when projects were
                    acquired, these were tied to performing a specific task. Protests by manager
                    Samec that such a model makes the pure research impossible had no effect. Not
                    even renaming the institute after deceased Boris Kidrič helped.</hi>
                <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn49" n="48"> Archives of SASA, Predsedstvo 1953–1963, folder 3, Zapisnik seje predsedstva SAZU (2. 12. 1955).</note></p>
            <p>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">Because of the new funding model and slow firing of
                    excess workers, Chemistry Institute found itself in serious financial trouble.
                    First crisis arose in summer 1955, solved by Slovenian government with
                    allocating a research project to the institute. In the next crisis in spring of
                    1957, Samec suggested introducing social management of his own initiative. He
                    expected that by proposing a management model to authority’s liking, he would
                    gain support of Slovenian authority and additional funds for the institute’s
                    function. To him, it was about finishing begun research before old age
                    debilitation would appear. The government rejected the proposed change due to
                    upcoming passing of legislation on scientific institutions, allocated the
                    institute bridging funds and procured economic orders.</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn50" n="49"> Oset, “Kemični inštitut (Borisa
                        Kidriča),” 188–92.</note></p>
            <p>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">In autumn 1957, the republic Act on scientific
                    institutions was passed, and in December 1958 a new decree stating that SASA,
                    University of Ljubljana and Executive council of People’s Republic of Slovenia
                    were cofounders of the Institute of Chemistry Boris Kidrič. The status change
                    provided that the manager becomes advisor to the new institute leadership.
                    Furthermore, it was provided that the institute maintain Samec’s research group
                    after reorganization.</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn51" n="50"> Ibid.</note></p>
            <p>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">Samec accepted the changes as executed fact and did not
                    want to overly upset himself, well aware of futility of such action. He accepted
                    the cabinet he was offered at the Institute of Chemistry, which enabled him
                    access to laboratories. He later denoted the reform in a letter to SASA head
                    secretary Milko Kos as “demolition of the institute”, blaming an undefined group
                    of younger colleagues.</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn52" n="51"> Archives of SASA, Predsedstvo 1953–1963, folder 11,
                        Zapisnik seje predsedstva SAZU (18. 6. 1963).</note>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">He connected the reform with ambition of chemistry
                    professors to conduct postgraduate studies at the Institute of Chemistry, which
                    Samec firmly opposed.</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn53" n="52"> Archives of SASA, Predsedstvo 1953–1963, folder 5,
                        Zapisnik seje predsedstva SAZU (6. 2. 1957).</note></p>
            <p>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">Samec took very personally the breaking of the agreement
                    on funding his research group – he first had to obtain research projects for its
                    function, then, since 1960, he obtained funds from Foundation Boris Kidrič and
                    SASA. In 1962, he gained a large research project (Modifying cereal starches by
                    physical procedures in goal of spreading the use of these starches), supported
                    by the US Ministry of Agriculture.</hi></p>
            <p>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">In line with his academic standards, Samec wanted to
                    designate his successor in the fund as head of project. He chose Marta Blinc.
                    After his death, the research group was joined to the Institute of Chemistry,
                    determined as the project executant, while Marta Blinc decided to retire due to
                    poor atmosphere.</hi>
                <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn54" n="53"> Oset, “Samec
                        postane vnovič član,” 175, 176.</note></p>
            <p>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">To Samec, founding of the cabinet was a last major life
                    break, enabling him to focus on his preferred research field (colloid
                    chemistry), a chance to participate in conferences abroad, and foremost, relief
                    from bureaucracy and fighting for funds. Research was a key part of his
                    identity, therefore he experienced organizational changes personally. In October
                    1963, he wrote in a letter to SASA head secretary Milko Kos that the chance
                    affected him personally. He even called it the “demolition of the
                    institute”.</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn55" n="54"> Archives of SASA, Predsedstvo 1953–1963, folder 11, Zapisnik seje predsedstva SAZU (18. 6. 1963).</note>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve">In some manner, he relived the trauma from summer of 1945. He estimated that his efforts in founding the Institute of Chemistry, even by researching a field less fond to him, was not adequately valorized. Despite adapting to post-war system of leading a research institute and science funding, he remained true to academic ideals conquered in his Viennese </hi><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:12pt">alma matris</hi><hi style="font-size:12pt">, and was therefore disappointed by actions of his younger colleagues who have
                    in striving to prove themselves, in his view, violated those academic standards.
                    In this way, his academic standards were violated in autumn 1963 at proposing
                    candidates for new members. In the candidacy procedure, an awkward embarrassment
                    occurred in who to suggest a candidate: academician (Samec), who was a
                    scientific authority for the field, or someone outside SASA.</hi>
                <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn56" n="55"> Archives of SASA,
                        Skupščina 1962–1972, Zapisnik skupščine SAZU (3. 7. 1964).</note>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">Candidates for the field of chemistry were Dušan Hadži,
                    proposed by Samec, and Roman Modic, proposed by the “made side”.</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn57" n="56"> Archives of SASA, Seje predsedstva 1953–1963, folder 11, Zapisnik seje predsedstva SAZU(18. 6. 1963).</note>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">Already after Samec’s death, Dušan Hadži, the first
                    doctorand of Samec at SASA and collaborator at the Institute of Chemistry Boris
                    Kidrič, won this “battle”.</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn58" n="57">
                        “Members of the SASA,” SAZU, accessed September 10, 2018, <ref target="http://www.sazu.si/o-sazu/clani/umrli.html">http://www.sazu.si/o-sazu/clani/umrli.html</ref>. </note></p></div>
           <div> <head>Conclusion</head>
            <p>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve">Maks Samec was formed as </hi><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:12pt">homo
                academicus</hi><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve"> at the University of Vienna. Because of defending strict academic standards and insisting on an outdated code of behavior, favoring some members at his institute, as well as modest job opportunities for young graduates, he fell out of favor with some of his younger colleagues, among them such who would become decision-makers after World War II.</hi></p>
            <p>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">At the post-war purge at the Ljubljana University, he was
                    detached, removing his habilitation, but as an irreplaceable scientist, he was
                    awarded opportunity to restart his career. Samec had two main goals: perform
                    research and educate young generation of chemists. His was granted substantial
                    amount of funds upon presentation of politically desirable research – i.e. the
                    research of the process of making metallurgical coke from domestic coals. He was
                    still allowed to proceed with his research of colloid chemistry but due to the
                    extent of organizational work, tutoring and health issues as well, to a lesser
                    extent.</hi></p>
            <p>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">Samec successful running of the Institute and encouraging
                    research results gained him public acclaim as a top home scientist and several
                    important awards as well. However, due to the importance of the Institute core
                    research, he was under UDBA surveillance. Samec has suspected surveillance,
                    which was disappointed realization of wariness in his academic honor. Even more,
                    he was disappointed in mid-1950’s upon introducing the new funding model,
                    so-called self-maintenance. Until then, the institute received almost all its
                    funds from the state, but now, it had to acquire the resources for its function
                    on the market. Protests by Samec that such a model makes the essential
                    scientific work impossible had no effect. Not even renaming the institute after
                    deceased Boris Kidrič helped.</hi></p>
            <p>
                <hi style="font-size:12pt">The final blow to his academic standard was his
                    retirement from the institute in 1959, which was for him the demolition of the
                    institute. Samec adapted to the post-war system in Slovenian academic community
                    (e.g. in terms of selecting research, preferred organization solutions and
                    funding of research), and was aware of political cliffs and issues that could
                    have been perceived as “sabotage”. Even though his academic standards were
                    out-dated, he tried to live by them, therefore his biggest disappointment of the
                    period after WWII was fumbled collegiality among scientists especially younger
                    one.</hi></p></div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <head>Sources and Literature</head>
            <list type="unordered">
                <head>Archival Sources:</head>
                <item>SI AS, Archives of the Republic Slovenia:<list>
                    <item>SI AS 223, Vlada SRS.</item>
                    <item>SI AS 1931, Republiški sekretariat za notranje zadeve RSNZ.</item></list></item>
                <item>SASA, Archives of the Slovenian Academy of Sciences and Arts:<list>
                <item>SASA, Kemijski inštitut.</item>
                <item>SASA, Predsedstvo SAZU.</item>
                    <item>SASA, Razna pošta.</item></list></item>
                <item>Archives’ of family Peterlin:<list>
                <item>Archives’ of family Peterlin, Notes of Anton
                    Peterlin.</item></list></item>
                <item>Library of the Slovenian Academy of Sciences and
                    Arts.</item>
            </list>
            <listBibl>
                <head>Literature:</head>
                <bibl><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">Bernik, France. “Iz zgodovine SAZU.” In: </hi><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Letopis Slovenske akademije znanosti in
                    umetnosti: 46. knjiga:
                    1995,</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve"> 147–50. Ljubljana: Slovenska akademija znanosti in umetnosti, 1996.</hi></bibl>
                <bibl>Bieber, Florian and Harald Heppner, eds. <hi rend="t41"><seg rend="italic">Universities and Elite Formation in Central, Eastern and South Eastern
                    Europe.</seg> Wien, Zürich, Münster: LIT, 2015.</hi></bibl>
                <bibl>Bukošek, Vili, Tanja Peterlin-Neumaier, Janez Stepišnik, Janez Strnad, Saša
                    Svetina and Anton Peterlin, eds. <hi rend="italic">Anton Peterlin 1908–1993:
                        življenje in delo.</hi> Ljubljana: Slovenska akademija znanosti in umetnosti
                    and Institut Jožef Stefan, 2008.</bibl>
                <bibl>Čepič, Zdenko, Tone Ferenc, Aleš Gabrič, Bojan Godeša, Boris Mlakar, Dušan
                    Nečak, Jože Prinčič, Janko Prunk, Božo Repe, Anka Vidovič-Miklavčič, Peter
                    Vodopivec and Milan Ževart. <hi rend="italic">Ključne značilnosti slovenske
                        politike v letih 1929–1955: znanstveno poročilo.</hi> Ljubljana: Inštitut za
                    novejšo zgodovino, 1995.</bibl>
                <bibl><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">Gabrič, Aleš and Peter Vodopivec, eds. </hi><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Politični pritiski in izključevanja
                    učiteljev in sodelavcev z Univerze v Ljubljani: poročilo Komisije za
                    rehabilitacijo univerzitetnih učiteljev in
                    sodelavcev.</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve"> Ljubljana: Univerza v Ljubljani, 2000.</hi></bibl>
                <bibl>Gabrič, Aleš. “Reforma visokega šolstva 1954–1961 ali kako uničiti ljubljansko
                    Univerzo.” In: <hi rend="italic">Nova revija</hi>, No. 149 (1994):
                    115–20.</bibl>
                <bibl>Gabrič, Aleš. “Znanstvena politika v Sloveniji po drugi svetovni vojni in
                    vloga Antona Peterlina.” In: <hi rend="italic">Anton Peterlin 1908–1993:
                        življenje in delo</hi>, edited by Vili Bukošek, Tanja Peterlin-Neumaier,
                    Janez Stepišnik, Janez Strnad, Saša Svetina and Anton Peterlin, 300–05.
                    Ljubljana: Slovenska akademija znanosti in umetnosti and Institut Jožef Stefan,
                    2008.</bibl>
                <bibl>Kidrič, France. “V novi Jugoslaviji.” In: <hi rend="italic">Letopis Akademije
                    znanosti in umetnosti v Ljubljani: druga knjiga: 1943–1947</hi>, 5–7.
                    Ljubljana: Akademija znanosti in umetnosti v Ljubljani, 1947.</bibl>
                <bibl>Krige, John. <hi rend="italic">American Hegemony and the Postwar
                    Reconstruction of Science in Europe.</hi> Cambridge, Massachusetts: MIT
                    Press, 2014.</bibl>
                <bibl><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">Movrin, David, Fran Bradač, Anton Sovre, Milan Grošelj, Jože Košar and Fran Petre. “Latinščina in grščina na ljubljanski univerzi v prvem desetletju po vojni.” In: </hi><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Keria: studia Latina et
                    Graeca</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve"> 15, No. 2 (2013): 147–79.</hi></bibl>
                <bibl>Movrin, David. “The Anatomy of a Revolution: Classics at the University of
                    Ljubljana after 1945.” In: <hi rend="italic">Classics and Communism: Greek and
                        Latin behind the Iron Curtain,</hi> edited by György Karsai, Gábor
                    Klaniczay, David Movrin and Elżbieta Olechowska, 141–68. Ljubljana: Znanstvena
                    založba Filozofske fakultete Univerze v Ljubljani; Budapest: Collegium Budapest
                    Institute for Advanced Study; Warsaw: The Faculty of ‘Artes Liberales,’
                    University of Warsaw, 2013.</bibl>
                <bibl>Oset, Željko. “Gradnja kemičnega inštituta Univerze kralja Aleksandra I.” In:
                    <hi rend="italic">Maks Samec (1881–1964): življenje in delo: zbornik ob
                        50-letnici smrti,</hi> edited by Stanovnik, Branko, Maks Samec, Tanja
                    Peterlin-Neumaier and Željko Oset, 138–40. Ljubljana: Slovenska akademija
                    znanosti in umetnosti and Slovensko kemijsko društvo, 2015.</bibl>
                <bibl>Oset, Željko. “Kemični inštitut (Borisa Kidriča) v letih med 1946 in 1959.”
                    In: <hi rend="italic">Maks Samec (1881–1964): življenje in delo: zbornik ob
                        50-letnici smrti</hi>, edited by Stanovnik, Branko, Maks Samec, Tanja
                    Peterlin-Neumaier and Željko Oset, 183–88. Ljubljana: Slovenska akademija
                    znanosti in umetnosti and Slovensko kemijsko društvo, 2015.</bibl>
                <bibl>Oset, Željko. “Samec vnovič postane član Slovenske akademije znanosti in
                    umetnosti.” In: <hi rend="italic">Maks Samec (1881–1964): življenje in delo:
                        zbornik ob 50-letnici smrti</hi>, edited by Stanovnik, Branko, Maks Samec,
                    Tanja Peterlin-Neumaier and Željko Oset, 168–72. Ljubljana: Slovenska akademija
                    znanosti in umetnosti and Slovensko kemijsko društvo.</bibl>
                <bibl>Oset, Željko. <hi rend="italic">Zgodovina Slovenske akademije znanosti in
                    umetnosti: razvoj najvišje znanstvene in umetniške ustanove, 1945–1992.</hi>
                    Ljubljana: Slovenska akademija znanosti in umetnosti, 2017.</bibl>
                <bibl>Peterlin Neumaier, Tatjana. “Življenjepis Maksa Samca.” In:
                    <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Maks Samec (1881–1964): življenje in delo: zbornik ob 50-letnici smrti, </hi>edited
                    by Stanovnik, Branko, Maks Samec, Tanja Peterlin-Neumaier and Željko Oset,
                    39–51. Ljubljana: Slovenska akademija znanosti in umetnosti and Slovensko
                    kemijsko društvo, 2015.</bibl>
                <bibl>Peterlin, Anton. “O slovenskem kemiku dr. Mariusu Rebeku.” In:
                    <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Ameriška domovina/American home. </hi>Cleveland,
                    Ohio, 25. 2. 1983.</bibl>
                <bibl><hi style="font-size:10pt" xml:space="preserve">Prinčič, Jože. “Razvoj gospodarstva do sredine petdesetih let.” In: </hi><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:10pt">Slovenska novejša zgodovina: od
                    programa Zedinjene Slovenije do mednarodnega priznanja Republike Slovenije:
                    2</hi><hi style="font-size:10pt">, edited by Fischer, Jasna, Jurij Perovšek,
                        Žarko Lazarević, Ervin Dolenc, Bojan Godeša, Aleš Gabrič, Zdenko Čepič,
                        Nataša Kandus, Igor Zemljič and Mateja Rihtaršič, 965–68. Ljubljana:
                        Inštitut za novejšo zgodovino and Mladinska knjiga, 2005.</hi></bibl>
                <bibl>Puhar, Alenka.
                    <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Izidor Cankar, Mojster dobro zasukanih stavkov: življenje in delo Izidorja Cankarja, 1886–1958. </hi>Ljubljana:
                    Mladinska knjiga, 2016.</bibl>
                <bibl><hi rend="italic">Slovenski poročevalec</hi> 15, No. 140 (1954)<hi rend="italic">.</hi> “Pot do moderne znanstvene ustanove.”</bibl>
                <bibl>Stanovnik, Branko, Maks Samec, Tanja Peterlin-Neumaier and Željko Oset, eds.
                    <hi rend="italic">Maks Samec (1881–1964): življenje in delo: zbornik ob
                        50-letnici smrti.</hi> Ljubljana: Slovenska akademija znanosti in umetnosti
                    and Slovensko kemijsko društvo, 2015.</bibl>
                <bibl>Suhadolc, Anton. <hi rend="italic">Profesor Rihard Zupančič.</hi> Ljubljana:
                    A. Suhadolc, 2011.</bibl>
                <bibl>Vidmar, Milan. <hi rend="italic">Spomini: II.</hi> Maribor: Založba Obzorja,
                    1964.</bibl>
            </listBibl>
            <listBibl>
                <head>Online Sources:</head>
                <bibl>SAZU. “Members of SASA.” Accessed September 10,
                    2018.
                    <ref target="http://www.sazu.si/o-sazu/clani/umrli.html">http://www.sazu.si/o-sazu/clani/umrli.html</ref>.</bibl>
            </listBibl>
     <div type="summary">
         <docAuthor>Željko
                Oset</docAuthor>
            <head><hi rend="allcaps">Maks Samec
                and his adapting to academic standards after World War II</hi></head>
            <head><hi rend="allcaps">Summary</hi></head>
            <p><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve">	In August 1945, Maks Samec lost his </hi><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve">venia docendi </hi><hi style="font-size:12pt">during the post-war purge at the University of Ljubljana
                    but retained a position as researcher till further notice. Thus, he was able to
                    conduct research at the dislocated unit of the university’s chemical institute.
                    Samec and his wife were under threat to be expelled from Yugoslavia to Austria
                    in a group of so-called “Volksdeutschers”. Upon intervention from the Slovenian
                    communist government, Samec (and his wife) was allowed to stay in Ljubljana as
                    an irreplaceable scientist.</hi></p>
            <p><hi style="font-size:12pt"> The Slovenian Prime Minister, Boris
                Kirdič, offered Samec to establish a new chemical institute within the Slovenian
                Academy of Sciences and Arts. New institute should research (primarily the
                production of metallurgical coal from Yugoslavian coals) and at the same time
                trained new, younger generation of researchers. Samec accepted the challenge in
                the new era that was marked by more assertive role of the state in academia, new
                rules of decision-making, lesser autonomy in determine research questions, and
                limitations and collaboration abroad. Even though Samec acknowledge new rules,
                he was still trying to enforce his personal academic standards. Due to his
                success, he was awarded public awards and honors as early as in 1949, moreover,
                he was promoted as role model for excellence and patriotism.</hi></p>
            <p><hi style="font-size:12pt"> In 1959, he was retired during a reform
                in the academia thus a special chemical cabinet was established for him within
                the framework of the Slovenian Academy of Sciences and Arts. He did not take it
                lightly, but he was aware about futility of protests.</hi></p></div>
            <div type="summary" xml:lang="sl">
                <docAuthor><hi style="font-size:12pt">Željko
                Oset</hi></docAuthor>
            <head><hi rend="allcaps">Maks Samec
                in njegovo prilagajanje akademskim standardom po drugi svetovni vojni</hi></head>
            <head><hi rend="allcaps">Povzetek</hi></head>
            <p>	Maks Samec je izgubil <hi rend="italic" style="font-size:12pt">venia
                    docendi</hi><hi style="font-size:12pt" xml:space="preserve"> na Univerzi v Ljubljani med povojno čistko profesorskega kadra; postavljen je bil na razpoloženje, kar pomeni, da je lahko nadaljeval z raziskovalnim delom v dislocirani enoti univerzitetnega kemijskega inštituta. Samcu in njegovi ženi je grozila izselitev iz Jugoslavije v Avstrijo v skupini Volskdeutscherjev, vendar sta bila umaknjena s seznama po intervenciji slovenske vlade. Samec je bil namreč opredeljen kot nenadomestljiv znanstvenik.</hi></p>
            <p><hi style="font-size:12pt"> Predsednik slovenske vlade Boris Kidrič
                je Samca povabil, da ustanovi kemijski inštitut pri Slovenski akademiji znanosti
                in umetnosti, ki bo utemeljen na dveh stebrih: raziskovalno delo (v prvi vrsti
                gre za raziskovalno vprašanje izdelave metalurškega koksa iz jugoslovanskih
                premogov) in vzgoja znanstvenega naraščaja. Samec je sprejel izziv v dobi, ki jo
                je zaznamoval večji vpliv države v akademski skupnosti; nove oblike odločanja,
                manjša avtonomija pri izbiri raziskovalnih vprašanj in omejitve pri mednarodnem
                sodelovanju. Navkljub spremenjenim pogojem je na inštitutu uvedel stroge
                akademske standarde. Zaradi svojega uspešnega raziskovalnega dela in vodenja
                inštituta je že v nekaj letih po drugi svetovni vojni pridobil javna priznanja
                in nagrade. Še več; bil je promoviran kot zgled znanstvene odličnosti in
                patriotizma.</hi></p>
            <p><hi style="font-size:12pt"> Samec je inštitut zapustil leta 1959 po
                izvedeni reformi, raziskovalno delo pa je nadaljeval v zanj ustanovljenem
                kabinetu na Slovenski akademiji znanosti in umetnosti. Spremembo je sprejel kot
                izvršeno dejstvo, zato se ni pritoževal, čeprav ga je odstranitev z inštituta
                osebno prizadela.</hi></p></div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>