<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Ivan Tomas and the Smuggler for the Pope</title>
                <author>
                    <forename>Domagoj</forename>
                    <surname>Tomas</surname>
                    <roleName>Dr</roleName>
                    <roleName>Assistant Professor</roleName>
                    <affiliation>Josip Juraj Strossmayer University of Osijek, Faculty of Humanities
                        and Social Sciences, Department of History</affiliation>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>;</addrLine>
                    </address>
                    <email>dtomas@ffos.hr</email>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>2022-10-27</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>
                    <orgName xml:lang="sl">Inštitut za novejšo zgodovino</orgName>
                    <orgName xml:lang="en">Institute of Contemporary History</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Privoz 11</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>SI-1000 Ljubljana</addrLine>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>http://ojs.inz.si/pnz/article/view/3986</pubPlace>
                <date>2022</date>
                <availability status="free">
                    <licence>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title xml:lang="sl">Prispevki za novejšo zgodovino</title>
                <title xml:lang="en">Contributions to Contemporary History</title>
                <biblScope unit="volume">62</biblScope>
                <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
                <idno type="ISSN">2463-7807</idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source, born digital.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc xml:lang="en">
                <p>Contributions to Contemporary History is one of the central Slovenian scientific
                    historiographic journals, dedicated to publishing articles from the field of
                    contemporary history (the 19th and 20th century).</p>
                <p>The journal is published three times per year in Slovenian and in the following
                    foreign languages: English, German, Serbian, Croatian, Bosnian, Italian, Slovak
                    and Czech. The articles are all published with abstracts in English and
                    Slovenian as well as summaries in English.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <projectDesc xml:lang="sl">
                <p>Prispevki za novejšo zgodovino je ena osrednjih slovenskih znanstvenih
                    zgodovinopisnih revij, ki objavlja teme s področja novejše zgodovine (19. in 20.
                    stoletje).</p>
                <p>Revija izide trikrat letno v slovenskem jeziku in v naslednjih tujih jezikih:
                    angleščina, nemščina, srbščina, hrvaščina, bosanščina, italijanščina, slovaščina
                    in češčina. Članki izhajajo z izvlečki v angleščini in slovenščini ter povzetki
                    v angleščini.</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="sl"/>
                <language ident="en"/>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords xml:lang="en">
                    <term>Ivan Tomas</term>
                    <term>Aloysius Stepinac</term>
                    <term>Frances Yenko Chilcoat</term>
                    <term>communist Yugoslavia</term>
                    <term>church-state relations</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords xml:lang="sl">
                    <term>Ivan Tomas</term>
                    <term>Alojzij Stepinac</term>
                    <term>Frances Yenko Chilcoat</term>
                    <term>komunistična Jugoslavija</term>
                    <term>odnosi med cerkvijo in državo</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change>
                    <date>2022-11-02T08:12:40Z</date>
                    <name>Mihael Ojsteršek</name>
                    <desc>Pretvorba iz DOCX v TEI, dodatno kodiranje</desc>
                </change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <docAuthor>Domagoj Tomas<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn1" n="*">
                    <hi rend="bold">Assistant Professor Dr, Josip Juraj Strossmayer University of
                        Osijek, Faculty of Humanities and Social Sciences, Department of History;
                            <ref target="mailto:dtomas@ffos.hr"
                >dtomas@ffos.hr</ref></hi></note></docAuthor>
            <docImprint>
                <idno type="cobissType">Cobiss tip: 1.01</idno>
                <idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.51663/pnz.62.3.07</idno>
            </docImprint>
            <div type="abstract">
                <head>IZVLEČEK</head>
                <head>IVAN TOMAS IN PAPEŽEVA TIHOTAPKA</head>
                <p><hi rend="italic">V času pontifikata papeža Pija XII (1939–1958) so bili odnosi
                        med Svetim sedežem in evropskimi komunističnimi državami napeti ali
                        prekinjeni. V takšnih okoliščinah je v Federativni ljudski republiki
                        Jugoslaviji (FLRJ) potekal sodni proces proti zagrebškemu nadškofu Alojziju
                        Stepincu, ki se je končal leta 1946, ko je bil obsojen na 16 let zapora. Po
                        prestani petletni zaporni kazni se je Stepinac moral odločiti, ali bo odšel
                        v Rim ali pa bo odslužil preostalo kazen v hišnem priporu v Krašiću, svojem
                        rojstnem kraju. Ko je bil Stepinac leta 1953 imenovan za kardinala, je FLRJ
                        prekinila diplomatske odnose s Svetim sedežem, zaradi česar ni mogel oditi v
                        Rim, da bi prevzel kardinalske insignije.</hi></p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Hrvaški katoliški duhovnik Ivan Tomas je v tistem času delal na
                        Radiu Vatikan v Rimu. Z njegovo pomočjo in s pomočjo ameriške turistke
                        slovenskega rodu Frances Yenko Chilcoat so Stepinčeva kardinalska oblačila
                        po zanimivi in nenavadni poti leta 1954 varno prispela na ozemlje FLRJ.
                        Frances Yenko Chilcoat je svoj podvig opisala v spominih z naslovom Smuggler
                        for the Pope </hi>(Papeževa tihotapka)<hi rend="italic">, ki so izšli leta
                        2006.</hi></p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">V tem prispevku bodo najprej pojasnjene mednarodne politične
                        okoliščine v času prihoda Frances Yenko Chilcoat iz Združenih držav Amerike
                        v Evropo ter cerkveno-državni odnosi med Svetim sedežem in FLRJ po drugi
                        svetovni vojni. Poleg tega bomo preverili pristnost in verodostojnost njenih
                        spominov in trditev ter analizirali Tomasovo vlogo pri pošiljanju
                        kardinalskih oblačil in posledice dejstva, da jih je Stepinac prejel. Na
                        koncu bo podan zaključek o pomenu in pomembnosti popotovanja Stepinčevih
                        kardinalskih oblačil iz Rima v FLRJ v kontekstu sodobnih odnosov med
                        cerkvijo in državo.</hi></p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Ključne besede: Ivan Tomas, Alojzij Stepinac, Frances Yenko
                        Chilcoat, komunistična Jugoslavija, odnosi med cerkvijo in državo</hi></p>
            </div>
            <div type="abstract" xml:lang="en">
                <head>ABSTRACT</head>
                <p><hi rend="italic">During the pontificate of Pope Pius XII (1939–1958), the
                        relations between the Holy See and the European communist countries were
                        either strained or severed. In such circumstances, the trial against the
                        Archbishop of Zagreb Alojzije Stepinac was held in the Federal People’s
                        Republic of Yugoslavia (FPRY). The proceedings were completed in 1946 when
                        Stepinac was sentenced to sixteen years in prison. After five years in
                        prison, he was given the choice of either going to Rome or serving the rest
                        of his sentence under house arrest in his hometown of Krašić. After Stepinac
                        was appointed cardinal in 1953, the FPRY severed its diplomatic relations
                        with the Holy See, while Stepinac lost the opportunity of going to Rome and
                        accepting the cardinal’s insignia.</hi></p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">At the time, the Croatian Catholic priest Ivan Tomas worked at
                        the Vatican Radio in Rome. Tomas’s efforts and the assistance from an
                        American tourist of Slovenian origin, Frances Yenko Chilcoat, resulted in a
                        fascinating and unusual journey of Stepinac’s cardinal robe and its safe
                        arrival to the territory of the FPRY in 1954. Yenko Chilcoat described her
                        endeavour in a memoir titled </hi>Smuggler for the Pope<hi rend="italic">,
                        published in 2006.</hi></p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">This paper will first explain the international political
                        context at the time of Yenko Chilcoat’s arrival from the United States of
                        America to Europe and the church-state relations between the Holy See and
                        the FPRY after World War II. Furthermore, the paper will verify the
                        authenticity of Chilcoat’s memoir and the credibility of her claims, analyse
                        Tomas’s role in the smuggling of the cardinal robe, as well as the
                        consequences of the cardinal robe coming into Stepinac’s possession.
                        Finally, a conclusion will be made about the meaning and importance of
                        Stepinac’s cardinal robe being sent from Rome to the FPRY in the context of
                        contemporaneous church-state relations.</hi></p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Keywords: Ivan Tomas, Aloysius Stepinac, Frances Yenko
                        Chilcoat, communist Yugoslavia, church-state relations</hi></p>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div>
                <head>Introduction</head>
                <p>This paper will attempt to determine the authenticity of the relevant sources and
                    the credibility of the testimony of Frances Yenko Chilcoat, an American of
                    Slovenian origin. In an interesting memoir titled <hi rend="italic">Smuggler for
                        the Pope</hi>,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn2" n="1"><bibl>Frances Yenko
                            Chilcoat, <hi rend="italic">Smuggler for the Pope. A True Story</hi>
                            (San Francisco: California Publishing Company, 2006).</bibl></note> she
                    described the transportation of the Archbishop of Zagreb Alojzije Stepinac’s
                    cardinal robe from Rome to Yugoslavia, which took place with the assistance of
                    the Croatian priest Ivan Tomas in 1954, two years after Stepinac had been
                    appointed cardinal. Furthermore, this development will be put into the context
                    of the church-state relations between the Holy See and the Federal People’s
                    Republic of Yugoslavia (FPRY), which were completely severed at the time.</p>
                <p>Simultaneously, the question of Yenko Chilcoat’s willingness to take the risk of
                    accepting the role of a smuggler and the role of Tomas and the Croatian emigrant
                    clergy in delivering the crimson cardinal robe to Stepinac will be discussed.
                    The potential role of the robe in church-state relations and the question of
                    whether Stepinac publicly wore it and under what circumstances will be answered
                    as well.</p>
                <p>As a specific topic, modern church-state relations have been the subject of
                    historiographical research for some time now. Among the Croatian historians who
                    have dealt with the relations between the Catholic Church and the communist
                    Yugoslavia, we should mention Miroslav Akmadža,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn3"
                        n="2"><bibl>Miroslav Akmadža, <hi rend="italic">Franjo Šeper. Mudrošću
                                protiv jednoumlja</hi> (Zagreb and Rijeka: Društvo za povjesnicu
                            Zagrebačke nadbiskupije “Tkalčić” and Otokar Keršovani, 2009). Miroslav
                            Akmadža, <hi rend="italic">Katolička crkva u komunističkoj Hrvatskoj
                                1945.–1980.</hi> (Zagreb and Slavonski Brod: Despot infinitus and
                            Hrvatski institut za povijest, Podružnica za povijest Slavonije, Srijema
                            i Baranje, 2013). Miroslav Akmadža, <hi rend="italic">Biskupi, komunisti
                                i svećenička udruženja</hi> (Zagreb and Sarajevo: Hrvatski institut
                            za povijest and Synopsis, 2018). Miroslav Akmadža, <hi rend="italic"
                                >Stepinac riječju i djelom</hi> (Zagreb: AGM, 2019) and other
                            works.</bibl></note> Jure Krišto,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn4" n="3"
                            ><bibl>Jure Krišto, <hi rend="italic">Katolička crkva u totalitarizmu
                                1945.–1990.</hi> (Zagreb: Nakladni zavod Globus, 1997). Jure Krišto,
                                <hi rend="italic">Partija, UDBA i svećenička udruženja</hi> (Zagreb:
                            Hrvatska kulturna zaklada – Hrvatsko slovo, 2014). Jure Krišto, <hi
                                rend="italic">Stoljeće naroda i Crkve. Povijest Katoličke Crkve u
                                Hrvatskoj i Bosni i Hercegovini u 20. stoljeću</hi> (Zagreb: Školska
                            knjiga, 2019).</bibl></note> Stipan Trogrlić,<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn5" n="4"><bibl>Stipan Trogrlić, <hi rend="italic">Mons. Božo
                                Milanović istarski svećenik (1890.–1980.). Crkveno-vjersko i
                                javno-političko djelovanje</hi> (Zagreb: Kršćanska sadašnjost,
                            2011). Stipan Trogrlić, <hi rend="italic">Represija jugoslavenskog
                                komunističkog režima prema katoličkoj crkvi u Istri 1945.–1971.</hi>
                            (Pazin and Pula: Državni arhiv u Pazinu and Institut društvenih znanosti
                            Ivo Pilar, Područni centar Pula, 2014).</bibl></note> Marina Beus,<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn6" n="5"><bibl>Marina Beus, <hi rend="italic">Kolar
                                između srpa i čekića. Položaj Katoličke Crkve i odnos komunističke
                                vlasti prema dijecezanskom svećenstvu u Hercegovini u razdoblju od
                                1945. do 1966. godine</hi> (Mostar: Crkva na kamenu,
                        2019).</bibl></note> Margareta Matijević,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn7"
                        n="6"><bibl>Margareta Matijević, <hi rend="italic">“Između partizana i
                                pristojnosti”. Život i doba Svetozara Rittiga (1873.–1961.)</hi>
                            (Zagreb and Slavonski Brod: Plejada and Hrvatski institut za povijest,
                            Podružnica za povijest Slavonije, Srijema i Baranje,
                        2019).</bibl></note> Slađana Josipović Batorek,<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn8" n="7"><bibl>Slađana Josipović Batorek, <hi rend="italic">Sukob
                                i(li) suradnja. Crkveno-državni odnosi u Đakovačkoj i Srijemskoj
                                biskupiji od 1945. do 1959. godine</hi> (Osijek: Oksimoron and
                            Ogranak Matice hrvatske u Osijeku, 2020).</bibl></note> and others.</p>
                <p>At the beginning of this article, a brief review is given of the relations
                    between the Holy See and the European communist countries after World War II,
                    followed by a short explanation of the communists’ persecution of Stepinac and
                    the role of Ivan Tomas in the Croatian programme of Radio Vatican. The article’s
                    conclusion provides an interpretation of the circumstances leading to the
                    smuggling of Stepinac’s cardinal robe into the territory of the FPRY, a feat
                    carried out by Tomas, Yenko Chilcoat, and other parties mentioned by Yenko
                    Chilcoat in her memoir.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>The Holy See and the European Communist Countries after World War II</head>
                <p>The relations between the Holy See and the European communist countries developed
                    after the Allied victory against the Axis powers in World War II, during the
                    time when the global bipolar geopolitical order was formed in which the United
                    States of America (the USA) were dominant in one part of the world and the Union
                    of Soviet Socialist Republics (the USSR) prevailed in the other. The attitude of
                    the Catholic Church towards communism had been clear ever since the 19<hi
                        rend="superscript">th</hi> century,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn9" n="8"
                            ><bibl>The opposition of the Catholic Church against communism was
                            clearly stated in Pope Pius IX encyclical <hi rend="italic">Nostis et
                                nobiscum</hi> (1849) and <hi rend="italic">Quanta cura</hi> (1864),
                            as well as in the social encyclical <hi rend="italic">Rerum novarum</hi>
                            (1891) by Pope Leo XIII.</bibl></note> and it was complicated further
                    following The Decree Against Communism issued by Pope Pius XII in 1949, provoked
                    by the Italian parliamentary election<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn10" n="9"
                            ><bibl>At the 1948 Italian general elections, the Communist – Socialist
                            coalition received 31 % of votes.</bibl></note> and coup d’état in
                        Czechoslovakia.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn11" n="10"><bibl>The Communists
                            came into power in 1948 with a coup d’état, after which they tried to
                            control the Catholic Church by establishing priest associations under
                            the patronage of the regime, regulating the Church finances, and with
                            the mandatory approval of the contents of all pastoral
                        letters.</bibl></note> The political relations between the Holy See and the
                    communist countries thus even exacerbated the tectonics of the Cold War bipolar
                    division of the world.</p>
                <p>Moreover, the post-war period was the time of the intense systemic communist
                    political repression against the Catholic Church and its leaders, who were
                    subject to trials in the European communist countries – for example Josyf Slipy
                    in the USSR, Alojzije Stepinac in the FPRY, József Mindszenty in Hungary, Josef
                    Beran in Czechoslovakia, and Stefan Wyszyński in Poland. Their unfavourable
                    position further complicated and hindered the relations between the Holy See and
                    the European communist countries, already challenged by the serious disputes
                    between communism and Catholicism.</p>
                <p>The processes in question ultimately resulted in the severance of the diplomatic
                    relations between the Holy See and the European communist countries, worsening
                    the position of the Catholics in these countries. Such conditions would later
                    encourage the Holy See to alter its political paradigm towards the European
                    communist countries, i.e. to shape the so-called <hi rend="italic">“Ostpolitik”
                        </hi>policy<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn12" n="11"><bibl><hi rend="italic"
                                >Ostpolitik</hi>, the Vatican policy towards Eastern Europe,
                            attempted to initiate a dialogue between the Holy See and the eastern
                            communist countries. It was shaped during the pontificate of Pope John
                            XXIII (1958–1963), and its architect was Agostino
                        Casaroli.</bibl></note> as a concept which, after the Second Vatican
                    Council, allowed for the coexistence ( <hi rend="italic">modus vivendi</hi>)
                    between the Catholic Church and the communist regimes. The success of this
                    policy is still being disputed today.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn13" n="12"
                            ><bibl>More in: Achille Silvestrini, “Uvod,” in: Agostino Casaroli, <hi
                                rend="italic">Mučeništvo strpljivosti. Sveta Stolica i komunističke
                                zemlje (1963.–1989.)</hi> (Zagreb: Kršćanska sadašnjost, 2001),
                            23–49.</bibl></note></p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>The Case of Alojzije Stepinac and the Severance of the Diplomatic Relations
                    Between the FPRY and the Holy See</head>
                <p>The church-state relations started deteriorating after the first arrest of
                    Archbishop Stepinac by the new government authorities in May 1945, followed by
                    the discussions between Stepinac and Josip Broz Tito in June of the same
                        year.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn14" n="13"><bibl>Akmadža, <hi
                                rend="italic">Katolička crkva u komunističkoj Hrvatskoj
                                1945.–1980.</hi>, 23–27.</bibl></note> However, the real problems
                    for Stepinac and the Catholic Church in the Democratic Federal Yugoslavia
                    started after the Bishops’ Conference of Yugoslavia, which issued a pastoral
                    letter in September 1945. The pastoral was read to the Catholics in the churches
                    throughout the country. It criticised the authorities (noting the murders and
                    arrests of the clergy), the issues of youth education, the appropriation of the
                    Church property, the destruction of graves, the confiscation of the Catholic
                    press and print shops, etc., and called for the complete freedom of all Catholic
                    institutions. The contents of the pastoral letter represented a severe blow for
                    the new authorities, which were preparing for the Constitutional Parliament
                    elections at the time.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn15" n="14"><bibl>Ibid.,
                            32–35.</bibl></note></p>
                <p>Stepinac’s predictions regarding his own arrest after having issued the pastoral
                    letter soon came true, followed by a general media campaign against him
                    personally and against the entire Catholic Church. The head prosecutor Jakov
                    Blažević served as the long arm of Tito’s regime in the trial against Stepinac,
                    who was finally arrested in September 1946.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn16"
                        n="15"><bibl>Ibid., 65–67.</bibl></note></p>
                <p>The trial was brief: as soon as in October 1946, a verdict was reached, and
                    Stepinac was sentenced to sixteen years in prison with forced labour and a
                    five-year suspension of political and civil rights.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn17" n="16"><bibl>Ibid., 77.</bibl></note></p>
                <p>Stepinac was supported by the Holy See’s apostolic delegate in the FPRY Joseph
                    Patrick Hurley, the French intellectuals François Mauriac and Paul Claudel, and
                    many others.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn18" n="17"><bibl>Akmadža, <hi
                                rend="italic">Stepinac riječju i djelom</hi>,
                    115–18.</bibl></note></p>
                <p>After World War II, the FPRY authorities tried to employ various measures to
                    sever or at least weaken the connections between the Catholic Church in the FPRY
                    and the Holy See. Their attempts to form a <hi rend="italic">National
                        Church</hi> under the control of the state encountered fierce opposition
                    from the Catholic bishops, which was blamed on Stepinac as well.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn19" n="18"><bibl>Ibid., 129.</bibl></note></p>
                <p>The issue of Archbishop Stepinac’s imprisonment compromised the Yugoslav
                    government, particularly in the eyes of the international community. Thus, in
                    1951, Tito expressed his willingness to release Archbishop Stepinac from prison
                    provided that he left the FPRY. However, the Holy See refused the offer. Shortly
                    after, Stepinac was transferred from Lepoglava Prison to house arrest in his
                    birthplace of Krašić, subject to Tito’s condition that he could not conduct the
                    duties of the archbishop or any other prominent ecclesiastical functions.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn20" n="19"><bibl>Akmadža, <hi rend="italic"
                                >Katolička crkva u komunističkoj Hrvatskoj 1945.–1980.</hi>, 81,
                            82.</bibl></note></p>
                <p>In November 1952, Radio Vatican announced that Stepinac had been appointed
                    cardinal. Consequently, the FPRY severed its diplomatic relations with the Holy
                        See.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn21" n="20"><bibl>Ibid., 145.</bibl></note>
                    Those relations had been previously challenged by the matters of Trieste<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn22" n="21"><bibl>The Yugoslav government blamed the
                            Holy See for its contribution to the decision of the London Conference
                            regarding Trieste in 1952, accusing it of pursuing Italian national
                            policy.</bibl></note> and the class-based priest associations,<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn23" n="22"><bibl>Some bishops, including Archbishop
                            Stepinac, immediately opposed the foundation and work of class-based
                            priest associations, while others tolerated it, and they were one of the
                            main reasons for the deterioration of the relations between the Holy See
                            and the FPRY. The 1950 Bishops’ Conference of Yugoslavia stated that it
                            was “not recommended” (<hi rend="italic">Non expedit</hi>) to take part
                            in such associations, while in 1952, the priests were unanimously
                            forbidden (<hi rend="italic">Non licet</hi>) from joining such
                            associations.</bibl></note> so Stepinac’s appointment was the last straw
                    that resulted in the complete cessation of diplomatic relations.</p>
                <p>Afterwards, the FPRY authorities hoped – encouraged by Svetozar Rittig’s
                        estimates<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn24" n="23"><bibl>Svetozar Rittig
                            (1873–1961), a Croatian priest, historian, and politician. He studied
                            theology in Sarajevo, Đakovo, and Vienna, where he attained a doctorate
                            in 1902. Until 1911, he taught ecclesiastical history at the seminary in
                            Đakovo, after which he was a secretary at the Archdiocese of Zagreb, a
                            professor at the Faculty of Theology in Zagreb, and the editor of the
                            Catholic newspaper <hi rend="italic">Katolički list</hi> (1912–1913). He
                            became politically active in 1908 as a member of the Croatian Party of
                            Rights in the Croatian Parliament. In 1918, he was a member of the
                            National Council of the State of Slovenes, Croats and Serbs, while from
                            1919 to 1920, he was a member of the Temporary National Representation.
                            When the Independent State of Croatia was established, he moved to
                            Selce, where he established contacts with the representatives of the
                            national liberation movement. In 1943, he was a member of the ZAVNOH
                            (National Anti-Fascist Council of the People’s Liberation of Croatia),
                            between 1944 and 1954 the president of the Commission for Religious
                            Affairs, while in 1945, he became a member of the Constituent Assembly
                            and then the Federal Assembly and the Croatian Parliament. In 1946, he
                            was appointed a minister without portfolio in the Croatian Government
                            (until his retirement in 1954). He encouraged the revival of the Old
                            Church Slavonic Academy (1948), which was renamed as the Old Church
                            Slavonic Institute in 1952. He was the Institute’s director until 1961.
                            In 1947, he was elected a full member of the JAZU (the Yugoslav Academy
                            of Sciences and Arts).</bibl></note> – that Stepinac’s appointment as a
                    cardinal would result in his departure to Rome, which would be in line with the
                    interests of the FPRY. However, Stepinac wanted to stay with his people, so he
                    decided to remain under house arrest in Krašić.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn25"
                        n="24"><bibl>Akmadža, <hi rend="italic">Stepinac riječju i djelom</hi>, 130,
                            131.</bibl></note> At that time, Tito saw Stepinac as “a pawn in the
                    game of Vatican’s international politics, primarily in Central Europe and
                    especially in Yugoslavia.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn26" n="25"><bibl>Peđa
                            Radosavljević, <hi rend="italic">Odnosi između Jugoslavije i Svete
                                Stolice 1963–1978.</hi> (Beograd: Službeni glasnik, 2012),
                            33.</bibl></note></p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Ivan Tomas and Radio Vatican</head>
                <p>After having served as a secretary of the Diocese of Skopje under Bishop Smiljan
                    Franjo Čekada, Ivan Tomas,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn27" n="26"><bibl>Ivan
                            Tomas (1911–1992), a priest of the Diocese of Mostar-Duvno. He attended
                            the grammar school in Stolac (1924–1925) and Travnik (1925–1932). In
                            1937, he graduated from the Faculty of Theology in Sarajevo. He was
                            ordained as a priest in 1937. He ran the parishes in Prenj and Šipovača
                            in Herzegovina, while since 1940, he served as the secretary of Bishop
                            Smiljan Franjo Čekada in Skopje. In 1941, he left for Rome for his
                            postgraduate studies and attained a doctorate in 1951 at the Gregoriana.
                            In the meantime, he also earned a degree in archivistics, diplomacy, and
                            palaeography. After World War II, he helped Croatian and other refugees
                            in Rome. From 1954 to 1962, he worked at Radio Vatican as the editor and
                            radio presenter of the Croatian programme and resided at the College of
                            St. Jerome until 1961. Since 1961, he lived at the Blessed Nikola
                            Tavelić House in Grottaferrata near Rome. He was the editor of the
                            magazines <hi rend="italic">Travničko smilje</hi> (1932), <hi
                                rend="italic">Blagovijest</hi> (1940–1941), and <hi rend="italic"
                                >Novi život</hi> (1962–1970). He wrote many articles about Croatian
                            history, culture, and the role of the clergy in the formation of the
                            national and world cultural history. He wrote for the Croatian emigrant
                            publications (<hi rend="italic">Glasnik Srca Isusova i Marijina</hi>,
                                <hi rend="italic">Hrvatska revija</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Studia
                                Croatica</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Križ</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
                                >Danica</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Naša nada</hi>, and others). See:
                            Vlado Šakić and Ljiljana Dobrovšak, eds., <hi rend="italic">Leksikon
                                hrvatskoga iseljeništva i manjina</hi> (Zagreb: Institut društvenih
                            znanosti Ivo Pilar and Hrvatska matica iseljenika, 2020),
                        994.</bibl></note> a priest of the Diocese of Mostar-Duvno, arrived in Rome
                    in 1941 for his postgraduate studies. He attained his doctorate in 1951 and then
                    worked at Radio Vatican as the editor and radio presenter of the Croatian
                    programme between 1954 and 1962.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn28" n="27"
                            ><bibl>Radio Vatican started broadcasting in 1931, while the Croatian
                            programme, aired twice per week, was introduced in 1947, mainly due to
                            the efforts of Juraj Magjerec and Ivo Omrčanin. The programme’s first
                            presenter was the writer Ljubo Wiesner, but he was soon replaced by the
                            priest Pavao Jesih (1947–1954), who worked as an editor, host, and
                            reporter. In 1954, Ivan Tomas took over the position. The programme was
                            later aired five times a week and then finally on a daily basis. Later,
                            its chief editors were Jesuits, Stjepan Tumbas being the first. Every
                            day, Radio Vatican’s Croatian programme would broadcast reports from the
                            Vatican and the world and discuss the religious, social, and political
                            events in Croatia, Bosnia and Herzegovina, and among the Croatian
                            emigration. See: Šakić and Dobrovšak, eds., <hi rend="italic">Leksikon
                                hrvatskoga iseljeništva i manjina</hi>, 873.</bibl></note> From his
                    arrival in Rome until 1961, Tomas resided at the Pontifical Croatian College of
                    St. Jerome. At the end of 1961 – as a result of mutual diplomatic initiatives
                    and concessions whose goal was to initiate formal negotiations about the
                    normalisation of the relations between the Holy See and the FPRY – Tomas was
                    forced to leave the College of St. Jerome as well as his post at Radio Vatican
                    due to Vatican’s response to one of the demands of the Yugoslav government,
                    which tried to depoliticise the College of St. Jerome.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn29" n="28"><bibl>Miroslav Akmadža, <hi rend="italic">Katolička
                                crkva u Hrvatskoj i komunistički režim 1945.–1966.</hi> (Rijeka:
                            Otokar Keršovani, 2004), 189, 190.</bibl></note> The Yugoslav demands
                    were listed and substantiated in a document titled <hi rend="italic">Kratak
                        istorijat Zavoda sv. Jeronima u Rimu, njegova uloga i sadašnje
                        stanje</hi>,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn30" n="29"><bibl>HR-HDA-310, box
                            44, Pov. 159/1-1961.</bibl></note> even though Tomas and Krunoslav
                        Draganović<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn31" n="30"><bibl>Krunoslav
                            Draganović (1903–1983), a Croatian priest, historian, and politician. He
                            studied at the Faculty of Theology in Sarajevo and was ordained as a
                            priest in 1928. In 1932, he went to Rome, where he attained a doctorate
                            at the Pontifical Oriental Institute in 1935. He became an assistant
                            professor in 1940 and a full professor at the Faculty of Theology in
                            Zagreb in 1942. Since 1943, he was a part of the Croatian diplomatic
                            post at the Holy See. After World War II, he stayed in Rome and was
                            active in the Croatian political emigrant circles until 1948. He moved
                            to Austria in 1960, while in 1967, he returned to Sarajevo under
                            mysterious circumstances. As a historian, he primarily dealt with the
                            issues of the Catholic Church in Bosnia and Herzegovina.</bibl></note>
                    had been named as the key threats to the relations between the FPRY and the Holy
                    See at the meeting of the Yugoslav Federal Commission for Religious Affairs back
                    in 1956.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn32" n="31"><bibl>Radmila Radić, <hi
                                rend="italic">Država i verske zajednice 1945–1970., drugi deo:
                                1954–1970.</hi> (Beograd: Institut za noviju istoriju Srbije, 2002),
                            426.</bibl></note></p>
                <p>While he was working at Radio Vatican, Tomas first ensured that the number of
                    Croatian radio broadcasts was increased to five a week in 1955 and later to
                    every day. As he was openly patriotic, the Croatian programme paid considerable
                    attention to historical topics as well as to the contemporaneous political
                    situation in the FPRY and around the world. Stepinac’s work inspired Tomas and
                    represented one of his favourite topics, which was particularly annoying for the
                    communist regime in the FPRY.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn33" n="32"
                            ><bibl>Domagoj Tomas, <hi rend="italic">Pet redaka. Rimski dnevnik
                                svećenika Ivana Tomasa (1943.–1944.)</hi> (Rim, Mostar, and Osijek:
                            Papinski hrvatski zavod svetog Jeronima u Rimu, Biskupski ordinarijat
                            Mostar, and Odjel za kulturologiju Sveučilišta Josipa Jurja
                            Strossmayera, 2014), 37.</bibl></note></p>
                <p>According to the sources in the Archive of the Ministry of Foreign Affairs of the
                    Republic of Serbia, the Tanjug news agency dedicated a special monitoring unit
                    for Radio Vatican,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn34" n="33"><bibl>The Telegraph
                            Agency of the New Yugoslavia (Tanjug) was a news agency founded in 1943.
                            Its primary task was to inform the public of the national liberation
                            movement’s activities in Yugoslavia. It was the sole privileged news
                            agency in the Democratic Federal Yugoslavia/Federal People’s Republic of
                            Yugoslavia/Socialist Federal Republic of Yugoslavia.</bibl></note> and
                    according to Peđa Radosavljević, Tomas’s editorial policy was under attack by
                    the FPRY authorities.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn35" n="34"
                            ><bibl>Radosavljević, <hi rend="italic">Odnosi između Jugoslavije i
                                Svete Stolice 1963–1978</hi>, 54, 55.</bibl></note></p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Frances Yenko Chilcoat – an American Tourist and Smuggler</head>
                <p>Frances Yenko,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn36" n="35"><bibl>Frances Yenko
                            Chilcoat, the daughter of Angela (née Bozner) and Cyril Yenko, married
                            Aaron Chilcoat in 1951. When her ancestors had immigrated to the USA,
                            they started using the Anglophone version of their surname, Yenko,
                            instead of Jenko, their original Slovenian surname.</bibl></note> an
                    American of Slovenian origin, grew up in a small town of Rock Springs<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn37" n="36"><bibl>Rock Springs, a small town in
                            Wyoming, in the western United States. According to the 2010, the town’s
                            population was around 20,000, while before the 1950s, it had been less
                            than 10,000.</bibl></note> in a family actively involved in the local
                    Slovenian Catholic community gathered around the Saints Cyril and Methodius
                    Catholic Church. At the time, the parish priest and spiritual advisor of the
                    Slovenian and Croatian community was a Slovenian by the name of Albin Gnidovec.
                    Thanks to her father’s persistent tutoring, Frances learned to read and speak
                        Slovenian.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn38" n="37"><bibl>Yenko Chilcoat,<hi
                                rend="italic"> Smuggler for the Pope</hi>, 2.</bibl></note></p>
                <p>Frances Yenko lived in Salt Lake City for a while before moving to San Francisco
                    at the age of 19, when she accepted a tempting business offer by the airplane
                    company United Airlines. When Gnidovec learned of this, he asked the Slovenian
                    priest Vital Vodušek, who worked in San Francisco, to look after Frances and
                    take her “under his wing”.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn39" n="38"><bibl>Ibid.,
                            15, 16.</bibl></note></p>
                <p>Soon after she had accepted the job in 1947 and moved to San Francisco, Frances
                    Yenko married Aaron Chilcoat. On Vodušek’s recommendation, she provided boarding
                    for the Croatian political emigrant Ivan Ivanković. For a while, she and her
                    husband looked after Ivanković, and through him, she got in touch with
                        Tomas.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn40" n="39"><bibl>Ibid.,
                        20–25.</bibl></note></p>
                <p>After working as an employee of United Airlines for nine and a half years, in
                    1954, Frances Yenko Chilcoat received a thirty-day travel pass, which she could
                    use to go anywhere in the world. She decided to fulfil her lifelong dream of
                    visiting Slovenia, at the time a part of the FPRY under the name of the People’s
                    Republic of Slovenia. Being an active Merchant Marine, her husband refused to
                    travel to a communist country, so she invited Grace Norton, her friend and
                    co-worker from United Airlines, to join her, which she accepted. Frances then
                    faced a painstaking procedure of acquiring a visa to visit the FPRY, where she
                    planned to visit her relatives in the People’s Republic of Slovenia.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn41" n="40"><bibl>Ibid., 20–27.</bibl></note></p>
                <p>After answering “many questions in a lengthy questionnaire from the Yugoslav
                    Consulate’s office in San Francisco”,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn42" n="41"
                            ><bibl>Ibid., 27.</bibl></note> as she states in her memoir, she finally
                    obtained a visa. In her memoir, she also underlines the role of the Consul
                    General at the time,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn43" n="42"><bibl>Based on the
                            testimony of Yenko Chilcoat, the Consul General was either Rafo
                            Ivančević or Branko Karađole. Ivančević was officially appointed the
                            Yugoslav Consul General on 21 March 1950. See: <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                                Consular Offices in the United States. April 1, 1950</hi>
                            (Washington: United States Government Printing Office, 1950), 48. Apart
                            from Ivančević, Siniša Košutić and Miodrag Vitorović were appointed as
                            the Consul General and the Vice-consul of the FPRY in San Francsico on 8
                            August 1951. See: <hi rend="italic">Foreign Consular Offices in the
                                United States. April 1, 1954</hi> (Washington: United States
                            Government Printing Office, 1954), 48. On 2 June 1954, Branko Karađole
                            replaced Ivančević as Consul General. See: <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                                Consular Offices in the United States. April 1, 1957</hi>
                            (Washington: United States Government Printing Office, 1957),
                        50.</bibl></note> in her opinion a Serb, who clearly cautioned her during
                    the interview “to comply with the Communist rule”<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn44" n="43"><bibl>Yenko Chilcoat,<hi rend="italic"> Smuggler for
                                the Pope</hi>, 27.</bibl></note> in the FPRY, otherwise she could go
                    to prison despite the fact that she and her mother had been born in the
                        USA.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn45" n="44"><bibl>Ibid., 27,
                        28.</bibl></note></p>
                <p>Frances Yenko Chilcoat also did not want to miss the opportunity of seeing Rome.
                    Quite surprisingly, Tomas met the two Americans at the airport on 14 November
                    1954. He continued to keep them company every day during their four-day stay in
                    Rome. “He wined and dined” them, pleasantly surprising Frances, who was
                    accustomed to people taking care of priests rather than the other way
                        around.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn46" n="45"><bibl>Ibid.,
                        28–31.</bibl></note></p>
                <p>On her last evening in Rome, as she was packing for the trip to the FPRY, Yenko
                    Chilcoat noticed that a piece of her Samsonite luggage had been damaged. A part
                    of a broken metal strip was dangling from the side of the suitcase, and the
                    hotel staff was unable to solve the problem. Around that time, Tomas phoned
                    Frances, suggesting that they meet in the hotel lobby. According to Yenko
                    Chilcoat, “he seemed rather anxious”, and she agreed to the meeting even though
                    she was tired and in the middle of packing. After Tomas’s arrival, she noticed
                    that he looked quite different than usual. He was wearing a black hat with the
                    brim pulled down. The collar of his long black coat was up and he was carrying a
                    black suitcase, conveying an impression of a person who was trying to avoid
                    recognition and acting suspiciously.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn47" n="46"
                            ><bibl>Ibid., 31, 32.</bibl></note></p>
                <p>After Yenko Chilcoat and Tomas sat at the table next to each other, he put the
                    small suitcase between them and ordered two double brandies, which Yenko
                    Chilcoat drank only after his insistence and due to his authority as a
                        priest.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn48" n="47"><bibl>Ibid.,
                        32.</bibl></note></p>
                <p>Tomas then told her the story of Cardinal Stepinac and his imprisonment in the
                    communist FPRY, explaining that his cardinal robe was in the small suitcase
                    between them. He also mentioned that Stepinac was the spiritual leader of seven
                    million Catholics in the FPRY and that he had become universally known for his
                    resistance to Communism. After serving five (out of sixteen) years of
                    imprisonment, he had been put in house arrest in his birthplace of Krašić.
                    There, he was appointed cardinal, but his confinement prevented him from
                    travelling to Rome to receive his cardinal vesture (a red robe and a galero).
                    Moreover, he knew that if he departed to Rome, he would never be allowed to
                    return to the FPRY, and he did not want to abandon his people.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn49" n="48"><bibl>Ibid., 32–34.</bibl></note></p>
                <p>When he finished explaining Stepinac’s role, Tomas asked Yenko Chilcoat to take
                    the cardinal robe to Stepinac in the name of the Catholic Church (“Frances, in
                    this suitcase, I have the robe for Cardinal Stepinac. We – meaning the Church,
                    F. Y. C. – are asking you to take this robe to him”). The only way Stepinac
                    would ever be able to receive the robe was if someone who was travelling as a
                    tourist could smuggle it into the FPRY,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn50" n="49"
                            ><bibl>Ibid., 34, 35.</bibl></note> and Yenko Chilcoat fitted that role
                    perfectly.</p>
                <p>At first, Frances turned down Tomas’s proposition, afraid of ending up in prison,
                    which was something that the Yugoslav Consul General in San Francisco had
                    actually warned her about. However, after kindly assuring her of the support and
                    prayers of the Bishops, the Cardinals, and Pope Pius XII himself, Tomas finally
                    managed to encourage and convince her that the task was feasible, adding that
                    only communists could enter and leave the FPRY and that she was the only person
                    trustworthy enough to deliver the cardinal robe to Stepinac.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn51" n="50"><bibl>Ibid., 35, 36.</bibl></note></p>
                <p>In any case, Chilcoat’s fear of what might happen to her if they found Stepinac’s
                    cardinal robe in her possession when she was crossing the Italian-Yugoslav
                    border was completely justified. Indeed, the FPRY criminal code at the time
                    provided for prosecution and three-year maximum security imprisonment or a death
                    penalty for those “who transported armed groups, individual terrorists, spies,
                    agitators, weapons, ammunition, or propaganda material into the territory of the
                    FPRY” (Article 111), while maximum security imprisonment awaited those “who
                    intentionally undermined the government of the working people, the defensive
                    capability of the country, the economic foundations of socialism, or those who
                    intended to destroy the brotherhood and unity of the FPRY by drawing, writing,
                    publicly speaking, or disseminating materials against the government, the social
                    system, or any other political, economic, military, and other important national
                    regulations” (Article 118).<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn52" n="51"
                            ><bibl>“Krivični zakonik,” <hi rend="italic">Službeni list Federativne
                                Narodne Republike Jugoslavije</hi> 7, No. 13 (1951): 197,
                            198.</bibl></note> Importing the publications of the political
                    emigration into the FPRY was considered smuggling enemy propaganda material, and
                    the enforcement of the regular criminal code can be seen in the examples of
                    Bruno Bušić,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn53" n="52"><bibl>Anđelko Mijatović,
                                <hi rend="italic">Bruno Bušić: prilog istraživanju života i
                                djelovanja (1939.–1978.)</hi> (Zagreb: Školska knjiga, 2010), 82,
                            83.</bibl></note> Janjko Sarajlić,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn54"
                        n="53"><bibl>More in: Ivica Miškulin, “Neprijatelj države iz Okučana: slučaj
                            političkog zatvorenika i emigranta Janjka Sarajlića,” <hi rend="italic"
                                >Scrinia Slavonica</hi> 19, No. 1 (2019): 241–69.</bibl></note>
                    Krešo Barišić,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn55" n="54"><bibl>Okružni sud u
                            Mostaru, nr. K. 72/70, Rješenje o produljenju pritvora za optuženoga
                            Krešu Barišića, Mostar, 4. lipnja 1970.; Vrhovni sud Bosne i
                            Hercegovine, nr. K.605/70, Presuda Kreši Barišiću i odbijenica na žalbu,
                            Sarajevo, 2. rujna 1970. (both documents in the private possession of
                            Krešo Barišić were presented to the author of the article, with consent
                            to use them for scientific purposes)</bibl></note> and many others. In
                    1974, a special legislative framework was introduced dealing with importing and
                    distributing foreign publications in the Yugoslav territory.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn56" n="55"><bibl>“Zakon o unošenju i raspačavanju inozemnih
                            sredstava masovnog komuniciranja i o inozemnoj informativnoj djelatnosti
                            u Jugoslaviji,” <hi rend="italic">Službeni list Socijalističke
                                Federativne Republike Jugoslavije</hi> 30, No. 39 (1974):
                            1290–300.</bibl></note></p>
                <p>Furthermore, prosecution and maximum security imprisonment awaited “the citizens
                    of the Federal People’s Republic of Yugoslavia whose intention was to take down
                    the government and the social system or to carry out other hostile activities
                    against the Federal People’s Republic of Yugoslavia by contacting a foreign
                    country, a foreign organisation, a certain party or an exile group, or by
                    helping such organisations carry out hostile activities” (Article 109).<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn57" n="56"><bibl>“Krivični zakonik,” <hi
                                rend="italic">Službeni list Federativne Narodne Republike
                                Jugoslavije</hi> 7, No. 13 (1951): 197.</bibl></note> The law was
                    put into practice in the case of Bušić, Franjo Tuđman, and Dragutin Škućanac,
                    who were accused of contacting several well-known political emigrants.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn58" n="57"><bibl>Wollfy Krašić, <hi rend="italic"
                                >Hrvatsko proljeće i hrvatska politička emigracija</hi> (Zagreb:
                            Školska knjiga, 2018), 346.</bibl></note></p>
                <p>The same thing would have undoubtedly happened to Yenko if the connection between
                    her and Tomas had been discovered. In the Yugoslav sources, Tomas was described
                    as “the Ustasha priest”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn59" n="58"><bibl>Akmadža,
                                <hi rend="italic">Katolička crkva u Hrvatskoj i komunistički režim
                                1945.–1966.</hi>, 184.</bibl></note> and a member of “the Ustasha
                        emigration”,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn60" n="59"><bibl>HR-HDA-310, box
                            38, Pov. 70/1-1958.</bibl></note> although no evidence has ever been
                    found that he was a member of the Ustasha movement. Moreover, the fact that
                    Tomas was in the service of the Holy See while the diplomatic relations between
                    the FPRY and the Holy See were severed would make Frances’s position even more
                    difficult. Consequently, the attempt to smuggle Stepinac’s cardinal robe into
                    the FPRY would be particularly incriminating at the time of the severed
                    diplomatic relations between the FPRY and the Holy See and Stepinac’s house
                    arrest.</p>
                <p>After she found out what Frances had agreed to do, her American companion Norton
                    tried to talk her out of it, pointing out how dangerous such smuggling was, but
                    Yenko Chilcoat managed to convince her of the righteousness of the mission.
                    After Tomas folded the robe very neatly into the suitcase and made it look like
                    a red blouse, he informed Yenko Chilcoat that she was not to speak Slovenian on
                    the train but to insist on communication only in English. He also advised both
                    of them to deny all knowledge of the cardinal robe should it be discovered
                    during luggage inspection and not to speak a word of their mission, not even to
                    their families after they returned to the USA.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn61"
                        n="60"><bibl>Yenko Chilcoat,<hi rend="italic"> Smuggler for the Pope</hi>,
                            36, 37.</bibl></note></p>
                <p>The two Americans travelled through Trieste and were inspected by the Yugoslav
                    Military near the Yugoslav border. When a Yugoslav inspector asked them to pull
                    their luggage from the overhead rack, Norton responded in English, using her
                    hands to point at the luggage and at him, implying that he should take it down
                    himself if he wanted to inspect it. After he tried to reach for the Samsonite
                    suitcase with the robe in it, the inspector cut himself on the edge of a broken
                    metal strip. He started bleeding profusely, so he left the compartment and never
                    returned to complete the search.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn62" n="61"
                            ><bibl>Ibid., 39–41.</bibl></note></p>
                <p>When they arrived in Ljubljana, Yenko Chilcoat and Norton boarded another train
                    for Škofja Loka, where they were graciously welcomed by Yenko Chilcoat’s uncle
                    Ivan Jenko and other relatives. On the evening of the day they arrived in the
                    nearby village of Pungert, Manca Jenko, Frances’s single aunt, appeared. She
                    lived and worked with the nuns<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn63" n="62"
                            ><bibl>Most likely the Ursuline Convent of Škofja Loka. In 1954 the
                            convent and school buildings were expropriated. More in: “<hi
                                rend="italic">Zgodovina -” Uršulinke Rimske Unije</hi>, accessed
                                30<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> October 2021, <ref
                                target="https://www.ursulinke.si/zgodovina/"
                                >https://www.ursulinke.si/zgodovina/</ref></bibl></note> who lived
                    nearby. When she entered the room, she sat down next to Yenko Chilcoat and asked
                    her if she had brought anything special. Then they went to the bedroom, where
                    she asked her if Frances had brought anything from Rome. Yenko Chilcoat
                    understood the hint and handed her the suitcase.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn64" n="63"><bibl>Ibid., 43, 44.</bibl></note></p>
                <p>Manca Jenko took the cardinal robe out of the suitcase, put it into a homemade
                    cloth bag, and went for a walk with Yenko Chilcoat. While they were walking
                    along the dark streets hand in hand, the two women started singing Slovenian
                    songs, which Yenko Chilcoat had learned from her father as a small child. After
                    about twenty or thirty minutes of walking, they heard a male voice ahead of
                    them. While the was passing by, Manca Jenko reached out, hanging the cardinal
                    robe to a man completely unknown to Yenko Chilcoat. They returned to Ivan
                    Jenko’s house, refraining from mentioning the robe or Cardinal Stepinac. Soon
                    after, Yenko Chilcoat and Norton returned to the USA, visiting Brussels on their
                    way home.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn65" n="64"><bibl>Ibid.,
                        44–49.</bibl></note></p>
                <p>After returning to the USA, Yenko Chilcoat received a postcard from Tomas stating
                    “mission accomplished”. Soon after the postcard had arrived, two strangers rang
                    Yenko Chilcoat’s doorbell, claiming they were two countrymen from Yugoslavia.
                    Yenko openly asked them whether she had met them on her travels there, but they
                    mysteriously answered “maybe”. After a bit of small talk, she telephoned her
                    husband and asked him to return home from work. When he arrived, he asked them
                    why they were in San Francisco, and they claimed to be shopping for “rope”.
                    After they left, Aaron Chilcoat was not sure if they said “rope” or “robe”.
                    Yenko Chilcoat and her husband had no idea whether the two men were friends or
                    enemies trying to extract information about the precious cargo transported from
                    Rome to the FPRY. Finally, Yenko Chilcoat claims that she did not reveal the
                    information about the smuggling of the cardinal robe to anyone in the USA other
                    than her husband.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn66" n="65"><bibl>Ibid., 51,
                            52.</bibl></note></p>
                <p>The Croatian public knew nothing about Yenko Chilcoat smuggling Stepinac’s
                    cardinal robe to the FPRY until she published her memoir <hi rend="italic"
                        >Smuggler for the Pope. </hi>However, the book did not enjoy a considerable
                    media response in Croatia, while it was somewhat successful in the USA,
                    especially in the Catholic press,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn67" n="66"
                            ><bibl>See: Dan Morris-Young, “Local parishioner records adventure as
                            ‘Smuggler for the Pope,’” <hi rend="italic">Catholic San Francisco</hi>,
                            19 December 2008, 24.</bibl></note> which had shared the untold story
                    even before the book was published.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn68" n="67"
                            ><bibl>First published in <hi rend="italic">San Mateo County Times</hi>
                            in December 1998 and in <hi rend="italic">Catholic San Francisco</hi> at
                            the beginning of 1999, and then in the following newspapers: Abby
                            Williams, “Wyoming native recalls smuggling adventure,” <hi
                                rend="italic">Casper Star-Tribune</hi>, 3 May 1999, 4, 5. “Woman
                            recounts role as robe smuggler,” <hi rend="italic">The Daily
                                Sentinel</hi>, 1 May 1999, 10. “Rock Springs native recounts robe
                            smuggling,” <hi rend="italic">The Billings Gazette</hi>, 16 May 1999,
                            25.</bibl></note></p>
                <p>Apart from the memoir, sources (diary entries) exist as a part of Ivan Tomas’s
                    legacy dealing with the period in which the cardinal robe was delivered from
                    Rome to the FPRY. As such, these entries could provide additional information
                    about the event, but they were not available to the author of this article.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn69" n="68"><bibl>Arhiv Biskupskoga ordinarijata u
                            Mostaru, Ostavština Ivana Tomasa, Dnevnici.</bibl></note></p>
                <p>Friar Dominik Mandić’s legacy was also researched to determine the potential
                    existence of any additional information about the organisational circumstances
                    of Stepinac’s cardinal robe being sent from Rome to Yugoslavia among the
                    prominent individuals among the Croatian emigrant clergy.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn70" n="69"><bibl>Mandić’s correspondence with Tomas between 1952
                            and 1956 was analysed.</bibl></note> Despite the existence of some
                    correspondence between Mandić and Tomas between 1953 and 1956, the content of
                    the letters does not reveal any further details about the event.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn71" n="70"><bibl>Arhiv Hercegovačke franjevačke
                            provincije, Ostavština fra Dominika Mandića, box 5, “Vlč. Dru Ivanu
                            Tomas” (a letter by Friar Dominik Mandić), Rome, 25 April 1953; box 5,
                            “Dragi Mnogopoštovani” (a letter by Ivan Tomas), Rome, 1 August 1953;
                            box 6, “Mnogopoštovani Oče!” (a letter by Ivan Tomas), Rome, 1 August
                            1954; box 6, “Mnogopoštovani!” (a letter by Ivan Tomas), Rome, 6
                            December 1954; box 6, “Rev. dr. Ivan Tomas, Roma, Italy.” (a letter by
                            Friar Dominik Mandić), Chicago, 4 December 1955; box 6, “Dragi
                            Mnogopoštovani!” (a letter by Ivan Tomas), Rome, 18 December
                            1956.</bibl></note></p>
                <p>In his <hi rend="italic">Journal</hi>, Josip Vraneković, a priest in Krašić
                    during Stepinac’s house arrest, never explicitly mentioned the circumstances of
                    Stepinac’s cardinal robe being brought into the FPRY during the relevant period
                    in 1954,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn72" n="71"><bibl>Josip Vraneković, <hi
                                rend="italic">Dnevnik: život u Krašiću zasužnjenog nadbiskupa i
                                kardinala Alojzija Stepinca (5. XII. 1951. – 10. II. 1960.)</hi>
                            (Zagreb: Postulatura blaženoga Alojzija Stepinca, 2011),
                        250–362.</bibl></note> even though, at one point, he noted Stepinac’s dream
                    about his installation ceremony in Rome, during which he put on a red cardinal
                        robe.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn73" n="72"><bibl>Vraneković, <hi
                                rend="italic">Dnevnik</hi>, 270.</bibl></note> Furthermore, in the
                    log entry of 30 July 1954, an interesting remark made by Stepinac can be found,
                    mentioning the possibility of receiving the cardinal robe in Zagreb.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn74" n="73"><bibl>“While we were taking a walk, he
                            mentioned that a certain man had visited Cardinal Initzer the other day
                            and told him that Cardinal Stepinac would soon be able to go to Zagreb
                            to receive the crimson robe. Then he added: “It might be so, but the
                            only thing I would like to live to see was the priest who would be my
                            successor. I believe that my mission is not to be the hammer but rather
                            the anvil upon which the executioners’ blows – those of the enemies of
                            the Church – will shatter.” See: Vraneković, <hi rend="italic"
                                >Dnevnik</hi>, 337.</bibl></note> This information was, by all
                    accounts, passed on to him by the Archbishop of Vienna Theodor Innitzer. Even
                    though this period is chronologically close and thus intriguing, it would be
                    unfounded to claim, based on only a single note, that the information is in any
                    way related to Frances Yenko Chilcoat smuggling the cardinal robe from Rome to
                    the FPRY. Thus, the context of Stepinac’s remark remains unclarified.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Conclusion</head>
                <p>Despite her well-founded concerns, Yenko Chilcoat apparently managed to smuggle
                    Stepinac’s red cardinal robe across the Italian-Yugoslav border. Keeping in mind
                    the severance of the diplomatic relations between the FPRY and the Holy See,
                    caused precisely by Stepinac’s appointment as cardinal, the vestment would have
                    been confiscated had it been discovered by the border control when Frances
                    entered the Yugoslav territory. Moreover, criminal sanctions would have been
                    imposed on her if her contacts with Tomas had been discovered, as the official
                    sources in the FPRY considered the priest a member of the hostile emigration. In
                    any case, the regular criminal code of the time provided for imprisonment in the
                    case of smuggling hostile propaganda materials. According to the notes contained
                    in her memoir, Frances was well aware of the risk she was taking, which was
                    intensified by the vivid memory of the unpleasant conversation she had
                    experienced at the Yugoslav consulate in San Francisco before her trip to
                    Europe.</p>
                <p>The successful delivery of the cardinal robe to the territory of the FPRY also
                    attested to the porosity of the Yugoslav border when it came to the smuggling of
                    undesirable goods from the West during the Cold War period, as well as to the
                    abilities of the Holy See – i.e., to the creativity and connections that the
                    Croatian emigrant clergy could employ to carry out classified and risky
                    tasks.</p>
                <p>The authenticity of Yenko Chilcoat’s memoir has been verified in multiple places
                    and is publicly available in online databases, where <hi rend="italic">Smuggler
                        for the Pope </hi>is listed as a self-published copyrighted work. All in
                    all, it is undoubtedly an authentic work.</p>
                <p>The credibility of Frances Yenko Chilcoat’s testimony is supported by the
                    promotion of <hi rend="italic">Smuggler for the Pope </hi>in the American
                    Catholic press, as well as by the fact that none of the clergy or the laity
                    denied Yelko Chilcoat’s testimony so far, which would be expected if it was
                    falsified, all the more as her testimony concerns the Blessed Alojzije Stepinac
                    and the current candidate for a saint, who is often at the centre of attention
                    of public discussions in the Republic of Croatia as well as in the territory of
                    the former Yugoslavia. Another fact that supports her testimony is Yenko
                    Chilcoat’s book dedication in the preface of her memoir, in which she also
                    addresses the Stepinac Museum in Zagreb and an article published in <hi
                        rend="italic">Catholic San Francisco</hi>, stating that Yelko Chilcoat’s
                    memoir describes the cardinal robe that is currently kept at the Stepinac
                    Museum. However, it is quite odd that the museum itself does not provide any
                    information about the origin of the cardinal robe on display.</p>
                <p>Finally, no evidence has been found that Stepinac ever appeared among the people
                    in his cardinal robe, so it seems that he refrained from wearing it publicly
                    after it had been smuggled across the border.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div>
                <head>Sources and Literature</head>
                <list type="unordered">
                    <head>Archive sources</head>
                    <item>Arhiv Hercegovačke franjevačke provincije: <list type="unordered">
                            <item>Ostavština fra Dominika Mandića. </item>
                        </list></item>
                    <item>HDA – Hrvatski državni arhiv: <list type="unordered">
                            <item>HR-HDA-310, Komisija za odnose s vjerskim zajednicama Izvršnog
                                vijeća Sabora Socijalističke Republike Hrvatske. </item>
                        </list></item>
                    <item>Personal archive of Krešo Barišić: <list type="unordered">
                            <item>Okružni sud u Mostaru, nr. K. 72/70, Rješenje o produljenju
                                pritvora za optuženoga Krešu Barišića, Mostar, 4. lipnja 1970. </item>
                            <item>Vrhovni sud Bosne i Hercegovine, nr. K.605/70, Presuda Kreši
                                Barišiću i odbijenica na žalbu, Sarajevo, 2. rujna 1970. </item>
                        </list></item>
                </list>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Literature</head>
                    <bibl>Akmadža, Miroslav. <hi rend="italic">Katolička crkva u Hrvatskoj i
                            komunistički režim 1945.–1966.</hi> Rijeka: Otokar Keršovani,
                        2004.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Akmadža, Miroslav. <hi rend="italic">Katolička crkva u komunističkoj
                            Hrvatskoj 1945.–1980.</hi> Zagreb and Slavonski Brod: Despot infinitus
                        and Hrvatski institut za povijest, Podružnica za povijest Slavonije, Srijema
                        i Baranje, 2013.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Akmadža, Miroslav. <hi rend="italic">Stepinac riječju i djelom</hi>.
                        Zagreb: AGM, 2019.</bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="italic">Foreign Consular Offices in the United States. April 1,
                            1950</hi>. Washington: United States Government Printing Office,
                        1950.</bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="italic">Foreign Consular Offices in the United States. April 1,
                            1954</hi>. Washington: United States Government Printing Office,
                        1954.</bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="italic">Foreign Consular Offices in the United States. April 1,
                            1957</hi>. Washington: United States Government Printing Office,
                        1957.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Krašić, Wollfy. <hi rend="italic">Hrvatsko proljeće i hrvatska politička
                            emigracija</hi>. Zagreb: Školska knjiga, 2018.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Mijatović, Anđelko. <hi rend="italic">Bruno Bušić: prilog istraživanju
                            života i djelovanja (1939.–1978.)</hi>. Zagreb: Školska knjiga,
                        2010.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Miškulin, Ivica. “Neprijatelj države iz Okučana: slučaj političkog
                        zatvorenika i emigranta Janjka Sarajlića.” <hi rend="italic">Scrinia
                            Slavonica</hi> 19, No. 1 (2019): 241–69.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Radić, Radmila. <hi rend="italic">Država i verske zajednice 1945–1970.,
                            drugi deo: 1954</hi>–<hi rend="italic">1970.</hi> Beograd: Institut za
                        noviju istoriju Srbije, 2002.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Radosavljević, Peđa. <hi rend="italic">Odnosi između Jugoslavije i Svete
                            Stolice 1963–1978.</hi> Beograd: Službeni glasnik, 2012.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Silvestrini, Achille. “Uvod.” In: Casaroli, Agostino. <hi rend="italic"
                            >Mučeništvo strpljivosti. Sveta Stolica i komunističke zemlje
                            (1963.–1989.)</hi>, 23–49. Zagreb: Kršćanska sadašnjost, 2001.</bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="italic">Službeni list Federativne Narodne Republike
                            Jugoslavije</hi> 7, No. 13 (1951), 185–224.</bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="italic">Službeni list Socijalističke Federativne Republike
                            Jugoslavije</hi> 30, No. 39 (1974), 1290–300.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Šakić, Vlado and Ljiljana Dobrovšak, eds. <hi rend="italic">Leksikon
                            hrvatskoga iseljeništva i manjina</hi>. Zagreb: Institut društvenih
                        znanosti Ivo Pilar and Hrvatska matica iseljenika, 2020.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Tomas, Domagoj. <hi rend="italic">Pet redaka. Rimski dnevnik svećenika
                            Ivana Tomasa (1943.–1944.)</hi>. Rim and Mostar and Osijek: Papinski
                        hrvatski zavod svetog Jeronima u Rimu and Biskupski ordinarijat Mostar and
                        Odjel za kulturologiju Sveučilišta Josipa Jurja Strossmayera, 2014.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Vraneković, Josip. <hi rend="italic">Dnevnik: život u Krašiću zasužnjenog
                            nadbiskupa i kardinala Alojzija Stepinca (5. XII. 1951. – 10. II.
                            1960.)</hi>. Zagreb: Postulatura blaženoga Alojzija Stepinca,
                        2011.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Yenko Chilcoat, Frances. <hi rend="italic">Smuggler for the Pope. A True
                            Story</hi>. San Francisco: California Publishing Company, 2006.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Newspaper sources</head>
                    <bibl>Morris-Young, Dan. “Local parishioner records adventure as ‘Smuggler for
                        the Pope’.” <hi rend="italic">Catholic San Francisco</hi>, 19 December
                        2008.</bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="italic">The Billings Gazette</hi>, 16 May 1999. “Rock Springs
                        native recounts robe smuggling.”</bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="italic">The Daily Sentinel</hi>, 1 May 1999. “Woman recounts
                        role as robe smuggler.”</bibl>
                    <bibl>Williams, Abby. “Wyoming native recalls smuggling adventure.” <hi
                            rend="italic">Casper Star-Tribune</hi>, 3 May 1999.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Online sources</head>
                    <bibl><hi rend="italic">Zgodovina – Uršulinke Rimske Unije</hi>. Accessed on 30
                        October 2021. <ref target="https://www.ursulinke.si/zgodovina/"
                            >https://www.ursulinke.si/zgodovina/</ref></bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
            <div>
                <docAuthor>Domagoj Tomas</docAuthor>
                <head>IVAN TOMAS IN PAPEŽEVA TIHOTAPKA</head>
                <head>POVZETEK</head>
                <p>V času pontifikata papeža Pija XII (1939–1958) so bili odnosi med Svetim sedežem
                    in evropskimi komunističnimi državami napeti ali prekinjeni. Leta 1949 je Sveti
                    sedež izdal Odlok proti komunizmu, uradni dokument, ki je po encikliki <hi
                        rend="italic">Divini Redemptoris</hi> iz leta 1937 obsodil komunizem,
                    katoličane, ki so zagovarjali komunistično doktrino, pa razglasil za izobčene iz
                    katoliške cerkve. Politični odnosi med Svetim sedežem in komunističnimi državami
                    so tako še bolj zapletli tektoniko bipolarne delitve sveta med hladno vojno.</p>
                <p>V takšnih povojnih okoliščinah je v Federativni ljudski republiki Jugoslaviji
                    (FLRJ) potekal sodni proces proti zagrebškemu nadškofu Alojziju Stepincu, ki se
                    je končal leta 1946, ko je bil obsojen na 16 let zapora. Po prestani petletni
                    zaporni kazni se je Stepinac moral odločiti, ali bo odšel v Rim ali pa bo
                    odslužil preostalo kazen v hišnem priporu v Krašiću, svojem rojstnem kraju.
                    Izbral je hišni zapor in tako postal živi simbol mučeništva pod komunistično
                    oblastjo. Ko je bil Stepinac leta 1953 imenovan za kardinala, je FLRJ prekinila
                    diplomatske odnose s Svetim sedežem, zaradi česar ni mogel oditi v Rim, da bi
                    prevzel kardinalske insignije.</p>
                <p>V tistem času je na Vatikanskem radiu v Rimu delal hrvaški duhovnik Ivan Tomas,
                    ki je javno govoril o Stepinčevem primeru in promoviral njegovo vlogo v uporu
                    proti komunistični vladavini v FLRJ. Ob njegovem posredovanju je ameriška
                    turistka slovenskega rodu Francis Yenko Chilcoat leta 1954 prinesla Stepinčevo
                    kardinalsko obleke na ozemlje FLRJ. Svoj zanimivi podvig je opisala v spominih z
                    naslovom <hi rend="italic">Smuggler for the Pope (Papeževa tihotapka)</hi>, ki
                    so izšli leta 2006.</p>
                <p>V prispevku so najprej pojasnjene mednarodne politične okoliščine v času njenega
                    prihoda iz ZDA v Evropo ter cerkveno-državni odnosi med Svetim sedežem in FLRJ
                    po drugi svetovni vojni. Prispevek si prizadeva ugotoviti tudi pristnost in
                    verodostojnost spominov in trditev Frances Yenko Chilcoat ter tveganje, ki ga je
                    prevzela v vlogi tihotapke. Analizirani so tudi Tomasova vloga pri prenosu
                    kardinalskih oblačil in druge okoliščine tega procesa ter posledice tega, da so
                    oblačila postala Stepinčeva last.</p>
                <p>Nazadnje sta v prispevku preverjeni pristnost spominov v knjigi<hi rend="italic">
                        Smuggler for the Pope</hi>, ki jo je napisala Frances Yenko Chilcoat, in
                    verodostojnost njenega pričevanja, ki jo je dodatno potrdil katoliški tisk v
                    ZDA. Frances Yenko Chilcoat je s tihotapljenjem kardinalske obleke na ozemlje
                    FLRJ nedvomno veliko tvegala, saj bi jo za takšno dejanje po takratnem kazenskem
                    zakoniku FLRJ lahko obsodili na zaporno kazen. Potem ko so prispela v FLRJ,
                    kardinalska oblačila niso imela pomembne vloge v cerkveno-državnih odnosih med
                    Jugoslavijo in Vatikanom ali v širšem kontekstu vojne, saj niso bila javno na
                    ogled. Vendar pa je uspešno tihotapljenje teh pomembnih oblačil zagotovo
                    pokazalo na prepustnost jugoslovanske meje, kar zadeva vnos nezaželenih
                    predmetov z Zahoda, pa tudi na iznajdljivost Svetega sedeža oziroma hrvaške
                    izseljenske duhovščine v njegovi službi.</p>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
